<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Gopal Investments, a large institutional investor committing INR 100 crore to a Category II AIF, negotiates a side letter. What is a side letter in the AIF context?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A letter from SEBI approving the investor's participation in the fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A letter of intent to invest that has no legal binding effect]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A supplementary agreement between the fund and a specific investor granting additional or modified terms that are not in the standard fund documents]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A notice sent by the fund manager to all investors about a change in strategy]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A side letter is a legally binding supplementary agreement between the fund and a specific investor (usually large institutional investors) that modifies or supplements the standard terms — such as preferential fee rates, enhanced reporting, co-investment rights, or most-favored-nation provisions. It is not a regulatory approval, a non-binding letter, or a general notice.
**The Trap:** The letter of intent option sounds plausible because 'side letter' sounds informal, but it is a legally binding document with contractual force.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XIX-B covers side letter management from the fund manager's compliance and operational perspective.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Large commitments give your client leverage to negotiate side letters. Key areas include fee discounts, enhanced reporting, co-investment rights, and most-favored-nation clauses. Always engage legal counsel for negotiation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>