<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_41" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In the PPM of Damodar Structured Credit AIF (Category II), the section on redemption conditions for close-ended AIFs states:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investors can redeem their units at any time like an open-ended mutual fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Redemption is available quarterly at NAV minus a 10% exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Close-ended AIFs generally do not allow redemption before the end of the fund's tenure, and any early exit is subject to transfer restrictions and manager/trustee consent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI mandates a mandatory redemption window every 6 months for all AIFs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Close-ended AIFs lock in investor capital for the fund's tenure. Early exit is generally not permitted through redemption — investors must find a transferee, obtain consent, and comply with transfer restrictions. Unlike open-ended mutual funds, there are no periodic redemption windows, and SEBI does not mandate quarterly redemption.
**The Trap:** The quarterly redemption option borrows mutual fund concepts (exit loads, quarterly redemption) that do not apply to close-ended AIFs, which operate on a fundamentally different liquidity model.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A contrasts open-ended and close-ended fund liquidity, directly relevant for understanding AIF illiquidity.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is the most critical point for investor suitability. Only recommend close-ended AIFs to clients with genuine long-term capital who will not need liquidity for 5-10 years. Illiquidity is the number one source of investor dissatisfaction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>