<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_47" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the Custodian Agreement for a Category III AIF, the custodian is required to maintain segregation of the AIF's assets. What does asset segregation mean?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The custodian must invest the AIF's assets separately from its own proprietary investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The custodian must separate equity and debt instruments into different vaults]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The AIF's assets must be held in separate accounts distinct from the custodian's own assets and those of other clients, ensuring clear identification and protection in case of custodian insolvency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Assets of different investors within the same AIF must be held in individual accounts]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Asset segregation requires the custodian to hold each client's (AIF's) assets in distinctly identifiable separate accounts, protecting them from being commingled with the custodian's proprietary assets or other clients' assets. This ensures the AIF's assets are ringfenced in case of custodian insolvency. Separating by asset type misunderstands the concept, and individual investor accounts within a pooled vehicle is not how AIFs work.
**The Trap:** Individual investor accounts seems protective but AIFs are pooled vehicles — the fund's assets are pooled and segregated from the custodian, not separated by individual investor.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VI (Depository Operations) extensively covers asset segregation principles for depository participants.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Verify that the custodian provides independent holding statements. Asset segregation is meaningless if the custodian's reporting is unreliable. A regulated, reputed custodian is a non-negotiable governance requirement.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>