<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_50" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Sneha is negotiating a side letter for her family office's INR 50 crore investment in Cauvery Growth Fund. She requests a Most Favored Nation (MFN) clause. What does an MFN clause provide?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sneha's family office gets voting rights on all investment decisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sneha's investment is guaranteed against losses by the fund manager]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[If the fund grants more favorable terms to any other investor through a side letter, Sneha's family office is entitled to receive the same favorable terms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund must invest at least 50% of its corpus in Sneha's preferred sectors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An MFN clause ensures that if the fund grants better terms to any subsequent investor through a side letter, the MFN holder automatically receives those same terms. This prevents the fund from offering preferential treatment to later investors at the expense of earlier commitments. It does not provide voting rights, loss guarantees, or investment direction.
**The Trap:** Voting rights confuses commercial terms with governance rights — MFN is about economic and reporting terms, not decision-making authority over investments.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XIX-B covers MFN clause management from the fund manager's operational and compliance perspective.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** MFN clauses are extremely valuable for large investors. If your client is among the first to commit, negotiate an MFN clause to ensure they are never disadvantaged relative to later investors. This is a standard ask for institutional commitments above INR 25 crore.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>