<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Deepak has signed a Subscription Agreement for a Category I - Venture Capital AIF with a capital commitment of INR 2 crore. He defaults on a drawdown notice. What is the most common consequence specified in such agreements?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager must waive the drawdown and find another investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI imposes a fine directly on Deepak for breach of the subscription agreement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Deepak faces penalties that may include forfeiture of a portion of his existing capital in the fund, loss of unfunded commitment rights, and potential forced transfer of his interest]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire fund is wound up due to the capital shortfall]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Default consequences in AIF Subscription Agreements are severe — they typically include penalty interest, forfeiture of a portion of contributed capital, loss of rights on unfunded commitments, dilution of interest, and forced transfer. SEBI does not directly enforce private contractual commitments, managers cannot simply waive defaults, and one investor's default does not trigger fund-wide winding up.
**The Trap:** The SEBI fine option confuses contractual obligations with regulatory enforcement — SEBI regulates the AIF, not individual investor-fund contracts.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XII covers investor obligations in securities market participation, including commitment adherence.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before a client commits to an AIF, stress-test their liquidity over the fund's entire tenure. Default consequences are among the harshest in financial products.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>