<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under data privacy obligations in AIF documentation, the fund manager must ensure protection of investors' Personally Identifiable Information (PII). Which of the following is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investor PII can be freely shared with any third party for marketing purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Data privacy applies only to foreign investors, not domestic Indian investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Investor PII must be protected in accordance with applicable data protection laws, shared only with authorized service providers on a need-to-know basis, and investors must be informed about data usage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PII protection is optional and depends on the fund manager's internal policies]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Data privacy in AIF documentation requires the fund manager to protect investor PII per applicable laws (IT Act, DPDP Act), share data only with authorized service providers for legitimate fund purposes, implement security measures, and inform investors about data collection and usage. Free sharing for marketing, limiting protection to foreign investors, and treating it as optional all violate data protection principles.
**The Trap:** The foreign-investor-only option might seem plausible given GDPR's prominence for European investors, but Indian data protection laws (including the Digital Personal Data Protection Act) apply to all investors.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XII covers data privacy in the broader securities market context.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Ensure your own data handling practices comply with PII protection standards. As a distributor, you collect investor data during onboarding — mishandling it exposes you to legal liability under the DPDP Act.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>