<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The PPM of Periyar Healthcare Fund discloses the fund's fee structure as: 2% management fee on committed capital and 20% performance fee above an 8% hurdle rate. Which component protects investors from paying performance fee on subpar returns?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The 2% management fee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The committed capital basis for management fee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The 8% hurdle rate, which ensures the manager earns performance fee only after investors receive at least 8% return]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The 20% performance fee percentage]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The hurdle rate (preferred return) of 8% ensures that the manager earns performance fee (carried interest) only after investors have received at least an 8% annualized return. This aligns manager incentives with investor outcomes. The management fee is charged regardless of performance, committed capital basis is about the fee calculation base, and the 20% rate determines the share, not the threshold.
**The Trap:** The committed capital basis option is about how management fee is calculated (on committed vs. invested capital), which is a separate investor concern but does not protect against paying performance fees on poor returns.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers expense ratios and fee structures for mutual funds, where hurdle rates are less common but expense caps serve a similar protective function.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Hurdle rates vary — 8% is common in India but negotiate hard for it. Also check if the hurdle is a hard hurdle (carry only on excess) or soft hurdle (catch-up provision allowing manager to earn carry on the full return once hurdle is crossed).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>