<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_43" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The capital commitment of INR 3 crore by Rohan in the Subscription Agreement for Betwa Digital Fund specifies a drawdown period of 4 years. If the fund manager does not call the entire committed capital within 4 years, what typically happens to the uncalled commitment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The uncalled commitment typically lapses, and the investor's obligation to fund that portion ends, unless the fund documents provide otherwise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The uncalled amount is automatically invested in government securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI imposes a penalty on the fund manager for not utilizing committed capital]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The uncalled amount is transferred to another AIF managed by the same manager]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If the drawdown period expires and committed capital remains uncalled, the investor's obligation for that uncalled portion typically lapses as per the Subscription Agreement terms. SEBI does not penalize for uncalled capital, automatic investment in g-secs is not standard, and transfer to another fund would be a misuse of investor commitment.
**The Trap:** The government securities option seems like a conservative approach but AIF Subscription Agreements do not provide for automatic alternative investments — uncalled capital simply releases the investor's obligation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XIX-B covers the fund manager's capital deployment efficiency metrics, where a high uncalled percentage may indicate poor deal sourcing.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A fund that doesn't call all committed capital may indicate a disciplined manager who didn't force-deploy capital into suboptimal deals. However, consistently large uncalled amounts could signal poor deal origination capability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>