<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_48" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Pankaj is reviewing the PPM of Jhelum Macro Fund (Category III). He notices the section on leverage. What must the PPM disclose about leverage for Category III AIFs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Category III AIFs are prohibited from using any leverage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the total amount of leverage in rupee terms needs to be disclosed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The maximum leverage the fund may employ, the sources of leverage, associated risks, and the impact of leverage on returns and losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Leverage details are confidential and shared only with the fund's prime broker]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Category III AIFs are permitted to use leverage (unlike Category I and II), and the PPM must comprehensively disclose the maximum leverage ratio, sources (prime broker, margin trading), associated risks (magnified losses), and impact on fund returns. Blanket prohibition is incorrect for Cat III, rupee-only disclosure is insufficient, and treating leverage as confidential violates SEBI's transparency mandate.
**The Trap:** The prohibition option would be correct for Category I and II AIFs (which generally cannot leverage except for certain operational needs), but Category III AIFs specifically can employ leverage.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) covers leverage extensively in margin trading and derivatives, directly relevant to Category III AIF strategies.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Leverage amplifies both gains and losses. Ensure your client understands that a 2x leveraged fund can lose twice as fast as an unleveraged fund. Leverage is the single biggest risk differentiator for Category III AIFs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>