<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The force majeure clause in the legal documentation of Chambal Opportunities Fund was invoked during the COVID-19 pandemic. What is the effect of invoking a force majeure clause?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All contractual obligations are permanently terminated]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Performance of affected obligations is suspended or excused for the duration of the force majeure event, with obligations resuming once the event subsides]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the fund manager's obligations are suspended; investor obligations continue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund immediately distributes all assets to investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Force majeure suspends or excuses performance of affected obligations during the event's duration. Once the event subsides, obligations resume. It does not permanently terminate contracts, apply one-sidedly, or trigger immediate liquidation. During COVID-19, many AIFs invoked force majeure to extend drawdown timelines and valuation deadlines.
**The Trap:** Permanent termination goes too far — force majeure provides temporary relief, not permanent termination. If the event is prolonged, separate termination provisions may apply.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII covers force majeure in derivatives contracts, where similar temporary suspension principles apply.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During market disruptions, proactively communicate with clients about force majeure implications. Understanding that obligations are suspended, not cancelled, prevents panic and maintains the client relationship.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>