<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The PPM of Kaveri Real Estate AIF states that the fund's tenure is 7 years with a provision for extension by up to 2 years. Who typically approves the extension of an AIF's tenure?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI automatically extends the tenure upon the manager's request]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Extension requires approval of at least two-thirds of investors by value of their investment in the AIF, as per SEBI AIF Regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager can unilaterally extend the tenure without any approval]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The trustee alone decides on extension without consulting investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI AIF Regulations require that tenure extension beyond the original term needs approval of at least two-thirds of investors by value of investment. This supermajority requirement protects investors from indefinite lock-up. SEBI does not auto-extend, the manager cannot act unilaterally, and the trustee cannot decide alone.
**The Trap:** Unilateral extension by the manager seems efficient but would allow managers to indefinitely extend funds, trapping investor capital — the two-thirds approval requirement is a critical investor safeguard.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers close-ended mutual fund maturity and rollover provisions, which require similar investor consent.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask about exit timelines, clarify that the stated tenure is the base period and extensions are possible but require supermajority consent. Clients should plan their liquidity needs for the maximum possible tenure (base + extension).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>