<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_38" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The IMA of Narmada Growth AIF includes a clause on the scope of the manager's investment authority. Which of the following would fall OUTSIDE the manager's authority under a typical IMA?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing in unlisted equity of companies within the stated strategy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Negotiating terms of investment agreements with portfolio companies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Making investments that are expressly prohibited in the PPM, such as investing in related-party entities without proper approval]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Engaging legal and financial advisors for transaction execution]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The IMA grants the manager broad authority to invest within the PPM-defined strategy but explicitly excludes prohibited investments, especially related-party transactions without proper governance approval. The manager can invest in unlisted equity, negotiate deal terms, and engage advisors, but cannot breach PPM restrictions or make conflicted investments without approval.
**The Trap:** Investing in unlisted equity seems restrictive because it is risky, but if the PPM states the strategy includes unlisted equity, the manager has full authority to invest in it.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers similar investment restrictions for mutual fund managers who must stay within scheme mandate.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Compare the IMA's investment authority with the PPM's stated strategy. Any mismatch is a red flag — the manager's authority should precisely mirror the disclosed strategy, no broader and no narrower.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>