<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Amrita signs a Subscription Agreement for Godavari Agri Fund (Category I - SME Fund). The agreement includes a 'clawback' provision. What does clawback mean in the AIF context?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The investor can claw back her capital commitment after signing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI can claw back the fund's registration certificate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[If the fund manager receives excess performance fee (carried interest) based on interim distributions, the manager must return the excess to investors to ensure overall returns align with the agreed waterfall]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund can recall distributions made to investors if subsequent losses occur]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Clawback provisions require the fund manager to return excess carried interest/performance fee if, at the end of the fund's life, interim performance fee payments exceeded what the manager was entitled to based on overall fund performance. This protects investors in American-style (deal-by-deal) waterfalls where carry is paid on individual deal profits.
**The Trap:** Recalling investor distributions describes a different concept — which is extremely rare and distinct from manager clawback. The clawback is specifically directed at the manager's excess compensation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XIX-B covers clawback mechanics from the fund manager's perspective, including escrow arrangements to secure clawback obligations.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always check if the fund has a clawback provision, especially for American-style waterfalls. Without a clawback, the manager could earn carry on early profitable exits while the overall fund underperforms.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>