<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_37" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The governing law clause in the PPM of Zuari Tech AIF states that the fund documentation shall be governed by the laws of India with courts in Mumbai having exclusive jurisdiction. What does 'exclusive jurisdiction' mean?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Supreme Court of India can hear disputes related to the fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund can only invest in companies headquartered in Mumbai]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Any dispute that goes to litigation (as opposed to arbitration) can only be filed in courts located in Mumbai, excluding all other courts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only investors residing in Mumbai can invest in the fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Exclusive jurisdiction means that if disputes proceed to litigation (not arbitration), they must be filed only in Mumbai courts, excluding courts in all other cities. This provides certainty on forum and avoids jurisdictional disputes. It has nothing to do with investment geography or investor eligibility, and it does not limit jurisdiction to the Supreme Court.
**The Trap:** The Supreme Court option confuses exclusive jurisdiction (a specific city's courts) with appellate jurisdiction — the Supreme Court is an appellate court, not a court of first instance for contractual disputes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XII covers jurisdictional clauses in securities market agreements.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Note the jurisdiction clause when onboarding clients from different cities. If a dispute arises, your client will need to litigate in Mumbai regardless of where they reside — factor in this practical consideration.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>