<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The tax considerations section of the PPM for Saraswati Tech Fund mentions pass-through tax status. What does this mean for Category I and II AIF investors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AIF pays all taxes on behalf of investors, and investors receive tax-free returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Income earned by the AIF is not taxed at the fund level but is taxed in the hands of investors based on their individual tax status, as per applicable pass-through provisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AIF and investors both pay tax on the same income, resulting in double taxation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tax obligations are deferred until the investor exits the fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 115UB of the Income Tax Act, Category I and II AIFs enjoy pass-through status for certain income — meaning the income is not taxed at the fund level but is instead taxed in the hands of investors according to their own tax status. This avoids double taxation. Category III AIFs do not get this pass-through benefit for all income types.
**The Trap:** The tax-free returns option incorrectly suggests taxes disappear — pass-through means the tax obligation passes to the investor, not that it disappears.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers mutual fund taxation which operates differently (dividend taxation, LTCG/STCG), providing a useful contrast.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Pass-through taxation is a key selling point for Category I and II AIFs. Help clients understand how AIF income will be taxed in their hands based on their specific tax bracket and residency status.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>