<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_49" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The PPM of Mahanadi Resources Fund includes a section on service providers. Besides the custodian, fund administrator, legal counsel, and auditor, which other service provider must typically be disclosed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The caterer providing food at the fund manager's office]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The valuation agency or independent valuer responsible for valuing unlisted and illiquid investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager's personal financial advisor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The office interior designer]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The independent valuer is a critical service provider for AIFs, especially those investing in unlisted/illiquid securities. SEBI requires independent valuation for Category I and II AIFs, and the valuer's identity, methodology, and frequency of valuation must be disclosed in the PPM. The other options are irrelevant to fund operations and investor interests.
**The Trap:** This question seems straightforward, but candidates sometimes overlook the valuer because they focus on the 'big four' service providers (custodian, administrator, legal counsel, auditor).
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XIX-B covers valuation requirements from the fund manager's operational perspective, including SEBI's guidelines on independent valuation.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For funds investing in unlisted securities, the valuer's independence and methodology are crucial. Ask whether the fund uses a SEBI-registered valuer and whether valuations are conducted at least semi-annually. Unreliable valuations can mask underperformance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>