<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Sanjay wishes to transfer his interest in a Category III AIF to his business associate Ritu. The Subscription Agreement restricts transfers. Which statement is correct regarding transfer restrictions in AIFs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AIF interests can be freely transferred like listed equity shares on a stock exchange]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI prohibits all transfers of AIF interests under any circumstances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Transfers are typically restricted and require prior consent of the fund manager and/or trustee, compliance with SEBI regulations, and may be subject to right of first refusal by existing investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer is automatically permitted after a 1-year lock-in period for all AIF categories]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AIF interests are illiquid by nature and transfers are heavily restricted. Subscription Agreements typically require manager/trustee consent, compliance with SEBI's minimum investment and eligibility norms, and may grant existing investors a right of first refusal. AIFs are not freely tradeable, SEBI does not impose a blanket ban, and there is no universal 1-year auto-transfer rule.
**The Trap:** The lock-in option seems reasonable because lock-in periods exist, but even after lock-in, transfer restrictions and consent requirements remain in place.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers transfer restrictions for close-ended mutual fund units, drawing a parallel to AIF illiquidity.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Set clear expectations with clients that AIF investments are highly illiquid. Unlike mutual funds, there is no redemption window or exchange listing in most cases.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>