<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AIF Legal Documentation_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The dispute resolution clause in the documentation of Mandovi Capital AIF specifies arbitration as the primary mechanism. What is the main advantage of arbitration over litigation for AIF disputes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Arbitration is always free of cost for all parties]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Arbitration awards can be easily appealed in any court of law]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Confidentiality of proceedings, faster resolution, and ability to appoint arbitrators with specialized financial expertise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Arbitration is mandatory for all financial disputes in India regardless of contract terms]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Arbitration offers confidentiality (crucial for fund disputes involving sensitive commercial information), faster resolution compared to overburdened Indian courts, and the ability to appoint arbitrators with specific financial/legal expertise. Arbitration is not free, awards have limited appeal grounds under the Arbitration Act, and it is not mandatory for all financial disputes.
**The Trap:** Easy appeal overstates appeal rights — arbitration awards can only be challenged on very limited grounds under Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996, which is actually an advantage of finality.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX covers arbitration in merchant banking disputes, and NISM Series VIII covers stock exchange arbitration mechanisms.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Arbitration clauses benefit both parties. If a client has concerns about dispute resolution, explain that arbitration typically resolves in 12-18 months versus 5-10 years in Indian courts, with expert arbitrators who understand financial products.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>