<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Alternative Investments_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[How is income of AIF Category III taxed, and how does this differ from Category I and II?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Category III has pass-through status; income is taxable only for unit-holders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three categories have pass-through status; income is taxable only for unit-holders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Category III income is exempt; Category I and II income is taxable at the fund level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Category III has NO pass-through status; income is taxable at the fund level at maximum marginal rate. Category I and II enjoy pass-through status.]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AIF Category I and II enjoy pass-through status -- income (other than business income) is exempt at the fund level and taxable in the hands of unit-holders. Category III does NOT have pass-through status -- income is taxed at the fund level at the maximum marginal rate (highest slab rate applicable). This is the most significant tax distinction across AIF categories.
**The Trap:** "All three categories have pass-through" is tempting because pass-through is generally considered a benefit of the AIF structure. However, Category III was deliberately excluded from pass-through to prevent tax arbitrage through hedge fund strategies.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B heavily tests this distinction as it directly impacts after-tax returns for investors and is crucial for investment suitability assessment.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The maximum marginal rate taxation on Category III AIFs means returns are significantly reduced by taxes at the fund level before distribution. Always present Category III returns on a post-tax basis to clients for accurate comparison with other investments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
