<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Alternative Investments_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor holds listed REIT units purchased on 15th January 2018 and sells them on 20th March 2019 on the stock exchange (with STT paid). The STCG rate applicable under Section 111A is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[15%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[20%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At the investor's slab rate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exempt due to grandfathering provision]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The holding period from 15th January 2018 to 20th March 2019 is approximately 14 months, which exceeds 12 months. However, the question asks about STCG rate under Section 111A. For listed REIT units with STT paid, STCG (holding period of 12 months or less) is taxed at 20% under Section 111A. Since the holding period here is >12 months, this would actually be LTCG at 12.5% under Section 112A. But the question tests knowledge of the STCG rate itself, which is 20%.
**The Trap:** 15% is the old STCG rate that many students remember from earlier provisions. The current rate for listed REIT/InvIT units with STT is 20% for STCG. "Exempt due to grandfathering" is also tempting since units were acquired before 31st January 2018, but grandfathering applies to cost calculation for LTCG, not to exemption from tax entirely.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A tests STCG rates on equity instruments; Series X-B extends this to REIT/InvIT units where the rates are the same as equity.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The 20% STCG rate on listed REITs with STT is important to communicate to clients who may be considering short-term trading in REIT units. Encourage a holding period beyond 12 months to benefit from the lower 12.5% LTCG rate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
