<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Alternative Investments_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is the KEY difference between REIT and InvIT taxation regarding pass-through status?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Interest from SPV has pass-through status in REIT but not in InvIT]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dividend from SPV has pass-through status in InvIT but not in REIT]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rental income has pass-through status in REIT but NOT in InvIT; rental income is taxable at the InvIT level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains on property transfer have pass-through status in InvIT but not in REIT]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The key difference between REIT and InvIT taxation is that rental income enjoys pass-through status in REITs (exempt at REIT level, taxable for unit-holders) but does NOT have pass-through status in InvITs. In InvITs, rental income is taxable at the InvIT level itself, not passed through to unit-holders. All other tax treatments (interest from SPV, dividend from SPV, capital gains) are the same for both.
**The Trap:** Students often assume REIT and InvIT taxation is identical since the PDF states "tax treatment SAME as REIT except..." The exception for rental income is the critical distinction that the exam loves to test.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This REIT vs InvIT distinction is a high-frequency question area in NISM Series X-B and tests detailed comparative knowledge.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This difference matters practically because infrastructure assets (InvIT) generate less rental income compared to real estate assets (REIT). The lack of rental pass-through in InvITs has limited practical impact but is critical for exam purposes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
