<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AML, CFT and PF Guidelines_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following activities falls within the definition of a Virtual Digital Asset Service Provider (SP)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Participation in and provision of financial services related to an issuer's offer and sale of a virtual digital asset]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trading in listed equity shares on a recognized stock exchange]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Operating a mutual fund distribution business]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing insurance advisory services]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The SP definition specifically includes: exchange between VDAs and fiat currencies, exchange between VDAs, transfer of VDAs, safekeeping/administration of VDAs, and participation in financial services related to an issuer's offer and sale of VDAs. The other options are traditional financial services, not VDA activities.

**The Trap:** Trading equity shares, distributing mutual funds, and insurance advisory are all regulated financial activities but NOT under the VDA SP definition. They fall under their respective regulatory frameworks (SEBI, IRDAI).

**Cross-Exam Context:** This question tests the boundary between traditional securities market activities and VDA activities. In NISM III-A, you study stockbroker regulations; here you learn that VDA activities have a separate regulatory treatment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If your client is involved in selling or distributing VDA tokens (like an ICO or token offering), they qualify as an SP. This means they must register with FIU-IND and comply with all AML obligations -- failure can lead to website blocking as seen in the Bybit case.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
