<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="AML, CFT and PF Guidelines_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under Section 12 of the Weapons of Mass Destruction and their Delivery Systems (Prohibition of Unlawful Activities) Act (WMDA), which entities are exempt from liability for mere carriage of WMD-related materials without knowledge?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Postal, financial service providers, courier, and telecom carriers are exempt if they transport without knowledge of the WMD materials]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All carriers are liable regardless of whether they had knowledge of the materials being transported]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only government-operated carriers are exempt from liability for carriage of such materials]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The exemption applies exclusively to postal services and does not extend to financial service providers or couriers]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 12 of the WMDA provides a specific "mere carriage without knowledge" exemption. Postal service providers, financial service providers, courier services, and telecom carriers are not held liable if they carry WMD-related materials without knowledge of the nature of what is being transported. The key condition is the absence of knowledge.

**The Trap:** Candidates may assume that all carriers bear strict liability regardless of knowledge, or that the exemption is narrow (only for government carriers or only postal services). The Act deliberately covers a broad range of carrier types but ties the exemption to the knowledge condition.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This exemption is important in understanding the balance between proliferation financing controls and the practical operations of service providers. It connects to the broader PF framework tested in NISM Series XXIV.

**Key Takeaway:** The WMDA exempts postal, financial, courier, and telecom carriers from liability for mere carriage of WMD materials, provided they had no knowledge of the prohibited nature of the materials being transported.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
