<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="AML_CFT_Guidelines_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the PML Rules, small accounts can only be opened at branches that are linked to which system, to ensure compliance with balance and transaction limits?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any branch of a scheduled commercial bank]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Core Banking Solution (CBS) linked branches or branches where manual monitoring is possible]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only metropolitan branches with dedicated AML officers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only designated branches approved by FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Small accounts must be opened at Core Banking Solution (CBS) linked branches, or at branches where it is possible to manually monitor and ensure that foreign remittances are not being credited to the account and that the prescribed monthly and annual limits on aggregate credits, withdrawals, and balances are not being breached.

**The Trap:** "Any branch" is too broad — the Rules specifically require monitoring capability. "Only metro branches" and "only designated branches" are fabricated restrictions. The key requirement is CBS linkage for automated monitoring, or manual monitoring capability.

**Cross-Exam Context:** CBS integration allows real-time monitoring of transactions across all branches. This is critical for small accounts where aggregate limits (e.g., balance not exceeding Rs. 50,000, total credits not exceeding Rs. 1,00,000 per year) must be enforced.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The CBS requirement ensures that small accounts — which lack full KYC — are subject to effective monitoring for compliance with prescribed limits and restrictions on foreign remittances.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>