<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="AML_CFT_Guidelines_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a mandatory element of the Digital KYC process as specified under the PML Rules?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Capturing a live photograph of the client with GPS coordinates (geo-tagging) and applying date-time watermarking]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Video recording of the client reading their Aadhaar number aloud for verification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capturing a scanned copy of the OVD with digital signature of the bank officer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Uploading a pre-existing passport-size photograph with biometric fingerprint scan]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Digital KYC process under the PML Rules involves capturing a live photograph of the client along with officially valid documents or proof of possession of Aadhaar. The process requires: (i) live photograph of the client, (ii) geo-tagging with GPS coordinates (latitude and longitude), (iii) date-time watermarking on the photograph, (iv) OTP-based verification, and (v) a declaration by an authorized officer of the reporting entity.

**The Trap:** Video recording of reading Aadhaar aloud is not part of Digital KYC (Video KYC is a separate process). Scanned copies with digital signatures describe a different document handling process. Pre-existing photographs defeat the purpose of Digital KYC, which requires LIVE capture. The key elements are live photo + geo-tagging + watermarking.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Digital KYC was introduced to facilitate remote account opening while maintaining identity verification integrity. It is distinct from Video-based Customer Identification Process (V-CIP), which involves video interaction with a bank official.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Digital KYC = Live photo + GPS geo-tagging + Date-time watermark + OTP validation + Authorized officer declaration. The emphasis is on "live" and "geo-tagged" to prevent fraud.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>