<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="AML_CFT_Guidelines_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[When conducting KYC for a company as a client, which of the following is the CORRECT combination of mandatory documents required under the PML Rules?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Certificate of Incorporation, Memorandum and Articles of Association, and PAN of the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Certificate of Incorporation, PAN of the company, and audited financial statements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Memorandum and Articles of Association, Board Resolution, and GST registration certificate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Certificate of Incorporation, PAN of directors, and company bank statement]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The PML Rules require the following KYC documents for a company: Certificate of Incorporation, Memorandum and Articles of Association (MoA &amp; AoA), PAN of the company, Board Resolution or Power of Attorney granted in favour of authorized signatories, documents for identification of beneficial owners, names of senior management personnel (managers, officers, or employees), and the registered office address.

**The Trap:** Audited financial statements, GST registration, company bank statements, and PAN of individual directors are NOT specifically listed as mandatory KYC requirements for a company client. The PAN required is of the company itself, not of individual directors. Board Resolution is needed for authorized signatories, not as a standalone identification document.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between KYC for individuals (OVDs like Aadhaar, passport) versus entities (incorporation documents, constitutional documents) is frequently tested. For companies, the emphasis is on legal existence, governance structure, and beneficial ownership.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Company KYC = Certificate of Incorporation + MoA/AoA + Company PAN + Board Resolution/PoA + Beneficial Owner documents + Senior Management names + Registered Office.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>