<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="AML_CFT_Guidelines_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text>Under Rule 9(12) of the PML Rules, ongoing due diligence by a reporting entity includes which of the following activities?</text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text>Periodically reviewing CDD records, applying CDD to existing customers based on materiality and risk, and scrutinizing past transactions where necessary</text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text>Only reviewing CDD records at the time of account opening and annual renewal</text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text>Applying enhanced due diligence to all existing customers uniformly, regardless of risk profile</text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text>Periodically reviewing CDD records and filing Suspicious Transaction Reports for all high-value transactions</text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text>**The Logic:** Rule 9(12) specifies three components of ongoing due diligence: (i) periodically review and update the existing CDD records, particularly for higher risk categories of clients; (ii) apply CDD measures to existing customers on the basis of materiality and risk; and (iii) scrutinize transactions undertaken throughout the course of the relationship to ensure consistency with the entity's knowledge of the client and risk profile, including the source of funds where necessary.

**The Trap:** Ongoing due diligence is NOT limited to account opening and annual reviews — it is a continuous process. It is risk-based, not uniformly applied to all customers. Filing STRs is a separate obligation and not the same as scrutinizing past transactions. The correct answer captures all three elements from Rule 9(12).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Ongoing due diligence is a cornerstone of the risk-based approach to AML/CFT. It ensures that customer information remains current and that transaction patterns are consistent with the known profile of the customer.

**Key Takeaway:** Ongoing CDD under Rule 9(12) = Review records + Apply CDD based on risk/materiality + Scrutinize past transactions. It is continuous and risk-based, not one-time or uniform.</text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>