<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="AML_CFT_Guidelines_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the PML Rules, every reporting entity that is part of a group is required to implement:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Individual branch-level AML policies only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Group-wide programmes against money laundering and terror financing, including policies for sharing information for CDD and risk management]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AML policies only in branches located in high-risk jurisdictions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AML policies only at the holding company level, not at subsidiary level]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 3A requires every reporting entity that is part of a group to implement group-wide programmes against money laundering and terror financing. These include group-wide policies for sharing information required for CDD and ML/TF risk management, with adequate safeguards on confidentiality and prevention of tipping-off.

**The Trap:** The requirement is for GROUP-WIDE implementation — not just individual branches, not only in high-risk areas, and not only at the holding company level. The entire group must be covered.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Group-wide AML policies are aligned with FATF recommendations on financial groups. This ensures consistent AML standards across conglomerates operating in multiple jurisdictions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** "Tipping-off" means alerting a client that an STR has been filed about them. Rule 3A specifically includes safeguards to prevent this while enabling information sharing within the group. If an employee tips off a client about an STR, it is a serious compliance breach.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>