<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Regarding Alternative Investment Funds (AIFs), which statement correctly describes the tax treatment of income earned by the fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three categories (I, II, III) enjoy complete pass-through status for all types of income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Category III AIFs enjoy pass-through for capital gains but not for business income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Category I and II AIFs have pass-through for all income except business income (taxed at fund level at MMR), while Category III has no pass-through — all income taxed at fund level at MMR]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Category I AIFs have pass-through status, but Category II and III do not]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AIF taxation framework distinguishes between categories: Category I & II AIFs enjoy pass-through status, meaning income (except business income) is taxed in the hands of investors as if they earned it directly. However, business income earned by Cat I & II is taxed at the fund level at Maximum Marginal Rate (MMR = 42.744%). Category III AIFs have NO pass-through benefit at all — all income (capital gains, interest, dividends, business income) is taxed at the fund level at MMR.
**The Trap:** Option A suggests complete pass-through for all categories, which is incorrect for Cat III and partially incorrect for business income in Cat I/II. Option B reverses the Cat III treatment.
**Cross-Exam Context:** AIF taxation is specifically tested in NISM Series XIX-A (Alternative Investment Fund) and NISM X-B. The distinction between categories is a high-value question.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Cat III AIFs (hedge funds) face a significant tax disadvantage due to fund-level taxation at MMR. For HNI clients in lower tax brackets, Cat I/II structures are more tax-efficient due to pass-through treatment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
