<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A REIT distributes income to its unitholders comprising: (i) Rs.5 per unit as interest income received from SPV, (ii) Rs.3 per unit as dividend received from SPV, and (iii) Rs.2 per unit as repayment of debt by SPV. How is each component taxed in the hands of the unitholder?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three components are exempt in the unitholder's hands due to pass-through status]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(i) Exempt, (ii) Taxable at slab as other sources, (iii) Taxable at slab as other sources]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[(i) Taxable at slab as other sources, (ii) Taxable at slab as other sources, (iii) Taxable u/s 56(2)(xii) as other sources]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(i) Taxable at slab, (ii) Exempt, (iii) Exempt as return of capital]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** REIT/InvIT distributions have three distinct components with different tax treatments: (i) Interest income from SPV: passes through to unitholders — taxable at slab rate as income from other sources. (ii) Dividend from SPV: exempt in the REIT's hands, but taxable in the unitholder's hands at slab rate as income from other sources. (iii) Debt repayment by SPV distributed to unitholders: taxable under Section 56(2)(xii) as income from other sources.
**The Trap:** Option D incorrectly treats dividend and debt repayment as exempt. Many candidates assume dividends are always exempt (pre-2020 mindset) and debt repayment is just return of capital. The 2020 amendments made dividends taxable, and s.56(2)(xii) specifically taxes debt repayment distributions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** REIT/InvIT taxation is increasingly tested in NISM Series X-B as these instruments gain market acceptance. The three-component analysis is unique to this topic.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising REIT/InvIT investors, break down the distribution into its three components for accurate tax planning. The headline yield may look attractive, but the post-tax yield depends on the investor's slab rate applied to all three components.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
