<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Shalini received right shares of a listed company. She was offered 100 rights at Rs.80 per share on 01-Jun-2025. Instead of subscribing, she renounced the rights on 15-Jun-2025 and received Rs.20 per right from the buyer. What is the capital gains treatment for Shalini?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[LTCG of Rs.2,000 since she held the original shares for more than 12 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[STCG of Rs.2,000 taxable at slab rate — cost is Nil, period from offer date to renouncement date (always short-term)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No capital gain arises — renouncement of rights is not a transfer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STCG of Rs.2,000 at 20% under Section 111A]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When an original shareholder renounces rights, the cost of acquisition of those rights is NIL (since the rights were received without paying anything). The holding period is measured from the date of offer (01-Jun-2025) to the date of renouncement (15-Jun-2025) = 14 days. This is always short-term given the typically short rights offer window. Capital gain = Rs.20 × 100 - Rs.0 = Rs.2,000. Since renouncement is not a sale on a stock exchange with STT, s.111A does not apply, and it is taxed at slab rate as "other STCG."
**The Trap:** Option A tries to link the holding period to the original shares — but renounced rights have their own independent holding period. Option C wrongly claims renouncement is not a transfer — it is a "relinquishment of rights" which IS a transfer. Option D applies s.111A which requires STT payment.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Rights renouncement is a niche but frequently tested topic in NISM X-B. The key facts: cost = Nil, period from offer to renouncement, always STCG.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients receive rights offers they don't wish to exercise, advise them that renouncement proceeds will be taxable as STCG at slab rate. If they're in a high tax bracket, the effective tax on renouncement income can be substantial.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
