<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Section 115QA, when a listed company buys back its own shares, which of the following correctly describes the tax treatment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The shareholder pays capital gains tax on the difference between buyback price and cost of acquisition]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The company pays buyback tax on the distributed income (consideration minus issue price), and the shareholder's receipt is exempt under Section 10(34A)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both the company and shareholder are taxed — company on distributed income and shareholder on capital gains]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The buyback is completely tax-free for both the company and the shareholder]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 115QA imposes a buyback tax on the COMPANY, not the shareholder. The company pays tax on the "distributed income," which is the difference between the buyback consideration and the amount received by the company at the time of issue of those shares. For the shareholder, the consideration received on buyback is EXEMPT from tax under Section 10(34A). This shifts the tax burden from the shareholder to the company.
**The Trap:** Option A applies the old regime (pre-115QA) where shareholders paid capital gains tax. Option C creates double taxation which the law specifically avoids. The key insight is that s.115QA and s.10(34A) work together to ensure single-point taxation at the company level.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Buyback taxation is tested in NISM X-B and is also relevant for NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) in the context of corporate actions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a company announces a buyback, advise shareholders that their receipt is tax-free. This makes buybacks sometimes more tax-efficient than dividends for shareholders, since dividend income is taxable at slab rate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
