<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Pooja lends 1,000 shares of ABC Ltd. (cost Rs.300 per share) through a Securities Lending and Borrowing (SLB) scheme and receives a lending fee of Rs.15,000. When the shares are returned, which of the following is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Return of shares is a transfer — capital gains arise on the difference between market value on return date and cost]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both the lending fee and return of shares are exempt from tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lending fee is capital gains and the return is not a transfer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Return of shares is NOT a transfer (no capital gains). The lending fee of Rs.15,000 is taxable income.]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Securities Lending and Borrowing scheme, the return of securities to the lender is specifically excluded from the definition of "transfer" — hence no capital gains arise on the return. However, the lending fee received (Rs.15,000) is taxable as income. The original cost (Rs.300 per share) and holding period continue to apply to the shares as if no lending occurred.
**The Trap:** Option A incorrectly treats the return as a transfer. Option B exempts the lending fee, which is incorrect — it is taxable. Option C classifies the lending fee as capital gains — it is actually taxable as other income (not a capital gain since there's no transfer of a capital asset).
**Cross-Exam Context:** SLB taxation is tested in NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) and X-B. The non-transfer status of securities return is a key concept.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SLB can be an income-enhancement strategy for long-term holders. The lending fee is additional income, and the shares' holding period is uninterrupted. But remind clients that the fee is fully taxable at slab rate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
