<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[For an eligible start-up, when is the perquisite tax on ESOPs deferred to under the special provision?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The perquisite tax is permanently exempt for start-up ESOPs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Deferred until 3 years from the date of exercise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Deferred to the earliest of: 5 years from allotment, date of sale of shares, or date of cessation of employment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Deferred until the date of sale of shares only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For eligible start-ups, the perquisite tax on ESOPs (the difference between FMV on exercise date and exercise price) is deferred. The tax becomes payable on the EARLIEST of three events: (1) expiry of 5 years from the date of allotment, (2) the date the employee sells the shares, or (3) the date the employee ceases employment with the start-up. This deferral addresses the liquidity problem — start-up employees had to pay tax on paper gains before having cash from selling shares.
**The Trap:** Option A suggests permanent exemption — the tax is only deferred, not exempted. Option B incorrectly says 3 years (it's 5 years). Option D captures only one trigger event. The three-trigger framework is critical — many start-up employees forget that leaving the company also triggers the deferred tax.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Start-up ESOP taxation is a specialized topic in NISM X-B. The broader ESOP two-stage taxation (perquisite + capital gains) is tested across X-A and X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise start-up employees to plan for the deferred tax liability. If they leave the company before selling shares or before 5 years, the perquisite tax becomes immediately due — even without any cash realization. Build this into their financial plan.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
