<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In the context of NPS (National Pension System), which statement correctly describes the tax treatment at maturity?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% of the corpus is exempt from tax at maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[60% is taxable as income, 40% must purchase an annuity which is also exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[60% lump sum withdrawal is exempt, 40% must purchase an annuity, and the annuity income received is taxable at slab rate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire corpus is taxable at a concessional rate of 10%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NPS follows the EET (Exempt-Exempt-Taxed) regime. At maturity: (a) 60% of the corpus can be withdrawn as a lump sum — this is EXEMPT from tax. (b) The remaining 40% MUST be used to purchase an annuity from an insurance company. While the annuity purchase itself is not taxed, the annuity income received periodically is taxable at the subscriber's slab rate.
**The Trap:** Option A suggests 100% exemption, which is incorrect — the annuity income is taxable. Option B reverses the treatment — the 60% lump sum is exempt, not taxable. The key nuance is that the annuity PURCHASE is not taxed, but the annuity INCOME is.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS taxation is tested in NISM Series X-A (Investment Adviser Level 1) as well, often focusing on the contribution-stage deductions under Section 80CCD.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When planning retirement with NPS, factor in that the 40% annuity will generate taxable income. The effective tax benefit of NPS depends on the client's expected tax slab at retirement versus their current slab during contribution years.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
