<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera Krishnan, a resident Indian aged 38, made several investment transactions during FY 2025-26. Her details are as follows:

Transaction 1 - Listed Equity Shares of TechCorp Ltd: Purchased 2,000 shares at Rs. 450 per share on 15-Jun-2017. Fair Market Value (FMV) on 31-Jan-2018 was Rs. 520 per share. Sold all shares at Rs. 780 per share on 10-Oct-2025. STT paid on both purchase and sale.

Transaction 2 - Unlisted Shares of StartUp Pvt Ltd: Purchased 5,000 shares at Rs. 30 per share on 01-Apr-2023. Sold all shares at Rs. 85 per share on 15-Dec-2025.

Transaction 3 - Sovereign Gold Bonds (SGBs): Purchased 50 units at Rs. 4,800 per gram on 01-Mar-2020 (8-year maturity). Sold 20 units on NSE at Rs. 7,200 per gram on 20-Sep-2025. Interest received during FY 2025-26: Rs. 12,000.

Transaction 4 - Listed Corporate Bonds: Purchased 500 bonds at Rs. 1,000 face value on 01-Jan-2025. Sold all at Rs. 1,050 on 15-Aug-2025. Annual coupon of 8% received.

Transaction 5 - Bonus Shares of InfoSys Ltd: Meera held 1,000 shares of InfoSys purchased on 01-Mar-2022 at Rs. 1,500 per share. She received 1,000 bonus shares (1:1 ratio) on 15-Jun-2023. She sold all 1,000 bonus shares at Rs. 1,800 per share on 20-Jan-2026. STT paid.

Meera's total salary income is Rs. 25,00,000 (30% tax bracket). She has no other income.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> What is the total tax impact of Meera's Sovereign Gold Bond (SGB) transactions in FY 2025-26, including both capital gains tax on units sold on NSE and tax on interest income?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains tax of Rs. 6,000 (LTCG at 12.5%) plus income tax on interest of Rs. 3,600 (at 30% slab), total Rs. 9,600]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No capital gains tax (SGBs are exempt) plus income tax on interest of Rs. 3,600, total Rs. 3,600]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains tax of Rs. 14,400 (STCG at 30%) plus income tax on interest of Rs. 3,600, total Rs. 18,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains tax of Rs. 6,000 (LTCG at 12.5%) and interest is tax-free, total Rs. 6,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SGB Capital Gains: Purchased Mar-2020, sold Sep-2025 on NSE = holding period of approximately 66 months, which exceeds 12 months — classified as LTCG. Gain = (7,200 - 4,800) x 20 = Rs. 48,000. Important: The capital gains exemption on SGBs applies ONLY when held to maturity (8 years) and redeemed with RBI. Since Meera sold on NSE before maturity, the capital gain is taxable. LTCG on SGBs (listed on exchange) is taxed at 12.5% without indexation. Tax = 12.5% x 48,000 = Rs. 6,000. SGB Interest: The 2.5% annual interest on SGBs is taxable as "Income from Other Sources" at the investor's applicable slab rate. Interest received = Rs. 12,000. Tax = 30% x 12,000 = Rs. 3,600. Total tax impact = Rs. 6,000 + Rs. 3,600 = Rs. 9,600.
**The Trap:** Option B assumes ALL SGB capital gains are exempt — this is wrong; exemption applies ONLY on maturity redemption with RBI, not on exchange sale. Option C incorrectly treats this as STCG (holding period >12 months makes it LTCG). Option D incorrectly assumes SGB interest is tax-free — only the capital gain on maturity is exempt, not the interest.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The SGB tax treatment distinction (maturity vs. pre-maturity sale) is a favourite exam question. Remember: (1) Capital gains on maturity = EXEMPT, (2) Capital gains on exchange sale before maturity = TAXABLE as LTCG/STCG, (3) Interest = ALWAYS taxable at slab rate regardless of how the SGB is disposed.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients to hold SGBs to maturity if capital gains tax exemption is a priority. If liquidity is needed, selling on the exchange triggers taxable capital gains. Also ensure clients report SGB interest in their ITR even though no TDS is deducted on it — this is a common compliance gap.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
