<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following transactions is NOT considered a "transfer" for capital gains purposes under the Income Tax Act?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sale of shares on a recognized stock exchange]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exchange of property as part of a barter arrangement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Transfer of shares by a shareholder in a scheme of amalgamation where shares of the amalgamated company are received]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Relinquishment of rights in a property for monetary consideration]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 47 of the Income Tax Act provides specific exemptions from the definition of "transfer." When shareholders receive shares of the amalgamated company in exchange for shares of the amalgamating company during a scheme of amalgamation, this is NOT treated as a transfer, and no capital gains arise at that point. The cost and holding period of original shares carry forward to the new shares.
**The Trap:** All other options — sale, exchange, and relinquishment — are explicitly listed as forms of "transfer" that trigger capital gains. Candidates may confuse amalgamation with a regular share exchange, but the s.47 exemption specifically covers this.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of "transfer" and its exemptions under s.47 is tested in NISM Series X-A as well. Other notable non-transfers include gifts/will, HUF partition, and MF consolidation.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client's company is being acquired through amalgamation, reassure them that no immediate tax liability arises if they receive shares of the acquiring company. The tax is deferred until they eventually sell the new shares.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
