<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Analysis of Equity and Debt Instruments_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser's client, Nisha, holds the following assets and wants to know which will be treated as long-term if sold today (assume current date is April 2026):
(i) Unlisted equity shares purchased in January 2024
(ii) Listed preference shares purchased in March 2025
(iii) Unlisted REIT units purchased in February 2024
(iv) Physical gold purchased in May 2024
Which combination is correctly classified as long-term capital assets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(i) and (iii) only — unlisted equity >24m and unlisted REIT >24m]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[(i), (ii), and (iii) — all have exceeded their respective thresholds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(i), (iii), and (iv) — all non-listed assets with >24 months holding]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All four are long-term capital assets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Evaluating each asset as of April 2026: (i) Unlisted equity shares (Jan 2024): Held ~27 months. Threshold = >24 months. LTCA. (ii) Listed preference shares (Mar 2025): Held ~13 months. Threshold for listed preference shares = >12 months. LTCA. (iii) Unlisted REIT units (Feb 2024): Held ~26 months. Threshold for unlisted REIT = >24 months. LTCA. (iv) Physical gold (May 2024): Held ~23 months. Threshold = >24 months. NOT yet LTCA — still short-term by one month. Therefore (i), (ii), and (iii) are long-term, but (iv) is not.
**The Trap:** Option A excludes listed preference shares — but listed preference shares need only >12 months (not 24 months) to qualify as LTCA post 23-Jul-2024. Option C includes gold but excludes listed preference shares — gold at 23 months falls just short of the 24-month threshold. Option D includes gold, which is still short-term. The main trap is physical gold narrowly missing the threshold and confusing listed vs unlisted holding periods for preference shares.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Multi-asset holding period analysis is a practical skill tested in NISM X-B. Advisers must know the specific threshold for each asset type — listed vs unlisted makes a critical difference.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a holding period tracker for each client asset. Missing a threshold by even one day means the difference between LTCG at 12.5% and STCG at slab rate (potentially 30%). For gold, the 24-month threshold is particularly important — advise clients to wait the full period.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
