<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser reviewing the insurance portfolio of her client Vikram (age 42), a business owner with annual income of Rs. 25,00,000. Vikram's current insurance portfolio includes: (1) A term life policy of Rs. 2,00,00,000 purchased 4 years ago - Vikram did not disclose his diabetes condition at the time of purchase, (2) Two health insurance (Mediclaim) policies - Policy A with Company X (sum insured Rs. 10,00,000) and Policy B with Company Y (sum insured Rs. 5,00,000), both held continuously for 6 years, (3) A property insurance policy on his factory worth Rs. 50,00,000, (4) A motor insurance policy for his SUV (2200 CC engine). Recently, Vikram's factory was damaged by fire caused by a neighbouring factory's negligence, and the insurer settled the claim for Rs. 30,00,000. Vikram also wants to compare insurance intermediary options - he currently buys through an individual agent but is considering switching to a direct broker. Additionally, Meera is advising Vikram on the correct sequence of insurance planning steps to fill gaps in his coverage.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Meera advises Vikram to follow the correct insurance planning steps to address gaps in his coverage. Which is the correct first step Meera should recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Compare premium quotes from multiple insurers to optimise costs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Select a suitable insurance product based on online reviews]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Identify Vikram's specific insurance needs (income replacement, income protection, asset protection)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Calculate the maximum premium Vikram can afford from his annual income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The correct sequence of insurance planning steps is: (1) Identify need, (2) Estimate coverage, (3) Identify suitable product, (4) Optimise premium, (5) Monitor coverage. The FIRST step is always to identify the client's insurance needs across the three categories: income replacement, income protection, and asset protection. Only after needs are identified should coverage be estimated and products selected.
**The Trap:** Option A (premium optimisation) is step 4, not step 1. Option D (affordability) may influence the final decision but should not drive the initial needs assessment. Starting with products (Option B) or premiums (Options A/D) is a product-push approach rather than a need-based approach.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The insurance planning process is tested in NISM Series X-A and X-B. It mirrors the broader financial planning process (assess → plan → implement → monitor) tested in CFP certification exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A need-based selling approach is not only good practice but also a regulatory requirement. Document the needs analysis conversation with the client. This protects against mis-selling allegations and ensures the client gets appropriate coverage.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
