<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Rajesh (age 35) is a salaried professional earning Rs. 15,00,000 per annum. He lives with his wife Sunita (age 30, homemaker), son Arjun (age 8), and daughter Priya (age 5). Rajesh has the following insurance portfolio: (1) A term life insurance policy of Rs. 1,00,00,000 with his mother Kamala as nominee, (2) A family floater health insurance (Mediclaim) with sum insured Rs. 5,00,000, co-pay clause of 15%, and compulsory deductible of Rs. 5,000, (3) A ULIP policy started 3 years ago with annual premium of Rs. 1,50,000, (4) A car insurance policy for his sedan (1400 CC engine) with compulsory deductible of Rs. 1,000 and voluntary deductible of Rs. 2,000. Recently, Sunita was hospitalised and incurred a bill of Rs. 3,50,000. Rajesh also wants to partially withdraw from his ULIP to fund his son's school admission. His investment adviser has recommended reviewing the nominee structure of his life insurance policy. The adviser also notes that Rajesh's ULIP was sold without any documented suitability analysis.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Rajesh's mother Kamala is the nominee on his term life insurance policy. If Rajesh were to die, what would be the legal position regarding the policy proceeds under the Insurance Act, 1938 (as amended in February 2015)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Kamala, as nominee, is the absolute beneficiary and can retain the entire Rs. 1,00,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The proceeds will be equally divided between Kamala, Sunita, Arjun, and Priya by law]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Kamala is a Beneficial Nominee under Section 39(7) since she is Rajesh's parent, and she is beneficially entitled to the proceeds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Kamala merely holds the proceeds in trust for Rajesh's legal heirs (Sunita, Arjun, and Priya) and must distribute to them]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 39(7) of the Insurance Act, 1938 (amended Feb 2015), a nominee who is a parent, spouse, or child of the policyholder is classified as a "Beneficial Nominee." Kamala, being Rajesh's mother (parent), qualifies as a Beneficial Nominee and is beneficially entitled to the insurance proceeds. She does NOT merely hold them in trust.
**The Trap:** Option D would be correct if Kamala were a sibling, friend, or any other person who is NOT a parent/spouse/child. The general rule is that a nominee holds proceeds in trust for legal heirs, but the Beneficial Nominee exception under Section 39(7) overrides this for parents, spouses, and children. This is a critical distinction.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The Beneficial Nominee concept under Section 39(7) is specifically tested in NISM Series X-B. However, the adviser should note that Rajesh may want to reconsider this nomination given that his wife and young children are financially dependent on him.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While Kamala is legally entitled as a Beneficial Nominee, Rajesh should consider whether his mother (who may have other sources of support) should receive the entire Rs. 1 crore when his wife and two young children are financially dependent on him. Advise splitting the nomination or changing it to spouse and children.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
