<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Anil has a group health insurance policy from his employer (Company X). He is now switching to Company Y after 2 years of continuous coverage. Regarding portability of his health insurance, which statement is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He can port his group policy to any individual policy of any insurance company immediately]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In the first year, he can convert the group policy to an individual policy within the same insurance company; from the second year onwards, he can port to any company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Group policies are not portable at all; he must buy a fresh individual policy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He can port to any company from day one, just like individual policies]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For group health insurance policies, portability rules differ from individual policies. In the first year, the policyholder can convert the group policy to an individual policy WITHIN the same insurance company. From the second year onwards, they can port to any insurance company. Individual policies, by contrast, can be ported to any company at any time.
**The Trap:** Option D treats group policies the same as individual policies, which is incorrect. Option C says group policies are not portable, which was true historically but is no longer the case under current regulations.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Health insurance portability rules are tested in NISM Series X-B. The distinction between individual and group policy portability is a nuanced point that differentiates Level 2 from Level 1.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients leaving their employer to immediately explore portability options. Do not let the group policy lapse without activating portability, as continuous coverage is critical for the 5-year moratorium benefit.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
