<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser reviewing the insurance portfolio of her client Vikram (age 42), a business owner with annual income of Rs. 25,00,000. Vikram's current insurance portfolio includes: (1) A term life policy of Rs. 2,00,00,000 purchased 4 years ago - Vikram did not disclose his diabetes condition at the time of purchase, (2) Two health insurance (Mediclaim) policies - Policy A with Company X (sum insured Rs. 10,00,000) and Policy B with Company Y (sum insured Rs. 5,00,000), both held continuously for 6 years, (3) A property insurance policy on his factory worth Rs. 50,00,000, (4) A motor insurance policy for his SUV (2200 CC engine). Recently, Vikram's factory was damaged by fire caused by a neighbouring factory's negligence, and the insurer settled the claim for Rs. 30,00,000. Vikram also wants to compare insurance intermediary options - he currently buys through an individual agent but is considering switching to a direct broker. Additionally, Meera is advising Vikram on the correct sequence of insurance planning steps to fill gaps in his coverage.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> After settling Vikram's factory fire claim of Rs. 30,00,000, the property insurer now wants to recover this amount from the neighbouring factory whose negligence caused the fire. Which insurance principle gives the insurer this right?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Principle of Contribution - the neighbouring factory's insurer must share the claim]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Principle of Indemnity - the neighbouring factory must be indemnified]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Principle of Subrogation - the insurer steps into the shoes of Vikram and can recover from the negligent third party]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Principle of Utmost Good Faith - the neighbouring factory must disclose its insurance details]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Subrogation is the principle by which the insurer, after paying the claim to the insured, "steps into the shoes" of the insured and acquires the right to recover the claim amount from the third party responsible for the loss. Here, the insurer paid Vikram Rs. 30,00,000 and now has the right to recover this from the neighbouring factory whose negligence caused the fire.
**The Trap:** Contribution is about multiple insurers sharing a claim on the same risk, NOT about recovery from a negligent third party. Indemnity is the broader principle of compensating actual loss - subrogation is a specific mechanism that supports indemnity by preventing double recovery.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Subrogation is applicable only to indemnity insurance (property, motor, health). It does NOT apply to defined benefit policies (life, critical illness). This distinction is tested in NISM Series X-A and X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** After a claim is settled, advise clients to cooperate fully with their insurer's subrogation efforts. The client should not independently settle with the third party or sign any release that might compromise the insurer's subrogation rights.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
