<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser reviewing the insurance portfolio of her client Vikram (age 42), a business owner with annual income of Rs. 25,00,000. Vikram's current insurance portfolio includes: (1) A term life policy of Rs. 2,00,00,000 purchased 4 years ago - Vikram did not disclose his diabetes condition at the time of purchase, (2) Two health insurance (Mediclaim) policies - Policy A with Company X (sum insured Rs. 10,00,000) and Policy B with Company Y (sum insured Rs. 5,00,000), both held continuously for 6 years, (3) A property insurance policy on his factory worth Rs. 50,00,000, (4) A motor insurance policy for his SUV (2200 CC engine). Recently, Vikram's factory was damaged by fire caused by a neighbouring factory's negligence, and the insurer settled the claim for Rs. 30,00,000. Vikram also wants to compare insurance intermediary options - he currently buys through an individual agent but is considering switching to a direct broker. Additionally, Meera is advising Vikram on the correct sequence of insurance planning steps to fill gaps in his coverage.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Vikram did not disclose his diabetes condition when purchasing his term life insurance 4 years ago. If Vikram files a claim now (after 4 years), what is the insurer's position under Section 45 of the Insurance Act?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The insurer can reject the claim because non-disclosure of a medical condition is always grounds for rejection]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The insurer cannot question the policy after 3 years from commencement; since 4 years have passed, the claim cannot be contested on grounds of non-disclosure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The insurer can reject the claim because the non-disclosure period is 5 years for life insurance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The insurer must pay the claim but can deduct a penalty equivalent to the additional premium that should have been charged]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 45 of the Insurance Act, a life insurance policy cannot be questioned after 3 years from the date of policy commencement, risk commencement, or revival (whichever is later). Since Vikram's policy was purchased 4 years ago and has not been revived, the 3-year period has elapsed. The insurer cannot contest the claim on grounds of non-disclosure of diabetes.
**The Trap:** Option C confuses the 5-year moratorium period for health insurance with the 3-year incontestability period for life insurance under Section 45. Option A ignores the statutory time limit altogether. These are the two most common errors candidates make.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Section 45 is a critical provision tested in NISM Series X-A and X-B. Note that while non-disclosure AFTER 3 years cannot be contested, proven FRAUD during the first 3 years can still be a basis for denial.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While Section 45 protects policyholders after 3 years, always emphasise to clients that full disclosure at the time of purchase is the safest approach. Relying on the 3-year window is risky - if the insured dies within 3 years, the family may face claim rejection when they need it most.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
