<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Rajesh (age 35) is a salaried professional earning Rs. 15,00,000 per annum. He lives with his wife Sunita (age 30, homemaker), son Arjun (age 8), and daughter Priya (age 5). Rajesh has the following insurance portfolio: (1) A term life insurance policy of Rs. 1,00,00,000 with his mother Kamala as nominee, (2) A family floater health insurance (Mediclaim) with sum insured Rs. 5,00,000, co-pay clause of 15%, and compulsory deductible of Rs. 5,000, (3) A ULIP policy started 3 years ago with annual premium of Rs. 1,50,000, (4) A car insurance policy for his sedan (1400 CC engine) with compulsory deductible of Rs. 1,000 and voluntary deductible of Rs. 2,000. Recently, Sunita was hospitalised and incurred a bill of Rs. 3,50,000. Rajesh also wants to partially withdraw from his ULIP to fund his son's school admission. His investment adviser has recommended reviewing the nominee structure of his life insurance policy. The adviser also notes that Rajesh's ULIP was sold without any documented suitability analysis.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> The adviser discovers that Rajesh's ULIP was sold without any documented suitability analysis. What is the regulatory implication of this?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no regulatory requirement for suitability analysis for ULIPs; it applies only to traditional plans]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The policy is automatically void if suitability analysis was not conducted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Insurance companies cannot issue investment-cum-insurance policies without suitability analysis; the only exception is written consent from the policyholder to skip it]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suitability analysis is required only when the annual premium exceeds Rs. 2,00,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulations mandate that insurance companies cannot issue investment-cum-insurance policies (including ULIPs) without conducting a suitability analysis. The agent must justify why the product is suitable for the client. The only exception is when the policyholder provides written consent to skip the suitability analysis. If Rajesh did not provide such written consent, the sale may be considered non-compliant.
**The Trap:** Option B is too extreme - the policy is not automatically void; it is a regulatory compliance issue for the insurer/agent, not a policy validity issue. Option D invents a premium threshold that does not exist in the regulations.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Suitability analysis requirements are tested in NISM Series X-B and align with SEBI's suitability requirements for investment advisers. The concept of protecting clients from mis-selling through documented suitability is a cross-cutting regulatory theme.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always maintain a documented suitability analysis for every investment-cum-insurance product sold. This protects both the client (from mis-selling) and the distributor (from regulatory action and client complaints). Keep records for at least the policy term plus 5 years.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
