<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When evaluating an investment-cum-insurance product like a ULIP or endowment plan, what approach does the NISM curriculum recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Evaluate only the investment return component since insurance coverage is always adequate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Compare the product only with other insurance products, not with pure investment options]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Decouple the insurance and investment components and evaluate each separately, prioritising adequacy of risk coverage first]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Focus solely on the tax benefits offered by the product]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The NISM curriculum explicitly recommends decoupling the insurance component and the investment component of investment-cum-insurance products. The adequacy of risk coverage should be evaluated first (is the sum assured sufficient?), and then the investment return should be assessed separately against pure investment alternatives.
**The Trap:** Option A ignores insurance adequacy, which is the primary purpose of insurance. Option B restricts comparison to insurance products only, but the curriculum recommends comparing the investment component with standalone investment products (mutual funds, etc.).
**Cross-Exam Context:** This concept is fundamental to NISM Series X-B and is also reflected in SEBI's advisory on investment advisers recommending insurance products. The principle of separating protection and investment is central to holistic financial planning.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Many investment-cum-insurance products provide inadequate life cover (e.g., 10x annual premium) while underperforming as investments due to high charges. A term plan + mutual fund SIP combination often provides better risk coverage AND higher investment returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
