<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The NISM curriculum uses the analogy of a cricket batsman to explain a key insurance concept. What does the analogy "a batsman wears protective gear before going out to bat" illustrate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Insurance products should be selected based on the highest returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Insurance coverage should be equal to the total investment portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Insurance should come before investments in personal financial planning]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Insurance premiums should be minimised to maximise investment corpus]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The cricket batsman analogy illustrates that just as a batsman puts on protective gear (helmet, pads, gloves) BEFORE batting (scoring runs), a person must first secure adequate insurance coverage BEFORE making investments. Insurance is the protective foundation of financial planning.
**The Trap:** Option D suggests minimising premiums to invest more, which contradicts the principle. The analogy emphasises that protection (insurance) is a prerequisite, not an afterthought or something to be minimised in favour of investments.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The role of insurance in personal financial planning is tested in NISM Series X-A, X-B, and also in CFP certification. The hierarchy is: Protection → Savings → Investments → Wealth creation.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use this analogy with clients who resist buying insurance and want to invest all their money. Ask them: "Would you go out to bat against a fast bowler without a helmet?" Insurance is non-negotiable protection before wealth creation begins.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
