<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Death is a certain event, yet life insurance is a valid form of insurance. Which characteristic of insurable risk does life insurance satisfy despite the certainty of death?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The loss must be entirely accidental in every case]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[While death is certain, the timing of death is uncertain, satisfying the requirement of uncertainty]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Life insurance is an exception that does not need to satisfy any insurable risk requirements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The insured must prove that death will be accidental to obtain life cover]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** One requirement of insurable risk is that the event must be accidental and unintentional. Life insurance is an acknowledged exception because while death itself is certain, the TIMING of death is uncertain. This uncertainty of timing satisfies the requirement of uncertainty in insurance.
**The Trap:** Option C suggests life insurance is completely exempt from insurable risk requirements, which is incorrect - it must still satisfy other requirements like insurable interest, large number of exposure units, etc. Option D incorrectly suggests death must be proven accidental.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This conceptual question is tested in NISM Series X-A and X-B. Understanding exceptions to general rules is a hallmark of Level 2 examination depth.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use this concept to explain to clients why term insurance premiums increase with age - as the uncertainty of timing decreases (older age = higher probability of death in near term), the risk to the insurer increases, hence higher premiums.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
