<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The principle of "Utmost Good Faith" (Uberrimae Fidei) in insurance places a duty on which party to disclose all material facts?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the insurer must disclose all policy terms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The insured must disclose all relevant information to the insurer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The insurance agent must disclose all competitors' products]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both insurer and insured share equal duty, but neither can reject claims for non-disclosure]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The principle of Utmost Good Faith (Uberrimae Fidei) requires the insured to disclose all relevant and material information to the insurer at the time of purchasing the policy. If any material information is suppressed or misrepresented, the insurer has the right to reject the claim.
**The Trap:** Option D is partially correct (both parties do have duties), but the key consequence - that the insurer CAN reject claims for non-disclosure by the insured - makes it incorrect. The primary burden of disclosure rests on the insured.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Utmost Good Faith is a fundamental insurance principle tested across NISM Series X-A, X-B, and IRDA examinations. It also has parallels with disclosure requirements in securities regulations.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always counsel clients to disclose every health condition, lifestyle habit (smoking, alcohol), and occupational hazard during proposal stage. Non-disclosure discovered during claim time leads to rejection, which is the worst possible outcome for the family.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
