<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser reviewing the insurance portfolio of her client Vikram (age 42), a business owner with annual income of Rs. 25,00,000. Vikram's current insurance portfolio includes: (1) A term life policy of Rs. 2,00,00,000 purchased 4 years ago - Vikram did not disclose his diabetes condition at the time of purchase, (2) Two health insurance (Mediclaim) policies - Policy A with Company X (sum insured Rs. 10,00,000) and Policy B with Company Y (sum insured Rs. 5,00,000), both held continuously for 6 years, (3) A property insurance policy on his factory worth Rs. 50,00,000, (4) A motor insurance policy for his SUV (2200 CC engine). Recently, Vikram's factory was damaged by fire caused by a neighbouring factory's negligence, and the insurer settled the claim for Rs. 30,00,000. Vikram also wants to compare insurance intermediary options - he currently buys through an individual agent but is considering switching to a direct broker. Additionally, Meera is advising Vikram on the correct sequence of insurance planning steps to fill gaps in his coverage.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Vikram is considering switching from his current insurance agent to a direct broker for purchasing insurance. Which of the following correctly describes the key advantage of using a direct broker over an insurance agent?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A direct broker charges no fees and earns only from commission, making it cheaper for the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A direct broker represents the client (not the insurer), can compare products across multiple insurers, and can charge both fee and commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A direct broker can represent up to 3 life, 3 general, and 3 health insurance companies simultaneously]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A direct broker is the same as a web aggregator and can only operate online]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Direct Broker represents the CLIENT (not the insurer), can compare products across the entire market, and can charge both a fee and commission. An Insurance Agent, by contrast, represents the INSURER and earns only commission. For Vikram, a direct broker would provide unbiased product comparison across all insurers, which is especially valuable given his complex insurance needs.
**The Trap:** Option A incorrectly states brokers charge no fees - they can charge BOTH fee and commission. Option C describes a Corporate Agent (composite), not a direct broker. Option D confuses a direct broker with a web aggregator - web aggregators only provide online price comparison, while brokers provide comprehensive advisory services.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between different insurance intermediaries (agent, broker, corporate agent, web aggregator) is tested in NISM Series X-B. Understanding whose interest each intermediary represents is critical for advising clients on channel selection.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For high-net-worth clients like Vikram with complex insurance needs spanning life, health, property, and motor, a direct broker can add significant value through comprehensive market analysis. The fee charged by the broker is often justified by better product selection and claims advocacy.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
