<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the moratorium period in health insurance?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[After 3 continuous years of coverage, no claim can be contested by the insurer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[After 5 continuous years of coverage, no claim can be contested including proven fraud]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[After 5 continuous years of coverage, no claim can be contested except on grounds of proven fraud and permanent exclusion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[After 7 continuous years of coverage, claims become absolutely incontestable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The health insurance moratorium period is 5 continuous years. After this period, no claim shall be contestable by the insurer except on grounds of proven fraud and permanent exclusion. This protects policyholders who have maintained continuous coverage.
**The Trap:** Option A confuses the 3-year contestability period for life insurance (Section 45) with the health insurance moratorium. Option B is almost correct but removes the fraud/permanent exclusion exception, which always remains.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between the 3-year incontestability for life insurance and the 5-year moratorium for health insurance is a high-frequency question in NISM Series X-B. Also note: if sum insured is enhanced, the 5-year moratorium starts afresh from the date of enhancement.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients to maintain continuous health insurance coverage without breaks. After 5 continuous years, they gain significant protection against claim denial. Switching insurers (portability) does not reset this clock if done properly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
