<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Securities and Types_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Kavita invested in a Fully Convertible Debenture (FCD) issued by GHI Ltd. Which of the following is an advantage to the issuer of FCDs compared to plain equity shares?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FCDs provide permanent equity capital from the date of issuance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[FCDs offer a lower coupon rate than non-convertible debentures and require no cash outflow for principal repayment on maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FCDs eliminate the risk of equity dilution for existing shareholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FCDs are exempt from all SEBI regulations on issuance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FCDs convert entirely into equity shares on maturity. The issuer benefits because: (1) the coupon rate is lower than non-convertible debentures since investors accept lower interest for the equity conversion upside, and (2) there is no cash outflow for repaying principal at maturity since the debentures convert to equity instead.
**The Trap:** Option A is wrong because FCDs start as debt and become equity only on conversion. Option C is the opposite — FCDs CAUSE equity dilution when they convert. This is actually a risk for existing shareholders.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) covers FCD/PCD/NCD issuance regulations. Series V-A (MF Distributors) tests convertible instruments as hybrid products.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** FCDs are attractive to investors who want current income (coupons) plus future equity upside. However, they should be aware that conversion terms and the company's equity value at conversion time determine the real return.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
