<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Rajesh (age 35) is a salaried professional earning Rs. 15,00,000 per annum. He lives with his wife Sunita (age 30, homemaker), son Arjun (age 8), and daughter Priya (age 5). Rajesh has the following insurance portfolio: (1) A term life insurance policy of Rs. 1,00,00,000 with his mother Kamala as nominee, (2) A family floater health insurance (Mediclaim) with sum insured Rs. 5,00,000, co-pay clause of 15%, and compulsory deductible of Rs. 5,000, (3) A ULIP policy started 3 years ago with annual premium of Rs. 1,50,000, (4) A car insurance policy for his sedan (1400 CC engine) with compulsory deductible of Rs. 1,000 and voluntary deductible of Rs. 2,000. Recently, Sunita was hospitalised and incurred a bill of Rs. 3,50,000. Rajesh also wants to partially withdraw from his ULIP to fund his son's school admission. His investment adviser has recommended reviewing the nominee structure of his life insurance policy. The adviser also notes that Rajesh's ULIP was sold without any documented suitability analysis.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Rajesh wants to make a partial withdrawal from his ULIP policy (started 3 years ago) to fund Arjun's school admission. What is the correct regulatory position?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He can make partial withdrawals since he has paid premiums for 3 consecutive years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He can surrender the policy without surrender charges after 3 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He cannot make partial withdrawals as the 5-year lock-in period has not been completed; he must wait 2 more years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He can make partial withdrawals up to 25% of the fund value after 3 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ULIP regulations mandate a strict 5-year lock-in period. Partial withdrawals are permitted ONLY after the completion of 5 years. Rajesh's ULIP is only 3 years old, so he must wait 2 more years before making any partial withdrawal. Additionally, no surrender charges apply only after 5 policy years.
**The Trap:** Option D invents a "25% after 3 years" rule that does not exist. Option A incorrectly equates premium payment years with the lock-in period. These are designed to trap candidates who confuse ULIP rules with other product rules.
**Cross-Exam Context:** ULIP lock-in and withdrawal rules are tested in NISM Series X-B and IRDA exams. Compare with mutual fund exit loads (typically 1 year for equity funds) and PPF lock-in (15 years with partial withdrawal after 7 years).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before selling a ULIP, always check if the client might need liquidity within 5 years. For goals within 5 years (like school admission fees), recommend more liquid products like debt mutual funds or fixed deposits instead of ULIPs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
