<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Regarding Top-up and Super Top-up health insurance policies, which of the following statements is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They do not have any deductible and cover all expenses from the first rupee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are designed to replace the base health insurance policy entirely]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[They are designed with a fixed deductible and provide coverage above that threshold, supplementing the base policy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They can only be purchased from the same insurer who provides the base health policy]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Top-up and Super Top-up health insurance policies are specifically designed with a fixed deductible. They provide coverage for expenses that exceed the deductible amount. The deductible is typically set equal to the base policy's sum insured, so the top-up/super top-up kicks in when the base policy is exhausted.
**The Trap:** Option A is incorrect because deductibles are the defining feature of top-up policies. Option D is incorrect because these policies can be purchased from any insurer, not necessarily the same one that provides the base cover.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Top-up and Super Top-up policies are tested in NISM Series X-B. The difference between a Top-up (deductible per claim) and Super Top-up (deductible on aggregate claims in a year) is an advanced concept.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Super Top-up policies are more client-friendly than plain Top-ups because the deductible is applied on aggregate claims in a policy year, not per hospitalisation. They are a cost-effective way to increase health coverage without paying for a high base sum insured.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
