<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Rajesh (age 35) is a salaried professional earning Rs. 15,00,000 per annum. He lives with his wife Sunita (age 30, homemaker), son Arjun (age 8), and daughter Priya (age 5). Rajesh has the following insurance portfolio: (1) A term life insurance policy of Rs. 1,00,00,000 with his mother Kamala as nominee, (2) A family floater health insurance (Mediclaim) with sum insured Rs. 5,00,000, co-pay clause of 15%, and compulsory deductible of Rs. 5,000, (3) A ULIP policy started 3 years ago with annual premium of Rs. 1,50,000, (4) A car insurance policy for his sedan (1400 CC engine) with compulsory deductible of Rs. 1,000 and voluntary deductible of Rs. 2,000. Recently, Sunita was hospitalised and incurred a bill of Rs. 3,50,000. Rajesh also wants to partially withdraw from his ULIP to fund his son's school admission. His investment adviser has recommended reviewing the nominee structure of his life insurance policy. The adviser also notes that Rajesh's ULIP was sold without any documented suitability analysis.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> If Rajesh had instead opted for a policy with NO co-pay but a higher compulsory deductible of Rs. 25,000, how much would the insurer have paid on Sunita's Rs. 3,50,000 hospitalisation bill, and how does this compare with his current policy's payout?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3,25,000; which is Rs. 25,750 more than the current policy - the alternative is always better]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3,25,000; which is Rs. 31,750 more than the current policy's payout of Rs. 2,93,250]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3,50,000; the insurer pays the full amount when there is no co-pay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3,12,500; because the deductible is applied twice]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** With no co-pay and deductible of Rs. 25,000: Insurer pays Rs. 3,50,000 - Rs. 25,000 = Rs. 3,25,000. Current policy pays Rs. 2,93,250 (calculated in Q1). Difference = Rs. 3,25,000 - Rs. 2,93,250 = Rs. 31,750 more under the alternative policy. However, this comparison is for a single claim - the premium difference and claim frequency should also be considered.
**The Trap:** Option A gets the insurer payout correct (Rs. 3,25,000) but calculates the difference incorrectly. Option C forgets the deductible entirely. This question tests whether candidates can apply and compare two different policy structures.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the trade-off between co-pay and deductible is tested in NISM Series X-B. This is a practical decision clients face when choosing health insurance features.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Co-pay reduces the insurer's payout proportionally on every claim, while a higher deductible is a fixed cost regardless of claim size. For large claims, a higher deductible with no co-pay is often better. For small claims, no deductible with co-pay may be preferable. Advise based on the client's health risk profile.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
