<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Basics of Insurance_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An insurance company wants to issue an investment-cum-insurance policy to a client. Under current regulations, which of the following is correct regarding suitability analysis?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suitability analysis is optional and at the discretion of the insurer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suitability analysis is required only for policies with premium above Rs. 1,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The insurer cannot issue the policy without conducting a suitability analysis, unless the policyholder provides written consent to skip it]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suitability analysis is required only for ULIPs, not for other investment-cum-insurance products]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Insurance companies cannot issue an investment-cum-insurance policy without conducting a suitability analysis. The agent must justify why the product is suitable for the client. The only exception is when the policyholder provides written consent to skip the suitability analysis.
**The Trap:** Option A suggests it is optional, which is incorrect - it is mandatory by default. Option D limits it to ULIPs only, but the requirement applies to ALL investment-cum-insurance products. The written consent exception in Option C is the key differentiator.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Suitability requirements are tested in NISM Series X-A, X-B, and also in SEBI's Investment Adviser regulations. The concept of suitability analysis is central to the fiduciary duty of advisers.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always document the suitability analysis thoroughly. If a client later complains about product mis-selling, the suitability report is your primary defence. Never skip it just because the client is in a hurry - get written consent if they insist on skipping.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
