<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Geeta, aged 35, buys a ULIP with INR 1.5 lakh annual premium primarily for Section 80C tax saving. Her adviser points out this may not be optimal. Which approach does the adviser recommend as a better alternative for combining insurance and tax-efficient investment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An endowment policy with higher sum assured for better tax benefits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Increasing the ULIP premium to INR 2.5 lakh for enhanced returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A term insurance policy for pure protection plus PPF for tax-saving investment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A combination of multiple endowment policies across different insurers]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Buying insurance primarily for tax saving is the wrong approach. A term policy provides pure life cover at low cost, while PPF (Public Provident Fund) offers tax-free returns under Section 80C. The combination "term policy + PPF" beats an endowment policy or ULIP bought solely for tax saving, as it separates insurance and investment needs efficiently.
**The Trap:** Endowment policies combine insurance and investment but typically deliver sub-par returns (4-6% pre-tax). Increasing ULIP premium doesn't address the fundamental problem of mixing insurance with investment. The adviser must find the "golden mean" — adequate coverage plus efficient investment.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) and X-A (Investment Adviser Level 1) both emphasize goal-based planning where insurance and investment are separate buckets. ELSS funds are another Section 80C option with equity market-linked returns.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always separate protection (term plan) from wealth creation (mutual funds, PPF, NPS). When a client says "I want insurance for tax saving," it's a red flag — educate them on the cost of bundling.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
