<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser is designing a risk tolerance questionnaire. She knows that framing can significantly impact client responses. What is the BEST approach to handle framing bias in risk profiling?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Use only gain-framed questions to make clients feel positive about investing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Use only loss-framed questions to ensure conservative allocations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Diagnose the client's preference for gain or loss framing, and discuss inconsistencies through detailed conversation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Avoid using questionnaires altogether and rely solely on the client's stated preferences]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Some clients prefer gain framing while others respond more to loss framing. The adviser must diagnose which framing resonates with each client and hold a detailed discussion to uncover the true risk tolerance. Simply using one type of framing will systematically bias the results in one direction.
**The Trap:** Using only gain-framed questions will overestimate risk tolerance, while using only loss-framed questions will underestimate it. Avoiding questionnaires entirely is not practical — SEBI regulations require documented risk profiling. The correct approach is diagnosis + discussion.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A (Investment Adviser Level 1) mandates risk profiling as part of the advisory process. Understanding framing bias ensures that the profiling tool itself doesn't introduce systematic errors.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** After completing the questionnaire, discuss the results with the client: "Your answers suggest moderate risk tolerance, but you seemed more cautious when I described potential losses. Let's explore this together." This conversation is more valuable than the score itself.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
