<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ramesh is negotiating to buy a flat in Pune. The seller initially quotes INR 1.2 crore. Even after independent valuation suggests INR 95 lakh, Ramesh finds himself negotiating around INR 1.05-1.10 crore. Similarly, when evaluating a stock, he keeps comparing the current price to its 52-week high of INR 850. Which cognitive error explains BOTH behaviors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Anchoring Bias — relying on initial or pre-existing information as a reference point]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Endowment Bias — overvaluing assets that one already owns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Status Quo Bias — preferring to maintain the current situation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mental Accounting — assigning different values based on categories]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Anchoring Bias is the tendency to rely heavily on pre-existing or initial information when making decisions. The first price quoted in a negotiation becomes the "anchor," and past stock performance (52-week high) serves as an anchor for future expectations. Both behaviors show Ramesh anchoring to irrelevant reference points.
**The Trap:** Endowment Bias would apply if Ramesh already owned the flat or stock and overvalued it. Mental Accounting involves treating money differently by source. The common thread here is fixation on an initial number, which is classic anchoring.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) covers option pricing where strike prices can act as psychological anchors. Traders often anchor to round numbers (Nifty 20,000) creating support/resistance levels.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients fixate on a stock's past high ("it was at INR 850, it will go back"), redirect them to intrinsic valuation metrics. The 52-week high is an anchor, not a target. Focus on fundamentals, not historical prices.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
