<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Nandini, a 45-year-old single mother in Chennai, has limited resources. Her two goals are: (1) Daughter Priya's engineering education in 3 years — INR 15 lakh, and (2) Her own retirement in 15 years — INR 1 crore. She can save only INR 30,000 per month. As her adviser, what is the MOST appropriate behavioral-finance-aware recommendation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest everything in equity for maximum growth to meet both goals]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Abandon the retirement goal entirely and focus only on Priya's education]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Prioritize Priya's education with a partial education loan, and allocate remaining savings toward retirement through equity SIPs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest in a single balanced fund that will automatically address both goals]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When resources are insufficient for all goals, the adviser must help prioritize. The adviser manages the greed-fear cycle by suggesting practical solutions: a partial education loan for Priya's education (leveraging the tax benefit under Section 80E) while continuing equity SIPs for the longer-term retirement goal. This balances emotional priority (daughter's education) with financial prudence (not sacrificing retirement).
**The Trap:** Investing everything in equity ignores the 3-year short-term horizon for education — equity is too volatile for goals within 3-5 years. Abandoning retirement entirely is emotionally driven, not rational. A single balanced fund doesn't address the different time horizons and risk profiles of the two goals.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers goal-based financial planning and asset allocation by time horizon. Education loans and their tax treatment under Section 80E are tested in both X-A and X-B exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client has conflicting goals, never frame it as "choose one." Instead, show how partial solutions (education loan + SIP) can address both. The adviser's role is to expand the solution space, not just allocate existing resources.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
