<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Deepak has not rebalanced his portfolio in 3 years despite significant equity appreciation. He avoids making changes because he fears that any action might lead to regret. His adviser notes that Deepak feels regret from commission (acting) more strongly than regret from omission (not acting). Richard Thaler's solution to this type of bias is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing detailed past performance data to build confidence]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Reducing the number of investment options available to the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Auto-enrollment or default options, such as automatic pension plan enrollment (nudging)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Increasing the client's exposure to financial literacy workshops]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Deepak exhibits Status Quo Bias linked to Regret Aversion — he avoids decisions because regret from commission (acting and being wrong) feels worse than regret from omission (not acting). Richard Thaler's famous nudge solution is auto-enrollment in pension plans — by making the desired action the default, the bias toward inaction actually works in the investor's favor.
**The Trap:** Financial literacy workshops address knowledge gaps, not emotional biases. Providing past performance data may increase overconfidence rather than address status quo bias. The nudge approach is specifically Thaler's contribution.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers pension planning (NPS). Understanding why auto-enrollment works (exploiting status quo bias positively) is directly relevant to advising on NPS contributions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Set up SIPs and automatic rebalancing triggers at the start of the advisory relationship. Once these are the "default," status quo bias works FOR the client — they'll stick with the disciplined plan.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
