<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Research shows that when employees are asked to rate their own performance, the majority rate themselves in the 60th to 75th percentile. Why is this finding significant in the context of investment advisory?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It proves that most investors are genuinely above average in financial literacy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It is an arithmetic impossibility that demonstrates widespread overconfidence bias, which the adviser must account for when clients claim superior investment ability]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It indicates that self-assessment questionnaires are the most reliable risk profiling tool]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It shows that anchoring to the 60-75 percentile range is a universal cognitive phenomenon]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If most people rate themselves between the 60th and 75th percentile, it is an arithmetic impossibility — by definition, only 25-40% can actually be in that range. This demonstrates widespread overconfidence bias. In investment advisory, this manifests when clients who made a small winning bet (say 5X return) become overconfident and want to aggressively modify their asset allocation.
**The Trap:** This finding does NOT prove people are actually above average — it proves the opposite (that they overestimate themselves). It is not anchoring bias — the employees are not fixating on an external reference number; they genuinely believe they are above average.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers suitability assessment. An overconfident client may push for aggressive allocation unsuitable to their actual risk capacity. The adviser must diplomatically manage this gap between perceived and actual competence.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client says "I know what I'm doing, just give me higher equity exposure," ask them to recall their worst investment loss and how it felt. Concrete loss experiences counter overconfidence better than abstract warnings.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
