<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Sunita wants to invest INR 10 lakh but has been researching options for 6 months without making a decision. Her adviser has presented her with 15 different mutual fund schemes across multiple categories. Sunita's inability to decide is MOST likely caused by:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overconfidence Bias — she believes she can find the perfect scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Loss Aversion — she fears losing her INR 10 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Choice Paralysis — too many options leading to decision avoidance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Anchoring Bias — she is fixated on a past return figure]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Choice Paralysis occurs when too many options or too much information leads to decision avoidance and inaction. The adviser presenting 15 schemes across multiple categories has overwhelmed Sunita, causing her to defer the decision indefinitely.
**The Trap:** Loss aversion might contribute to hesitation, but the specific trigger here is information overload from too many choices. An overconfident investor would actually decide quickly (perhaps too quickly), not delay for 6 months.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) requires distributors to recommend suitable schemes. Presenting too many options violates the spirit of suitability — the adviser should curate 2-3 relevant options, not dump the entire fund universe on the client.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Follow the "Rule of 3" — present at most 3 well-researched options with clear rationale for each. This respects bounded rationality and prevents choice paralysis. Less is more in financial advice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
