<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Vikram, a day trader in Hyderabad, made INR 2 lakh profit in a bull market. He now trades with concentrated bets in a single sector, ignoring diversification. He says, "I have a special ability to read the market." When his trades go wrong, he blames market manipulation. This combination of biases is BEST described as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Loss aversion combined with anchoring bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mental accounting combined with framing bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Endowment bias combined with status quo bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Overconfidence bias combined with self-attribution bias]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Overconfidence Bias is unwarranted faith in one's own judgment, leading to portfolio concentration, excessive trading, and sector/country bias. Self-Attribution Bias means crediting success to skill and blaming failure on external factors. Combined, these biases cause investors to "confuse their brain with a bull market."
**The Trap:** Loss aversion would make Vikram hold losing positions, not trade more aggressively. Mental accounting involves treating money differently by source — while related, the primary issue here is overconfidence driving concentrated, excessive trading.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) covers the risks of concentrated positions and leverage. Overconfident traders often use derivatives aggressively, amplifying losses.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client claims special market-reading ability after a winning streak, gently ask: "Did your peers also make money in this period?" If yes, it's likely the market, not skill. Recommend maintaining diversification regardless of recent success.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
