<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser recommends a pre-decided asset allocation with upper limits per asset class, a Nifty 500 index fund for broad diversification instead of multiple schemes, and a monthly SIP for disciplined investing. Which behavioral finance principles does this strategy address?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It addresses anchoring bias and stereotype bias by using passive index investing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It addresses framing bias and prospect theory by focusing on long-term wealth creation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Upper limits prevent overexposure from overconfidence, a broad index counters home/sector bias and excessive diversification, and SIP counters action bias and emotional timing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It only addresses choice paralysis by reducing the number of investment decisions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** This strategy addresses multiple biases simultaneously: (1) Pre-decided upper limits per asset class prevent overexposure driven by overconfidence or greed. (2) A top-500 index fund provides broad diversification, countering both concentrated portfolios (too few stocks) and excessive diversification (too many overlapping schemes) — both of which are bad. It also counters home/sector bias. (3) SIP enforces disciplined investing, countering action bias (too many transactions) and emotional market timing.
**The Trap:** While choice paralysis is partially addressed (fewer decisions), the strategy's benefits go far beyond just reducing choices. Anchoring and stereotype bias are not the primary biases addressed by asset allocation limits and indexing. The comprehensive answer captures all three structural elements and their corresponding biases.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) covers index funds and SIPs as investor tools. NISM Series X-A covers asset allocation and rebalancing. This question integrates behavioral awareness with practical product knowledge.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The simplest portfolios are often the best. A 3-fund approach (equity index + debt fund + gold ETF) with pre-set allocation bands and monthly SIP is a powerful, bias-resistant strategy. Complexity is the enemy of execution.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
