<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser uses "Fusion Investing" — integrating fundamental analysis with behavioral finance insights. As Benjamin Graham said, "In the short run, the market is a voting machine, but in the long run it is a weighing machine." What are the three steps of the Fusion Investing approach?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Technical screening → Sentiment analysis → Momentum trading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Value screening (P/E, P/BV, P/S) → Fundamental strength (Piotroski Score 0-9) → Momentum filter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk profiling → Asset allocation → Periodic rebalancing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Top-down sector selection → Bottom-up stock picking → Portfolio optimization]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Fusion Investing integrates fundamental analysis with behavioral finance in three steps: (1) Value screening using ratios like P/E, P/BV, and P/S to find undervalued stocks; (2) Fundamental strength assessment using the Piotroski Score (scaled 0-9); (3) A momentum filter to time entry. This combines Graham's value approach with behavioral momentum insights.
**The Trap:** "Risk profiling → Asset allocation → Rebalancing" is a valid financial planning process but describes the advisory workflow, not the Fusion Investing stock selection methodology. Technical screening and sentiment analysis are not part of the three-step fusion framework.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XV (Research Analyst) covers fundamental valuation ratios like P/E and P/BV. The Piotroski Score uses financial statement data, linking to accounting knowledge tested across multiple NISM exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Fusion Investing is practical — screen the BSE 500 universe by low P/E, check Piotroski Score (aim for 7+), then apply a 6-month momentum filter. This systematic approach counters emotional buying and selling.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
