<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Anita inherited 500 shares of a PSU bank stock from her late father. Despite the stock underperforming the Nifty Bank index for 5 years, she refuses to sell, saying "These shares are special — Papa bought them." Which bias is Anita displaying, and what are its two key attributes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Endowment Bias — valuing ownership disproportionately and loss aversion toward owned assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Status Quo Bias — fear of making a wrong decision and maintaining the current portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Anchoring Bias — fixating on the original purchase price as the reference point]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Disposition Effect — holding losers and selling winners too early]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Endowment Bias causes people to value an asset more simply because they own it. It has two key attributes: (1) disproportionately valuing ownership, and (2) loss aversion toward the owned asset. Inherited stocks are a classic example — they are rarely sold regardless of performance.
**The Trap:** Status Quo Bias is about avoiding decisions altogether. Disposition Effect is about the pattern of selling winners and holding losers. Anita's attachment is specifically about the emotional value of ownership (inherited from her father), not just reluctance to realize a loss.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A tests on portfolio rebalancing. Endowment bias is a major obstacle to rebalancing because clients refuse to sell inherited or emotionally significant holdings.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients attached to inherited stocks, suggest keeping a symbolic quantity (say 50 shares) and redeploying the rest. This honors the emotional connection while improving portfolio efficiency.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
