<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Kavita receives a bonus of INR 5 lakh and immediately invests it in a speculative small-cap stock, saying "It's bonus money — I can afford to lose it." However, she would never invest her salary savings in such a risky stock. According to Richard Thaler (1999), which bias does this illustrate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Prospect Theory — evaluating gains and losses relative to a reference point]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mental Accounting — treating money differently based on its source despite money being fungible]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overconfidence Bias — unwarranted faith in her stock-picking ability]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Framing Bias — responding differently depending on how information is presented]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mental Accounting, conceptualized by Richard Thaler (1999), is the tendency to treat money differently based on its origin or intended use, even though money is fungible (INR 1 from bonus = INR 1 from salary). Kavita creates separate mental "buckets" and applies different risk tolerances to each, which is irrational.
**The Trap:** Prospect Theory deals with asymmetric reactions to gains vs losses, not the source of money. While Kavita may also be overconfident, the primary bias shown is mental accounting — she treats windfall gains differently from earned income.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) teaches that risk profiling should apply to the client's ENTIRE financial situation. Mental accounting causes clients to assess risk for each "bucket" separately, leading to suboptimal overall portfolios.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remind clients that all money — salary, bonus, inheritance, lottery — has the same purchasing power. A consolidated financial plan treats all resources as one pool aligned to goals, not separate buckets with different risk rules.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
