<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE about market bubbles as described by Kindleberger (1978)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Bubbles only form in equity markets and never in commodity or real estate markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sir Isaac Newton profited from the Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1630s by selling early]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Conditions that foster bubbles include inexperienced traders, high uncertainty about true value, possible leveraged buying, and difficulty in short selling]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Tech Bubble of the 2000s was the first recorded market bubble in financial history]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Kindleberger (1978) identified conditions that foster bubbles: inexperienced traders entering the market, high uncertainty about the true value of assets, leveraged buying amplifying demand, and difficulty in short selling (preventing price correction). Historical examples include Dutch Tulip Mania (1630s), South Sea Bubble (1720s), and Tech Bubble (2000s).
**The Trap:** Newton lost GBP 20,000 in the South Sea Bubble (1720s), not the Dutch Tulip Mania. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1630s was the first recorded bubble, not the Tech Bubble. Bubbles have formed in tulips, real estate, and many asset classes — not just equities.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XII (Securities Markets) covers market regulation designed to prevent bubbles, including circuit breakers, margin requirements, and short-selling regulations — all of which address Kindleberger's bubble conditions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When you see all four conditions present — novice investors flooding in, no one can justify valuations, leverage is easy, and short sellers are being squeezed — warn clients. Historical patterns repeat because human psychology does not change.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
