<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Manoj's investment adviser establishes advance ground rules: "If equity allocation exceeds 65% of the portfolio, we will automatically rebalance by booking partial profits." This pre-agreed rule is an example of:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mental Accounting — creating separate buckets for different asset classes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Nudging — a built-in mechanism that ensures disciplined rebalancing by exploiting status quo bias positively]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Anchoring — fixating on the 65% figure as an arbitrary reference point]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Framing — presenting rebalancing as profit booking to make it palatable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Setting advance ground rules for rebalancing is a "built-in nudge." Once agreed upon, status quo bias actually helps — the client sticks with the pre-agreed rules. Asset rebalancing means booking profits when an asset class is high and buying when it is low, which is systematically disciplined behavior.
**The Trap:** While the 65% figure might seem like an anchor, the purpose is not to fixate on a number but to create an automatic trigger for action. Framing may be used in how the rebalancing is described, but the structural mechanism is nudging — designing the choice architecture to promote good outcomes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers strategic and tactical asset allocation. Rebalancing triggers (time-based or threshold-based) are standard practice, and behavioral nudges make clients more likely to follow through.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** At the start of every advisory relationship, establish written rebalancing rules with specific triggers. When the market is euphoric and the client wants to "let winners run," point to the pre-agreed rules. The nudge was built in precisely for this moment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
