<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following CORRECTLY distinguishes cognitive biases from emotional biases in behavioral finance?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cognitive biases arise from deep-rooted personal experiences, while emotional biases are statistical errors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Emotional biases are always irrational, while cognitive biases are always rational]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cognitive biases cannot be corrected, while emotional biases can be easily eliminated through education]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Cognitive biases are information-processing errors that can be corrected with vigilance, while emotional biases stem from spontaneous, deep-rooted experiences and are not necessarily irrational]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Cognitive biases are statistical and information-processing errors resulting from shortcut approaches — they CAN be corrected with awareness and vigilance. Emotional biases are spontaneous reactions arising from deep-rooted personal experiences — they are NOT irrational per se (they have an experiential logic) but are harder to correct.
**The Trap:** The statement "emotional biases are always irrational" is incorrect — the curriculum explicitly states emotional biases are NOT irrational per se. Similarly, saying cognitive biases cannot be corrected reverses the actual relationship.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A (Investment Adviser Level 1) covers risk tolerance assessment. Distinguishing between cognitive and emotional sources of bias helps advisers choose the right intervention — education for cognitive errors, empathy and framing for emotional ones.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For cognitive biases (anchoring, framing, mental accounting), provide data and frameworks. For emotional biases (loss aversion, endowment), use stories, analogies, and patient dialogue. Different biases need different tools.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
