<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Behavioral Finance_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Arun, a salaried professional in Delhi, invests only in Indian equity and fixed deposits. His adviser suggests international diversification through the Liberalised Remittance Scheme (LRS). Arun refuses, saying "I don't understand foreign markets." Under LRS, what is the annual limit per individual, and which behavioral bias is Arun exhibiting?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[USD 150,000 per year; Status Quo Bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[USD 250,000 per year; Home Country Bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[USD 250,000 per year; Endowment Bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[USD 100,000 per year; Choice Paralysis]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The LRS scheme allows Indian residents to remit up to USD 250,000 per financial year for investments abroad. Arun exhibits Home Country Bias — the tendency to invest predominantly in domestic markets due to familiarity, ignoring international diversification benefits. This is a well-documented real-life deviation from rational portfolio construction.
**The Trap:** The LRS limit of USD 250,000 is specific — USD 150,000 and USD 100,000 are incorrect figures designed to test whether you know the exact limit. Endowment Bias is about overvaluing what you own, not about geographic preference.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) covers international fund-of-funds and feeder funds that allow Indian investors to access global markets. NISM Series X-A covers asset allocation across geographies.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Combat home country bias by showing correlation data — Indian and US markets don't move in lockstep. Even a 10-15% allocation to international equities via a Nasdaq 100 fund-of-fund can improve risk-adjusted returns through diversification.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
