<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ravi (age 30) and Sita (age 28) are a dual-income couple. Ravi earns Rs. 12,00,000 per annum and Sita earns Rs. 8,00,000 per annum. They have one child, Arjun, aged 2. Their monthly household expenses are Rs. 60,000. Current savings: Rs. 5,00,000 in a Fixed Deposit, Rs. 3,00,000 in an equity mutual fund, and Rs. 2,00,000 in PPF. They have no outstanding loans.

Their financial goals are: (1) Arjun's higher education at age 18 — current cost of the programme is Rs. 25,00,000 with education inflation at 10% per annum. (2) House purchase in 5 years with a target property value of Rs. 50,00,000 — they plan to make their own contribution of Rs. 15,00,000 and finance the rest through a home loan. (3) Retirement at age 60 — monthly expenses at retirement of Rs. 60,000 (in today's terms), inflation 7% per annum, expected investment return during retirement 9% per annum, plan for 25 years in retirement.

Assume expected investment returns: equity 12% p.a., debt 8% p.a., balanced/hybrid fund 10% p.a. All calculations use annual compounding unless stated otherwise.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> For Arjun's education goal (16 years away, target Rs. 1.15 crore), which product combination is most suitable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in PPF — tax-free and safe for a critical goal like child's education]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in FD ladder — guaranteed returns with no market risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Child ULIP plan with insurance cover and market-linked returns for 16 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual fund SIP for the first 12 years, then gradually shift to debt/balanced fund in the last 4 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** With a 16-year horizon, equity SIP is the optimal wealth creator (12% expected return vs 7-8% for debt). However, de-risking in the last 3-4 years protects accumulated wealth from market crashes near the goal date. The SIP route through mutual funds offers flexibility, transparency, and lower costs compared to ULIPs. PPF at 7.1% would require monthly contributions of Rs. 30,000+ (much higher than equity SIP of ~Rs. 18,500 at 12%) and has a Rs. 1.5 lakh annual limit, making it insufficient as the sole vehicle for a Rs. 1.15 crore goal.
**The Trap:** PPF has an annual contribution cap of Rs. 1.5 lakh, so even at 7.1% for 16 years, maximum PPF accumulation is approximately Rs. 45-50 lakh — far short of Rs. 1.15 crore. ULIP charges (premium allocation, mortality, fund management) typically erode 2-3% of returns in the early years. FD at 7% pre-tax (4.9% post-tax at 30% slab) would need over Rs. 35,000/month.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Product suitability for goal-based planning is a core NISM X-B topic. Series V-A tests mutual fund suitability, while X-A covers the broader product comparison framework.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Label the SIP as "Arjun Education Fund" in your records and the client's portfolio. Goal-tagging reduces the temptation to redeem prematurely. Set up an automatic STP (Systematic Transfer Plan) from equity to debt fund 4 years before the goal date to automate the de-risking.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
