<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C4_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mahesh (age 50) is a successful businessman with a net worth of Rs. 10 crore. Annual income: Rs. 60,00,000. Wife Neha (age 47). Two adult children: son Arjun (age 25, working in the family business) and daughter Priya (age 22, MBA student). Assets: residential house Rs. 3,00,00,000, business equity Rs. 4,00,00,000, equity mutual funds Rs. 1,50,00,000, FD and debt mutual funds Rs. 80,00,000, gold and real estate investments Rs. 70,00,000. Liabilities: business loan Rs. 50,00,000. Life insurance: term plan Rs. 2,00,00,000 (Rs. 2 crore).

Financial goals: (1) Retire at age 60, maintain current lifestyle of Rs. 1,50,000 per month (in today's terms). (2) Daughter Priya's marriage in 3 years — current estimated cost Rs. 30,00,000 with general inflation of 8% p.a. on marriage expenses. (3) Smooth transfer of business to son Arjun. (4) Estate plan for family wealth distribution.

Assumptions: General inflation 6% p.a., equity return 12% p.a., debt return 8% p.a., blended retirement return 9% p.a. Investment return for HLV calculation: 10% p.a.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> For Mahesh's goal of transferring the Rs. 4 crore family business to his son Arjun while ensuring daughter Priya is not disadvantaged, which estate planning tool is most appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A simple will bequeathing the business entirely to Arjun and the house to Priya]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A private family trust with Mahesh as settlor, clearly defining business shares for Arjun and equivalent financial assets for Priya, with professional trustees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Converting the business to a partnership with Arjun as the sole partner immediately]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Creating a Hindu Undivided Family (HUF) to hold the business assets for tax benefits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A private family trust offers the best combination of: (1) Business continuity — Arjun can be named as managing trustee for business operations. (2) Equitable distribution — financial assets equivalent to Priya's fair share can be ring-fenced within the trust. (3) Protection from disputes — trust deed clearly defines rights, unlike a will which can be contested. (4) Tax planning — income can be distributed among beneficiaries. (5) Succession clarity — avoids probate delays and family disputes.
**The Trap:** A simple will can be contested under Indian succession law and does not provide ongoing management structure for a business. Converting immediately to a partnership may trigger capital gains and stamp duty, and strips Mahesh of control while he is still active. HUF cannot be newly created for this purpose — it is a Hindu law concept based on family lineage, not a business structuring tool, and its tax benefits are limited.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Estate planning tools (will, trust, nomination, HUF) are covered in NISM X-B Chapter on Estate Planning. The distinction between revocable and irrevocable trusts, and their suitability for business succession, is a key exam topic.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For HNIs with business assets, always recommend involving a legal professional alongside the financial planner. The trust deed should include: income distribution clauses, exit mechanisms, successor trustee provisions, and clear valuation methodology for the business. The trust can also protect family wealth from creditors if structured correctly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
