<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Suresh (age 45) is the sole earner in his family. His wife Kavita (age 42) is a homemaker. They have two children: daughter Meera (age 18, starting college with fees of Rs. 8,00,000 per year for 4 years at current cost) and son Rohan (age 15, higher education estimated at Rs. 30,00,000 needed 3 years from now — this is already the projected future cost). Monthly income: Rs. 1,50,000. Monthly expenses: Rs. 90,000. Existing investments: Rs. 30,00,000 in EPF, Rs. 15,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 10,00,000 in FD, and Rs. 5,00,000 in PPF. Outstanding home loan: EMI of Rs. 25,000/month with 10 years remaining. Life insurance: term plan of Rs. 1,00,00,000 (Rs. 1 crore).

Suresh plans to retire at age 60 and expects 25 years in retirement. Current monthly expenses at retirement: Rs. 90,000 (in today's terms). Inflation: 6% p.a. Expected returns: equity 12% p.a., debt 7.5% p.a. For retirement corpus calculation, assume a blended portfolio return of 9% p.a. during retirement.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> What is the total education funding required for both children in nominal terms?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 52,00,000 (Rs. 32 lakh for Meera + Rs. 20 lakh for Rohan)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 62,00,000 (Rs. 32 lakh for Meera + Rs. 30 lakh for Rohan)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 70,00,000 (Rs. 40 lakh for Meera + Rs. 30 lakh for Rohan)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 38,00,000 (Rs. 8 lakh for Meera + Rs. 30 lakh for Rohan)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Meera's education: Rs. 8,00,000 per year x 4 years = Rs. 32,00,000 (current cost, payable starting now through the next 3 years). Rohan's education: Rs. 30,00,000 (already stated as the projected cost needed 3 years from now). Total nominal funding: Rs. 32,00,000 + Rs. 30,00,000 = Rs. 62,00,000. Note that Meera's cost is at current rates since she is starting now, while Rohan's is already a future projection.
**The Trap:** Rs. 52,00,000 incorrectly uses Rs. 20 lakh for Rohan instead of the stated Rs. 30 lakh. Rs. 38,00,000 counts only one year of Meera's fees (Rs. 8 lakh) instead of 4 years. Rs. 70,00,000 inflates Meera's fees by 10 lakh, perhaps adding phantom inflation on a cost that is already current.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Education funding calculations are a staple across NISM X-A and X-B. The distinction between current costs (to be inflated) and already-projected future costs is a common source of exam errors.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rs. 62 lakh in education costs is a significant chunk of the family's Rs. 60 lakh in savings. Suresh needs to carefully earmark existing FDs and partial equity MF redemption for Meera's immediate needs, while dedicating fresh SIPs for Rohan's goal 3 years away.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
