<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C3_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Lakshmi (age 55) works in the private sector and plans to retire in 5 years at age 60. Current monthly income: Rs. 2,00,000. Monthly expenses: Rs. 1,20,000. She saves Rs. 80,000 per month and will continue doing so until retirement.

Existing corpus: Rs. 80,00,000 in EPF/PPF (expected return 7.5% p.a.), Rs. 40,00,000 in equity mutual funds (expected return 11% p.a.), Rs. 20,00,000 in Fixed Deposits (expected return 7.5% p.a.). NPS corpus expected to be Rs. 30,00,000 at age 60. No outstanding loans. No employer pension (private sector).

Life expectancy: 85 years (25 years in retirement). Inflation: 6% p.a. Expected returns during retirement: debt 7.5% p.a., equity 11% p.a. Monthly savings of Rs. 80,000 are invested at a blended return of 10% p.a. NPS withdrawal rules: 60% lump sum (tax-free), 40% must purchase annuity at 6% p.a. yield.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Lakshmi is comparing three options for generating regular income from her FD corpus (projected Rs. 28,71,259 at age 60): (A) Debt mutual fund SWP at 7.5% for 25 years, (B) Senior Citizens' Savings Scheme (SCSS) at 8.2% p.a. (paid quarterly), and (C) Annuity at 6% p.a. Which generates the highest effective monthly income?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCSS at Rs. 19,620/month equivalent — highest due to government backing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three give approximately the same monthly income of Rs. 18,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annuity at Rs. 14,356/month — highest due to guaranteed lifetime income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Debt MF SWP at Rs. 21,218/month — highest as it depletes both interest and principal over 25 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** (A) Debt MF SWP: PMT = Rs. 28,71,259 x (0.075/12) / (1 - (1 + 0.075/12)^(-300)) = Rs. 21,218/month (corpus fully depleted after 25 years). (B) SCSS: Annual interest = Rs. 28,71,259 x 8.2% = Rs. 2,35,443. Quarterly payout = Rs. 58,861. Monthly equivalent = Rs. 19,620 (capital preserved, subject to SCSS Rs. 30 lakh limit and 5-year tenure with extensions). (C) Annuity: Annual income = Rs. 28,71,259 x 6% = Rs. 1,72,276. Monthly = Rs. 14,356 (capital lost, income guaranteed for life). SWP gives the highest monthly income because it draws down both interest and principal.
**The Trap:** SCSS appears attractive at 8.2% but preserves capital (lower monthly income). Annuity has the lowest rate and the capital is irrevocably surrendered. Candidates may confuse "highest rate" with "highest income" — SWP wins because it is a corpus-depleting strategy over a defined period.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Comparing income products for retirees is a core NISM X-B topic. The trade-off between capital preservation (SCSS), capital depletion (SWP), and capital surrender (annuity) is fundamental to decumulation planning.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In practice, recommend a combination: SCSS for the first Rs. 30 lakh (government-guaranteed, 8.2%, capital safe), debt MF SWP for amounts beyond SCSS limit, and annuity only for a baseline guaranteed floor income. SCSS has a 5-year tenure extendable by 3 years — plan reinvestment at maturity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
