<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C4_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mahesh (age 50) is a successful businessman with a net worth of Rs. 10 crore. Annual income: Rs. 60,00,000. Wife Neha (age 47). Two adult children: son Arjun (age 25, working in the family business) and daughter Priya (age 22, MBA student). Assets: residential house Rs. 3,00,00,000, business equity Rs. 4,00,00,000, equity mutual funds Rs. 1,50,00,000, FD and debt mutual funds Rs. 80,00,000, gold and real estate investments Rs. 70,00,000. Liabilities: business loan Rs. 50,00,000. Life insurance: term plan Rs. 2,00,00,000 (Rs. 2 crore).

Financial goals: (1) Retire at age 60, maintain current lifestyle of Rs. 1,50,000 per month (in today's terms). (2) Daughter Priya's marriage in 3 years — current estimated cost Rs. 30,00,000 with general inflation of 8% p.a. on marriage expenses. (3) Smooth transfer of business to son Arjun. (4) Estate plan for family wealth distribution.

Assumptions: General inflation 6% p.a., equity return 12% p.a., debt return 8% p.a., blended retirement return 9% p.a. Investment return for HLV calculation: 10% p.a.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Which tax-efficient strategy is most appropriate for Mahesh to transfer wealth to his children during his lifetime?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gift Rs. 5 crore directly to each child — gifts from parents are fully tax-free regardless of amount]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Combination approach — gift financial assets (tax-free under Section 56) up to reasonable amounts, settle a family trust for business assets, and use the existing HUF (if any) for incremental tax efficiency on investment income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Create a new HUF and transfer all personal assets into it for tax-free partition later]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell all assets, pay capital gains tax, and distribute the after-tax proceeds equally to both children]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Indian tax law: (1) Gifts from parents to children (and certain specified relatives) are completely exempt under Section 56(2)(x) — no limit on amount for specified relatives. (2) However, clubbing provisions (Section 64) apply if gifting to a minor child or spouse — income from gifted assets is clubbed with the donor. Since Arjun (25) and Priya (22) are adult children, clubbing does not apply. (3) A family trust provides structured, controlled transfer of business assets while maintaining operational continuity. (4) HUF can provide an additional PAN for tax purposes on investment income. The combination approach maximises tax efficiency while maintaining control and equitable distribution.
**The Trap:** While gifts to children are tax-free, gifting Rs. 5 crore each without planning is reckless — it surrenders all control immediately and may trigger capital gains on assets transferred (if not in cash/shares). Creating a new HUF is not possible — HUF is created by operation of Hindu law, not by individual choice (though an existing HUF can receive gifts). Selling all assets triggers unnecessary capital gains tax.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Wealth transfer, gift taxation, and trust structures are covered in NISM X-B estate planning chapters. Section 56(2)(x) exemption for relatives and Section 64 clubbing provisions are commonly tested.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For HNIs like Mahesh, the sequence matters: (1) First, ensure adequate insurance and retirement corpus are ring-fenced. (2) Then, transfer wealth in a phased manner — too much too soon can be counterproductive for young recipients. (3) The trust structure allows Mahesh to remain settlor and control distributions during his lifetime while ensuring smooth succession. (4) Always involve a CA and lawyer for the tax and legal structuring.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
