<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C3_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Lakshmi (age 55) works in the private sector and plans to retire in 5 years at age 60. Current monthly income: Rs. 2,00,000. Monthly expenses: Rs. 1,20,000. She saves Rs. 80,000 per month and will continue doing so until retirement.

Existing corpus: Rs. 80,00,000 in EPF/PPF (expected return 7.5% p.a.), Rs. 40,00,000 in equity mutual funds (expected return 11% p.a.), Rs. 20,00,000 in Fixed Deposits (expected return 7.5% p.a.). NPS corpus expected to be Rs. 30,00,000 at age 60. No outstanding loans. No employer pension (private sector).

Life expectancy: 85 years (25 years in retirement). Inflation: 6% p.a. Expected returns during retirement: debt 7.5% p.a., equity 11% p.a. Monthly savings of Rs. 80,000 are invested at a blended return of 10% p.a. NPS withdrawal rules: 60% lump sum (tax-free), 40% must purchase annuity at 6% p.a. yield.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> From the NPS corpus of Rs. 30,00,000, Lakshmi must use 40% to purchase an annuity at 6% per annum yield. What monthly annuity income will she receive, and what is the tax-free lump sum?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lump sum Rs. 18,00,000 and monthly annuity Rs. 9,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lump sum Rs. 12,00,000 and monthly annuity Rs. 9,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Lump sum Rs. 18,00,000 and monthly annuity Rs. 6,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lump sum Rs. 18,00,000 and monthly annuity Rs. 15,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NPS lump sum (60% of Rs. 30,00,000) = Rs. 18,00,000 (tax-free under current rules). Annuity corpus (40% of Rs. 30,00,000) = Rs. 12,00,000. Annual annuity at 6% yield = Rs. 12,00,000 x 6% = Rs. 72,000. Monthly annuity = Rs. 72,000 / 12 = Rs. 6,000 per month. Note: the annuity income is taxable as per the subscriber's income tax slab.
**The Trap:** Rs. 9,000 monthly results from applying 6% to the full Rs. 18 lakh instead of Rs. 12 lakh. Rs. 15,000 applies 6% to the full Rs. 30 lakh corpus. The 60:40 split must be applied first, then the annuity rate only on the 40% portion. Rs. 12 lakh lump sum incorrectly reverses the 60:40 ratio.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS withdrawal rules (60% lump sum tax-free, 40% mandatory annuity) are frequently tested in NISM X-A and X-B. The annuity taxation (taxable at slab rate) versus lump sum taxation (tax-free) is a critical distinction.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rs. 6,000/month from a Rs. 30 lakh NPS corpus is modest. This underscores why NPS should be supplemented with other retirement vehicles. The annuity rate of 6% is fixed for life, providing no inflation protection — in 15 years, Rs. 6,000 will have the purchasing power of approximately Rs. 2,500 at 6% inflation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
