<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Case Studies_C3_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Lakshmi (age 55) works in the private sector and plans to retire in 5 years at age 60. Current monthly income: Rs. 2,00,000. Monthly expenses: Rs. 1,20,000. She saves Rs. 80,000 per month and will continue doing so until retirement.

Existing corpus: Rs. 80,00,000 in EPF/PPF (expected return 7.5% p.a.), Rs. 40,00,000 in equity mutual funds (expected return 11% p.a.), Rs. 20,00,000 in Fixed Deposits (expected return 7.5% p.a.). NPS corpus expected to be Rs. 30,00,000 at age 60. No outstanding loans. No employer pension (private sector).

Life expectancy: 85 years (25 years in retirement). Inflation: 6% p.a. Expected returns during retirement: debt 7.5% p.a., equity 11% p.a. Monthly savings of Rs. 80,000 are invested at a blended return of 10% p.a. NPS withdrawal rules: 60% lump sum (tax-free), 40% must purchase annuity at 6% p.a. yield.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> As Lakshmi approaches retirement over the next 5 years, which asset allocation shift is most appropriate for her overall portfolio?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Increase equity allocation to 70% to maximise growth in the final 5 years before retirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Move 100% to fixed deposits and EPF for complete capital protection]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Gradually reduce equity from the current ~29% to about 20-25%, increase allocation to short-term debt, SCSS-eligible instruments, and liquid funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maintain the current allocation unchanged since 5 years is still a medium-term horizon]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Lakshmi's current equity allocation is approximately Rs. 40 lakh out of Rs. 140 lakh total (~29%). With only 5 years to retirement, the priority shifts from growth to capital preservation. Gradually reducing equity to 20-25% while increasing short-term debt, liquid funds, and SCSS-eligible instruments ensures: (1) protection against a market crash just before retirement (sequence-of-returns risk), (2) availability of liquid funds for immediate post-retirement expenses, and (3) readiness to invest in SCSS on turning 60.
**The Trap:** Increasing equity to 70% exposes the corpus to devastating sequence-of-returns risk — a 30% market fall at age 59 could wipe out Rs. 30+ lakh with no time to recover. 100% fixed deposits sacrifice the inflation-beating potential of equity that is still needed for a 25-year retirement. Maintaining status quo ignores the approaching transition from accumulation to decumulation phase.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The asset allocation shift approaching retirement (glide path) is a key concept in NISM X-B and lifecycle investing. SEBI guidelines for target-date funds embed this principle.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Start the "retirement readiness" transition 5 years before retirement: (1) STP from equity to short-term debt over 3 years, (2) build a 2-year expense buffer in liquid funds, (3) create a mental "bucket" framework — Bucket 1 (years 1-3: liquid/short-term), Bucket 2 (years 4-10: debt), Bucket 3 (years 10+: equity for inflation protection).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
