<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Vikram gifted mutual fund units worth Rs.3,00,000 to his wife Shalini. In the same year, the mutual fund incurred a loss of Rs.25,000. Which of the following statements is correct regarding this loss?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The loss belongs to Shalini as the legal owner; no clubbing for losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The loss is completely disallowed for both Vikram and Shalini]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The loss of Rs.25,000 is clubbed with Vikram's income, as clubbing provisions apply to both income and losses from transferred assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The loss is split equally between Vikram and Shalini (Rs.12,500 each)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Clubbing provisions under Section 64 apply to INCOME from transferred assets. If the net result is a LOSS, the loss is also clubbed with the transferor. So the Rs.25,000 loss from the mutual fund units gifted to Shalini will be included in Vikram's computation — he can use this loss for set-off against his other income as per applicable rules.
**The Trap:** Option A assumes clubbing applies only to positive income, not losses. This is incorrect — clubbing is about attributing the income/loss to the right person, regardless of sign.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The "clubbing of losses" concept is a nuanced point tested in NISM X-B to differentiate from basic X-A questions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clubbing of losses can actually benefit the transferor if they have income to set off against. However, this should never be the primary motive for gifting assets.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
