<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rekha has a 25% share in the profits of M/s Dhanush Enterprises, a partnership firm. Her husband Mohan is employed by the same firm and receives a salary of Rs.6,00,000 per year. Mohan does not hold any professional qualifications relevant to his role. In whose hands will Mohan's salary be clubbed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mohan's income, since salary is always taxable in the hands of the person earning it]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Shared equally between Rekha and Mohan]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The partnership firm's income, as it is a disallowed expense]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rekha's income, as she has substantial interest in the concern employing Mohan and he lacks relevant professional qualifications]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 64(1)(ii), if a spouse has substantial interest (20%+ voting power or profit share) in a concern where the other spouse is employed, the remuneration of the employed spouse is clubbed with the spouse having substantial interest — UNLESS the employed spouse has professional qualifications and the income is solely due to those qualifications. Rekha holds 25% (>20%), so she has substantial interest, and Mohan lacks relevant qualifications.
**The Trap:** The exception for professional qualifications is critical. If Mohan were a qualified CA or engineer and the role required that qualification, the salary would remain in his hands.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers the concept of substantial interest in a simpler context.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before structuring family employment in a business, verify if the employed family member has bona fide professional qualifications — it can make a Rs.1,80,000 slab difference in tax.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
