<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ms. Ananya, an investment adviser, is reviewing a client's portfolio. The client has brought-forward STCL of Rs.2,50,000 (from FY 2024-25, year 7 of 8 for carry forward). The client currently holds equity shares with unrealized LTCG of Rs.5,00,000 and unrealized STCG of Rs.1,00,000. What should Ananya recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Do nothing — STCL will automatically set off in future years whenever gains are realized]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Realize only the STCG of Rs.1,00,000 to partially absorb the STCL; carry forward the balance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Realize sufficient capital gains (STCG or LTCG) of at least Rs.2,50,000 before FY 2025-26 ends to fully absorb the STCL, as it is in its penultimate year of carry forward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Convert the STCL to LTCL by waiting, as LTCL has unlimited carry forward]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** STCL can be carried forward for a maximum of 8 assessment years. This is year 7, meaning only one more year remains. Since STCL can be set off against ANY capital gain (STCG or LTCG), Ananya should recommend realizing at least Rs.2,50,000 of gains before the carry forward expires. The client has ample unrealized gains to do this.
**The Trap:** Option B is suboptimal — why absorb only Rs.1,00,000 when the full Rs.2,50,000 can be absorbed? Option D is nonsensical — losses don't "convert" from short-term to long-term, and LTCL also has only 8 years (not unlimited) carry forward.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Tax-loss harvesting strategy is a practical application tested in NISM X-B adviser-level questions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Track carry-forward loss expiry dates in a spreadsheet. Proactively book gains in the 7th or 8th year to ensure losses don't expire unused — this is a concrete value-add an adviser provides.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
