<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the new tax regime, Mr. Vinod has a loss from house property of Rs.2,50,000 in FY 2025-26. His salary income is Rs.10,00,000. What is the correct treatment of this house property loss?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.2,00,000 can be set off against salary; Rs.50,000 carried forward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Full Rs.2,50,000 can be set off against salary income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NO inter-head set-off is allowed against salary; the loss is deemed to have been allowed and carried forward for set-off only against house property income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[House property loss is completely disallowed under the new tax regime and cannot be carried forward]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the new tax regime, inter-head set-off of house property loss against other heads (like salary) is NOT allowed. However, the loss is deemed to have been given effect to and can be carried forward for 8 years, to be set off ONLY against house property income in subsequent years. This differs from the old regime where Rs.2,00,000 inter-head set-off was available.
**The Trap:** Option A applies the old regime rule (Rs.2,00,000 cap) to the new regime. Option D wrongly suggests the loss is permanently lost.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between old and new regime treatment of house property loss is a high-priority exam topic for NISM Series X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients with large home loan interest and no rental income should evaluate whether the old regime is better, as the Rs.2,00,000 inter-head set-off can be valuable.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
