<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Ramesh has two minor children — Aarav (age 12) and Bhavya (age 8). Aarav earns Rs.45,000 from a singing competition on a TV show, and Bhavya earns Rs.20,000 as interest on a fixed deposit gifted by her grandfather. Which income will be clubbed with Ramesh's income?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both Aarav's and Bhavya's income will be clubbed with Ramesh's income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Only Bhavya's Rs.20,000 will be clubbed (subject to Rs.1,500 exemption); Aarav's income from skill/talent is excluded from clubbing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Neither income is clubbed since both children are below 13 years of age]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Aarav's income is clubbed since it exceeds Rs.1,500; Bhavya's Rs.20,000 is fully exempt]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Minor child income is generally clubbed with the parent having higher income under Section 64(1A). However, income earned by a minor from manual work or activity involving skill/talent is EXCLUDED from clubbing. Aarav's singing competition income qualifies as skill/talent, so it is not clubbed. Bhavya's FD interest (Rs.20,000) is clubbed, but Rs.1,500 per child exemption is available under Section 10(32).
**The Trap:** The Rs.1,500 exemption applies per child per year, not a blanket exemption. Also, candidates often forget the skill/talent exception for minor children.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A tests minor child clubbing in the context of mutual fund investments made in minor's name.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When parents invest in a minor child's name, remind them that investment income will be clubbed — but income from child prodigies (sports, arts, etc.) is not clubbed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
