<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Deepak incurred the following losses in FY 2025-26: Non-speculative business loss Rs.5,00,000 and Short-term capital loss Rs.2,00,000. His salary income is Rs.12,00,000. Which of the following is the correct treatment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both losses can be set off against salary income, reducing taxable income to Rs.5,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Non-speculative business loss Rs.5,00,000 can be set off against salary; STCL of Rs.2,00,000 is carried forward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Neither loss can be set off against salary — non-speculative business loss cannot be set off against salary, and capital loss cannot be set off against any other head; both are carried forward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STCL Rs.2,00,000 can be set off against salary; business loss of Rs.5,00,000 is carried forward]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Non-speculative business loss can be set off against any income EXCEPT salary. Capital loss (both STCL and LTCL) CANNOT be set off against any other head of income — only against capital gains. Since Deepak's only other income is salary, neither loss can be set off. Both are carried forward: business loss for 8 years (against business income only) and STCL for 8 years (against any capital gain).
**The Trap:** Option B is very tempting — many candidates wrongly assume "any income except salary" means inter-head set-off is possible with salary. The rule is the opposite: business loss can be set off against other heads EXCEPT salary.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A tests basic set-off rules. The salary exception for business loss is a frequently tested distinction.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Salaried clients with side businesses should understand that business losses won't reduce their salary tax liability. They need other non-salary income to absorb the loss.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
