<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Suresh transferred shares worth Rs.5,00,000 to his son's wife Kavita without adequate consideration. The shares generated a dividend of Rs.40,000 and Kavita sold them for a short-term capital gain of Rs.60,000. What amount is clubbed with Suresh's income?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only dividend of Rs.40,000 is clubbed; capital gain is Kavita's income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.1,00,000 (both dividend Rs.40,000 and STCG Rs.60,000), as all income from the transferred asset is clubbed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nil — clubbing provisions do not apply to transfers to son's wife]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only STCG of Rs.60,000 is clubbed; dividend income belongs to Kavita as the shareholder]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 64(1)(vi), income from assets transferred to son's wife without adequate consideration is clubbed with the transferor. ALL income arising from the transferred asset — whether dividend, interest, or capital gains — is clubbed with Suresh. The total clubbed amount is Rs.40,000 + Rs.60,000 = Rs.1,00,000.
**The Trap:** Option A creates a false distinction between types of income from the transferred asset. Clubbing applies to ALL income from the asset, not just passive income.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A tests clubbing for daughter-in-law transfers in the context of investment planning.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Transfers to son's wife (daughter-in-law) without consideration trigger clubbing just like transfers to spouse. Adequate consideration is the key — if fair market value is paid, clubbing does not apply.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
