<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Clubbing, Set-Off and Carry Forward of Losses_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ms. Vandana has a speculative business loss of Rs.4,00,000 in FY 2025-26. She also has the following incomes: Non-speculative business profit Rs.6,00,000, Salary income Rs.3,00,000, and Short-term capital gain Rs.1,50,000. Against which income can she set off the speculative loss?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Against non-speculative business profit of Rs.6,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Against both non-speculative business profit and short-term capital gain]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Against any income except salary — so against business profit, STCG, and any other income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Against NONE of these — speculative loss can only be set off against speculative business profit, which she does not have]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Speculative business loss can ONLY be set off against speculative business profit. It cannot be set off against non-speculative business income, salary, capital gains, or any other head. Since Vandana has no speculative profit, the entire Rs.4,00,000 must be carried forward for up to 4 years, to be set off only against speculative profit.
**The Trap:** Option A is the strongest distractor — many candidates assume speculative and non-speculative business incomes are under the same head (Profits & Gains of Business or Profession), so intra-head set-off should work. But speculative loss has a special restriction.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) tests speculative vs. non-speculative income classification for F&O trading.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients engaged in speculative trading (intraday equity) should understand that losses can only absorb future speculative profits — they offer no relief against other income streams.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
