<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Verma, aged 68, wants to avail a reverse mortgage. His property is a shop-cum-residence where the ground floor is a commercial shop and the first floor is his residence. Can he avail a reverse mortgage on this property?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, since he is above 60 and the property has a residential component]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only on the value attributable to the residential portion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because reverse mortgage cannot be availed against commercial property, and mixed-use properties with commercial use do not qualify]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, if he converts the commercial portion to residential use within 6 months]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Reverse mortgage can only be availed against a residential property that is the borrower's permanent primary residence. It cannot be availed against commercial property. A mixed-use property with commercial components would not qualify as a purely residential property free from encumbrance for this purpose.
**The Trap:** Candidates may think the residential portion alone can be mortgaged, but the property must be entirely residential. The "partial value" option sounds reasonable but is not how reverse mortgage works.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers basic property and loan concepts relevant to retirement planning.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients with mixed-use properties should be advised to separate the commercial and residential portions (if legally possible) before considering reverse mortgage. The residential unit must be their permanent primary residence with no commercial use.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
