<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor sells unlisted (not traded on exchange) Sovereign Gold Bonds after 20 months at a profit. How will the capital gains be classified and taxed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[STCG taxed at the investor's income tax slab rate, since holding period is 24 months or less for unlisted SGBs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[LTCG taxed at 12.5% without indexation, since holding period exceeds 12 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fully exempt from capital gains tax as it is a government security]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STCG taxed at a flat rate of 15%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For unlisted SGBs (not traded on a stock exchange), the holding period threshold for LTCG classification is 24 months. Since the holding period is 20 months (less than 24 months), it is classified as STCG and taxed at the investor's applicable income tax slab rate. Had the SGBs been listed and traded on exchange, the 12-month threshold would apply, and 20 months would qualify as LTCG.
**The Trap:** The 12-month threshold (Option B) applies to LISTED SGBs, not unlisted ones. This distinction between listed and unlisted holding period thresholds is a frequently tested concept. The 15% flat rate applies to listed equity STCG, not SGBs.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A and X-B both test the listed vs. unlisted holding period distinction extensively.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before recommending SGBs, verify if the tranche is listed on the exchange. Listed SGBs offer better tax treatment for pre-maturity exits (12-month LTCG threshold vs. 24 months for unlisted).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
