<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor compares three gold investment options: Physical Gold, Gold ETF, and Sovereign Gold Bond held to maturity. Assuming identical gold price appreciation and ignoring transaction costs, which option provides the HIGHEST post-tax return?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Physical Gold, because there is no expense ratio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold ETF, because it tracks gold prices most accurately]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sovereign Gold Bond, because of 2.50% annual interest and tax-free capital gains at maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three provide identical post-tax returns since gold appreciation is the same]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SGBs provide the highest post-tax return due to two advantages: (1) 2.50% annual interest on the initial investment (no other gold product pays interest), and (2) capital gains at maturity are FULLY EXEMPT from tax. Physical gold and Gold ETFs both attract capital gains tax (12.5% LTCG without indexation for appropriate holding periods). Physical gold also has storage/insurance costs, and Gold ETFs have expense ratios.
**The Trap:** Physical gold having "no expense ratio" ignores storage costs, insurance, purity risk, and making charges. Gold ETF accuracy is irrelevant to returns comparison. The "identical returns" option ignores the interest component and differential tax treatment.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A tests comparative analysis of gold investment products. Series X-B requires deeper tax-adjusted return analysis.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients with 8+ year horizons, SGBs are the clear winner. Use a simple comparison table showing: SGB (interest + exempt gains) vs Gold ETF (no interest + taxable gains) vs Physical Gold (no interest + taxable gains + storage costs).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
