<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser is comparing rental yield from direct real estate investment versus income distribution from REITs for a client. Which of the following observations is MOST accurate in the Indian context?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Direct real estate in India typically offers higher rental yields than REIT distributions because there is no intermediary cost]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Direct real estate rental yields in India are typically low relative to high property prices, making REITs potentially more attractive for income-seeking investors due to professional management and commercial property focus]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs and direct real estate offer identical yields since both derive income from the same asset class]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Neither direct real estate nor REITs provide meaningful income; both are purely capital appreciation plays in India]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In India, direct residential real estate rental yields are typically low (2-3%) relative to the high purchase prices. REITs, which primarily invest in commercial properties (offices, etc.), can potentially offer better yields due to professional management, economies of scale, and focus on higher-yielding commercial real estate. REITs also offer the advantage of liquidity through stock exchange listing.
**The Trap:** The "identical yields" option ignores that REITs focus on commercial property (typically higher yields) while most individual investors buy residential property (lower yields). The "no meaningful income" option incorrectly dismisses real estate income entirely.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B covers comparative analysis of direct vs. indirect real estate investment through REITs and their relative merits.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For income-focused clients, explain that a Rs. 1 crore residential apartment might yield only Rs. 2-3 lakh annually in rent, while the same amount in REITs could potentially yield higher distributions with daily liquidity and no maintenance hassles.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
