<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the ownership of property under a reverse mortgage is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The borrower remains the owner of the property throughout the loan tenure and even after tenure ends]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ownership transfers to the lender once 50% of the property value has been disbursed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lender becomes a joint owner from the date of first disbursement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ownership automatically transfers to the lender when the loan tenure expires]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under a reverse mortgage, the borrower remains the OWNER of the property at all times - during the loan tenure, after the tenure ends, and until death or permanent departure. The lender has a mortgage/lien on the property but does NOT become the owner. The property is settled (sold or repaid by heirs) only after the last surviving borrower dies or permanently moves out.
**The Trap:** Candidates often assume the lender gradually takes ownership as disbursements increase, similar to a hire-purchase arrangement. This is fundamentally wrong - reverse mortgage is a loan secured by property, not a sale of property.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers property rights and mortgage structures in the context of retirement planning.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The biggest misconception about reverse mortgage is that "the bank takes your house." Educate clients that they NEVER lose ownership. Heirs always get first right to repay the loan and retain the property.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
