<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mrs. Patel, aged 65, avails a reverse mortgage on her residential property. She receives Rs. 40,000 per month for 15 years. After the loan tenure of 15 years ends, what happens to the periodic payments and the loan?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Payments continue at the same rate until death, and interest stops accruing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The property is immediately transferred to the lender]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Periodic payments cease but interest continues to accrue on the outstanding loan; she continues to live in the property]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The borrower must start repaying the loan in monthly installments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** After the reverse mortgage tenure ends, periodic payments to the borrower cease. However, interest continues to accrue on the outstanding loan amount. The borrower retains ownership and can continue living in the property. The loan becomes due only when the last surviving borrower dies or permanently moves out.
**The Trap:** Many assume the property is transferred to the lender after tenure ends, but the borrower remains the owner throughout. Others assume payments continue indefinitely - that feature is available only under RMLEA (annuity version).
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers basic retirement products. The distinction between reverse mortgage and RMLEA is tested at Level 2.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients worried about outliving their reverse mortgage tenure, recommend RMLEA instead, which provides lifetime annuity payments through an insurance company.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
