<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Commodity and Real Estate Investment_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Consider the following statements about a property eligible for reverse mortgage:

1. The property must have a residual life of at least 20 years
2. The property can be a farmhouse used as primary residence
3. The property must be free from any encumbrance
4. The maximum monthly payment under reverse mortgage is capped at Rs. 50,000

Which of the above statements are correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1 and 2 only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[1, 3, and 4 only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1, 2, 3, and 4]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2, 3, and 4 only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Statement 1 is correct - the property must have a residual life of at least 20 years. Statement 2 is INCORRECT - the property must be a residential property that is the borrower's permanent primary residence; a farmhouse may not qualify as standard residential property. Statement 3 is correct - the property must be free from encumbrance (no existing mortgage or lien). Statement 4 is correct - the maximum monthly payment is capped at Rs. 50,000.
**The Trap:** The farmhouse option sounds plausible since it can be a "residence," but reverse mortgage requires a standard residential property. Candidates who don't carefully distinguish property types will include statement 2.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A and X-B cover reverse mortgage eligibility criteria with increasing specificity.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before a client applies for reverse mortgage, verify: (a) property is purely residential, (b) no existing loans on it, (c) building is structurally sound with 20+ years of life, and (d) it is their permanent primary residence.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
