<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Company Analysis_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Deepak Verma is performing DuPont analysis on two competing pharmaceutical companies for FY 2025-26: PharmaCo A: Revenue Rs.10,000 crore, PAT Rs.1,500 crore, Total Assets Rs.12,000 crore, Equity Rs.6,000 crore. PharmaCo B: Revenue Rs.8,000 crore, PAT Rs.640 crore, Total Assets Rs.16,000 crore, Equity Rs.4,000 crore. Both companies operate in the same therapeutic segment and have similar market capitalization.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Which company represents better investment quality based on DuPont analysis?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PharmaCo B because it uses more leverage, which always leads to higher returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PharmaCo A because its higher ROE is driven by superior profit margins and asset efficiency rather than excessive leverage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both are equally attractive because leverage compensates for low margins]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Neither because pharma companies should not be analyzed using DuPont]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** PharmaCo A is higher quality: ROE driven by 15% margin and 0.83x turnover (operational excellence). B relies on 4x leverage with only 8% margin. A's returns are more sustainable and less risky.
**The Trap:** More leverage does not always mean better returns — it adds risk. A achieves higher ROE with half the leverage.
**Cross-Exam Context:** DuPont quality analysis tested in NISM XV Ch 8.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When two companies have similar ROE, DuPont decomposition reveals which generates returns sustainably (margins/efficiency) vs artificially (leverage).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>