<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a role played by mutual funds in the economy?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteeing minimum returns to all investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Facilitating wealth creation for retail investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Channelizing household savings into capital markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Acting as a stabilizing force in the capital markets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mutual funds play several critical roles in the economy: wealth building for individuals, enabling capital market participation for retail investors, contributing to economic development by channelizing savings, and acting as market stabilizers through disciplined investment. However, mutual funds are subject to market risks and CANNOT guarantee returns. The phrase "Mutual fund investments are subject to market risks" exists precisely for this reason.

**The Trap:** The word "guaranteeing" is the giveaway, but some candidates get confused because Capital Protection Oriented Funds exist. Even those funds do NOT guarantee capital protection -- they are only "oriented" towards it and must carry a credit rating. No MF scheme can guarantee returns.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B covers the role of MFs in economic development extensively. NISM XII (Securities Markets Foundation) tests the broader role of institutional investors including MFs as market stabilizers who provide liquidity and depth to markets.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never use the word "guarantee" when discussing mutual funds with clients. Even FMPs (Fixed Maturity Plans) that hold securities to maturity carry credit risk. Always set realistic expectations about returns being market-linked.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
