<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about REITs (Real Estate Investment Trusts) is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[REITs are listed on stock exchanges and are NOT classified as mutual fund schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs are a sub-category of mutual fund schemes under SEBI categorization]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs can only be purchased through AMCs and mutual fund distributors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs are regulated by RBI under the Banking Regulation Act]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** REITs (Real Estate Investment Trusts) and InvITs (Infrastructure Investment Trusts) are separate investment vehicles regulated by SEBI under their own regulations (SEBI REIT Regulations, 2014 and SEBI InvIT Regulations, 2014). They are NOT mutual fund schemes, even though they share some structural similarities (trust structure, pooling of investor money). REITs are listed and traded on stock exchanges like shares.

**The Trap:** Because mutual fund chapters discuss REITs alongside MF schemes, candidates often assume REITs are a type of MF. They are NOT. REITs are distinct pooled investment vehicles with different regulatory frameworks. However, mutual funds CAN invest in REITs/InvITs as part of their portfolio (e.g., some hybrid or multi-asset funds may hold REIT units).

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM XII covers REITs and InvITs as separate capital market instruments. NISM V-B may test that MF schemes can invest in REIT/InvIT units. The distinction between REITs (commercial real estate exposure) and Real Estate Mutual Funds (a separate SEBI-defined MF category) is frequently tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a client wants real estate exposure through financial instruments, explain the options: (1) Real Estate MF scheme (if available), (2) REIT units on the exchange, (3) Mutual funds that invest in REITs. Each has different risk-return characteristics, liquidity profiles, and minimum investments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
