<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI categorization, Solution-Oriented Schemes include which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Retirement Benefit Scheme and Children's Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS (Tax Saving) and Arbitrage Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital Protection Oriented Fund and Fixed Maturity Plan]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Balanced Advantage Fund and Multi-Asset Allocation Fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI categorization defines exactly 2 sub-categories under Solution-Oriented Schemes: (1) Retirement Benefit Scheme (with a minimum lock-in of 5 years or till retirement age, whichever is earlier) and (2) Children's Fund (with a minimum lock-in of 5 years or till the child attains age of majority, whichever is earlier). These are goal-based investment solutions with mandatory lock-in periods.

**The Trap:** ELSS is an Equity Scheme (not Solution-Oriented) with a 3-year lock-in for tax benefits under Section 80C. Arbitrage Fund is under Hybrid Schemes. Capital Protection Oriented Fund is under "Other Schemes." Balanced Advantage Fund and Multi-Asset Allocation Fund are Hybrid Schemes. The exam frequently tests whether candidates can correctly place schemes in their SEBI category.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B tests all 36 SEBI categories with their exact grouping. In NISM III-C, advisers must know lock-in periods: ELSS (3 years), Solution-Oriented (5 years), close-ended equity (per scheme tenure). The "Other Schemes" category (Index Fund/ETF and Fund of Funds) is also a common confusion point.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Retirement Benefit Schemes and Children's Funds are powerful goal-based selling tools. The lock-in enforces discipline, which is actually beneficial for long-term wealth creation. Position the lock-in as a feature, not a constraint: "This fund won't let you withdraw impulsively -- it's designed to protect your retirement/child's future from emotional decisions."]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
