<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI categorization, how many sub-categories are defined for Debt Schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[16 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[10 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[12 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[6 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's 2017 categorization defines 16 sub-categories for Debt Schemes, making it the largest category by number. These span from Overnight Fund (1-day maturity) to Long Duration Fund (Macaulay duration > 7 years), plus credit-based categories like Credit Risk Fund, Corporate Bond Fund, Banking & PSU Fund, and Gilt funds. The 16 categories provide a granular framework for debt fund classification based on maturity/duration and credit quality.

**The Trap:** 10 is the count for Equity sub-categories. 6 is for Hybrid sub-categories. 12 is a fabricated number. The full SEBI categorization count: Equity (10) + Debt (16) + Hybrid (6) + Solution-Oriented (2) + Other (2) = 36 total categories. Remember "10-16-6-2-2" as a memory aid.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B requires knowledge of all 16 debt sub-categories with their specific duration/maturity parameters. In NISM XII, the rationale for granular debt categorization relates to interest rate risk management -- different durations react differently to rate changes.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Debt fund selection requires matching the client's investment horizon with the fund's Macaulay duration. Explain to clients: "If you need money in 3 months, use Liquid Fund; if in 1 year, use Low Duration Fund; if in 3+ years, consider Medium to Long Duration." Mismatched horizons lead to negative surprises from interest rate movements.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
