<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI categorization, a Large Cap equity fund must invest a minimum of what percentage of total assets in equity and equity-related instruments of large cap companies?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[80% in large cap companies (1st to 100th by full market capitalization)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[65% in large cap companies (1st to 100th by full market capitalization)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[80% in large cap companies (1st to 200th by full market capitalization)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[75% in large cap companies (1st to 50th by full market capitalization)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI's mutual fund categorization circular, a Large Cap fund must invest a minimum of 80% of total assets in equity and equity-related instruments of large cap companies. SEBI defines large cap companies as the 1st to 100th company in terms of full market capitalization. This definition is updated by AMFI semi-annually.

**The Trap:** 65% is the minimum equity allocation required for a fund to be classified as an "equity fund" for taxation purposes -- a completely different threshold. Option C mixes the correct percentage (80%) with the wrong universe (1st to 200th includes mid caps). Option D uses wrong percentage and wrong universe. The SEBI definition is precise: Large Cap = Top 100, Mid Cap = 101st to 250th, Small Cap = 251st onwards.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B extensively covers SEBI categorization with specific allocation thresholds for each sub-category. In NISM III-C, advisers must know these definitions to correctly categorize client portfolios. The 65% equity threshold for tax treatment is tested in the taxation chapter.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client says "I want a safe equity fund," clarify what "safe" means. A Large Cap fund (80% in top 100 stocks) is relatively less volatile than a Small Cap fund, but it still carries full equity market risk. Use SEBI category definitions to set proper expectations about the risk-return spectrum.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
