<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued from Question 25):

Question 28: For Goal 2 (daughter's education in 13 years), Mr. Ankit recommends Scheme B, a Flexi Cap Fund. Under SEBI categorization, a Flexi Cap Fund differs from a Multi Cap Fund in which of the following ways?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Flexi Cap has no mandated minimum allocation across large, mid, and small cap; the fund manager has full flexibility, whereas Multi Cap must invest at least 25% each in large, mid, and small cap stocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Flexi Cap invests only in large cap stocks while Multi Cap invests across all market capitalizations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Flexi Cap is a close-ended scheme while Multi Cap is open-ended]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no difference; Flexi Cap and Multi Cap are two names for the same SEBI sub-category]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Flexi Cap Fund and Multi Cap Fund are two DISTINCT SEBI sub-categories with a critical difference. Multi Cap Fund must invest a minimum of 25% each in large cap, mid cap, and small cap stocks (total minimum 75% in equity). Flexi Cap Fund must invest minimum 65% in equity but has NO mandated allocation across market cap segments -- the fund manager has complete flexibility to shift between large, mid, and small caps based on market conditions and opportunities.

**The Trap:** Option D is the most dangerous distractor because before SEBI's 2020 circular (which introduced mandatory 25% allocation for Multi Cap), Multi Cap and Flexi Cap WERE effectively the same. Many candidates with outdated knowledge fall for this. The Flexi Cap category was created AFTER the Multi Cap mandate was introduced, specifically to preserve the flexibility that Multi Cap funds previously had. Option B is wrong because Flexi Cap invests across ALL caps, not just large cap.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the Flexi Cap vs. Multi Cap distinction is one of the most tested recent regulatory changes. In NISM V-A, distributors must understand this to recommend correctly. In NISM III-C, the allocation flexibility of Flexi Cap vs. the forced diversification of Multi Cap has implications for portfolio construction and risk management.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Mrs. Sharma's 13-year goal, a Flexi Cap fund is excellent because the fund manager can dynamically shift between large, mid, and small caps over the cycle. In bull markets, the manager might increase small/mid cap allocation for higher returns; in bear markets, shift to large caps for stability. For a Multi Cap fund, the mandatory 25% small cap allocation means the fund cannot reduce small cap exposure even during market downturns -- a key risk factor to communicate to clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
