<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is an advantage of investing in mutual funds compared to direct equity investing?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Affordable portfolio diversification even with small investment amounts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteed protection against all market losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Complete elimination of systematic risk through diversification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Zero cost of investment management]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** One of the primary advantages of mutual funds is affordable diversification. With as little as Rs. 500 (SIP minimum), an investor can gain exposure to a diversified portfolio of 40-60 stocks, which would require lakhs of rupees to replicate directly. Other MF advantages include professional management, economies of scale, liquidity, tax efficiency, transparency, flexibility, and regulation.

**The Trap:** Option B is wrong because no investment can guarantee protection against ALL market losses. Option C is wrong because diversification can reduce unsystematic (company-specific) risk but NOT systematic (market) risk. Option D is wrong because MFs charge expense ratios (TER) -- they are NOT free. These are classic "absolute statement" traps.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the distinction between systematic and unsystematic risk is fundamental. NISM XII tests risk concepts across all securities. The concept of TER (Total Expense Ratio) limiting costs is tested in NISM V-A Chapter on operations and compliance.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the diversification advantage as your primary pitch for first-time investors. Show them: "With Rs. 5,000, you can own a piece of 50 companies through a diversified equity fund. To buy even 1 share of each of those 50 companies directly, you might need Rs. 5 lakhs." This makes the concept tangible.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
