<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A Smart Beta fund uses which of the following approaches to construct its portfolio?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rule-based strategy that follows an alternative index weighting methodology instead of traditional market-cap weighting]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Active fund management based purely on the fund manager's discretionary stock picks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing only in beta-neutral (market-neutral) strategies with zero equity exposure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Algorithmic trading using artificial intelligence to time market entry and exit]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Smart Beta funds follow a rules-based (systematic) approach that uses alternative index construction methodologies instead of traditional market-cap weighting. They target specific "factors" like value, momentum, quality, low volatility, or equal weighting. These funds sit between purely passive (index) and fully active strategies -- they use a passive, rules-based approach but select/weight stocks differently than a standard index.

**The Trap:** Option B describes active management, which is the opposite of Smart Beta's rules-based approach. Option C confuses "beta" (market sensitivity) with "Smart Beta" (factor-based indexing) -- Smart Beta funds have equity exposure and are not market-neutral. Option D describes Quant Funds, which may use AI/ML for trading signals -- related but distinct from Smart Beta.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, Smart Beta is discussed alongside passive investment strategies and ETFs. In NISM XII, factor investing (value, momentum, quality, low volatility) is tested as part of modern portfolio theory. The distinction between Smart Beta and Quant Funds is a emerging exam topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Position Smart Beta funds for clients who are skeptical of active fund management but want something beyond plain vanilla index funds. Explain it as: "The stock selection is automatic based on proven factors like quality or value -- no fund manager bias, but smarter than just following the market." Be honest that factor strategies can underperform in certain market cycles.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
