<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Read the following scenario and answer Questions 25-28.

Mrs. Priya Sharma, aged 35, is a salaried professional with a monthly income of Rs. 1.5 lakh. She approaches her mutual fund distributor, Mr. Ankit, with three financial goals:

Goal 1: Tax saving for the current financial year (needs to invest Rs. 1.5 lakh under Section 80C).
Goal 2: Building a corpus for her daughter's higher education (daughter is 5 years old, needs funds in 13 years).
Goal 3: Parking Rs. 5 lakh emergency fund that she can access instantly at any time.

Mr. Ankit analyzes her goals and suggests three different schemes:
- Scheme A: An ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Scheme) with a 3-year lock-in period
- Scheme B: A Flexi Cap Fund with SIP of Rs. 10,000/month
- Scheme C: An Overnight Fund

The current NAV of Scheme A is Rs. 45, Scheme B is Rs. 120, and Scheme C is Rs. 1,015.

Question 25: For Goal 1 (tax saving), Mr. Ankit recommends Scheme A (ELSS). Under SEBI categorization, ELSS falls under which category?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Equity Schemes -- with a mandatory lock-in period of 3 years and minimum 80% investment in equity as per the ELSS guidelines]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Solution-Oriented Schemes -- because it solves the specific goal of tax saving]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Hybrid Schemes -- because ELSS invests in both equity and debt for tax efficiency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Other Schemes -- because tax-saving funds are a special regulatory category outside the standard classification]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Scheme) is classified under Equity Schemes in SEBI's categorization framework. It must invest a minimum of 80% of total assets in equity and equity-related instruments as per the Equity Linked Saving Scheme, 2005 guidelines. It carries a mandatory lock-in of 3 years, the shortest among all tax-saving investments under Section 80C. ELSS is one of the 10 equity sub-categories under SEBI norms.

**The Trap:** The most tempting distractor is Option B -- "Solution-Oriented Schemes" -- because ELSS does "solve" a tax-saving goal. However, SEBI categorization places ELSS under Equity Schemes, NOT Solution-Oriented. Solution-Oriented has ONLY two sub-categories: Retirement Benefit Scheme and Children's Fund. This is a high-frequency exam trap that tests whether candidates know the EXACT SEBI placement vs. logical inference.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the exact SEBI category placement of each scheme type is critical. NISM V-A tests the lock-in period knowledge (ELSS = 3 years, Solution-Oriented = 5 years). In NISM III-C, advisers must compare ELSS with other Section 80C options (PPF 15 years, NSC 5 years, FD 5 years) -- ELSS has the shortest lock-in with the highest return potential.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ELSS is the most distributor-friendly tax-saving product -- it has the shortest lock-in (3 years), potential for highest returns (equity exposure), and earns trail commission for the distributor. Always position ELSS first in your Section 80C recommendation, especially for clients in the higher tax brackets. After the 3-year lock-in, the units become open-ended for redemption.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
