<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund in India is legally constituted as which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A trust under the Indian Trusts Act, 1882]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A company under the Companies Act, 2013]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A partnership firm under the Indian Partnership Act, 1932]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A Limited Liability Partnership under the LLP Act, 2008]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A mutual fund in India is set up as a trust under the Indian Trusts Act, 1882. The trust is established by a sponsor and registered with SEBI. This trust structure ensures that the fund is managed for the benefit of the unitholders (beneficiaries) by the trustees, with the AMC acting as the investment manager.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse the legal structure of an AMC (which IS a company under the Companies Act) with the mutual fund itself. The AMC manages the fund, but the fund itself is a trust. Similarly, AIFs may be set up as trusts, companies, or LLPs -- but mutual funds can ONLY be trusts.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B (MF Foundation), this concept is tested alongside the four-tier structure (Sponsor-Trust-AMC-Custodian). In NISM III-C (Investment Adviser), you need to distinguish MF trust structure from PMS (which operates via a SEBI-registered portfolio manager, not a trust).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining to clients why their money is safe, emphasize the trust structure -- the AMC cannot use investor money for its own purposes because the trust holds assets separately. This fiduciary responsibility is the bedrock of investor protection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
