<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mark to Market (MTM) valuation in the context of mutual funds means:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Valuing portfolio securities at their current market price rather than their acquisition cost]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Valuing portfolio securities at the price at which they were originally purchased]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Valuing portfolio securities at their face value or par value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Valuing portfolio securities at the average of purchase price and current market price]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mark to Market (MTM) means valuing all securities in the mutual fund portfolio at their current market price as on the valuation date. This ensures that the NAV reflects the true, real-time value of the portfolio. Without MTM, the NAV would be based on historical costs and would not represent the actual worth of an investor's holdings.

**The Trap:** Option B describes historical cost accounting, which is NOT used for NAV computation of MF schemes. Option D (average of purchase and market price) sounds reasonable but is completely fictitious -- no such valuation method exists in MF accounting. Some debt securities that are not traded may use amortization-based valuation, but even that is moving towards MTM under SEBI guidelines.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, MTM connects to NAV computation methodology. In NISM XII, MTM is discussed in the broader context of fair value accounting across financial instruments. Post the Franklin Templeton episode, SEBI tightened MTM norms for debt funds -- a topic frequently tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients see sudden NAV drops in debt funds, explain that MTM causes NAV to reflect credit events or interest rate changes immediately. This is actually a feature (transparency) not a bug. Side-pocketing is the mechanism used when MTM reveals credit defaults.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
