<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor seeking the HIGHEST combination of safety and liquidity with minimal return expectation should invest in which type of mutual fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Overnight Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Liquid Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ultra Short Duration Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Money Market Fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Among the options, Overnight Funds invest in securities with a maturity of 1 day, making them the safest and most liquid category. They carry virtually zero credit risk and zero interest rate risk. The trade-off is that returns are the lowest among all debt fund categories. The investment objectives triangle (Safety-Liquidity-Returns) dictates that maximizing two objectives means the third will be minimized.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse Liquid Funds with Overnight Funds. Liquid Funds invest in securities with maturity up to 91 days -- they offer high safety and liquidity but carry marginally more risk than Overnight Funds. Ultra Short Duration Funds (3-6 months Macaulay duration) and Money Market Funds (up to 1 year maturity) carry even more risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B tests the entire spectrum of debt fund categories by duration. The 16 SEBI-defined debt fund categories (from Overnight to Long Duration) are frequently tested. In NISM III-C (Investment Adviser), matching fund category to client risk profile is a key competency.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Recommend Overnight Funds for parking emergency funds or short-term surplus. They are superior to savings bank accounts for amounts above Rs. 1 lakh (post-tax returns often beat savings account interest). No exit load, no lock-in -- true instant liquidity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
