<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's mutual fund categorization norms (2017), how many sub-categories are permitted under Equity Schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[10 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[6 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[16 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[11 sub-categories]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's 2017 categorization circular defined 10 sub-categories under Equity Schemes: Multi Cap, Large Cap, Large & Mid Cap, Mid Cap, Small Cap, Dividend Yield, Value/Contra, Focused, Sectoral/Thematic, and ELSS. Each AMC can have only ONE scheme per sub-category (with some exceptions like index funds and sectoral/thematic funds). Note: Flexi Cap was added later, making it 11 in practice, but the original 2017 circular had 10.

**The Trap:** 16 is the number of Debt fund sub-categories, not Equity. 6 is the number of Hybrid fund sub-categories. Candidates who mix up these numbers across categories lose easy marks. A useful memory aid: Equity=10, Debt=16, Hybrid=6, Solution-oriented=2, Other=2 (Total = 36 categories).

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B goes deeper into each sub-category with minimum investment thresholds (e.g., Large Cap must invest minimum 80% in top 100 stocks by market cap). NISM XII tests the rationale behind SEBI's categorization -- reducing confusion and enabling apple-to-apple comparison.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When recommending equity funds, always clarify the SEBI category. A "Multi Cap" fund is NOT the same as a "Flexi Cap" fund -- Multi Cap must invest minimum 25% each in large, mid, and small caps, while Flexi Cap has full discretion. This distinction matters for client risk profiling.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
