<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued from Question 25):

Question 26: Mrs. Sharma invests her Rs. 5 lakh emergency fund in Scheme C (Overnight Fund) at a NAV of Rs. 1,015 per unit. After 30 days, the NAV increases to Rs. 1,016.25. Which of the following BEST explains why the NAV change is minimal?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Overnight Funds invest in securities with 1-day maturity, carrying negligible credit and interest rate risk, resulting in very small but stable daily NAV movements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager is performing poorly and the fund is generating below-average returns compared to equity benchmarks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The NAV is artificially suppressed by the AMC to maintain stability for conservative investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overnight Funds have a regulatory cap on the maximum NAV increase permitted per month]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Overnight Funds invest exclusively in securities with a residual maturity of 1 day (overnight instruments like CBLO, tri-party repo, overnight reverse repo). With 1-day maturity, these instruments carry virtually zero credit risk and zero interest rate risk. The returns are modest (roughly equivalent to the overnight lending rate) but extremely stable. The NAV increase of Rs. 1.25 on a base of Rs. 1,015 over 30 days translates to approximately 1.48% annualized -- typical for overnight funds.

**The Trap:** Option B attempts to make candidates compare overnight fund returns with equity returns, which is an apples-to-oranges comparison. Different categories serve different purposes. Option C suggests market manipulation, which is false -- NAV must be calculated based on actual portfolio values. Option D is fabricated -- there is no regulatory cap on NAV movement for any fund category.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the risk-return spectrum across all 16 debt categories (from Overnight at the safest end to Credit Risk/Long Duration at the riskier end) is fundamental. NISM XII tests the relationship between maturity/duration and risk. Understanding why different debt categories generate different returns is core exam knowledge.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the Overnight Fund NAV movement to educate clients about risk-return trade-off. Show them: "Your Rs. 5 lakh in Overnight Fund earned Rs. 617 in 30 days (approximately). In a Long Duration Fund, it might have earned Rs. 2,500 -- but could also have LOST Rs. 5,000 if rates moved adversely. For emergency money, stability is more important than maximizing returns."]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
