<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In an open-ended mutual fund scheme, units can be purchased and redeemed:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[On any business day at the applicable NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only during the New Fund Offer (NFO) period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only on the stock exchange where the fund is listed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only at specified intervals as declared by the AMC]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Open-ended funds are characterized by continuous offer of units for purchase and redemption at the prevailing NAV on any business day. There is no fixed maturity period, and the fund stands ready to buy back (redeem) units at all times. This is the most common structure in India, constituting over 95% of all MF schemes.

**The Trap:** Option B describes a close-ended fund (where units are offered only during NFO and have a fixed maturity). Option C describes ETFs (Exchange Traded Funds), which trade on stock exchanges like shares. Option D describes an Interval fund, which allows transactions only during specified intervals. Each option describes a REAL but DIFFERENT fund structure.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B deeply covers the operational mechanics of each structure. In NISM XII, the distinction matters for understanding market liquidity -- open-ended funds provide liquidity by creating/canceling units, while close-ended funds have fixed capital and trade on exchanges.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always clarify to clients that "open-ended" means they can exit anytime (subject to exit load). This is the single biggest advantage for retail investors compared to close-ended funds or traditional insurance policies. However, warn them about exit loads applicable in the first 1-2 years for equity funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
