<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A Fixed Maturity Plan (FMP) is structured as which type of mutual fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Close-ended debt fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Open-ended debt fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Interval equity fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Close-ended hybrid fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Fixed Maturity Plan (FMP) is a close-ended debt fund with a specific maturity date. The fund manager invests in debt instruments whose maturity aligns with the FMP's tenure, effectively locking in a yield at the time of investment. Since it is close-ended, units are offered only during the NFO and the fund has a fixed maturity period (commonly 1 year, 3 years, or 5 years).

**The Trap:** FMPs are often confused with Fixed Deposits because of the word "Fixed" in the name. However, FMPs are NOT guaranteed-return products. They are debt funds subject to credit risk. Also, FMPs are NOT open-ended -- you cannot redeem before maturity from the AMC. The units are listed on exchanges but may trade at a discount to NAV.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, FMPs are tested alongside Capital Protection Oriented Funds and Target Maturity Funds. In NISM III-C, FMPs are relevant for tax planning since a 3-year+ FMP used to qualify for indexation benefits on LTCG (rules have changed post-2023 tax amendments for debt funds).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** With the 2023 tax changes removing indexation benefits for debt funds, FMPs have lost their primary tax advantage. However, they still serve a purpose for investors seeking relatively predictable returns over a fixed tenure without interest rate risk (since securities are held to maturity). Discuss this trade-off with clients honestly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
