<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Investment policy of a mutual fund scheme comprises two key components. These are:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Asset allocation and investment style]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NAV calculation method and expense ratio structure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Entry load and exit load policy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Benchmark selection and dividend distribution policy]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The investment policy of a mutual fund scheme has two components: (1) Asset Allocation -- which determines WHAT asset classes the fund invests in (equity, debt, gold, etc.) and in what proportion, and (2) Investment Style -- which determines HOW the fund manager selects securities within those asset classes (growth vs. value, focused vs. diversified, active vs. passive). Together, these define the fund's investment approach.

**The Trap:** The other options describe operational or structural aspects of a fund, not its investment policy. NAV calculation and expense ratio are accounting/regulatory features. Entry/exit loads are pricing features (note: SEBI banned entry loads in 2009). Benchmark and dividend policy are disclosure/distribution features. None of these define the investment policy itself.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, investment policy connects to the Scheme Information Document (SID), which must clearly state the fund's asset allocation pattern and investment strategy. In NISM III-C, advisers must evaluate a fund's investment policy to determine its suitability for clients.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When comparing two funds in the same SEBI category, look at their investment style. For example, two Large Cap funds may have very different outcomes -- one following a growth style (buying high-growth companies at premium valuations) vs. value style (buying undervalued stocks). This explains performance divergence within the same category.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
