<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An Interval Fund combines features of which two types of fund structures?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Open-ended and close-ended funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity and debt funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Domestic and international funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Active and passive funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An Interval Fund is a unique structure that combines features of both open-ended and close-ended funds. It remains close-ended for most of the time (units cannot be redeemed) but opens at specified intervals (called "transaction periods") for purchase and redemption at NAV. These transaction periods must be at least 2 days and the minimum gap between two transaction periods must be 15 days. The fund must be listed on an exchange for liquidity between intervals.

**The Trap:** The question asks about fund STRUCTURE classification, not investment classification. Options B, C, and D describe investment-related combinations (asset type, geography, management style), not structural features. A hybrid fund combines equity and debt (investment classification), while an interval fund combines open-ended and close-ended features (structural classification). This distinction between classification dimensions is key.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B tests the three structural types (open-ended, close-ended, interval) as fundamental concepts. In NISM XII, interval funds are compared with listed investment companies in global markets. Interval funds are relatively rare in India, with FMPs and close-ended equity funds being more common.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Interval funds are uncommon in practice, but understanding the concept is exam-critical. If you ever encounter one, explain to clients that they can only transact during specific windows. For most retail investors, open-ended funds offer far better liquidity and flexibility. Recommend interval funds only when the specific investment strategy requires limited redemption windows (e.g., certain debt strategies).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
