<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A close-ended mutual fund scheme has a fixed maturity period and units are mandatorily listed on:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A recognized stock exchange to provide liquidity to investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC's website for direct redemption by investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both stock exchange and AMC platform simultaneously]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The RTA (Registrar and Transfer Agent) platform]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations mandate that close-ended schemes must list their units on at least one recognized stock exchange. Since close-ended funds do not offer continuous repurchase (unlike open-ended funds), listing on a stock exchange is the primary mechanism for investors to exit before maturity. Investors can sell their units on the exchange to other buyers, just like selling shares.

**The Trap:** Close-ended funds do NOT allow redemption through the AMC before maturity (unlike open-ended funds). The AMC website and RTA platform are used for open-ended fund transactions, not close-ended. Some candidates confuse interval funds (which allow periodic transactions with the AMC) with close-ended funds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the listing requirement connects to SEBI (Mutual Funds) Regulations, 1996. NISM XII covers listing requirements across various securities. The practical challenge with close-ended fund listing is that units often trade at a discount to NAV due to low liquidity on exchanges.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When selling close-ended funds (like ELSS or FMPs), always inform clients that while units are listed on exchanges, liquidity may be thin. They should ideally be prepared to hold until maturity. The exchange listing is a safety valve, not a primary exit route.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
