<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An AMC wants to launch a new equity scheme called "Growth Opportunities Fund" that will invest in high-growth mid-cap and small-cap companies. Under SEBI categorization norms, the AMC can launch this scheme ONLY if:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It does not already have a scheme in the same SEBI-defined sub-category, as only one scheme per sub-category is generally permitted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It merges all existing equity schemes into this single new scheme first]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It obtains approval from RBI since this involves equity market participation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The scheme name includes the SEBI category name verbatim in its title]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's 2017 categorization circular mandates that each AMC can have only ONE scheme per sub-category (with limited exceptions for index funds, ETFs, sectoral/thematic funds, and Fund of Funds). This was introduced to reduce scheme proliferation and confusion. If the AMC already has a Mid Cap fund, it cannot launch another Mid Cap fund. The AMC must ensure the new scheme falls into a sub-category where it doesn't already have an existing scheme.

**The Trap:** Option B is extreme -- SEBI never required merging ALL equity schemes, only those that didn't fit the new categorization had to be merged, re-categorized, or wound up. Option C is wrong because SEBI (not RBI) regulates mutual funds. Option D is incorrect -- while the scheme name should not be misleading, it doesn't need to contain the exact SEBI category name verbatim.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the one-scheme-per-category rule and its exceptions are tested in detail. NISM V-A tests the distributor's responsibility to understand scheme categorization for recommending the right fund. The 2017 re-categorization caused massive scheme mergers across the industry -- this historical context is relevant for NISM XII.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The one-scheme-per-category rule benefits distributors and clients alike. Before 2017, an AMC might have had 5 different "large cap" funds with confusing names. Now, with one scheme per category, comparison is straightforward. Use SEBI category as the first filter when shortlisting schemes for clients, then evaluate performance, expense ratio, and fund manager track record within that category.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
