<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued from Question 25):

Question 27: Scheme A (ELSS) is close-ended with a 3-year lock-in, while Scheme B (Flexi Cap Fund) is open-ended. If Mrs. Sharma wants to redeem units of Scheme A before the 3-year lock-in period ends, which statement is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[She cannot redeem units from the AMC before the lock-in period; however, ELSS units are listed on stock exchanges where she may sell, though liquidity is typically poor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She can redeem units from the AMC at any time by paying a penalty of 1% of NAV as early redemption charge]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She can redeem units after 1 year by forfeiting the Section 80C tax benefit already claimed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She cannot sell or transfer ELSS units under any circumstances until the 3-year lock-in expires]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ELSS has a mandatory 3-year lock-in period during which units cannot be redeemed from the AMC. However, since ELSS units of close-ended schemes (or close-ended tranches) are mandatorily listed on stock exchanges, an investor can technically sell units on the exchange to another buyer. In practice, exchange liquidity for ELSS units is very poor, and units often trade at a significant discount to NAV. After the 3-year lock-in, ELSS units become open-ended and can be redeemed at NAV from the AMC.

**The Trap:** Option B is fabricated -- there is no early redemption penalty mechanism for ELSS. The lock-in is absolute from the AMC's side. Option C is wrong -- you cannot redeem after 1 year, and the tax benefit once claimed cannot be "forfeited" to enable early redemption. Option D is wrong because it says "under any circumstances" -- exchange sale is technically possible, making this option too absolute.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-A, the lock-in mechanism and listing requirement for ELSS are tested. NISM V-B covers the structural difference between how close-ended (listed, no AMC redemption) and open-ended (AMC redemption anytime) funds provide liquidity. In NISM III-C, advisers must explain these liquidity constraints during suitability assessment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always inform ELSS investors upfront: "Your money is locked for 3 years. Do NOT invest emergency funds in ELSS." While exchange listing exists, selling on exchange usually results in a loss (discount to NAV + brokerage). For SIP investors in ELSS, each SIP installment has its own 3-year lock-in from the date of investment -- the first SIP completes 3 years while the last 36th SIP still has 3 years to go.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
