<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[ESG Investing in mutual funds focuses on companies meeting criteria related to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Environmental stewardship, Social responsibility, and corporate Governance standards]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Earnings growth, Share price momentum, and GDP correlation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exchange listing, SEBI compliance, and Global diversification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity allocation, Sector rotation, and Growth-value balance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ESG stands for Environmental, Social, and Governance. ESG investing evaluates companies based on: Environmental factors (carbon emissions, waste management, resource efficiency), Social factors (labor practices, human rights, community impact, diversity), and Governance factors (board composition, executive compensation, shareholder rights, transparency). ESG funds invest only in companies that meet specified ESG criteria or score well on ESG ratings.

**The Trap:** The distractors cleverly create alternative "ESG" acronyms that sound plausible. Candidates who don't know the actual meaning of ESG might pick an option that sounds financially relevant. This is a straightforward knowledge question but the acronym-confusion trap is effective on test day.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B covers ESG as a thematic investment approach. SEBI has introduced disclosure requirements for ESG schemes including Business Responsibility and Sustainability Reporting (BRSR). In NISM XII, ESG is tested under responsible investing and sustainable finance topics, which are increasingly important globally.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ESG funds are growing rapidly in India. When recommending them, explain that ESG is not just "feel-good investing" -- companies with strong ESG practices often demonstrate better long-term risk management and sustainability. However, clarify that ESG funds may have a concentrated portfolio (excluding many sectors), which can lead to periods of underperformance vs. broader indices.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
