<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a disadvantage of investing through mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Costs in the form of expense ratios which dilute overall returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lack of any regulatory oversight on fund operations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Inability to invest small amounts through systematic plans]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Complete absence of portfolio transparency]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mutual funds charge an expense ratio (TER - Total Expense Ratio) that covers fund management fees, distribution costs, administrative expenses, and other operational costs. This cost directly reduces investor returns. For example, if the portfolio generates 12% return and TER is 2%, the investor gets approximately 10%. This is a genuine disadvantage compared to direct stock investing where no ongoing management fee applies.

**The Trap:** Options B, C, and D are factually WRONG -- they describe the opposite of reality. MFs are heavily regulated by SEBI (Option B is false). SIPs allow investments as low as Rs. 500 (Option C is false). SEBI mandates monthly portfolio disclosure (Option D is false). The actual disadvantages of MFs include: costs (TER), no guaranteed returns, over-diversification risk, dilution of returns, and selection complexity.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, TER limits are detailed (e.g., 2.25% for equity AUM up to Rs. 500 crore, with slabs reducing as AUM increases). NISM V-A tests the distributor's obligation to disclose all costs to investors. In NISM III-C, advisers must compare costs across investment products (MF vs PMS vs AIF).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Be transparent about costs. Show clients the difference between Direct Plan (lower TER) and Regular Plan (higher TER that includes your commission). An informed client is a retained client. The cost difference can compound to significant amounts over 20+ years.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
