<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Concept and Role of Mutual Fund_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund scheme has 10 crore units outstanding with a face value of Rs. 10 per unit. The current NAV of the scheme is Rs. 25 per unit. What is the AUM (Assets Under Management) of this scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 250 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 100 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 150 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 350 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AUM (Assets Under Management) represents the total market value of all assets managed by the scheme. It is calculated as:
AUM = NAV per unit x Total Number of Outstanding Units

AUM = Rs. 25 x 10 crore units = Rs. 250 crore

Note that AUM is calculated using NAV (market value per unit), NOT face value. The face value (Rs. 10) is used only to calculate Unit Capital (Face Value x Units = Rs. 100 crore), which represents the initial capital, not the current market value.

**The Trap:** Option B (Rs. 100 crore) is what you get if you use face value (Rs. 10) instead of NAV (Rs. 25) -- this gives you Unit Capital, not AUM. This is the most common trap. Option C (Rs. 150 crore) might result from subtracting unit capital from AUM. Option D (Rs. 350 crore) could result from adding face value and NAV (10+25=35 x 10 crore).

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, AUM is used to determine expense ratio slabs (TER limits reduce as AUM increases). In NISM XII, industry AUM figures are used to measure the size of the MF industry. As of recent data, Indian MF industry AUM has crossed Rs. 60 lakh crore. Unit Capital vs. AUM distinction is a key exam concept.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** AUM is a key indicator for clients evaluating fund size. Larger AUM generally indicates investor confidence, but very large AUM can be a disadvantage for small/mid cap funds (difficulty deploying large capital in smaller stocks without impacting prices). For debt funds, larger AUM usually means better negotiating power for yields and lower impact cost.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
