<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Corporate Actions_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[After a bonus issue, what happens to the total value of a shareholder's holdings (immediately, before any market movement)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It remains the same as the share price adjusts proportionally downward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It decreases because new shares dilute the value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It increases by the bonus ratio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It increases because bonus shares are issued from free reserves]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A bonus issue increases the number of outstanding shares but does not change the company's fundamentals or total market capitalization (immediately). The share price adjusts downward proportionally, so the total value of each shareholder's holdings remains the same. For example, if you hold 100 shares at Rs.200 each (total Rs.20,000) and receive 1:1 bonus, you now have 200 shares at approximately Rs.100 each (still Rs.20,000).
**The Trap:** Candidates often think bonus shares represent "free money." While shareholders receive additional shares without paying, the price adjusts to keep total value constant. The real benefit is long-term if the company grows.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers bonus impact on mutual fund NAV adjustment; NISM Series VIII covers price adjustment in derivative contracts.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Explain to clients that bonus shares are a sign of company confidence and financial strength (issued from accumulated profits), but the immediate economic impact is neutral. The long-term benefit depends on the company's future earnings growth.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
