<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Corporate Actions_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[During a merger of Company A (transferor) into Company B (transferee), Anand holds 1,000 demat shares of Company A. The approved exchange ratio is 3:5 (3 shares of B for every 5 shares of A). What happens to Anand's holdings?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He retains his 1,000 shares of Company A unchanged]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He receives 1,667 shares of Company B in addition to retaining his Company A shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He must sell his Company A shares on the stock exchange before the merger completes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[His 1,000 shares of Company A are cancelled and he receives 600 shares of Company B]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Exchange ratio 3:5 means for every 5 shares of Company A, the holder receives 3 shares of Company B. Anand holds 1,000 shares of A. New shares of B = (3/5) × 1,000 = 600 shares. His Company A shares are cancelled (Company A ceases to exist in the merger), and he receives 600 shares of Company B.
**The Trap:** Candidates may reverse the ratio (getting 1,667 shares) or think the old shares are retained alongside new shares. In an amalgamation, the transferor company ceases to exist, so its shares must be cancelled.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX covers merger exchange ratios and valuation; Series II-A covers the RTA's role in executing the share exchange.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a merger is announced, help clients understand the exchange ratio and calculate their new holding. Also check the tax implications -- share exchange in a court/NCLT-approved merger is generally tax-neutral under Section 47.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
