<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Corporate Actions_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Bharati Infosystems Ltd. (BIL), a listed IT company, has 2 crore outstanding equity shares with a face value of Rs.5 each. The current market price is Rs.400 per share. BIL has accumulated free reserves of Rs.500 crore and paid-up capital of Rs.10 crore.

On March 1, 2025, the Board of Directors approves a bonus issue in the ratio of 1:1 (one bonus share for every one share held). The record date is set as March 15, 2025 (T Day). Naveen Sharma, the RTA officer, is responsible for processing the bonus issue. The beneficial owner download from the depository shows 15,000 individual shareholders and 200 institutional shareholders.

Three months later, on June 15, 2025, BIL's Board announces a buyback of shares through tender offer at Rs.220 per share (post-bonus adjusted price), for a total buyback amount of Rs.88 crore. The record date for the buyback is July 1, 2025. Ramesh Gupta, a retail investor, holds 2,000 shares (post-bonus) with a market value of Rs.4.2 lakh on the record date. Seema Jain, another investor, holds 800 post-bonus shares with a market value of Rs.1.68 lakh on the record date.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Under the revised SEBI timeline (effective October 2024), when will trading in BIL's bonus shares commence if the record date is March 15, 2025?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[March 15, 2025 (same day as record date)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[March 17, 2025 (T+2)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[March 20, 2025 (T+5 working days)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[March 22, 2025 (T+7 days)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the revised framework: Record date = T Day (March 15). Deemed allotment = T+1 (March 16). Trading commences = T+2 (March 17). No temporary ISIN is needed; bonus shares are credited directly to the permanent ISIN and are available for trading on T+2.
**The Trap:** Candidates using older material may recall longer timelines with temporary ISINs. The October 2024 revision significantly compressed the bonus processing timeline. Note: Calendar days are used here, not working days.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VI covers depository processing timelines; Series II-A covers the RTA's role in meeting these compressed timelines.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The T+2 trading start means clients can sell bonus shares within 2 days of the record date. This is important for clients who want to quickly rebalance their portfolios after a bonus issue.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
