<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Depository Services and Dematerialisation_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is an advantage of holding securities in dematerialised form compared to physical form?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Higher dividend rate is paid on dematerialised securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dematerialised securities are exempt from capital gains tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No stamp duty is payable on transfer of dematerialised securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dematerialised securities carry double voting rights]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** One of the key financial advantages of demat holding is the elimination of stamp duty on transfer. Physical share transfers attract stamp duty, but electronic transfers through the depository system are exempt. Other advantages include elimination of risk of loss, mutilation, forgery, faster transactions, easier transfer/transmission/nomination, and lower overall transaction costs.

**The Trap:** Demat does not change the fundamental characteristics of the security — the dividend rate, tax treatment, and voting rights remain the same whether held in physical or demat form. The advantages are operational and cost-related, not substantive changes to the security itself.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Note that no stamp duty is payable on dematerialisation itself either. This is a separate advantage — the conversion process from physical to electronic is also stamp-duty-free, encouraging investors to shift to demat.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The stamp duty saving is a compelling argument for clients still holding physical certificates. For frequent traders, the cumulative stamp duty savings on transfers can be substantial. Use this as a key selling point for demat conversion.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
