<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Depository Services and Dematerialisation_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When unclaimed shares are credited to the Investor Education and Protection Fund (IEPF), which of the following statements is TRUE?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The shares are treated as a transfer and stamp duty is applicable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The rightful owner permanently loses all rights over the shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All corporate action benefits including rights issues are credited to IEPF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It is treated as deemed transmission, and voting rights remain frozen until the rightful owner claims]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Crediting shares to IEPF is treated as a deemed transmission (not a transfer), which means no stamp duty applies. Voting rights on these shares are frozen until the rightful owner claims them. All benefits like bonus, split, and consolidation are credited to IEPF, but rights issues are specifically excluded.

**The Trap:** Two common traps here: (1) confusing transmission with transfer — transmission happens by operation of law and does not attract stamp duty; (2) assuming all corporate benefits go to IEPF — rights issues are the exception because they require the shareholder to actively apply and pay.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The rightful owner can reclaim shares from IEPF by filing Form IEPF-5, and the refund is made to their Aadhaar-linked bank account. The shares must be credited to IEPF within 30 days of becoming due. This connects to the broader investor protection framework.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Proactively help clients check if any of their holdings have been transferred to IEPF due to non-claiming of dividends for 7 consecutive years. The IEPF Authority maintains a searchable database. Recovery is possible but involves paperwork.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
