<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Depository Services and Dematerialisation_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Meera opens a demat account with a DP. Which of the following is NOT a right she enjoys as a beneficial owner of dematerialised securities?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to receive dividends and other entitlements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to pledge her securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to nominate a person to receive securities in case of her death]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Right to appoint or remove the Depository Participant's compliance officer]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A beneficial owner's rights include: transacting freely, receiving entitlements (dividends, bonus, rights, interest), exercising voting rights, consolidation, transfer, transposition, nomination, and pledge. However, the appointment or removal of a DP's compliance officer is an internal governance matter of the DP entity, not an investor right.

**The Trap:** The question tests whether candidates can distinguish between investor rights and DP governance. All the other options are genuine BO rights — dividends, pledge, and nomination. The compliance officer appointment is clearly a corporate function of the DP.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The DP must provide monthly transaction statements at minimum. If there are no transactions, a statement must still be sent at least once a year. This transparency obligation supports the BO's rights.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Encourage clients to exercise all their BO rights, especially nomination. Many investors neglect to set up nomination in their demat accounts, which creates complications for their families in case of the investor's demise.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
