<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Depository Services and Dematerialisation_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Sunita wants to convert her dematerialised shares back into physical form. What is the maximum time allowed for the RTA to complete the rematerialisation process?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[30 days from receipt of the request]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[15 days from receipt of the request]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[21 days from receipt of the request]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[45 days from receipt of the request]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rematerialisation must be completed within 30 days. This is longer than the 15-day dematerialisation timeline because remat involves additional steps — creating a new folio, assigning new certificate numbers and distinctive numbers, affixing revenue stamps, and applying the company's common seal on the certificate.

**The Trap:** The most common confusion is between 15 days (demat) and 30 days (remat). A useful mnemonic: Physical to Electronic is faster (15 days) because it involves destruction; Electronic to Physical is slower (30 days) because it involves creation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** During rematerialisation, the DP first validates the investor's signature and checks free balance. New certificate numbers and distinctive numbers are assigned from the already-dematerialised shares range. The BO's name replaces the depository's name in the ROM.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Discourage clients from rematerialising unless absolutely necessary. Physical certificates carry risks of loss, theft, forgery, and stamp duty on transfer. Also, most market transactions now require demat form.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
