<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Derivative Markets_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An interest rate swap is a derivative contract where two parties agree to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Exchange interest rate payments, typically fixed rate for floating rate, on a notional principal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exchange the principal amount of their respective loans]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buy and sell equity shares at a predetermined price]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Deliver physical commodities at agreed upon prices]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In an interest rate swap, one party pays a fixed rate and receives a floating rate, while the other does the opposite. The principal amount (called notional principal) on which interest is computed is agreed upon, but only the interest payments are exchanged — the principal itself is NOT exchanged. Swaps are common in interest rate and currency markets and are typically OTC.

**The Trap:** The principal amount is NOT exchanged — only interest payments are. Swaps are not about equity shares or physical commodities. Swaps help borrowers convert floating rate obligations to fixed rate, or vice versa, based on their risk preferences.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Derivatives basics overlap with Series VIII, XIII. Swaps are advanced derivatives — the foundation exam tests the basic concept, while specialized exams go deeper.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Swaps are typically used by institutional participants like banks and corporates. For retail investors, understanding swaps helps them appreciate how interest rate risk is managed in the broader financial system, even if they do not directly participate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
