<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Derivative Markets_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Arbitrage in the derivatives market involves:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Exploiting price differentials between the cash and derivatives markets for riskless profits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Taking a long position expecting prices to rise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Using derivatives to protect an existing portfolio from losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Writing options to earn premium income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Arbitrageurs evaluate whether the price difference between cash and derivative markets exceeds the cost of borrowing. If yes, they buy in the cheaper market and sell in the expensive one, locking in the differential. If both trades are settled on the expiry date, they make the gain less interest costs, irrespective of the settlement price — as both legs settle at the same price on expiry.

**The Trap:** Taking a long position is speculation, not arbitrage. Protecting portfolios is hedging. Writing options for premium is an income strategy. Arbitrage specifically involves simultaneous positions in two markets to exploit price differences with minimal risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Derivatives basics overlap with Series VIII, XIII. Arbitrage is also relevant to understanding arbitrage mutual funds in the MF context.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Arbitrage opportunities in well-functioning markets are small and short-lived. Arbitrage mutual funds use this strategy systematically — they buy stocks in the cash market and sell equivalent futures, capturing the spread. This makes them relatively low-risk despite having 65%+ equity allocation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
