<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Derivative Markets_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements correctly distinguishes OTC derivatives from exchange-traded derivatives?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[OTC derivatives are non-standard and carry counterparty risk, while exchange-traded derivatives are standardized and settled through a clearing corporation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[OTC derivatives are more liquid than exchange-traded derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[OTC derivatives are regulated by SEBI while exchange-traded derivatives are unregulated]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[OTC derivatives require margin deposits while exchange-traded derivatives do not]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** OTC derivatives are settled between counterparties on mutually agreed terms — they are non-standard and carry counterparty risk (risk of one party defaulting). They are prevalent between institutions that trust each other. Exchange-traded derivatives are standardized, defined by the exchange, and settled through a clearing corporation, which eliminates counterparty risk through margins.

**The Trap:** Exchange-traded derivatives are typically more liquid due to standardization. Both types have regulatory oversight. Exchange-traded derivatives (not OTC) require margin deposits with the clearing corporation. Forwards are OTC; futures are exchange-traded.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Derivatives basics overlap with Series VIII, XIII. The OTC vs exchange-traded distinction is tested across all derivative certification exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For retail investors, exchange-traded derivatives offer the safety of standardized contracts and clearing corporation guarantees. OTC derivatives are primarily for institutional participants who can manage counterparty risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
