<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Derivative Markets_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Since October 2019, what settlement method has SEBI mandated for all stock derivatives (futures and options on individual securities) that remain open on expiry?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Physical settlement (delivery of underlying stock)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cash settlement only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Either cash or physical settlement at the choice of the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Net settlement through clearing corporation without delivery]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Since October 2019, SEBI has mandated physical settlement (settlement by delivery of underlying stock) for all stock derivatives. All positions in futures and options on individual securities which remain open on the expiry date of the contract are to be settled by physical delivery only. However, Index futures and Index options contracts continue to be settled in cash.

**The Trap:** Cash settlement was the earlier practice for stock derivatives. Students may recall the pre-2019 regime. The choice between cash and physical is not available - physical delivery is mandatory for stock derivatives. Index derivatives remain cash-settled, and confusing stock with index derivatives is a common error.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The shift to physical settlement is tested in NISM VIII (Equity Derivatives) and NISM XII. This represents a significant regulatory change in derivative market structure.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Physical settlement means clients holding open positions in stock futures or in-the-money stock options at expiry must be prepared for actual delivery of shares. Ensure clients have adequate funds in their trading accounts and shares in their demat accounts to fulfill settlement obligations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>