<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Derivative Markets_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A Professional Clearing Member (PCM) in the derivatives market is typically a bank or custodian that __________. Unlike a Trading Member Clearing Member (TM-CM), a PCM does not have trading rights.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[can clear and settle trades for other trading members but cannot trade on its own account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[can both trade and clear for other members]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[can only clear and settle its own proprietary trades]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[performs the same functions as a Trading Member Clearing Member]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** There are three types of clearing members in derivatives markets: (1) TM-CM (Trading Member Clearing Member) -- can both trade and clear for self and others; (2) PCM (Professional Clearing Member) -- can clear and settle for others but cannot trade on its own; typically banks and custodians; (3) SCM (Self-Clearing Member) -- can only clear and settle its own trades. The PCM's role is purely clearing and settlement, providing this service to trading members who are not clearing members.

**The Trap:** "Can both trade and clear" describes a TM-CM, not a PCM. "Can only clear own trades" describes an SCM. "Performs the same functions as TM-CM" is wrong because TM-CM has trading rights while PCM does not. The key distinction is that PCM = clearing only, no trading.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Clearing member categories are tested in NISM Series XII and VIII (Equity Derivatives). Understanding the three-tier clearing membership structure is essential.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PCM = clearing for others, no trading. TM-CM = trading + clearing for self and others. SCM = clearing for self only. Banks and custodians typically operate as PCMs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>