<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Discussion on PMLA-related Cases_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the common lesson that emerges from all the PMLA-related cases discussed in Chapter 8?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Reporting entities must implement AML mechanism, categorize clients by risk, properly handle alerts/STRs, and appoint a Principal Officer -- failure attracts penalties]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only large intermediaries need to worry about AML compliance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Penalties for AML violations are always minimal and can be ignored]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FIU-IND and SEBI do not have enforcement powers for AML violations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Across all cases, the common themes are: (1) implement a proper AML mechanism -- not just on paper but in practice, (2) categorize clients into risk categories with documented basis, (3) properly investigate and document alert handling, (4) appoint a Principal Officer and inform FIU-IND timely, and (5) correct deficiencies promptly when identified. Penalties range from Rs. 1 lakh to Rs. 9.27 Crore.

**The Trap:** AML compliance applies to ALL entities regardless of size. Penalties are NOT minimal -- they range from lakhs to crores. Both FIU-IND and SEBI have strong enforcement powers.

**Cross-Exam Context:** These case studies bring together concepts from all chapters. The practical application of PMLA, PML Rules, SEBI circulars, and FIU-IND requirements is demonstrated through real enforcement actions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The cases teach a clear hierarchy: (1) have policies documented, (2) implement them in practice, (3) monitor and report actively, (4) correct deficiencies immediately when found, and (5) cooperate fully with regulators. Proactive compliance is always cheaper than reactive penalties and litigation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
