<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Discussion on PMLA-related Cases_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What was the penalty imposed on SKSE Securities for failure to have an AML policy in place and delayed appointment of a Principal Officer?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 2,00,000 (Two Lakh Rupees)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1,00,000 (One Lakh Rupees)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3,00,000 (Three Lakh Rupees)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 5,00,000 (Five Lakh Rupees)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In the SKSE Securities case, a penalty of Rs. 2,00,000 was imposed for the intermediary's failure to have an Anti-Money Laundering policy in place and for the delayed appointment of a Principal Officer. These are fundamental compliance obligations, and the penalty reflects the seriousness of non-compliance with basic AML infrastructure requirements.

**The Trap:** Candidates may guess higher amounts like Rs. 3 lakh or Rs. 5 lakh assuming severe penalties for AML failures. The Rs. 1 lakh option may seem plausible as a minimum penalty. The actual amount of Rs. 2 lakh is a specific figure from the case that must be memorised.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This case demonstrates that even basic compliance failures - not having an AML policy and delaying Principal Officer appointment - attract monetary penalties. It serves as a warning that compliance infrastructure must be in place from the outset of operations, not implemented reactively.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SKSE Securities was penalised Rs. 2,00,000 for lacking an AML policy and delayed PO appointment - remember that basic compliance infrastructure failures attract specific monetary penalties in PMLA enforcement.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
