<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Discussion on PMLA-related Cases_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Raima Equities defended its lack of PEP identification system by claiming that clients were "known persons" introduced by directors/shareholders. How did the Adjudicating Officer (AO) view this defense?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The AO did not find any merit in this submission and concluded that no PEP identification system existed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AO accepted this as a valid PEP identification method]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AO recommended this approach for all small brokers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AO suspended the case pending further investigation]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AO categorically rejected the "known persons" defense. Simply knowing clients through directors or sub-brokers does NOT constitute a PEP identification system. A proper system requires formal screening procedures using databases, public information, and client declarations.

**The Trap:** Personal relationships or informal knowledge of clients is NOT a substitute for formal PEP identification. The AO explicitly stated this defense had no merit.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PEP identification requires proactive, documented systems -- not informal relationships. In NISM V-A, even mutual fund distributors who personally know their clients must still follow formal PEP screening procedures.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** "I know my clients personally" is NEVER an acceptable defense for not having PEP screening. Use commercial PEP databases, self-declaration forms, and public records to identify PEPs. Document the screening process for every client, regardless of your personal relationship.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
