<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Discussion on PMLA-related Cases_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[In the BOI Shareholding Limited (BOISL) vs SEBI case, what was the original penalty imposed by SEBI and what was it reduced to by the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Original: Rs. 40 Lakh; Reduced to: Rs. 6 Lakh by SAT]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Original: Rs. 10 Lakh; Reduced to: Rs. 2 Lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Original: Rs. 40 Lakh; SAT upheld the same amount]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Original: Rs. 6 Lakh; Enhanced to Rs. 40 Lakh by SAT]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI imposed Rs. 40 Lakh on BOISL for delayed AML/CFT policy implementation (delays of 2-4 years across six violations). BOISL appealed to SAT arguing the penalty was disproportionate since violations were procedural and eventually corrected. SAT agreed and REDUCED the penalty to Rs. 6 Lakh, noting that in similar cases SEBI had imposed Nil or Rs. 1.5 Lakh.

**The Trap:** The reduction from Rs. 40 lakh to Rs. 6 lakh is a key learning point. SAT found the original penalty "excessive" given the procedural nature of violations and penalty precedents in similar cases.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This case establishes the principle that penalties must be proportionate to violations. SAT referenced SEBI's own precedents (IFCI Financial Services = Nil, Triveni Management = Rs. 1.5 lakh) to argue disproportionality.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While SAT may reduce excessive penalties, do not count on it. The legal costs and reputational damage of going to SAT far exceed the penalty amount. It is always better to comply proactively than to litigate retroactively.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
