<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="DTAA Provisions_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mrs. Kavitha, an NRI client based in Singapore, earns Rs.12,00,000 as dividend income from Indian equities. The India-Singapore DTAA prescribes a withholding tax rate of 15% on dividends, while the Indian Income Tax Act prescribes 20%. She has a valid Tax Residency Certificate from Singapore. As her investment adviser, what should you recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She must pay 20% tax under the IT Act as domestic law always overrides DTAA provisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should pay 15% under the DTAA and additionally 5% under the IT Act to cover the differential]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[She should claim the DTAA rate of 15% as it is more beneficial than the IT Act rate, since Section 90 allows the taxpayer to choose the more beneficial provision]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She cannot claim DTAA benefits as an NRI since DTAAs apply only to foreign nationals, not Indian citizens residing abroad]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 90, where India has a DTAA with a country, the taxpayer can be taxed under either the IT Act or the DTAA, whichever is more beneficial. Since the DTAA rate (15%) is lower than the IT Act rate (20%), Mrs. Kavitha should opt for the DTAA rate. She has a valid TRC, which is the mandatory prerequisite.
**The Trap:** Domestic law does not override DTAA — the taxpayer gets the more beneficial treatment. There is no requirement to pay a "differential." DTAA benefits are available based on residency, not citizenship — NRIs who are tax residents of a DTAA country can claim benefits.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This application question tests the interplay of Section 90, TRC requirements, and practical advisory — all core to NISM Series X-B Level 2.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For NRI clients, always verify three things: (1) DTAA exists with the country, (2) client has a valid TRC, (3) DTAA rate is actually lower — only then recommend claiming DTAA benefits.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
