<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="DTAA Provisions_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Vilayati, a UK citizen, becomes a Resident and Ordinarily Resident (ROR) of India in FY 2026-27. He earns Rs.5,00,000 as interest on UK government bonds. The UK deducts tax at 10% under the India-UK DTAA. India's applicable tax rate is 30%. What is the correct tax treatment in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The UK bond interest is exempt in India as it is already taxed in the UK]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[India will tax the full Rs.5,00,000 at 30% without any credit, resulting in Rs.1,50,000 tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[India will tax Rs.5,00,000 at 30% (Rs.1,50,000) and give credit for UK tax of Rs.50,000, resulting in Rs.1,00,000 net tax in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[India will tax only the difference between the two rates, i.e., 20% of Rs.5,00,000 = Rs.1,00,000, with no credit mechanism]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As an ROR in India, Mr. Vilayati is taxed on worldwide income. India taxes the UK bond interest at 30% = Rs.1,50,000. Under the Credit Method (which India follows), credit is given for tax paid in the UK: Rs.50,000 (10% of Rs.5,00,000). Net Indian tax = Rs.1,50,000 - Rs.50,000 = Rs.1,00,000.
**The Trap:** While the net amount is Rs.1,00,000 in both options C and D, the mechanism matters. Option D incorrectly suggests India directly applies a differential rate — the correct mechanism is full taxation with credit. Option A wrongly applies the Exemption Method.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This scenario mirrors the Mr. Vilayati example from the NISM curriculum, directly testable in Series X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The credit method means the effective tax rate is the higher of the two countries' rates — advise clients to factor this into expected post-tax returns on foreign investments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
