<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Kavita purchased shares off-market from Deepak, but the certificates were lost in transit before the transfer could be registered. What is the recommended course of action?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Kavita should directly apply to the RTA for duplicate certificates in her name]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Kavita should file an FIR and the transfer will be automatically processed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Kavita should ask Deepak (the holder) to apply for duplicate certificates and execute a fresh Form ISR-4]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The stock exchange will issue replacement certificates to Kavita]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When certificates are lost in transit before transfer in an off-market transaction, the proposed transferee (Kavita) cannot apply for duplicates since the transfer was never registered. The existing holder (Deepak) must apply for duplicate certificates and then execute a fresh Form ISR-4 to complete the off-market transfer process.

**The Trap:** The process differs based on whether it was a stock exchange transaction or an off-market transaction. For stock exchange transactions, the proposed transferee needs a contract note and proof of payment. For off-market, the original holder must initiate the duplicate process.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This scenario illustrates why the certificate holder is the key party in any duplicate certificate application. Only the registered holder has the standing to apply for duplicates — a proposed transferee whose name is not yet on the records cannot do so.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For off-market share purchases, always use insured or registered post for sending physical certificates. Better yet, advise both parties to dematerialise the shares first and execute the transfer electronically to avoid transit risk entirely.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
