<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Meena, a single holder of physical shares worth Rs.4 lakhs, passed away without registering any nomination. Her son Vikram is the sole legal heir. Which additional document is required from Vikram compared to a case where nomination was registered?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Original share certificates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Notarized affidavit from all legal heirs and succession certificate or probate of will]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Certified death certificate of the deceased]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Self-attested PAN card copy]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When there is no nomination, the legal heir must provide additional documents beyond the standard death certificate, transmission form, and PAN: specifically a notarized affidavit from ALL legal heirs plus a succession certificate/probate/will/letter of administration. These are not required when valid nomination exists.

**The Trap:** Original certificates, death certificate, and PAN are required in BOTH scenarios (with and without nomination). The question asks what is ADDITIONAL — only the legal documentation (affidavit + succession certificate) differentiates the two processes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Since the value is Rs.4 lakhs (under Rs.5 lakhs for physical mode), relaxed documentation applies — NOC from non-objecting heirs or family settlement deed with indemnity bond may be accepted instead of full succession certificate.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For holdings under Rs.5 lakhs in physical mode, inform the legal heirs about the relaxed documentation option. A family settlement deed with indemnity bond is much faster and cheaper than obtaining a succession certificate from court.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
