<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the key difference between transfer and transmission of securities?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer is automatic while transmission requires approval]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer applies only to demat shares while transmission applies only to physical shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer requires court orders while transmission does not]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Transfer is a voluntary act between parties while transmission occurs by operation of law such as on death of a holder]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Transfer is a voluntary transaction where the owner willingly sells/transfers securities to another party using an instrument of transfer. Transmission occurs by operation of law — typically on the death of a holder, where securities pass to legal heirs or nominees without a sale transaction.

**The Trap:** Some candidates think transfer and transmission are interchangeable terms. The distinction is fundamental — transfer involves consideration (payment), while transmission involves devolution of title by law.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This distinction is practically important because since April 2019, physical transfer is banned but physical transmission is still permitted. Also, transmission uses reason code "TLH" (Transmission to Legal Heirs) for CBDT reporting purposes.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When bereaved family members approach you, use the term "transmission" correctly. Calling it a "transfer" may cause confusion with the RTA, as the documentation requirements are entirely different for each process.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
