<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Anita's share certificates worth Rs.8 lakhs were lost. For obtaining duplicate certificates, she must advertise the loss in which publication(s)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only in a local newspaper of the city where she resides]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In the Official Gazette and a widely circulated newspaper at the location of the company's registered office]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[In any two national English newspapers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No advertisement is required regardless of value]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When the value of lost securities exceeds the specified limit (Rs.5 lakhs), the holder must advertise the loss in the Official Gazette AND a widely circulated newspaper at the location of the company's registered office. Since Anita's certificates are worth Rs.8 lakhs (above Rs.5 lakhs), this advertisement is mandatory.

**The Trap:** The newspaper must be widely circulated at the location of the COMPANY'S registered office, not the investor's residence. Also, both Gazette AND newspaper are required — not just one of them. For values up to Rs.5 lakhs, neither FIR nor advertisement is required.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The Rs.5 lakh threshold waives both FIR and newspaper advertisement. Above this limit, the full documentation process applies: FIR + Gazette notification + newspaper advertisement + indemnity bond + affidavit.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For high-value lost certificates, factor in the cost and time for Gazette notification and newspaper advertisement when advising investors. These publications can take weeks to arrange, extending the overall timeline beyond the 30-day processing period.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
