<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[For registering a Power of Attorney (POA) with the RTA, which of the following steps is part of the process?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The POA must be separately registered with SEBI before submission to RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The holder's signature is not verified since the attorney will act on their behalf]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[RTA verifies holder's signature, records holder and attorney details, assigns a registration number with date, and scans the donee's signature]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a court-certified POA is accepted by the RTA]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The POA registration process involves: (1) RTA verifies the holder's signature against specimen on record, (2) records both the holder's and attorney's (donee's) details, (3) assigns a unique registration number with date, and (4) scans the donee's signature for future verification purposes.

**The Trap:** The holder's signature IS verified — this is a security check to ensure the POA is genuinely authorised by the actual holder. Also, the POA does not need separate SEBI registration; RTA registration is sufficient for securities-related transactions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** POA registration connects to the broader investor protection framework. After registration, the donee (attorney) can act on behalf of the holder for service requests. The scanned donee signature enables future verification of any requests made by the attorney.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising NRI clients or elderly investors who may need a POA, ensure the POA document specifically covers securities-related transactions. A general POA may not be sufficient for all RTA service requests.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
