<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Suresh holds shares jointly with his wife Priya. Suresh passes away. What is the first step for Priya to get the securities transmitted in her name?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtain a succession certificate from the court]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File an FIR for the share certificates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Apply for deletion of Suresh's name with death certificate, original certificates, and self-attested PAN]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Execute a new instrument of transfer (Form SH-4) in her name]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When one of the joint holders dies, the surviving holder(s) apply for deletion of the deceased's name from the records. The required documents are: original share certificates, certified death certificate, and self-attested PAN of the surviving holders. No succession certificate or transfer form is needed.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse joint holder transmission with single holder transmission. In joint holdings, the surviving holder already has rights to the securities — it is simply a name deletion process, not a full transmission requiring succession certificates.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is fundamentally different from a single holder scenario where, without nomination, legal heirs need succession certificate, notarized affidavit, etc. Joint holding itself serves as a form of automatic succession mechanism.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Encourage clients to hold securities jointly with family members. In the event of one holder's death, the transmission process for surviving joint holders is far simpler than for a single holder, requiring only basic documents.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
