<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Duplicate Share Certificates and Transmission of Securities_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Pradeep holds demat shares worth Rs.12 lakhs and passes away without any nomination. His two children, Neha and Amit, are the legal heirs. Which of the following documentation alternatives is available to them given the value of holdings?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No relaxation is available — full succession certificate is mandatory regardless of value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Family settlement deed alone is sufficient without any indemnity bond]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NOC from non-objecting heirs or family settlement deed along with an indemnity bond can be accepted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a court-issued letter of administration is acceptable for demat holdings]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For demat holdings up to Rs.15 lakhs (or physical up to Rs.5 lakhs), relaxed documentation is accepted: either a NOC from non-objecting heirs OR a family settlement deed along with an indemnity bond. Since Pradeep's demat holdings are Rs.12 lakhs (within the Rs.15 lakh limit), Neha and Amit qualify for this relaxed procedure.

**The Trap:** The thresholds differ by mode: Rs.5 lakhs for physical and Rs.15 lakhs for demat. Candidates must remember BOTH thresholds. Also, the family settlement deed alone is NOT sufficient — it must be accompanied by an indemnity bond.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The dual threshold (Rs.5 lakhs physical / Rs.15 lakhs demat) reflects the different risk profiles. Physical certificates have higher fraud risk, hence the lower threshold. For duplicate certificates, a separate Rs.5 lakh threshold applies for FIR and newspaper advertisement exemption.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For families dealing with transmission, first check the total value across all holdings. If demat holdings are under Rs.15 lakhs, the family settlement deed route saves significant time and legal costs compared to obtaining a succession certificate from court.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
