<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="E-Voting and Proxy Services_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Gopal, an institutional investor, uses a particular e-voting service provider's platform. After SEBI's single login initiative through demat accounts, which category of shareholders may continue to use the existing login facility of e-voting service providers (ESPs)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only retail individual shareholders holding shares in demat form]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Physical shareholders and institutional/corporate shareholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All shareholders regardless of category must use the single login]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only NRI shareholders and HUF holders]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** While SEBI's single login initiative through demat accounts is aimed at simplifying e-voting for retail/public non-institutional shareholders, ESPs may continue to provide their existing login facilities for physical shareholders (who do not have demat accounts) and institutional/corporate shareholders (who have established workflows with specific ESPs).

**The Trap:** Candidates may assume the single login mandate applies universally to all categories. The carve-out for physical and institutional shareholders reflects practical considerations — physical shareholders have no demat account, and institutions have established processes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This nuance connects to the broader understanding of different shareholder categories in the NISM II-A curriculum — physical vs. demat holders, retail vs. institutional investors — and how regulatory solutions are tailored to each segment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When onboarding institutional clients, confirm their preferred ESP and login method. Despite the single login initiative, institutions often prefer their existing ESP arrangements due to bulk voting capabilities and integration with their internal systems.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
