<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="E-Voting and Proxy Services_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Anil holds shares in physical form and wants to vote on a resolution proposed by his company. He finds it cumbersome to manage multiple login IDs for different e-voting service providers. What solution has SEBI mandated to address this challenge?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Single login facility through demat accounts or websites of Depositories and DPs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mandatory physical attendance at all AGMs for retail shareholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Consolidation of all e-voting service providers into a single government entity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Elimination of e-voting for retail shareholders and reverting to postal ballots only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI recognized that negligible usage of e-voting among retail/public non-institutional shareholders was due to the burden of maintaining multiple login IDs across different e-voting service providers (ESPs). The solution was to enable a single login through demat accounts or websites of Depositories/DPs, implemented in a phased manner.

**The Trap:** The question describes a real problem (multiple logins) and offers plausible but incorrect solutions. SEBI's approach was interoperability through demat accounts, not consolidation of ESPs or elimination of e-voting.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This SEBI initiative connects to the broader depository system topics in NISM II-A, showing how demat infrastructure serves purposes beyond just holding securities — it also facilitates corporate governance participation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Note that ESPs may continue their existing login facilities for physical shareholders and institutional/corporate shareholders. The single login via demat is primarily aimed at improving retail participation in e-voting.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
