<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="E-Voting and Proxy Services_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Kavita, a shareholder who does not have a registered email address, requests the company for the full annual report before the AGM. Which of the following is correct regarding her request?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The company must provide a hard copy of the full annual report upon her request]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The company can refuse since she does not have a registered email]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She will only receive the salient features and cannot request the full report]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She must first register her email to receive any version of the annual report]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 136 of the Companies Act, 2013, shareholders without registered email addresses automatically receive hard copies of salient features. However, any shareholder can request and must receive hard copies of the full annual report — this right cannot be denied regardless of email registration status.

**The Trap:** Candidates may think that shareholders without email only get salient features with no recourse. The law provides for hard copies of the full report on request as a safety net.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This three-tier annual report distribution system (full soft copy to email holders, salient features hard copy to non-email holders, full hard copy on request) is a frequently tested concept in NISM II-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** RTAs should include a note in the salient features document informing shareholders of their right to request the full annual report. This proactive communication reduces last-minute requests and improves shareholder satisfaction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
