<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="E-Voting and Proxy Services_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Harish, an RTA executive, receives a call from a major institutional shareholder wanting to submit a representation letter for the AGM scheduled for Monday morning. It is now Saturday at 10:00 AM. Can the representation letter still be accepted?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because the letter is being submitted more than 48 hours before the AGM]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because representation letters must be submitted at least 7 days before the AGM]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because no documents can be accepted over the weekend]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only if the shareholder holds more than 10% of the company's shares]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Proxy forms and financial institution representation letters must be received by the company at least 48 hours before the AGM. If the AGM is on Monday morning and the letter is submitted on Saturday at 10:00 AM, it is being submitted more than 48 hours before the meeting, making it valid for acceptance.

**The Trap:** Some candidates may calculate the 48 hours incorrectly or assume weekend submissions are not valid. The 48-hour rule is a calendar-time requirement, not a business-hours requirement. Saturday 10 AM to Monday morning exceeds 48 hours.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This scenario-based question tests practical application of the 48-hour proxy rule. It combines knowledge of the regulatory timeline with real-world calendar calculations — a common testing approach in NISM II-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a clear system for accepting and logging proxy forms and representation letters. Record the exact date and time of receipt. In case of disputes about whether the 48-hour deadline was met, timestamped records serve as evidence of compliance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
