<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Economic Analysis_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> The Economic Advisory Council has released the following data for the Indian economy for Q3 FY 2025-26: GDP Growth Rate: 6.5% (down from 7.2% in Q2). CPI Inflation: 5.8% (up from 4.9% in Q2). WPI Inflation: 4.2%. RBI Repo Rate: 6.50% (unchanged for 3 consecutive meetings). Fiscal Deficit: 5.9% of GDP (target: 5.1% for the full year). Current Account Deficit: 2.8% of GDP. FPI outflows: Rs.25,000 crore during the quarter. USD/INR: Depreciated from Rs.83.50 to Rs.85.20 during the quarter. Crude oil prices: Up 15% during the quarter to $92/barrel. Nirmala Agarwal, a research analyst at Sunrise Securities, needs to analyze these indicators and their implications for different sectors and asset classes.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Based on the data, the Indian economy is most likely in which phase of the economic cycle?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Recovery phase with accelerating growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Expansion phase transitioning to a slowdown as GDP growth is decelerating while inflation is rising]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Deep recession with negative GDP growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Stagflation with zero growth and high inflation]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** GDP growth has decelerated from 7.2% to 6.5% while inflation has risen from 4.9% to 5.8%. This pattern of slowing growth with rising inflation suggests transition from expansion to slowdown.
**The Trap:** GDP is still positive at 6.5% (not recession or stagflation). Growth is decelerating, not accelerating (not recovery).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Economic cycle analysis tested in NISM Series XV Chapters 5 and 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During expansion-to-slowdown transition, defensive sectors (FMCG, pharma, utilities) tend to outperform cyclicals (auto, capital goods, real estate).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>