<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Economic Analysis_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> The Economic Advisory Council has released the following data for the Indian economy for Q3 FY 2025-26: GDP Growth Rate: 6.5% (down from 7.2% in Q2). CPI Inflation: 5.8% (up from 4.9% in Q2). WPI Inflation: 4.2%. RBI Repo Rate: 6.50% (unchanged for 3 consecutive meetings). Fiscal Deficit: 5.9% of GDP (target: 5.1% for the full year). Current Account Deficit: 2.8% of GDP. FPI outflows: Rs.25,000 crore during the quarter. USD/INR: Depreciated from Rs.83.50 to Rs.85.20 during the quarter. Crude oil prices: Up 15% during the quarter to $92/barrel. Nirmala Agarwal, a research analyst at Sunrise Securities, needs to analyze these indicators and their implications for different sectors and asset classes.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Which sectors would Nirmala expect to be MOST negatively affected by the current economic data?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IT services and pharmaceuticals (export-oriented)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Real estate and automobile (interest-rate sensitive and discretionary spending dependent)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FMCG and utilities (defensive sectors)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold and government bonds (safe-haven assets)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Real estate and auto are most negatively affected because: (1) high interest rates make loans expensive, reducing demand, (2) rising inflation reduces discretionary income, (3) slowing GDP reduces consumer confidence.
**The Trap:** IT and pharma may actually benefit from INR depreciation (export revenues increase). FMCG and utilities are defensive. Gold benefits from uncertainty.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Sector sensitivity analysis tested in NISM Series XV Chapters 5 and 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When CPI rises and RBI maintains hawkish stance, reduce exposure to rate-sensitive sectors and increase allocation to exporters and defensives.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>