<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Economic Analysis_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Karan Singh is advising a manufacturing company that exports automotive components. The following economic changes have occurred simultaneously: (1) RBI has cut the repo rate by 75 basis points over the last 6 months from 6.50% to 5.75%. (2) The Indian Rupee has depreciated 8% against the US Dollar from Rs.82 to Rs.88.50. (3) Global crude oil prices have fallen 25% from $90 to $67.50 per barrel. (4) India's GDP growth has improved from 5.5% to 7.0%. (5) The US Federal Reserve has started cutting rates, weakening the US Dollar globally. (6) WPI inflation has fallen from 6.5% to 3.2%. The company earns 60% of its revenue from exports (invoiced in USD) and imports 30% of its raw materials (also priced in USD). The remaining revenue is domestic, and 70% of raw materials are sourced domestically. Karan needs to assess the net impact on the company.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> The combined effect of all six economic changes on this company is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Entirely negative across all parameters]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mixed — some factors help and others hurt, but the net effect is significantly positive]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No impact as positive and negative factors cancel out exactly]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Positive for revenue but negative for profitability]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rate cut: lower borrowing cost (positive). INR depreciation: higher export revenue (positive). Lower crude: lower costs (positive). GDP growth: domestic demand up (positive). Falling WPI: lower input costs (positive). US rate cuts: favorable for EM assets. Almost all factors favor this company.
**The Trap:** While 30% imported raw materials become costlier due to INR depreciation, this is more than offset by the 60% export revenue boost, lower crude/energy costs, and improved domestic demand.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Multi-factor economic analysis tested in NISM Series XV and X-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is why economic analysis matters for stock selection — a company that benefits from multiple macro tailwinds can outperform significantly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>