<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Economic Analysis_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> The Economic Advisory Council has released the following data for the Indian economy for Q3 FY 2025-26: GDP Growth Rate: 6.5% (down from 7.2% in Q2). CPI Inflation: 5.8% (up from 4.9% in Q2). WPI Inflation: 4.2%. RBI Repo Rate: 6.50% (unchanged for 3 consecutive meetings). Fiscal Deficit: 5.9% of GDP (target: 5.1% for the full year). Current Account Deficit: 2.8% of GDP. FPI outflows: Rs.25,000 crore during the quarter. USD/INR: Depreciated from Rs.83.50 to Rs.85.20 during the quarter. Crude oil prices: Up 15% during the quarter to $92/barrel. Nirmala Agarwal, a research analyst at Sunrise Securities, needs to analyze these indicators and their implications for different sectors and asset classes.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> The fiscal deficit at 5.9% of GDP versus the target of 5.1% suggests:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The government is running a surplus]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Government spending is higher than budgeted or revenue collection is lower, which may push up interest rates through higher borrowing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The government has completely eliminated its debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no fiscal pressure on the economy]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Fiscal deficit of 5.9% exceeding the 5.1% target means government spending is overshooting or revenue underperforming. This requires higher government borrowing, which pushes up interest rates and may crowd out private investment.
**The Trap:** A deficit is not a surplus. It does not eliminate debt (it adds to it). There is clear fiscal pressure when deficit exceeds target.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Fiscal deficit analysis tested in NISM Series XV and I.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Higher-than-expected government borrowing can push up bond yields, increasing borrowing costs for corporates too. This is negative for corporate earnings growth.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>