<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Economic Analysis_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> The Economic Advisory Council has released the following data for the Indian economy for Q3 FY 2025-26: GDP Growth Rate: 6.5% (down from 7.2% in Q2). CPI Inflation: 5.8% (up from 4.9% in Q2). WPI Inflation: 4.2%. RBI Repo Rate: 6.50% (unchanged for 3 consecutive meetings). Fiscal Deficit: 5.9% of GDP (target: 5.1% for the full year). Current Account Deficit: 2.8% of GDP. FPI outflows: Rs.25,000 crore during the quarter. USD/INR: Depreciated from Rs.83.50 to Rs.85.20 during the quarter. Crude oil prices: Up 15% during the quarter to $92/barrel. Nirmala Agarwal, a research analyst at Sunrise Securities, needs to analyze these indicators and their implications for different sectors and asset classes.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> CPI inflation at 5.8% is above RBI's target. What is RBI most likely to do at its next meeting?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cut the repo rate by 50 basis points to stimulate growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Maintain or increase the repo rate to control inflation as it approaches the upper tolerance band of 6%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Eliminate CRR requirements for all banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Convert all government bonds to floating rate]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** CPI at 5.8% is near RBI's upper tolerance band of 6% (target 4% +/- 2%). With inflation rising, RBI is likely to maintain or hike rates rather than cut. Growth is still healthy at 6.5%.
**The Trap:** Cutting rates would worsen inflation. CRR elimination and bond conversion are extreme measures not warranted by this data.
**Cross-Exam Context:** RBI rate decision analysis tested in NISM Series XV, IV, and I.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Watch for RBI's inflation forecast in the monetary policy statement. If projected CPI exceeds 6%, a rate hike becomes likely.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>