<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Economic Analysis_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Karan Singh is advising a manufacturing company that exports automotive components. The following economic changes have occurred simultaneously: (1) RBI has cut the repo rate by 75 basis points over the last 6 months from 6.50% to 5.75%. (2) The Indian Rupee has depreciated 8% against the US Dollar from Rs.82 to Rs.88.50. (3) Global crude oil prices have fallen 25% from $90 to $67.50 per barrel. (4) India's GDP growth has improved from 5.5% to 7.0%. (5) The US Federal Reserve has started cutting rates, weakening the US Dollar globally. (6) WPI inflation has fallen from 6.5% to 3.2%. The company earns 60% of its revenue from exports (invoiced in USD) and imports 30% of its raw materials (also priced in USD). The remaining revenue is domestic, and 70% of raw materials are sourced domestically. Karan needs to assess the net impact on the company.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> The falling WPI inflation from 6.5% to 3.2% suggests:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Wholesale prices are rising faster than retail prices]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Input costs for manufacturers are moderating, which should improve manufacturing margins]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The economy is entering hyperinflation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Consumer prices must also be falling at the same rate]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** WPI falling from 6.5% to 3.2% means wholesale prices are growing much slower. For manufacturers, this means input costs are moderating, which directly improves profit margins.
**The Trap:** Falling WPI means prices are rising slower (not hyperinflation). CPI may not fall at the same rate due to different baskets and weightages.
**Cross-Exam Context:** WPI and manufacturing margin linkage tested in NISM Series XV and IV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When WPI falls but CPI remains stable, manufacturers benefit: input costs fall (tracked by WPI) while selling prices hold (supported by CPI-driven demand).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>