<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Exempt Incomes, Deductions, Rebates_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about dividend income from Indian companies is correct as per the current tax law (FY 2024-25 onwards)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dividend income is exempt in the hands of shareholders as the company pays Dividend Distribution Tax (DDT)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dividend income is taxed at a flat rate of 10% without any deduction for expenses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Dividend income is taxable in the hands of shareholders at applicable slab rates, and interest expense up to 20% of dividend income is allowed as deduction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dividend income is exempt up to Rs.10,00,000 and taxed at 10% thereafter]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Since FY 2020-21, DDT was abolished and dividends from Indian companies are taxable in the hands of shareholders at their applicable slab rates. Under Section 57, interest expense incurred to earn dividend income is allowed as a deduction, limited to 20% of the dividend income.
**The Trap:** Option A reflects the pre-2020 regime when DDT applied. Option B confuses it with the erstwhile Section 115BBDA (10% tax on dividends exceeding Rs.10L). Option D mixes elements of the old and new regimes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A MFD and Series V-B equity dealer exams test the shift from DDT to shareholder-level taxation — crucial for comparing dividend plans of mutual funds.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Post-DDT abolition, dividend income from equity shares and mutual funds adds to total income and is taxed at slab rates, making growth option/reinvestment more tax-efficient for clients in higher tax brackets.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
