<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Exempt Incomes, Deductions, Rebates_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ritu, a salaried employee with a basic salary of Rs.8,00,000 per annum, works for a private company. Her employer contributes Rs.1,20,000 (15% of salary) to NPS on her behalf. Under Section 80CCD(2), what deduction is available to Ritu, and in which tax regime(s)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.1,20,000 deduction, available only in the old regime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.80,000 deduction (10% of salary), available only in the old regime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.1,12,000 deduction (14% of salary), available in both old and new regimes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.1,20,000 deduction, available in both old and new regimes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 80CCD(2), employer's contribution to NPS is allowed as a deduction. For private sector employees, the limit is 14% of salary under the new regime and 10% under the old regime (14% under new regime per latest amendments). Since the question asks what deduction is available: employer contributed Rs.1,20,000 (15% of Rs.8L), but the cap for private employees under the new regime is 14% of salary = Rs.1,12,000. This deduction is available in BOTH regimes. The excess Rs.8,000 (15% - 14% = 1%) is not deductible.
**The Trap:** Option A limits it to old regime only — 80CCD(2) is available in both. Option B uses the old 10% cap. Option D allows the full 15% without applying the 14% ceiling.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B specifically tests which deductions survive under the new regime — 80CCD(2) is a key one.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** 80CCD(2) is one of the few deductions available under BOTH regimes. Advise private sector clients to ensure employer NPS contribution stays within the 14% cap to maximize tax efficiency.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
