<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Exempt Incomes, Deductions, Rebates_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Shalini earns long-term capital gains of Rs.2,50,000 from sale of listed equity shares (with STT paid) in FY 2024-25. Her total income under the new regime is Rs.6,80,000 (including the LTCG). Can she claim Section 87A rebate on the LTCG component?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, since her total income is below Rs.7,00,000, the entire tax including on LTCG is eligible for rebate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, Section 87A rebate cannot be claimed against tax on LTCG under Section 112A (equity shares/MF with STT)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only for LTCG up to Rs.1,25,000 (the exempt threshold)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because 87A rebate is not available in the new regime at all]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 87A rebate is NOT available against tax computed under Section 112A on long-term capital gains from equity shares, equity mutual funds, ULIPs, and business trusts where STT has been paid. Even though Shalini's total income is below Rs.7L, the LTCG component taxed under 112A cannot benefit from the 87A rebate. The rebate applies only to the non-112A portion of her income.
**The Trap:** Option A wrongly assumes 87A covers all types of income below Rs.7L. Option C confuses the Rs.1.25L LTCG exemption threshold with the rebate. Option D incorrectly states 87A is unavailable in the new regime — it IS available in the new regime, just not against 112A gains.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A and Series VIII (equity derivatives) exams test the interplay between 112A LTCG and 87A rebate.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients with equity LTCG should be warned that Section 87A will NOT offset the 112A tax — this is a common surprise when filing returns and discovering that 87A does not reduce the capital gains tax bill.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
