<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Exempt Incomes, Deductions, Rebates_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A farmer's agricultural land in a rural area was compulsorily acquired by the State Government for a highway project. He received Rs.45,00,000 as compensation. What is the tax treatment of the capital gains arising from this compulsory acquisition?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Fully exempt under Section 10(37) as it is compulsory acquisition of agricultural land]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Taxable as long-term capital gains at 20% with indexation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exempt only if the compensation is reinvested in another agricultural land within 2 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exempt only up to Rs.20,00,000 and balance taxable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 10(37) provides complete exemption for capital gains arising from compulsory acquisition of agricultural land. The conditions are: (a) the land was used for agricultural purposes during the 2 years immediately preceding the transfer, and (b) the compensation is received after 1st April 2004. There is NO monetary ceiling on this exemption and NO reinvestment condition.
**The Trap:** Option B ignores the specific exemption provision. Option C invents a reinvestment requirement (which exists for 54B voluntary sale of agricultural land, not for compulsory acquisition under 10(37)). Option D fabricates a monetary limit.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A and X-B test the distinction between Section 10(37) (compulsory acquisition — full exemption) and Section 54B (voluntary sale — reinvestment required).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Compulsory acquisition of agricultural land is fully exempt — advise such clients to invest the proceeds wisely rather than feeling pressured to reinvest in land solely for tax reasons.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
