<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Exempt Incomes, Deductions, Rebates_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser is evaluating tax-saving options for Neha, a 30-year-old salaried client who has opted for the new tax regime for FY 2025-26. Which of the following strategies would provide her a valid tax benefit?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest Rs.1,50,000 in ELSS funds to claim deduction under Section 80C]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Purchase health insurance of Rs.25,000 to claim deduction under Section 80D]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Request employer to increase NPS contribution within the 14% salary limit to claim deduction under Section 80CCD(2)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Make additional NPS contribution of Rs.50,000 to claim deduction under Section 80CCD(1B)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the new tax regime, Sections 80C, 80D, and 80CCD(1B) are NOT available. However, Section 80CCD(2) — employer's contribution to NPS — is available in both old and new regimes. For private sector employees, the limit is 14% of salary under the new regime. This is the only valid tax-saving strategy among the options for someone on the new regime.
**The Trap:** Options A, B, and D are all legitimate tax-saving strategies under the OLD regime but are explicitly excluded from the new regime. Many candidates assume all NPS deductions are treated the same — but 80CCD(1B) (self-contribution) is NOT available in the new regime while 80CCD(2) (employer contribution) IS.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B directly tests advisers' ability to recommend appropriate strategies based on the chosen tax regime.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For new regime clients, the ONLY Chapter VI-A deduction levers are 80CCD(2) and 80CCH. Focus advisory conversations on salary restructuring to maximize employer NPS contribution rather than pushing traditional 80C instruments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
