<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A distributor in Jaipur (a B30 city) brings in a new investor who invests Rs. 50,000 in an equity mutual fund through the Regular Plan. How does this transaction benefit the distributor compared to a similar transaction from Mumbai (a T30 city)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The distributor earns double the trail commission for B30 city investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The distributor receives an additional transaction charge of Rs. 300 for B30 city transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The AMC may charge additional TER of up to 30 bps on B30 inflows, potentially translating to higher distributor commissions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[B30 city transactions are exempt from the prohibition on upfront commissions, so the distributor earns upfront commission]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI allows AMCs to charge an additional TER of up to 30 basis points for net new inflows from B30 (beyond top 30) cities. This additional TER can be used by AMCs to pay higher commissions to distributors who bring in investments from these cities. This incentivizes distributors to expand mutual fund penetration in smaller towns and cities.

**The Trap:** Option A exaggerates — the commission is not doubled but may be incrementally higher. Option B invents an additional transaction charge that does not exist. Option D is critically wrong — upfront commission prohibition applies uniformly regardless of city classification. The B30 benefit works through additional TER, not through exemptions from other rules.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The B30 incentive is part of SEBI's strategy to increase mutual fund penetration beyond metro cities. The additional 30 bps TER is conditional on the scheme meeting minimum B30 inflow thresholds. This connects to TER regulations (Chapter 5) and the broader goal of financial inclusion. Remember: B30 = 30 bps is a useful mnemonic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you operate in B30 cities, leverage this incentive by actively building your investor base. The additional commission for B30 inflows gives you a competitive edge over metro-focused distributors. Combine this with investor awareness programs to build a loyal client base in underserved markets.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
