<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a role typically performed by a mutual fund distributor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Assessing client risk profile and recommending suitable schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Processing transactions and providing after-sales service]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Making investment decisions on behalf of the fund's portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Educating investors about different mutual fund products]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A mutual fund distributor's role includes client interaction, need assessment, product recommendation, transaction processing, and after-sales service. However, making investment decisions for the fund's portfolio is the role of the fund manager (employed by the AMC), not the distributor. The distributor helps investors choose schemes but does not manage the underlying portfolio.

**The Trap:** Options A, B, and D all sound like things a distributor should NOT do (especially A, which sounds like advisory), but these are all legitimate distributor functions. The key distinction is between recommending schemes to investors (distributor's role) and managing the scheme's investments (fund manager's role).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the distributor's role boundary is critical. Distributors recommend products but do not provide investment advice (that requires SEBI RIA registration). They also do not manage money or make portfolio-level decisions. This distinction between distribution and advisory is tested frequently.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Stay within your role boundaries. You can assess needs and recommend suitable products, but do not cross into portfolio management or specific stock/bond advice territory — that requires a different license. Focus on scheme suitability, not security selection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
