<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following distribution channels is most likely to offer only Direct Plans of mutual funds to investors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A bank acting as a corporate distributor with ARN]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An individual financial advisor with ARN and EUIN]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An online investment platform like Kuvera that does not charge commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An NBFC distributing mutual funds through its branch network]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** New-age online platforms like Kuvera, Groww (in its direct plan mode), and similar platforms offer Direct Plans to investors. These platforms do not earn distributor commissions — instead they may earn through premium subscriptions, advisory fees, or other revenue models. Since Direct Plans have no distributor commission embedded in TER, they are cheaper for investors.

**The Trap:** Options A, B, and D all involve entities with ARN — they earn trail commissions and therefore offer Regular Plans (though they may also offer Direct Plans as an option). The key differentiator is the business model: commission-based distributors primarily offer Regular Plans, while commission-free platforms offer Direct Plans.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The rise of fintech platforms has disrupted traditional distribution. SEBI's push for Direct Plans (mandatory since January 2013) and the growth of digital platforms have given investors more choice. However, the exam tests whether candidates understand that Direct Plan platforms are not "distributors" in the traditional ARN-holding sense.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rather than viewing Direct Plan platforms as competition, focus on the advisory value you provide. Many investors who start with Direct Plans eventually seek professional guidance for complex financial planning. Your expertise in asset allocation, tax planning, and behavioral coaching justifies the Regular Plan route.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
