<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following entities serve as Registrar and Transfer Agents (RTAs) for mutual funds in India and also operate investor service centers where transactions can be processed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[CAMS and KFintech]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSDL and CDSL]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSE and BSE]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMFI and SEBI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Computer Age Management Services (CAMS) and KFintech (formerly Karvy Fintech) are the two major RTAs in India's mutual fund industry. They maintain investor records, process transactions, and operate Investor Service Centers (ISCs) across the country where investors can submit their transaction requests for multiple AMCs serviced by that RTA.

**The Trap:** NSDL and CDSL (Option B) are depositories for securities, not RTAs for mutual funds. NSE and BSE (Option C) are stock exchanges that have MF platforms but are not RTAs. AMFI is the industry association and SEBI is the regulator — neither performs RTA functions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** RTAs serve as a crucial transaction channel. An investor can visit a CAMS or KFintech office to transact in any scheme serviced by that RTA, regardless of which AMC manages the scheme. This makes RTAs a convenient single-window service point. The RTA concept also links to Chapter 3 (Legal Structure) where RTAs are discussed as key service providers.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Know which AMCs are serviced by CAMS and which by KFintech. When a client needs to process transactions urgently, direct them to the nearest RTA office — it is often more accessible than the AMC's own branch, especially in smaller cities.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
