<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_41" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When an investor requests a change of distributor code from one distributor to another, the commission treatment is that ________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No commission is payable to either the old or the new distributor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The old distributor continues to receive trail commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The new distributor receives trail commission from the date of change]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The commission is split equally between the old and new distributor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI/AMFI guidelines, when an investor voluntarily changes their distributor code, NO commission (including trail commission) is payable to either the outgoing or the incoming distributor. This rule prevents churning and ensures that distributor changes are not motivated by commission considerations.

**The Trap:** Many candidates assume the old distributor keeps trail (Option B) since they originally sold the investment, or that the new distributor picks up trail (Option C) since they are now servicing the investor. The "split equally" option (D) sounds fair but is incorrect. The rule is absolute: zero commission to both parties.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a frequently tested rule from PDF Section 6.10 on distributor code changes. There is one important exception -- when the original distributor voluntarily ceases business, the new distributor does receive trail commission.

**Key Takeaway:** Change of distributor code at investor's request = zero commission to both old and new distributor. No exceptions unless the original distributor ceases business.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
