<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An AMC conducts due diligence of its distributors. What is the primary purpose of this due diligence process?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To determine the commission rate payable to each distributor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To assess the distributor's credentials, track record, and compliance history to protect investor interests]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To verify whether the distributor can meet minimum sales targets set by the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To check if the distributor has invested their personal money in the AMC's schemes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AMCs are required to conduct due diligence of their distributors to ensure that only fit and proper persons distribute their schemes. This involves assessing the distributor's credentials (NISM certification, ARN validity), track record, compliance history, and any past regulatory actions. The ultimate purpose is investor protection — ensuring distributors serve investors ethically.

**The Trap:** Option A suggests due diligence determines commission rates — commission is a commercial decision, not a due diligence outcome. Option C suggests sales targets — AMCs do not typically make empanelment conditional on sales targets (though they may have incentive structures). Option D is irrelevant to the due diligence process.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI has enhanced due diligence requirements for distributors, especially for those with high commission concentration (earning a disproportionate share from one AMC or scheme). AMCs must also review distributors who generate excessive complaints or have unusual transaction patterns.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a clean compliance record. AMCs regularly review their distributor panel, and any regulatory action against you can lead to de-empanelment. Proactively share your credentials and compliance documentation with AMCs during empanelment renewals.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
