<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following best describes what "after-sales service" means in the context of mutual fund distribution?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteeing a minimum return to the investor after the sale is completed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Processing only the initial purchase transaction and collecting commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Providing ongoing portfolio reviews, account statements, addressing queries, and facilitating additional transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Offering a buyback guarantee if the investor is dissatisfied with the scheme's performance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** After-sales service is a critical role of the distributor that goes beyond the initial transaction. It includes periodic portfolio reviews with clients, helping them understand their account statements, addressing queries about NAV, dividends, or taxation, facilitating additional transactions (SIP changes, switches, redemptions), and keeping clients informed about market developments and scheme changes.

**The Trap:** Option A and D involve guarantees that no distributor can provide — mutual funds are market-linked products. Option B describes a transactional approach that ignores the ongoing service component that justifies trail commission. The exam tests whether candidates understand the holistic nature of the distributor's role.

**Cross-Exam Context:** After-sales service is directly linked to the trail commission model — distributors earn ongoing commissions because they provide ongoing service. If a distributor only processes transactions and provides no follow-up service, the value proposition for Regular Plans becomes questionable. AMFI's code of conduct emphasizes ongoing client engagement.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Excellent after-sales service is your strongest retention tool. Schedule periodic portfolio reviews, send market updates, proactively reach out during market volatility, and help clients with operational issues. This service is what differentiates you from Direct Plan platforms and justifies your commission.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
