<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fundamentals of Research_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ananya Sharma is a research analyst at Meridian Securities, a mid-sized brokerage firm. She is researching Vividha Pharma Ltd, a pharmaceutical company listed on NSE. During her research process, she undertakes the following activities: (1) She reviews Vividha Pharma's annual reports and quarterly filings from the last 5 years. (2) During a conference, she overhears the CFO of Vividha Pharma telling another analyst that "the next quarter will be significantly better than expected" — this information has not been announced to the exchange. (3) She visits a hospital that is a major customer of Vividha Pharma and learns from doctors that they have been ordering more of Vividha's oncology drugs lately. (4) She reads an industry report from IQVIA showing 15% growth in the Indian oncology market. (5) She speaks to a raw material supplier who mentions that Vividha has placed unusually large orders for API (Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients) in the last 2 months. She now needs to prepare her research report with a recommendation.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Ananya's information from the hospital doctors (increased oncology drug orders) and the supplier (large API orders), when combined with the IQVIA industry growth data, represents:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Insider trading because she got non-public information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mosaic analysis — combining individually non-material pieces to derive meaningful insights]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Technical analysis of Vividha Pharma's stock]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Unauthorized access to confidential business information]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Combining information from doctors about increased orders, supplier information about large API purchases, and published industry growth data is mosaic analysis. Each piece individually is not material or price-sensitive, but together they paint a coherent picture.
**The Trap:** None of these individual pieces constitute insider information — doctors sharing purchase patterns and suppliers discussing order volumes are normal business conversations, not UPSI.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Mosaic analysis vs insider information is a key distinction tested in NISM Series XV and III-A. CFA Institute also emphasizes this concept.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Mosaic analysis is the hallmark of excellent research. Document each information source carefully to demonstrate that insights were derived from legitimate mosaic, not insider information.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>