<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The exception to the "no commission on distributor change" rule applies when the new distributor receives trail commission. This exception is triggered ________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[When the original distributor voluntarily ceases business]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[When the investor specifically requests commission transfer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[When the AMC decides to reassign the account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[When the original distributor retires from the industry]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The general rule is that no commission is payable to either distributor when an investor changes their distributor code. However, there is one specific exception: if the original distributor voluntarily ceases their business operations, the new distributor assigned to service the investor receives trail commission. This ensures continuity of investor servicing when the original distributor is no longer in business.

**The Trap:** "Investor requests" (Option B) is wrong -- the investor's request alone does not trigger this exception. "AMC decides" (Option C) is incorrect -- this exception is driven by the distributor's action, not the AMC's. "Retires" (Option D) is subtly different from "voluntarily ceases business" -- retirement alone may not qualify unless it constitutes formal cessation of business operations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This exception is a high-value exam point because it is the ONLY scenario where the new distributor gets trail commission upon a distributor change. The distinction between voluntary cessation and other reasons for departure is critical.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** New distributor gets trail only when the original distributor VOLUNTARILY ceases business. All other distributor changes = zero commission.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
