<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When a mutual fund distributor makes investments in mutual fund schemes for their own account (self-business), the commission treatment is that ________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No commission is payable for the distributor's own investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Regular commission is payable as for any other investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A reduced commission rate applies for self-investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only trail commission is payable, not upfront commission]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations clearly state that no commission (neither upfront nor trail) is payable to a distributor for investments made in their own name or for their own benefit. This prevents distributors from earning commission on their personal investments, which would be a conflict of interest. Distributors investing for themselves should use the direct plan, which has a lower expense ratio.

**The Trap:** "Regular commission" (Option B) would create a perverse incentive for distributors to route their own investments through their ARN code just to earn commission. "Reduced commission" (Option C) is a common middle-ground assumption but is incorrect -- it is zero, not reduced. "Trail only" (Option D) assumes partial commission, which is also wrong.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This rule aligns with SEBI's broader objective of eliminating conflicts of interest in mutual fund distribution. It is often tested alongside the direct plan concept -- distributors investing for themselves should logically use the direct plan.

**Key Takeaway:** Distributor's own investments = zero commission. No exceptions. Distributors should use direct plans for personal investments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
