<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the earlier transaction charge framework (before its withdrawal in August 2025), what happened when an investor invested less than Rs. 10,000 through a distributor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A reduced transaction charge of Rs. 50 was applicable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The transaction charge was proportionately reduced based on the investment amount]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The distributor had to absorb the transaction charge from their commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No transaction charge was applicable for investments below Rs. 10,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Transaction charges are applicable ONLY for subscription amounts of Rs. 10,000 and above. For investments below Rs. 10,000, no transaction charge is levied. This threshold ensures that small investors are not disproportionately impacted by fixed charges.

**The Trap:** Option A invents a reduced charge that does not exist. Option B suggests proportionate reduction, which sounds logical but is incorrect — it is a binary threshold, not a sliding scale. Option C suggests the distributor absorbs the charge, which is also incorrect. The rule is simple: below Rs. 10,000 = zero transaction charge.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Remember the complete transaction charge framework: (1) Rs. 150 for new investors, (2) Rs. 100 for existing investors, (3) Only for amounts of Rs. 10,000 or more, (4) Deducted from the investment amount, (5) Applicable only through distributor (Regular Plan) route. This is a favorite numerical question in the exam.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For SIP amounts below Rs. 10,000 per installment, no transaction charge is deducted from each installment. This makes SIPs more efficient for small-ticket investors. Use this information to encourage systematic investing even with small amounts.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
