<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, upfront commission from AMCs to mutual fund distributors has been largely abolished. What was the primary regulatory concern that led to this change?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Upfront commissions were too expensive for AMCs and reduced their profitability]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Upfront commissions created an incentive for distributors to churn portfolios by encouraging unnecessary switches and fresh purchases]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Upfront commissions were being paid from investor capital, reducing the NAV at the time of purchase]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Upfront commissions violated the AMFI code of conduct regarding maximum compensation limits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The primary concern with upfront commissions was churning — distributors had a financial incentive to encourage investors to redeem from one scheme and reinvest in another (or in the same scheme afresh) to earn a new upfront commission each time. This was detrimental to investor interests as frequent switching incurs tax costs and disrupts long-term compounding.

**The Trap:** Option A focuses on AMC costs — the regulatory concern was about investor protection, not AMC profitability. Option C partially describes the mechanism but entry loads (which funded upfront commissions) were abolished separately in 2009. Option D fabricates a specific AMFI rule. The exam wants candidates to identify the investor-protection rationale, specifically the anti-churning objective.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The abolition of upfront commissions was a phased regulatory shift: first, entry loads were banned (2009), then upfront commissions from scheme assets were restricted. The shift to trail-only commissions aligns distributor incentives with long-term investor wealth creation. This is a landmark regulatory change in mutual fund history.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The trail-only model actually benefits good distributors in the long run. Instead of chasing one-time payouts, build a growing AUM book that generates predictable, increasing trail income. Think of it as building an annuity for your business — the bigger and stickier your client base, the more sustainable your income.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
