<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[SEBI regulations require that Direct Plans must have which of the following characteristics compared to Regular Plans of the same scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A lower Total Expense Ratio (TER) by at least the amount of distributor commission charged in the Regular Plan]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A higher minimum investment amount to compensate for the absence of distributor services]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A separate fund manager and investment strategy optimized for cost-conscious investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A mandatory lock-in period of 1 year since the investor has no distributor to guide early redemption]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates that the TER of a Direct Plan must be lower than that of the Regular Plan by at least the distributor commission (trail and transaction charges) that the Regular Plan bears. This ensures that the cost advantage of bypassing the distributor is fully passed on to the Direct Plan investor. The expense difference must be at least equal to the commission component.

**The Trap:** Option B is wrong — there is no higher minimum investment requirement for Direct Plans. Option C is a critical misconception — both plans share the same fund manager, investment strategy, and portfolio. Option D fabricates a lock-in period that does not exist. The ONLY mandated difference is in TER (and consequently NAV over time).

**Cross-Exam Context:** This regulation ensures that AMCs cannot create artificial parity between Direct and Regular Plans. SEBI monitors TER disclosures to ensure compliance. This connects to TER regulations in Chapter 5 and the broader goal of investor protection through cost transparency.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understanding this regulatory requirement helps you explain to clients exactly how much they save in Direct Plans vs. the service value you provide in Regular Plans. If the TER difference is 0.50%, you need to demonstrate that your advice and service are worth more than 0.50% per annum to the client.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
