<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a key advantage of the trail commission model over the upfront commission model for mutual fund distribution?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trail commission provides a larger one-time payout to the distributor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trail commission is paid directly by the investor, ensuring full transparency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trail commission aligns the distributor's interest with the investor's by incentivizing long-term asset retention]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trail commission eliminates the need for EUIN disclosure on transaction forms]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Trail commission is paid as a percentage of the investor's AUM on an ongoing basis. This means the distributor earns more when the investor stays invested and the portfolio grows. This alignment of interests — distributor benefits when investor benefits — reduces the incentive for churning (unnecessary switching to generate commissions) that was prevalent under the upfront commission model.

**The Trap:** Option A describes upfront commission, not trail. Option B is wrong — trail commission is paid from the scheme's TER, not directly by the investor. Option D is incorrect — EUIN disclosure is mandatory regardless of the commission model.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's shift from upfront to trail-only commission was designed specifically to address churning and mis-selling. Under the upfront model, distributors had an incentive to encourage redemptions and fresh investments to earn new commissions. Trail commission removes this perverse incentive. This regulatory philosophy is a key exam theme.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Embrace the trail model as a sustainable business foundation. Focus on building a growing AUM book through regular investments and client retention. A Rs. 10 crore AUM book at even 0.5% trail generates Rs. 5 lakh annually — and grows with the market.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
