<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the validity period of the NISM Series V-A: Mutual Fund Distributors Certification, after which renewal is required?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1 year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[3 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The NISM Series V-A certification is valid for 3 years from the date of passing the examination. Before the certification expires, the distributor must either pass the certification exam again or complete the prescribed Continuing Professional Education (CPE) requirements to renew their certification. Without a valid NISM certification, the ARN cannot be renewed.

**The Trap:** The most common distractors are 2 years and 5 years. Some candidates confuse this with other financial certifications that may have different validity periods. The key number to remember is 3 years — this is a frequently tested factual question with no ambiguity.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 3-year validity ensures that distributors keep their knowledge current. The renewal process may involve either re-taking the exam or completing CPE credits. This mandatory renewal links to SEBI's objective of maintaining minimum competency standards in the distribution workforce. ARN renewal is contingent on valid NISM certification.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Plan your certification renewal well in advance. Do not wait until the last month — exam centers may be fully booked, or you may need multiple attempts. A lapsed NISM certification means your ARN becomes invalid, effectively shutting down your business. Many distributors opt for CPE as a less stressful renewal route.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
