<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_46" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[EUIN stands for ________, and it is mandatory for employees of institutional distributors to quote this number in mutual fund application forms.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Employee Unique Identification Number, issued by AMFI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Employee Unique Identification Number, issued by SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Employee Unique Identification Number, issued by NSE]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Employee Unique Identification Number, issued by the AMC]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** EUIN (Employee Unique Identification Number) is issued by AMFI (Association of Mutual Funds in India) to individual employees/relationship managers of mutual fund distributors (particularly institutional distributors like banks and national distributors). It must be quoted on mutual fund application forms to identify the specific employee who interacted with and advised the investor. This creates individual accountability within large distribution organizations.

**The Trap:** SEBI (Option B) is the regulator but does not issue EUINs -- AMFI handles this operationally. NSE (Option C) is a stock exchange, not involved in distributor registration. AMCs (Option D) are fund houses, not the issuing authority. The distinction between AMFI (which issues both ARN codes and EUINs) and SEBI (which mandates the requirement) is a frequently tested point.

**Cross-Exam Context:** EUIN complements the ARN (AMFI Registration Number) system. ARN identifies the distributor entity; EUIN identifies the specific employee within that entity. Both are required on application forms for institutional distributor transactions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** EUIN = Employee Unique Identification Number. Issued by AMFI. Required for employees of institutional distributors. Ensures individual accountability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
