<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A tech-savvy client wants to invest in Direct Plans of multiple AMCs using a single platform with a user-friendly app interface. Which type of channel would best serve this client?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A traditional individual distributor with ARN who offers Regular Plans through paper forms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC's own branch office where the client must visit separately for each AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A new-age online investment platform like Groww or Kuvera that aggregates Direct Plans of multiple AMCs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A bank's mutual fund distribution desk that offers Regular Plans with advisory support]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** New-age online platforms like Groww, Kuvera, Paytm Money, and Zerodha Coin provide aggregated access to Direct Plans of multiple AMCs through a single mobile app or web interface. These platforms cater specifically to tech-savvy, DIY investors who want low-cost investing (Direct Plans), digital convenience, and a consolidated portfolio view.

**The Trap:** Option A involves a traditional distributor offering Regular Plans — this does not meet the client's requirement for Direct Plans or digital convenience. Option B requires multiple AMC visits — impractical for a tech-savvy client. Option D involves a bank offering Regular Plans, not Direct Plans. The question tests whether candidates can match client profiles to appropriate channels.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The rise of new-age platforms represents a significant shift in mutual fund distribution. While traditional distributors still dominate in terms of AUM, these platforms have captured a large share of new, young, digitally native investors. The exam tests awareness of this evolving landscape and the ability to recommend appropriate channels.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understand what these platforms offer so you can articulate your comparative advantage. Direct plan platforms provide convenience but no personalized advice. Position yourself as the comprehensive financial partner who offers goal planning, tax optimization, and behavioral coaching — services that an app cannot replicate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
