<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the first mandatory step for a person who wants to become a mutual fund distributor in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtaining an AMFI Registration Number (ARN) from AMFI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Passing the NISM Series V-A: Mutual Fund Distributors Certification Examination]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Registering with SEBI as an investment adviser]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Completing the KYD (Know Your Distributor) process with CAMS]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The first and foremost mandatory step is passing the NISM Series V-A Certification Examination. Only after obtaining the NISM certification can a person apply for an ARN from AMFI. The sequence is: NISM Certification → ARN from AMFI → KYD compliance → Empanelment with AMCs → Start distributing.

**The Trap:** Option A (ARN from AMFI) is the second step, not the first — you cannot get an ARN without first having NISM certification. Option C is wrong because mutual fund distributors register with AMFI, not SEBI (investment advisers register with SEBI). Option D (KYD) comes after obtaining ARN.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM certification is valid for 3 years and must be renewed before expiry. Similarly, ARN must be renewed periodically. This sequential process — NISM → ARN → KYD → Empanelment — is a frequently tested topic. SEBI mandated NISM certification to ensure minimum competency standards for distributors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Mark your NISM certification expiry date and start the renewal process well in advance. If your certification lapses, your ARN becomes invalid and you cannot process any transactions. Set a reminder at least 3 months before expiry.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
