<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the AMFI Registration Number (ARN) is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ARN is issued by SEBI directly to all mutual fund distributors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ARN is a lifetime registration that never requires renewal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ARN is issued by AMFI after the distributor obtains NISM certification and needs periodic renewal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ARN is issued separately by each AMC whose schemes the distributor wants to sell]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AMFI (Association of Mutual Funds in India) issues the ARN to distributors after they obtain NISM Series V-A certification. The ARN is a unique registration number that identifies the distributor across all AMCs. It requires periodic renewal — the distributor must ensure their NISM certification is valid and renew their ARN before it expires.

**The Trap:** Option A says SEBI issues ARN — SEBI is the regulator but AMFI (the industry body) handles ARN issuance. Option B claims it is lifetime — ARN requires renewal. Option D suggests each AMC issues separate ARNs — the ARN is universal across all AMCs, issued centrally by AMFI.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The ARN system creates a centralized distributor registry managed by AMFI. Every mutual fund application form requires the distributor's ARN. If an ARN is invalid or expired, the distributor cannot process any transactions. This links to the NISM certification requirement and KYD compliance.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Your ARN is your professional identity in the mutual fund industry. Keep it current by tracking renewal dates for both your NISM certification and ARN. Set up reminders at least 3 months in advance. Also, ensure your ARN details (name, address, contact) are always updated with AMFI.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
