<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An existing mutual fund investor invests Rs. 25,000 through a distributor in a Regular Plan. What is the net amount that gets invested in the scheme after accounting for the transaction charge?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 24,850 (after deducting Rs. 150 transaction charge for existing investors)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 24,900 (after deducting Rs. 100 transaction charge for existing investors)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 25,000 (no transaction charge is applicable)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 24,750 (after deducting Rs. 250 transaction charge for large investments)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For an existing investor investing Rs. 25,000 (which is above the Rs. 10,000 threshold), the transaction charge is Rs. 100. This is deducted from the investment amount, so the net amount invested in the scheme is Rs. 25,000 - Rs. 100 = Rs. 24,900. The Rs. 100 goes to the distributor as a transaction charge.

**The Trap:** Option A applies the new investor charge of Rs. 150 instead of the existing investor charge of Rs. 100 — this is the most common error. Option C ignores the transaction charge entirely. Option D invents a Rs. 250 charge. The two numbers to memorize: Rs. 150 for new investors, Rs. 100 for existing investors, both for amounts of Rs. 10,000 or above.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a straightforward calculation question but the exam deliberately tests whether candidates can correctly identify the investor type (new vs. existing) and apply the right transaction charge. The Rs. 10,000 threshold, new investor charge (Rs. 150), and existing investor charge (Rs. 100) are the three numbers to know.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always disclose transaction charges to clients upfront. When processing large investments, show the client the exact calculation: investment amount minus transaction charge equals net amount invested. This transparency prevents surprises when the client checks their allotment statement and sees slightly fewer units than expected.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
