<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following stock exchange platforms is used for mutual fund transactions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSE NEAT and BSE BOLT]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NSE NMF II and BSE StAR MF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSE NOW and BSE BEST]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSE EMERGE and BSE SME]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NSE's NMF II (NSE Mutual Fund Platform II) and BSE's StAR MF (BSE Stock Exchange Platform for Allotment and Repurchase of Mutual Funds) are the two dedicated exchange platforms for mutual fund transactions. These platforms allow distributors and investors to place mutual fund orders through the stock exchange infrastructure.

**The Trap:** Option A (NEAT and BOLT) are trading platforms for equity and derivatives, not mutual funds. Option C and D refer to other exchange platforms for different purposes (trading terminals, SME listings). The exam specifically tests whether candidates know the exact platform names — NMF II and StAR MF are the correct ones.

**Cross-Exam Context:** An important nuance is that while these platforms use exchange infrastructure for order routing, the stock exchanges do NOT provide settlement guarantee for mutual fund transactions (unlike equity trades). This is a frequently tested distinction. SEBI also allowed direct investor access to exchange MF platforms from February 2020.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Exchange platforms offer operational advantages — real-time order confirmation, consolidated portfolio view, and systematic transaction facilities. However, remind clients that unlike equity trades, there is no exchange settlement guarantee for MF transactions routed through these platforms.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
