<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the significance of SEBI's February 2020 circular regarding mutual fund transactions through stock exchange platforms?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It mandated that all mutual fund transactions must go through stock exchange platforms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It introduced settlement guarantee for mutual fund transactions on exchange platforms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It allowed investors to directly access stock exchange mutual fund infrastructure without necessarily going through a broker]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It restricted exchange platforms to only process transactions above Rs. 1 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's February 2020 circular was significant because it allowed investors direct access to the stock exchange infrastructure for mutual fund transactions. Previously, investors needed to go through a registered stock broker to use exchange MF platforms. This circular expanded access by allowing direct investor participation, increasing convenience and reach.

**The Trap:** Option A overstates the circular — it allowed direct access but did not mandate exclusive use of exchange platforms. Option B is incorrect because settlement guarantee was NOT introduced (this remains a key distinction). Option D fabricates a minimum transaction threshold that does not exist.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This circular is part of SEBI's broader digitization push. Combined with the growth of online platforms and apps, it represents the expansion of transaction channels available to investors. The exam tests whether candidates understand the specific impact of this circular versus general exchange platform features.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This direct access provision means more competition in the distribution space but also more opportunities. Leverage exchange platforms for operational efficiency — real-time order confirmation and systematic transaction facilities can improve your service delivery to clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
