<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor holds units in a Regular Plan and wants to switch to the Direct Plan of the same scheme. What are the implications?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The switch is treated as a mere administrative change with no tax or NAV impact]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The switch is treated as a redemption from the Regular Plan and a fresh purchase in the Direct Plan, potentially attracting capital gains tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The switch is not allowed by SEBI — investors must redeem and then separately invest in the Direct Plan]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The switch automatically converts existing units at the same cost basis with no tax implications]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Switching from a Regular Plan to a Direct Plan (or vice versa) of the same scheme is treated as a redemption from one plan and a fresh purchase in the other. This means the investor may incur capital gains tax on the redemption proceeds from the Regular Plan, and the purchase in the Direct Plan starts with a new cost basis and new holding period.

**The Trap:** Option A and D suggest the switch is tax-neutral — this is a common misconception. Even though the underlying scheme is the same, SEBI and tax authorities treat Regular and Direct as separate plans. Option C is incorrect because the switch IS allowed as a standard switch transaction within the same scheme.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a critical concept that bridges Chapter 6 (distribution) with Chapter 9 (taxation). Many investors and even some distributors mistakenly believe switching between plans is a simple administrative change. Understanding the tax implications helps distributors provide better advice and avoid client dissatisfaction.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client considers switching to Direct Plan, calculate the potential capital gains tax liability first. If the holding is in long-term capital gains territory with significant unrealized gains, the tax cost of switching may outweigh several years of TER savings. Present this analysis objectively to demonstrate your advisory value.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
