<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor wants to invest in mutual funds but does not want any distributor involvement. Which of the following options is most suitable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing through a bank's mutual fund desk using their ARN]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Investing directly through the AMC website or app in a Direct Plan]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing through an individual distributor who charges a separate advisory fee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing through a stock broker who routes orders via BSE StAR MF]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If an investor wants zero distributor involvement, they should invest directly through the AMC's website, app, or office in a Direct Plan. Direct Plans have no distributor commission component in TER, and the investor transacts directly with the AMC without any intermediary's ARN being associated with the investment.

**The Trap:** Option A involves a bank acting as distributor (with ARN), so there is distributor involvement. Option C still involves a distributor, even though they charge a separate fee. Option D involves a stock broker who is technically an intermediary. Only the Direct Plan through AMC's own channels ensures no distributor involvement whatsoever.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Direct Plans were mandated by SEBI from January 1, 2013. The investor can also use platforms like MFU or SEBI-registered investment advisers (RIAs) who may facilitate Direct Plan investments. However, the most straightforward no-intermediary route is directly through the AMC.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask about Direct Plans, be honest about the cost difference. Then articulate your value — behavioral coaching during market crashes, rebalancing advice, tax-efficient withdrawal strategies, and financial planning. Many clients who try Direct Plans eventually return for professional guidance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
