<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): A young, financially literate client, Vikram, approaches Priya and says he wants to invest in Direct Plans to save on expenses. He does his own research and does not need advisory support. He asks Priya whether she can help him invest in Direct Plans.

Question 39: What should Priya advise Vikram regarding Direct Plans?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should refuse to discuss Direct Plans because they threaten her commission income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should tell Vikram that Direct Plans have higher risk because there is no distributor oversight]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[She should transparently explain that Direct Plans have lower TER but no distributor service, and suggest he invest directly through AMC websites or platforms like Kuvera or Groww if he does not need advisory support]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should convince Vikram that Regular Plans always deliver better returns because distributors select the best schemes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per AMFI's code of conduct, distributors must act in the investor's best interest and provide transparent information. If Vikram is financially literate, does his own research, and does not need advisory support, Priya should honestly explain the difference between Direct and Regular Plans. She should inform him that Direct Plans have lower TER and guide him to appropriate channels (AMC websites, online platforms) for Direct Plan investments.

**The Trap:** Option A prioritizes Priya's income over client interest — this violates the code of conduct. Option B spreads misinformation — Direct Plans have the same risk profile as Regular Plans (identical portfolio). Option D makes a false claim — Regular Plans do NOT deliver better returns; they have higher TER, which reduces returns. All three wrong options represent ethical violations or factual errors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This question tests the distributor's ethical obligations under AMFI's code of conduct. A distributor must prioritize investor interest over personal commission. The exam frequently tests scenarios where the distributor's commercial interest conflicts with the client's best interest — the correct answer always favors the client.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Being transparent about Direct Plans actually builds trust. Clients who feel you are honest about cost differences are more likely to refer others to you and stay with you for complex financial planning. The clients who need guidance will choose your Regular Plan route, while those who do not need advice will appreciate your honesty — and may return when their financial situation becomes more complex.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
