<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[KYD (Know Your Distributor) compliance is a requirement for mutual fund distributors. What does the KYD process primarily involve?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Testing the distributor's knowledge of mutual fund products through an examination]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Verification of the distributor's identity, address, and credentials through document submission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Assessment of the distributor's financial net worth to determine distribution capacity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Evaluation of the distributor's past sales performance across all AMCs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** KYD (Know Your Distributor) is a process similar to KYC (Know Your Customer) but applied to distributors. It involves verification of the distributor's identity, address, and relevant credentials through submission and verification of documents such as PAN, address proof, NISM certification, and photographs. This is handled by designated KYD Registration Agencies.

**The Trap:** Option A describes the NISM certification exam, not KYD. Option C sounds like a SEBI requirement for investment advisers (net worth criterion), not for distributors. Option D describes due diligence or performance evaluation, which is different from KYD. The key distinction is that KYD is about identity and document verification, not testing or assessment.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The sequence of compliance requirements is: NISM exam → ARN from AMFI → KYD compliance → Empanelment with AMCs. KYD was introduced to create a centralized repository of verified distributor information, similar to how KYC works for investors. CAMS handles KYD operations.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Complete your KYD process promptly after obtaining ARN. Keep your KYD records updated — any change in address or credentials must be reported. An incomplete or expired KYD can delay your empanelment with AMCs and disrupt your business.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
