<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fundamentals of Research_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ananya Sharma is a research analyst at Meridian Securities, a mid-sized brokerage firm. She is researching Vividha Pharma Ltd, a pharmaceutical company listed on NSE. During her research process, she undertakes the following activities: (1) She reviews Vividha Pharma's annual reports and quarterly filings from the last 5 years. (2) During a conference, she overhears the CFO of Vividha Pharma telling another analyst that "the next quarter will be significantly better than expected" — this information has not been announced to the exchange. (3) She visits a hospital that is a major customer of Vividha Pharma and learns from doctors that they have been ordering more of Vividha's oncology drugs lately. (4) She reads an industry report from IQVIA showing 15% growth in the Indian oncology market. (5) She speaks to a raw material supplier who mentions that Vividha has placed unusually large orders for API (Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients) in the last 2 months. She now needs to prepare her research report with a recommendation.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Which of Ananya's research activities constitutes secondary research?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Visiting the hospital to speak with doctors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Reading Vividha Pharma's annual reports and the IQVIA industry report]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Speaking to the raw material supplier about order patterns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overhearing the CFO's comments at the conference]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Secondary research involves using existing published data. Annual reports (regulatory filings) and industry reports from IQVIA are published data sources — hence secondary research.
**The Trap:** Hospital visits and supplier conversations are primary research (direct investigation). The CFO's overheard comment is neither primary nor secondary — it's potential insider information.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Research methodology classification is fundamental to NISM Series XV and also tested in Series IX (Merchant Banking).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Systematic research starts with secondary research (filings, reports) to build a baseline, then primary research (visits, interviews) to verify and deepen insights.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>