<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the key difference between an Investor Service Center (ISC) operated by an AMC and an RTA service center like CAMS or KFintech?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ISCs can process only purchase transactions while RTA centers handle only redemptions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ISCs charge a fee for transactions while RTA centers provide free services]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ISCs typically handle transactions for only that particular AMC, while RTA service centers can process transactions for all AMCs serviced by that RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ISCs are located only in metro cities while RTA centers operate only in non-metro areas]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An AMC's Investor Service Center handles transactions only for that particular AMC's schemes. In contrast, an RTA service center (like a CAMS or KFintech office) can process transactions for all AMCs that use that RTA's services. For example, if CAMS services 15 AMCs, a single visit to a CAMS office can handle transactions across all 15 AMCs.

**The Trap:** Option A fabricates a transaction-type restriction that does not exist — both ISCs and RTA centers can handle all types of transactions. Option B is wrong — neither charges investors directly for processing transactions. Option D creates a geographic distinction that does not exist — both operate in various cities.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the distinction between AMC ISCs and RTA service centers is important for the practical aspects of fund distribution. RTAs serve as a shared infrastructure, reducing duplication of offices. This is similar to how MFU provides shared services across AMCs for transaction processing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients with investments across multiple AMCs, recommend RTA service centers for one-stop processing. Knowing which AMCs are with CAMS and which with KFintech helps you guide clients to the right office and saves them multiple trips.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
