<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fundamentals of Research_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ananya Sharma is a research analyst at Meridian Securities, a mid-sized brokerage firm. She is researching Vividha Pharma Ltd, a pharmaceutical company listed on NSE. During her research process, she undertakes the following activities: (1) She reviews Vividha Pharma's annual reports and quarterly filings from the last 5 years. (2) During a conference, she overhears the CFO of Vividha Pharma telling another analyst that "the next quarter will be significantly better than expected" — this information has not been announced to the exchange. (3) She visits a hospital that is a major customer of Vividha Pharma and learns from doctors that they have been ordering more of Vividha's oncology drugs lately. (4) She reads an industry report from IQVIA showing 15% growth in the Indian oncology market. (5) She speaks to a raw material supplier who mentions that Vividha has placed unusually large orders for API (Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients) in the last 2 months. She now needs to prepare her research report with a recommendation.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> The CFO's statement that 'the next quarter will be significantly better than expected' represents:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mosaic information that can be freely used]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Unpublished price-sensitive information (UPSI) that Ananya must not use in her report]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Public information since it was said at a conference]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A research recommendation from a company official]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The CFO's statement about unexpectedly better quarterly performance, if not yet announced to the exchange, constitutes unpublished price-sensitive information (UPSI). Ananya must not use this in her analysis or trading decisions.
**The Trap:** Although said at a conference, it was not a public announcement to the exchange. A statement made privately to another analyst does not make it public information.
**Cross-Exam Context:** UPSI definition and handling is a critical compliance topic in NISM Series XV, III-A, and XXIV. The source and materiality determine classification.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If an analyst inadvertently receives UPSI, the proper course is to inform the compliance officer immediately and place the security on the restricted list.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>