<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the additional TER (Total Expense Ratio) that AMCs are allowed to charge for inflows from B30 cities (beyond top 30 cities)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[15 basis points]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[30 basis points]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50 basis points]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[25 basis points]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI allows AMCs to charge an additional TER of up to 30 basis points (0.30%) on the daily net assets of the scheme if the new inflows from beyond the top 30 cities (B30 cities) are at least 30% of gross new inflows in the scheme, or 15% of the average AUM (whichever is higher). This incentivizes distributors to expand mutual fund penetration in smaller cities.

**The Trap:** The numbers 15, 25, and 50 are all plausible-sounding alternatives. The key figure to remember is 30 bps for B30 — notice the mnemonic: "B30 = 30 bps." Many candidates confuse this with the general TER limits or other regulatory thresholds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This B30 incentive connects to SEBI's broader goal of increasing mutual fund penetration beyond metro cities. The additional TER can be used to pay higher commissions to distributors operating in these locations. This topic frequently appears alongside questions about TER regulations in Chapter 5.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you operate in smaller cities, the B30 incentive means AMCs can pay you higher commissions for bringing in investors from these locations. This is a genuine business opportunity — focus on investor education and awareness in these markets for a competitive advantage.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
