<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fundamentals of Research_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Rajiv Kapoor is an investment manager evaluating two different approaches to investing in the Indian equity market. He manages a corpus of Rs. 50 crore and is considering the following options: (1) Strategy A — Active Fundamental Approach: Hire a team of 3 research analysts to conduct bottom-up fundamental analysis, visiting companies, building financial models, and selecting 25-30 undervalued stocks. Expected expense ratio: 2.5% per annum. Historical outperformance vs Nifty 50: 3% per annum over the last 5 years. (2) Strategy B — Passive Index Approach: Invest in a Nifty 50 index fund with an expense ratio of 0.1% per annum. Expected return: Nifty 50 return minus tracking error of 0.05%. (3) Additionally, he has access to a quantitative model that uses regression analysis to predict quarterly earnings of Nifty 50 companies. The model has shown 65% accuracy in predicting the direction of earnings surprises over the last 3 years. Rajiv is in his 40s and has a 15-year investment horizon for this corpus which is part of a pension fund.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Strategy A is best described as which approach to investing?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Passive indexing strategy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Active fundamental investing approach]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pure quantitative/algorithmic strategy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Technical analysis-based trading approach]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Strategy A involves hiring analysts for fundamental analysis, visiting companies, building financial models, and selecting undervalued stocks — this is the classic active fundamental investing approach.
**The Trap:** Passive indexing replicates an index without stock selection. The strategy clearly involves active stock selection based on fundamental research.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Active vs passive investing approaches are fundamental concepts in NISM Series XV Chapter 4 and V-A (Mutual Fund Distributors).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Active management justifies its higher cost only if it consistently outperforms passive alternatives after fees. This is the central question Rajiv must answer.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>