<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Priya wants to maximize her operational efficiency. She has clients investing across 8 different AMCs and is looking for a platform that allows consolidated transaction processing. She also wants to leverage her location in Lucknow (a B30 city) for better commissions.

Question 40: Which combination of platform choice and B30 strategy would best serve Priya's needs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Use NSE NMF II for all transactions because it provides settlement guarantee, and claim B30 incentive for all existing investors regardless of their city of residence]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Use MF Utilities (MFU) for consolidated multi-AMC transactions, and focus on acquiring new investors from Lucknow and surrounding B30 cities to benefit from the additional 30 bps TER incentive]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Use individual AMC websites for each of the 8 AMCs to maintain direct relationships, and register her Mumbai office address to avoid B30 classification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Use BSE StAR MF exclusively because it offers the highest commission rates, and the B30 incentive applies automatically to all transactions processed from any B30 city]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** MFU is ideal for Priya's multi-AMC operation because it allows consolidated processing across all 8 AMCs using CAN, Common Transaction Form, and consolidated payment. For the B30 strategy, she should focus on acquiring new investors from Lucknow and surrounding B30 areas — the additional 30 bps TER incentive is available for new inflows from these cities, which AMCs can pass on as higher commissions.

**The Trap:** Option A incorrectly states NSE NMF II provides settlement guarantee (it does not for MF transactions) and misapplies the B30 rule. Option C suggests using 8 separate AMC websites, which is the opposite of operational efficiency, and suggesting a fake Mumbai address is unethical. Option D claims BSE StAR MF offers highest commissions (platforms do not determine commission rates — AMCs do) and oversimplifies the B30 incentive mechanism.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This question integrates multiple chapter concepts: transaction channels (MFU vs. exchange platforms vs. AMC direct), B30 incentive mechanics, settlement guarantee limitations, and ethical conduct. The exam often presents such multi-layered scenarios in case studies to test comprehensive understanding.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Combine MFU for operational efficiency with a strong B30 acquisition strategy. In Lucknow, focus on investor education — conduct workshops, partner with local businesses, and build community trust. The combination of efficient operations and growing B30 AUM creates a strong, differentiated business model. Track your B30 inflows separately to negotiate better commission terms with AMCs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
