<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which feature of MF Utilities (MFU) allows an investor to make a single payment for subscriptions in multiple mutual fund schemes across different AMCs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Common Account Number (CAN)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Common Transaction Form]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Consolidated payment facility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Unified portfolio statement]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** MFU's consolidated payment facility allows investors to make a single payment for subscriptions across multiple schemes of different AMCs. Instead of issuing separate cheques or transfers for each AMC, the investor can consolidate everything into one payment, which MFU then distributes to the respective AMCs.

**The Trap:** CAN (Option A) is the identification number, not the payment facility. Common Transaction Form (Option B) is the single form used for transactions across AMCs, but it is not the payment mechanism. Unified portfolio statement (Option D) sounds relevant but is not a specific MFU feature — it refers to the Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) issued by RTAs/depositories.

**Cross-Exam Context:** MFU offers three key conveniences: (1) CAN for unified identification, (2) Common Transaction Form for simplified paperwork, and (3) Consolidated payment for single-payment processing. The exam may test each of these features individually, so understanding the distinction between them is important.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The consolidated payment facility is a game-changer for clients doing lump sum investments across multiple AMCs — one transaction instead of many. Promote MFU to clients who have diversified portfolios across several fund houses to save time and effort.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
