<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_38" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Priya is now empaneled and starts distributing mutual funds. A new client, Mr. Sharma, invests Rs. 1,00,000 through Priya in an equity fund's Regular Plan. Another existing client, Mrs. Gupta, invests Rs. 15,000 in a debt fund's Regular Plan.

Question 38: What is the total transaction charge Priya earns from these two transactions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 250 (Rs. 150 from Mr. Sharma as a new investor + Rs. 100 from Mrs. Gupta as an existing investor)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 300 (Rs. 150 from each investor since both amounts exceed Rs. 10,000)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 200 (Rs. 100 from each investor as standard transaction charge)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 150 (only Mr. Sharma's transaction qualifies as Mrs. Gupta's amount is below Rs. 50,000)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mr. Sharma is a new investor investing Rs. 1,00,000 (above Rs. 10,000 threshold) → transaction charge = Rs. 150. Mrs. Gupta is an existing investor investing Rs. 15,000 (above Rs. 10,000 threshold) → transaction charge = Rs. 100. Total = Rs. 150 + Rs. 100 = Rs. 250. Both investments exceed the Rs. 10,000 threshold, so transaction charges apply to both.

**The Trap:** Option B incorrectly applies the new investor charge (Rs. 150) to both — Mrs. Gupta is an existing investor, so her charge is Rs. 100, not Rs. 150. Option C applies Rs. 100 to both, ignoring that Mr. Sharma is a new investor. Option D invents a Rs. 50,000 threshold that does not exist. The exam tests precise application of the dual-rate structure.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This calculation question tests three things simultaneously: (1) ability to distinguish new vs. existing investors, (2) knowledge of the correct charge amounts (Rs. 150 vs. Rs. 100), and (3) understanding of the Rs. 10,000 minimum threshold. Both amounts exceed the threshold, so both transactions attract charges. This is a high-probability exam question format.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Transaction charges are a small but tangible benefit, especially when you are building your practice. Track them as part of your revenue planning. More importantly, the higher charge for new investors (Rs. 150) incentivizes you to grow your client base — every new investor you bring in earns you 50% more in transaction charges compared to an existing investor's transaction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
