<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When an investor purchases a Regular Plan of a mutual fund scheme, who bears the cost of the distributor's commission?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC pays it from its own profits, not from the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All investors in the Regular Plan bear the cost as it is included in the scheme's TER]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the specific investor whose transaction generated the commission bears the cost]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMFI reimburses the distributor commission from its member fees]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Distributor commission in Regular Plans is embedded within the Total Expense Ratio (TER) of the scheme. TER is charged to the scheme's assets as a whole, meaning ALL investors in the Regular Plan collectively bear this cost through a slightly lower NAV. This is why Regular Plan NAV is always lower than the corresponding Direct Plan NAV over time.

**The Trap:** Option A suggests the AMC pays from its own pocket — this is incorrect as commission is a scheme-level expense included in TER. Option C suggests only the transacting investor bears the cost — this misunderstands how TER works (it is applied to the entire AUM, not to individual transactions). Option D is completely fictitious.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is why Direct Plans have lower TER and higher NAV compared to Regular Plans — the distributor commission component is absent. Understanding the cost flow (TER → Commission → Distributor) is fundamental to explaining plan differences to investors and is heavily tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Be transparent with clients about how your commission works. Explaining that the commission comes from the TER (and thus affects their returns slightly) builds trust. Position your value proposition around the advisory and service benefits that justify this cost.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
