<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a recognized transaction channel for mutual fund investments in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMC branches and Investor Service Centers (ISCs)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTA offices such as CAMS and KFintech service centers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[India Post offices as authorized mutual fund transaction points]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Stock exchange platforms such as NSE NMF II and BSE StAR MF]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The recognized transaction channels for mutual funds include AMC branches/ISCs, RTA offices (CAMS, KFintech), stock exchange platforms (NSE NMF II, BSE StAR MF), MF Utilities (MFU), distributor offices, and online/mobile platforms. India Post offices, while they distribute certain government savings instruments (PPF, NSC, etc.), are not standard authorized mutual fund transaction points.

**The Trap:** India Post has a vast network and handles postal savings schemes, so it sounds plausible as a mutual fund channel. However, mutual fund transactions require specific infrastructure (RTA integration, payment processing, KYC verification) that standard post offices do not have. All other options are well-established MF transaction channels.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The exam tests whether candidates can distinguish between actual and plausible-sounding transaction channels. The official channels are: AMC offices, RTA service centers, stock exchange platforms, MFU, online platforms, and distributor/bank channels. Understanding the full ecosystem of transaction channels is essential.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Know your transaction channel options well. Different channels suit different situations — RTA offices for multi-AMC transactions, exchange platforms for real-time confirmation, AMC websites for Direct Plans, and your own office for personalized service. Guide clients to the most appropriate channel for each transaction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
