<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the primary difference between a Direct Plan and a Regular Plan of the same mutual fund scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Direct Plans have a higher NAV at launch compared to Regular Plans]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Direct Plans have a lower Total Expense Ratio (TER) as no distributor commission is included]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Direct Plans invest in different securities than Regular Plans of the same scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Direct Plans are available only to institutional investors while Regular Plans are for retail investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Direct Plans and Regular Plans of the same scheme invest in an identical portfolio of securities. The only difference is that Direct Plans do not include distributor commission in their TER, making them cheaper. Over time, this lower expense ratio leads to a higher NAV for Direct Plans compared to Regular Plans.

**The Trap:** Option A is tricky because Direct Plans DO eventually have a higher NAV — but not "at launch." At launch, both plans start at the same NAV (typically Rs. 10 for NFOs). The NAV divergence happens over time due to the TER difference. Option C is a common misconception — the underlying portfolio is identical.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This concept links to Chapter 5 (TER regulations) and Chapter 8 (NAV computation). SEBI mandated separate plans from January 1, 2013. The TER difference directly impacts long-term returns, making this a favorite exam topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask why Direct Plan NAV is higher, explain it is because of the compounding effect of lower expenses over time — not because the fund manager does anything differently. This transparency builds trust and helps you justify the advisory value you provide through Regular Plans.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
