<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[During a New Fund Offer (NFO), what is the typical sequence of events?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Listing → Subscription → Allotment → Launch]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Subscription → Launch → Listing → Allotment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Launch → Subscription → Allotment → Listing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Allotment → Launch → Subscription → Listing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The NFO process follows a logical sequence: (1) Launch — the AMC files documents with SEBI and announces the NFO; (2) Subscription — the NFO is open for investors to subscribe during a specified period (typically 15 days for open-ended schemes); (3) Allotment — after the NFO period closes, units are allotted to investors; (4) Listing — the scheme is listed for ongoing transactions (for open-ended schemes, this means reopening for sale/repurchase at NAV-based prices).

**The Trap:** Option B puts launch after subscription, which makes no sense — the NFO must be launched before investors can subscribe. Option D puts allotment before launch. These are sequencing traps designed for candidates who have not carefully thought through the process flow.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For close-ended schemes, listing refers to listing on a stock exchange. For open-ended schemes, the scheme reopens for continuous sale and repurchase after a brief period post-allotment. The NFO price is typically Rs. 10 per unit. This links to scheme types covered in Chapter 4.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During NFO periods, help clients understand that they are buying at a fixed price (usually Rs. 10) with no track record. Evaluate the scheme's mandate, fund manager, and AMC reputation. Never recommend an NFO solely because it is "new" or "cheap" at Rs. 10 — NAV has no bearing on value.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
