<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which type of commission provides a mutual fund distributor with ongoing income based on the assets under management (AUM) of the investor's portfolio?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trail commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Upfront commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transaction charge]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Performance fee]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Trail commission is an ongoing commission paid to the distributor as a percentage of the AUM of the investor's holdings in a scheme, for as long as the investor remains invested. This creates an annuity-like income stream for the distributor and aligns the distributor's interest with the investor's (keeping the investor invested and growing the portfolio).

**The Trap:** Upfront commission (Option B) was a one-time payment at the time of investment, but SEBI has largely abolished upfront commissions for most scheme categories to prevent mis-selling. Transaction charge (Option C) is a fixed amount, not a percentage of AUM. Performance fee (Option D) is associated with fund managers of certain schemes like PMS, not with distributors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The shift from upfront to trail-only commission was a landmark regulatory change. Trail commission is paid out of the TER charged to the scheme. This means Regular Plan investors bear the cost of distributor commissions, while Direct Plan investors do not — explaining the TER difference between the two plans.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Trail commission rewards you for building long-term client relationships. Focus on growing client AUM through regular investments rather than chasing one-time large transactions. A steadily growing book of business provides predictable, recurring income.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
