<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fundamentals of Research_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Rajiv Kapoor is an investment manager evaluating two different approaches to investing in the Indian equity market. He manages a corpus of Rs. 50 crore and is considering the following options: (1) Strategy A — Active Fundamental Approach: Hire a team of 3 research analysts to conduct bottom-up fundamental analysis, visiting companies, building financial models, and selecting 25-30 undervalued stocks. Expected expense ratio: 2.5% per annum. Historical outperformance vs Nifty 50: 3% per annum over the last 5 years. (2) Strategy B — Passive Index Approach: Invest in a Nifty 50 index fund with an expense ratio of 0.1% per annum. Expected return: Nifty 50 return minus tracking error of 0.05%. (3) Additionally, he has access to a quantitative model that uses regression analysis to predict quarterly earnings of Nifty 50 companies. The model has shown 65% accuracy in predicting the direction of earnings surprises over the last 3 years. Rajiv is in his 40s and has a 15-year investment horizon for this corpus which is part of a pension fund.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> The quantitative model showing 65% accuracy in predicting earnings direction is an example of:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Technical analysis using price charts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fundamental analysis using financial statements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Quantitative/econometric approach to research]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Behavioral finance application]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A regression model predicting earnings is a quantitative/econometric approach. It uses statistical methods to analyze historical data and make predictions about future financial performance.
**The Trap:** Technical analysis uses price/volume data, not earnings predictions. Pure fundamental analysis involves qualitative judgment. The model uses regression — a statistical technique.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Quantitative research methods are discussed in NISM Series XV Chapter 4. The distinction between quant approaches and traditional fundamental/technical analysis is tested.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A 65% accuracy rate means 35% of predictions are wrong. Always use quantitative models as one input among many, not as the sole basis for investment decisions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>