<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI (Prohibition of Fraudulent and Unfair Trade Practices) Regulations 2003, mis-selling in mutual funds includes: (1) making false or misleading statements, (2) concealing material facts, (3) concealing risk factors of the scheme, and (4) not ensuring suitability to the investor. Which of these constitute mis-selling?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All four -- false statements, concealing material facts, concealing risks, and not ensuring suitability -- constitute mis-selling]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the first two -- false statements and concealing material facts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the last one -- not ensuring suitability to the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mis-selling occurs only when the investor actually suffers a financial loss]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI PFUTP Regulations 2003, ALL four acts constitute mis-selling: (1) making false or misleading statements about a scheme, (2) concealing or omitting material facts about the scheme, (3) concealing the risk factors of the scheme, and (4) not taking reasonable steps to ensure suitability of the recommendation to the investor. Each of these independently qualifies as mis-selling.

**The Trap:** Option B limits mis-selling to only active deception (false statements and concealment) while ignoring the suitability requirement. Option C focuses only on suitability, ignoring the deception-based grounds. Option D is a dangerous misconception -- mis-selling is defined by the ACT, not by the outcome. A distributor can be guilty of mis-selling even if the investor happens to make a profit.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The four-part definition of mis-selling is a high-frequency exam topic. Remember: mis-selling does NOT require actual investor loss -- the wrongful act itself constitutes the violation.

**Key Takeaway:** Mis-selling = false statements + concealing facts + concealing risks + ignoring suitability. All four are violations regardless of whether the investor loses money.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
