<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following entities is responsible for framing the code of conduct and best practices guidelines for mutual fund distributors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI (Securities and Exchange Board of India)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[AMFI (Association of Mutual Funds in India)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI (Reserve Bank of India)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NISM (National Institute of Securities Markets)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AMFI (Association of Mutual Funds in India) frames the code of conduct and best practices guidelines for mutual fund distributors. While SEBI is the overarching regulator and issues broad regulations, AMFI — as the industry self-regulatory body — develops specific operational guidelines and codes of conduct that distributors must follow.

**The Trap:** SEBI (Option A) sets the regulatory framework, but AMFI develops the distributor-specific code of conduct. RBI (Option C) regulates banks but not MF distributor conduct. NISM (Option D) conducts the certification examination but does not frame distributor codes of conduct. The distinction between SEBI's regulatory role and AMFI's self-regulatory role is frequently tested.

**Cross-Exam Context:** AMFI's best practices cover areas like: suitability assessment, risk disclosure, complete information to investors, no guarantees of returns, no rebating of commission, and proper documentation. These guidelines are enforceable — violations can lead to ARN suspension. This connects to the broader regulatory framework in Chapter 4.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Familiarize yourself thoroughly with AMFI's code of conduct — it is not just an exam topic but a practical guide for ethical distribution. Following these guidelines protects you from regulatory action and builds a sustainable, reputation-driven practice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
