<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following best describes the role of banks in mutual fund distribution?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Banks can only distribute mutual funds managed by their own group AMCs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Banks act as RTAs for mutual fund schemes they distribute]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Banks act as corporate distributors using their branch network to sell mutual fund schemes of various AMCs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Banks guarantee the returns of mutual fund schemes they distribute to their customers]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Banks are major corporate distributors of mutual funds. They leverage their extensive branch network and existing customer relationships to distribute schemes from multiple AMCs (not just their group AMCs). Banks obtain ARN and their employees involved in MF sales need EUIN. They earn trail commissions like any other distributor.

**The Trap:** Option A is wrong because banks can and do distribute schemes of multiple AMCs, not just their group companies. Option B confuses the bank's role — RTAs are separate entities like CAMS and KFintech. Option D is a critical misconception — banks DO NOT guarantee mutual fund returns, and they must clearly disclose this to customers. Mis-selling by banks suggesting guarantee is a regulatory concern.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Bank distribution of mutual funds falls under RBI and SEBI regulatory oversight. Banks must ensure that their staff clearly communicates that mutual funds are different from bank deposits and do not carry any guarantee of returns. This links to investor protection and the code of conduct for distributors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you work in bank distribution, ensure every client interaction clearly distinguishes mutual fund investments from bank deposits. Use proper risk disclosure at the point of sale. Regulatory penalties for mis-selling through bank channels have been significant.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
