<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_37" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Priya has recently passed the NISM Series V-A Certification Examination and wants to set up her own mutual fund distribution practice. She plans to operate from Lucknow (a B30 city) and wants to build a client base of both new and experienced mutual fund investors. She is evaluating various transaction platforms and trying to understand the commission structure before approaching AMCs for empanelment.

Question 37: What is the correct sequence of steps Priya must follow after passing the NISM exam to start distributing mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYD compliance → ARN from AMFI → Empanelment with AMCs → Start distributing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ARN from AMFI → KYD compliance → Empanelment with AMCs → EUIN for herself and any employees → Start distributing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Empanelment with AMCs → ARN from AMFI → KYD compliance → Start distributing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Register with SEBI as distributor → ARN from AMFI → KYD compliance → Start distributing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** After passing the NISM exam, Priya must: (1) Obtain ARN from AMFI (using her NISM certification), (2) Complete KYD compliance, (3) Get empaneled with AMCs (AMCs conduct due diligence), (4) Obtain EUIN for herself and any employees who will interact with investors, and then (5) Start distributing. The ARN is the foundational requirement — without it, she cannot proceed to other steps.

**The Trap:** Option A puts KYD before ARN — you need the ARN first before completing KYD. Option C puts empanelment before ARN — AMCs require ARN for empanelment. Option D mentions SEBI registration — mutual fund distributors register with AMFI (through ARN), not directly with SEBI. SEBI registration is for investment advisers, which is a different category.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This case study integrates multiple regulatory requirements. The sequential nature of these steps is important — each step is a prerequisite for the next. Missing any step means Priya cannot legally distribute mutual funds. This is a practical application of the regulatory framework covered in the chapter.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Create a checklist when setting up your distribution practice. Beyond the regulatory steps, also plan for: choosing an office location, setting up technology (CRM, portfolio tracking), creating marketing materials compliant with AMFI guidelines, and building relationships with AMC sales teams. A well-planned launch saves months of confusion.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
