<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fundamentals of Research_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ananya Sharma is a research analyst at Meridian Securities, a mid-sized brokerage firm. She is researching Vividha Pharma Ltd, a pharmaceutical company listed on NSE. During her research process, she undertakes the following activities: (1) She reviews Vividha Pharma's annual reports and quarterly filings from the last 5 years. (2) During a conference, she overhears the CFO of Vividha Pharma telling another analyst that "the next quarter will be significantly better than expected" — this information has not been announced to the exchange. (3) She visits a hospital that is a major customer of Vividha Pharma and learns from doctors that they have been ordering more of Vividha's oncology drugs lately. (4) She reads an industry report from IQVIA showing 15% growth in the Indian oncology market. (5) She speaks to a raw material supplier who mentions that Vividha has placed unusually large orders for API (Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients) in the last 2 months. She now needs to prepare her research report with a recommendation.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> If Ananya publishes a 'Buy' recommendation based solely on the CFO's overheard statement, she would be violating:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the company's internal policies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI (Prohibition of Insider Trading) Regulations by acting on UPSI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI guidelines on credit assessment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Using UPSI (the CFO's non-public statement about better-than-expected results) as the basis for a recommendation violates SEBI (Prohibition of Insider Trading) Regulations, 2015.
**The Trap:** This is not just an internal policy violation — it's a regulatory violation under SEBI PIT Regulations. It doesn't relate to mutual fund regulations or RBI guidelines.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Insider trading violations carry severe penalties under SEBI regulations, tested in NISM Series XV, III-A, III-C, and XXIV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The penalty for insider trading can include disgorgement of profits, monetary penalty up to Rs. 25 crore or three times the profit made, and even imprisonment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>