<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Fund Distribution and Channel Management_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A client wants to start a monthly SIP of Rs. 5,000 across three different AMCs. The distributor suggests using MF Utilities (MFU). Why is this recommendation appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MFU offers higher returns on SIP investments compared to investing directly with AMCs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MFU eliminates the transaction charge for SIP investments below Rs. 10,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[MFU allows the client to use a single Common Transaction Form and make one consolidated payment for SIPs across all three AMCs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MFU guarantees that SIP installments will never miss due to its automated debit system]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** MFU's key advantage for multi-AMC investors is operational convenience. With a Common Account Number (CAN), the client can use a single Common Transaction Form to set up SIPs across multiple AMCs and make consolidated payments. Instead of managing three separate forms and three separate debits, everything is streamlined through one platform.

**The Trap:** Option A is wrong — MFU is a transaction platform, not an investment optimizer that affects returns. Option B is misleading — the Rs. 10,000 threshold for transaction charges is a SEBI rule that applies regardless of the platform used. Option D overpromises — MFU facilitates transactions but cannot guarantee that debits will always succeed (bank account balance, mandate issues can still cause failures).

**Cross-Exam Context:** MFU is designed as a shared services infrastructure for the industry. Its core value proposition is simplification: one form, one account, one payment for multi-AMC investments. This is especially valuable for distributors managing clients with diversified portfolios. The exam tests practical application of MFU features.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Register your clients on MFU early in the relationship. As their portfolio grows across AMCs, the operational convenience of CAN will save both you and your client significant time and paperwork. MFU also provides a consolidated view of all investments, making portfolio reviews easier.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
