<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="I Accounting and Taxation_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The ICAI Guidance Note on Accounting for Derivatives Contract was revised in which year, and which regulatory framework superseded Accounting Standard (AS) 30 for entities following the Ind AS framework?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ICAI Guidance Note revised in 2021; Ind AS 109 (based on IFRS 9) superseded AS 30 for Ind AS entities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ICAI Guidance Note revised in 2018; AS 30 continues to apply to all Indian entities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ICAI Guidance Note revised in 2021; Ind AS 32 superseded AS 30 for Ind AS entities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ICAI Guidance Note revised in 2019; IFRS 9 directly applies to all listed companies]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The text states: "The Institute of Chartered Accountants of India (ICAI) has issued guidance notes on Accounting for Derivatives Contract (Revised 2021)" and "Accounting Standard 30 was eventually withdrawn and replaced by Ind AS 109 when India adopted the Indian Accounting Standards (Ind AS) framework. Ind AS 109, which is based on IFRS 9, is now the relevant and mandatory standard for companies that fall under the Ind AS roadmap."
**The Trap:** Ind AS 32 covers financial instrument presentation, not measurement. Ind AS 109 covers recognition, measurement, hedge accounting, and derecognition — the full financial instruments standard.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Three regimes: Ind AS entities → Ind AS 109; Non-Ind AS entities not covered by specific AS → ICAI Guidance Note (2021); Banking/NBFC/Insurance entities → RBI/IRDAI prescribed treatment.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** 2021 = ICAI Guidance Note revision year; Ind AS 109 = Ind AS entities' derivatives standard (replaced AS 30 + based on IFRS 9).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
