<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="I Accounting and Taxation_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Section 43(5) of the Income-tax Act, exchange-traded currency derivatives transactions carried out on a recognised stock exchange are classified as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Non-speculative business income, and losses can be set off against any normal business income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Speculative business income, and losses can only be set off against speculative income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains for all investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Income from other sources, taxed at a flat 30%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The text states: "Section 43(5) has specifically excluded certain derivative transactions from the meaning of speculative transaction... an eligible transaction in respect of trading in derivatives referred to in clause (ac) of section 2 of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956) carried out in a recognized stock exchange shall not be deemed to be a speculative transaction. Thus, income or loss from dealing in exchange traded currency derivatives shall be deemed as normal business income (non-speculative business)."
**The Trap:** The default rule for futures contracts settled without delivery is speculative income. But Section 43(5) carves out exchange-traded derivatives — making them non-speculative. FPIs are an exception: their derivatives income is always capital gains.
**Cross-Exam Context:** For FPIs: profits from derivatives = capital gains (always). For all others: exchange-traded currency derivatives = non-speculative PGBP income.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Section 43(5) = non-speculative exception for exchange-traded derivatives. This is critical for tax planning — losses from ETCD can offset general business income, unlike speculative losses.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
