<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="I Codes of Conduct and Investor Protection_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the SEBI Code of Conduct for brokers, what should a stock broker do when a conflict of interest arises between himself and a client?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Inform the client of the conflict, not seek to gain personal advantage from the situation, and not consider the client's interests inferior to his own]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Prioritise the broker's interests since the broker bears market risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Refer the client to another broker without disclosing the conflict]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cancel all pending client orders until the conflict is resolved]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The text states: "A stock-broker, when dealing with a client, shall disclose whether he is acting as a principal or as an agent and shall ensure at the same time that no conflict of interest arises between him and the client. In the event of a conflict of interest, he shall inform the client accordingly and shall not seek to gain a direct or indirect personal advantage from the situation and shall not consider clients' interests inferior to his own."
**The Trap:** The broker's obligation is disclosure AND not exploiting the conflict — not simply cancelling orders or referring the client. Client interest must not be subordinated.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The broker must also disclose to clients whether acting as principal or agent — a fundamental transparency requirement that precedes the conflict of interest rule.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Conflict of interest rule = Disclose + Don't exploit + Don't subordinate client interest. Three obligations, not just one.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
