<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="I Codes of Conduct and Investor Protection_38" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's SCORES (Complaints Redress System) framework, what is the correct escalation sequence for an investor who has a grievance against a broker?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[First approach the broker/intermediary → if unsatisfied, escalate to the stock exchange or SCORES → if still unresolved, initiate ODR (Online Dispute Resolution) through the ODR Portal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[First approach SEBI directly → if no action, approach the stock exchange → finally approach the broker]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[First file a civil court case → if not resolved, approach SEBI → then approach the stock exchange]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[First approach the stock exchange → if unsatisfied, approach the broker → finally approach SEBI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The text describes the escalation: "any investor having a complaint can first approach the stock exchange for resolution of the complaint and if not satisfied, lodge a complaint with the SCORES. After exhausting these avenues, any complainant who is not satisfied, may opt for the arbitration mechanism of the exchanges." Additionally, the ODR framework states: "an aggrieved investor or client must take up his grievance by directly lodging a complaint against the market participant."
**The Trap:** SEBI is not the first port of call — the investor must first approach the broker/intermediary, then the exchange/SCORES, then ODR. Going to SEBI or courts first skips required steps.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The Market Participant can also initiate ODR after giving at least 15 days' notice to the investor/client. Both parties have ODR access, not just investors.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Grievance escalation: Broker → Exchange/SCORES → ODR Portal. Three steps, three institutions, in that order. SEBI SCORES is the second step, not the first.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
