<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Introduction to AML CFT and PF_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following functions is NOT performed by FIU-IND?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Receiving Cash Transaction Reports and Suspicious Transaction Reports]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sharing information with national intelligence and law enforcement agencies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Directly prosecuting money laundering offences in court]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Establishing and maintaining a national database of reported transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FIU-IND's functions include: Collection of information (receiving CTRs, STRs, NTRs, CBWTRs, IPRs), Analysis of information, Sharing information with intelligence/enforcement agencies, Acting as Central Repository, Coordination of financial intelligence networks, and Research and Analysis. FIU-IND does NOT directly prosecute offences -- prosecution is handled by the Directorate of Enforcement and the Special Courts under PMLA.

**The Trap:** FIU-IND is an intelligence-gathering and dissemination body, not a prosecuting agency. The Directorate of Enforcement investigates and prosecutes ML offences. FIU-IND's role is to analyze and share intelligence, not to take cases to court.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests FIU-IND's role vis-a-vis SEBI intermediaries. The IFSCA exam adds the context that IFSC entities must report to FIU-IND through FINGate 2.0 and that the Directorate of Enforcement handles prosecution.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Think of FIU-IND as the intelligence hub -- it collects, analyzes, and distributes financial intelligence. The enforcement leg (prosecution) is handled by the Directorate of Enforcement. Your obligation as an IFSC entity is to report to FIU-IND, not to investigate or prosecute.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>