<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is V-CIP (Video based Customer Identification Process) under the IFSCA Guidelines?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An alternate method of customer identification using seamless, secure, live, informed and consent-based audio-visual interaction with facial recognition]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A pre-recorded video submitted by the customer for identity verification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A video call with FIU-IND for high-risk customer verification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A surveillance system installed at the customer's premises for monitoring]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** V-CIP is an alternate method of customer identification with facial recognition and CDD, by an authorised official of the Regulated Entity, through seamless, secure, live, informed and consent-based audio-visual interaction to obtain identification information and ascertain veracity through independent verification while maintaining an audit trail.

**The Trap:** V-CIP must be LIVE (not pre-recorded), consent-based, and conducted by an AUTHORIZED official of the Regulated Entity. It is treated on par with face-to-face identification when it meets prescribed standards.

**Cross-Exam Context:** V-CIP is relevant in IFSCA-01 for onboarding Indian nationals in IFSC entities. Series XXIV covers SEBI's digital KYC provisions. IFSCA-01 adds the offshore client dimension.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** V-CIP can be used for: (a) new customer onboarding for individuals, proprietors, authorized signatories, and BOs; and (b) periodic KYC updation. It must be live, secure, consent-based, with audit trail.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>