<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[For life insurance and investment-related insurance, what additional CDD must be conducted on beneficiaries?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Obtain the full name including aliases of named beneficiaries, sufficient information for class beneficiaries, and determine if any beneficiary is a PEP]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No additional CDD is required for beneficiaries of insurance policies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only verify the beneficiary's identity at the time of policy purchase]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only screen beneficiaries against sanctions lists at the time of claim]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For life insurance, the RE must: (i) obtain full name including aliases of named natural person beneficiaries; (ii) for class beneficiaries (e.g., spouse, children), obtain sufficient information to identify them at payout time; and (iii) determine if beneficiaries or their BOs are PEPs — at latest at the time of payout.

**The Trap:** Beneficiary CDD is ongoing — not just at policy inception. PEP determination must happen at the LATEST at payout time. Higher risks identified should be escalated to Senior Management before payout.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Insurance-specific CDD is unique to IFSCA-01's coverage since IFSCA regulates insurance in IFSC. Series XXIV doesn't cover insurance-specific provisions as it focuses on securities markets.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Insurance beneficiary CDD: named persons = get full name/aliases; class beneficiaries (spouse/children) = get enough info to identify at payout; PEP check = at latest at payout. If PEP, escalate to Senior Management.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>