<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Scheduled Offences_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Part B of the Schedule to the PMLA 2002, which of the following offences is listed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Murder under the Bharatiya Nyaya Sanhita]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Terrorist financing under the UAPA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[False declaration, false documents, etc. under Section 132 of the Customs Act, 1962]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Kidnapping for ransom under BNS]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Part B specifically lists offences under the Customs Act, 1962. Section 132 (False declaration, false documents, etc.) is listed in Part B. Part B offences are subject to a monetary threshold -- they qualify as scheduled offences only if the total value involved is one crore rupees or more. Part A also lists Section 135 (Evasion of duty or prohibitions) of the Customs Act.

**The Trap:** Murder, terrorism financing, and kidnapping are Part A offences (no monetary threshold). Part B is specifically for Customs Act offences with a monetary threshold. The distinction matters because Part B offences only trigger PMLA if the value exceeds Rs. 1 crore.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the Part A vs Part B distinction. The IFSCA exam emphasizes Part B because customs-related offences (false declarations, duty evasion) are particularly relevant for IFSC entities involved in trade finance and cross-border transactions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Part B has a monetary gateway: only customs offences with value exceeding Rs. 1 crore qualify as scheduled offences. For IFSC entities handling trade finance, this threshold is important -- cross-border trade fraud below Rs. 1 crore under Part B would not trigger ML proceedings, though it could fall under Part C if it has cross-border implications.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>