<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under FATF Special Recommendation VI (SR VI), persons or legal entities that provide money or value transfer services, including informal or underground banking systems such as hawala, are required to be:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Licensed or registered by a competent authority]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Self-certified with a declaration filed to the central bank]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exempt from regulation if operating below a specified threshold]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only registered but not required to be licensed]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SR VI requires that persons or legal entities providing money/value transfer services (including informal hawala-type systems) must be "licensed or registered" by a competent authority. This brings informal remittance channels under the regulatory net to prevent their exploitation for money laundering and terrorist financing.

**The Trap:** "Self-certified" is too weak a standard and does not provide adequate regulatory oversight. "Exempt from regulation" is the opposite of what SR VI intends -- it seeks to bring these services INTO the regulatory framework. "Only registered" is partially correct but incomplete -- the standard requires either licensing OR registration, providing flexibility to countries.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Hawala and other informal value transfer systems are significant in the IFSC context because of cross-border fund flows. SR VI ensures these channels cannot operate outside the regulatory perimeter, which is especially relevant for GIFT City's international financial services.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SR VI = Alternative remittance providers (including hawala) must be LICENSED OR REGISTERED. Both options are acceptable; the key is bringing them under formal regulatory oversight.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>