<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Trade-Based Money Laundering (TBML) is a method of disguising proceeds of crime by moving value through trade transactions. Which of the following correctly identifies the three main methods of laundering money?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Through the financial system, through physical movement of banknotes, and through false documentation of traded goods]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Through the financial system, through cryptocurrency exchanges, and through false documentation of traded goods]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Through physical movement of banknotes, through shell companies, and through offshore accounts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Through the financial system, through physical movement of banknotes, and through real estate transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The three main methods of laundering money are: (1) through the financial system (wire transfers, bank transactions), (2) through physical movement of banknotes (cash smuggling, couriers), and (3) through false documentation of traded goods (over/under-invoicing, phantom shipments). TBML specifically exploits the third method -- trade transactions with falsified documentation.

**The Trap:** Cryptocurrency, shell companies, offshore accounts, and real estate are all vehicles used in money laundering, but they are not the three MAIN categories identified in the FATF framework. The three categories represent the fundamental channels through which value can be moved: electronically, physically, or through trade-based misrepresentation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** TBML is particularly relevant for IFSC entities involved in trade finance, banking, and insurance. Understanding how trade transactions can disguise illicit funds helps compliance officers in GIFT City detect suspicious patterns in international trade documentation.

**Key Takeaway:** Three main ML methods: (1) Financial system, (2) Physical cash movement, (3) False trade documentation (TBML). TBML is the third and often the hardest to detect.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>