<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Section 56 of the PMLA 2002 deals with which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Punishment for the offence of money laundering]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Attachment of property involved in money laundering]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Agreements with foreign countries for enforcement and exchange of information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Appointment of the Adjudicating Authority]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 56 deals with international cooperation. It allows the Central Government to enter into agreements with governments of foreign countries for enforcing PMLA provisions and exchanging information for prevention of ML offences or investigation of cases. The Central Government can also notify conditions, exceptions, or qualifications for applying this chapter to contracting states with reciprocal arrangements.

**The Trap:** Section 4 deals with punishment, Section 5 with attachment, Section 6 with Adjudicating Authority. Section 56 is specifically about international cooperation -- agreements with foreign countries. This is particularly relevant for IFSC entities given their cross-border operations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may not emphasize Section 56 as much. The IFSCA exam specifically tests it because international cooperation is fundamental to the IFSC ecosystem where cross-border financial flows are the core business.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Section 56 enables the legal framework for cross-border cooperation in ML investigations. For IFSC entities, this means foreign authorities can seek and receive information about transactions processed through the IFSC under bilateral agreements.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>