<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Scheduled Offences_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following offences from the Bharatiya Nyaya Sanhita (BNS) 2023 is listed as a scheduled offence under Part A of the PMLA Schedule?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minor traffic violations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Simple defamation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Murder (Section 103(1) of BNS)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Civil breach of contract]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Murder under Section 103(1) of BNS 2023 (corresponding to Section 302 of the erstwhile IPC) is a scheduled offence under Part A, Paragraph 1. Part A lists serious criminal offences including murder, attempt to murder, kidnapping for ransom, extortion, robbery, dacoity, cheating, counterfeiting, and criminal conspiracy, among others.

**The Trap:** Traffic violations, defamation, and civil breach of contract are not scheduled offences. Part A covers SERIOUS criminal offences that are likely to generate significant proceeds of crime. The BNS 2023 has replaced the IPC with new section numbers, so candidates must know the updated references.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may still reference IPC sections. The IFSCA exam uses both IPC and BNS references since the workbook includes a mapping table between old IPC sections and new BNS sections.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The BNS 2023 has replaced the IPC. For IFSC entity officers, the key takeaway is that murder, kidnapping, extortion, robbery, cheating, counterfeiting, and criminal conspiracy all generate proceeds that constitute ML if laundered. Know the categories even if you do not memorize every section number.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>