<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A suspicious transaction under the PMLA includes which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only transactions made in cash that give rise to suspicion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only completed transactions that appear to involve proceeds of crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Any transaction, whether or not made in cash, including attempted transactions that give rise to reasonable suspicion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only transactions exceeding Rs. 10 lakh that involve financing of terrorism]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A suspicious transaction is defined broadly as a transaction (including an attempted transaction), whether or not made in cash, which gives rise to reasonable suspicion that it may involve proceeds of crime, appears made in circumstances of unusual complexity, appears to have no economic rationale or bona fide purpose, or may involve financing of terrorism-related activities. The key elements are: includes attempted transactions, not limited to cash, and covers four types of suspicion.

**The Trap:** The definition explicitly includes ATTEMPTED transactions and is NOT limited to cash transactions. There is no monetary threshold for suspicious transactions -- even a small-value transaction can be suspicious. All four grounds of suspicion are independently sufficient.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the STR definition similarly. The IFSCA exam emphasizes that no cash transactions are permitted in IFSC, making electronic and non-cash STRs even more important for IFSC entities.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The four grounds of suspicion are: (1) may involve proceeds of crime, (2) unusual/unjustified complexity, (3) no economic rationale, (4) may involve terrorism financing. ANY one of these is sufficient to trigger an STR. The transaction need not be completed -- even attempts must be reported.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>