<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Scheduled Offences_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PMLA 2002, what is a mandatory pre-condition for initiating proceedings for the offence of money laundering?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Registration of an FIR under any cognizable offence]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Detection of a suspicious transaction by a reporting entity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Commission of a scheduled offence listed in Parts A, B, or C of the Schedule and generation of proceeds of crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Issuance of a show-cause notice by FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** To proceed against a person under PMLA, a scheduled offence as defined under Section 2(1)(y) and mentioned in Parts A, B, and C of the Schedule must have been committed AND proceeds of crime must have been generated. The scheduled offence is the foundation -- without a predicate offence generating proceeds of crime, there can be no money laundering offence.

**The Trap:** An FIR under any general offence is not sufficient -- it must be a SCHEDULED offence. Detection of STR by a reporting entity is an investigative lead, not a pre-condition for prosecution. FIU-IND does not issue show-cause notices for ML prosecution. The link between the scheduled offence and proceeds of crime is essential.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the predicate offence concept. The IFSCA exam specifically tests the scheduled offence requirement because IFSC entities must understand which underlying crimes can trigger ML proceedings involving their clients' transactions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As an IFSC entity officer, understand that money laundering is always a secondary offence -- it requires a primary (scheduled) offence. When conducting due diligence, assess whether your client's source of funds could be connected to any scheduled offence.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>