<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Introduction to AML CFT and PF_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a basic technique of trade-based money laundering?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Over-invoicing and under-invoicing of goods and services]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Multiple invoicing of goods and services]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Filing Cash Transaction Reports with FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Falsely described goods and services]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Trade-based money laundering (TBML) involves disguising criminal proceeds through trade transactions. The basic techniques include: over/under-invoicing, multiple invoicing, over/under-shipment, and falsely describing goods and services. Filing CTRs with FIU-IND is a compliance obligation under PMLA, not a money laundering technique -- it is precisely the opposite, a measure to PREVENT money laundering.

**The Trap:** The question includes three legitimate TBML techniques and one compliance action. Filing CTRs is what regulated entities must do to combat ML, not a laundering method. This tests whether you can distinguish between ML techniques and AML compliance measures.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may test TBML in the context of domestic securities fraud. The IFSCA exam emphasizes TBML because IFSC entities handle significant cross-border trade finance, making them potentially vulnerable to these techniques.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** TBML is particularly relevant for IFSC entities dealing with trade finance, letter of credit transactions, and cross-border payments. Any mismatch between invoice values and market prices should trigger enhanced scrutiny.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>