<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Introduction to AML CFT and PF_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a common tactic used during the integration stage of money laundering?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Breaking large cash amounts into smaller deposits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Converting digital currency from one blockchain to another]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Paying dividends to shareholders of companies controlled by criminals]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Using casino transactions to introduce cash into the system]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** During the integration stage, laundered money is reintroduced into the legitimate economy. Paying dividends from criminal-controlled companies is a classic integration tactic -- it gives the money a legitimate appearance as business income. Other integration tactics include fake employees on payroll, loans to directors that are never repaid, and purchasing luxury assets.

**The Trap:** Breaking cash into smaller deposits (smurfing) is placement. Chain-hopping between blockchains is layering. Casino transactions for introducing cash is placement. Only dividends from controlled companies represent the final integration of laundered funds into the legitimate economy.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV focuses on integration through securities markets (e.g., buying and selling stocks). The IFSCA exam may test integration through international business structures available in the IFSC.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Integration is the hardest stage to detect because the money now looks legitimate. In the IFSC, be alert to unusually high dividends, suspicious loan arrangements, or investments with no clear business rationale in entities operating within the centre.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>