<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Section 5 of the PMLA 2002, provisional attachment of property suspected to be proceeds of crime can be ordered for a maximum period of:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[90 days from the date of the order]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[120 days from the date of the order]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[180 days from the date of the order]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[365 days from the date of the order]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 5 allows the Director or any officer not below the rank of Deputy Director (authorized by the Director) to provisionally attach property suspected to be proceeds of crime for a period not exceeding 180 days from the date of the order. This is a provisional measure to prevent the property from being concealed, transferred, or dealt with in any manner that would frustrate confiscation proceedings.

**The Trap:** The number 180 days is specific and commonly tested. The attachment is PROVISIONAL -- it requires confirmation through adjudication. Note the rank requirement: only the Director or an officer not below Deputy Director rank can issue the order, and there must be recorded reasons to believe.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests Section 5 similarly. The IFSCA exam may combine it with knowledge of the Adjudicating Authority's role in confirming the attachment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** 180 days is the key number. During this period, the attached property cannot be transferred, converted, or disposed of. This is a powerful tool for authorities and a critical compliance risk for IFSC entities dealing with suspicious property.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>