<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PMLA, 'property' is defined to include:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only immovable property such as land and buildings]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only corporeal and tangible assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Property of every description, whether corporeal or incorporeal, movable or immovable, tangible or intangible, including deeds and instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only property located within India]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 2(v) defines 'property' expansively as any property or assets of every description, whether corporeal or incorporeal, movable or immovable, tangible or intangible, and includes deeds and instruments evidencing title to or interest in such property, wherever located. The Explanation further clarifies it includes property used in the commission of an offence under PMLA or any scheduled offences.

**The Trap:** The definition is deliberately broad to prevent criminals from escaping by hiding proceeds in unusual forms of property. It covers ALL types of property without geographic limitation ('wherever located'). It even includes documents that evidence ownership or interest.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the property definition similarly. The IFSCA exam places special emphasis on 'wherever located' because IFSC entities deal with cross-jurisdictional assets.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The broad definition means ANY form of asset can be attached or confiscated under PMLA -- bank accounts, securities, real estate, intellectual property, digital assets, etc. IFSC entities must be aware that property across all jurisdictions is covered.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>