<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA Related Cases_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the common lesson for IFSCA-regulated entities from all the PMLA cases discussed in Chapter 7?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Regulated entities must have robust AML systems, comply with all regulatory directions promptly, and maintain physical operational presence with qualified personnel]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only large entities face enforcement action; small entities are exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Penalties are only imposed for intentional fraud, not for compliance failures]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Registration with the regulator is sufficient compliance; no ongoing obligations exist]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The cases collectively teach that: (i) robust AML systems for detection and reporting are mandatory (Way2Wealth, Paytm); (ii) registration and compliance with regulatory directions is non-negotiable (Bybit, Prowess); (iii) physical presence and operational substance are required (NEO Asset Management); and (iv) penalties range from warnings to cancellation depending on severity.

**The Trap:** Penalties are imposed for compliance FAILURES, not just intentional fraud. Small entities (like Way2Wealth) also face enforcement. And registration is just the starting point — ongoing compliance is equally important.

**Cross-Exam Context:** These case studies provide practical context for all the theoretical AML/CFT concepts covered in IFSCA-01 Chapters 5 and 6. They also connect to Series XXIV's domestic enforcement examples.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Three key lessons for IFSC entities: (1) Build robust AML systems — don't wait for FIU-IND to find gaps; (2) Respond to regulatory communications immediately; (3) Maintain real operational presence at IFSC. Graduated enforcement: warning -> penalty -> cancellation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>