<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is a 'mutual evaluation' in the context of FATF?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A peer review process where a country's AML/CFT framework is assessed by other FATF members to determine the effectiveness of its implementation of FATF Recommendations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A bilateral agreement between two countries to share intelligence on specific money laundering cases]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An annual financial audit of FATF's own organizational budget and expenditure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A self-assessment questionnaire filled by each country without external review]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mutual evaluations are FATF's core assessment mechanism — they involve in-depth peer review of a country's AML/CFT measures to determine how well it has implemented the FATF Recommendations and how effective its system is. The evaluation team consists of experts from other member jurisdictions and the process can involve stakeholder outreach and public consultations.
**The Trap:** Option D describes a self-assessment rather than a mutual evaluation. While countries do complete questionnaires, the mutual evaluation involves external assessors conducting an independent review.
**Cross-Exam Context:** FATF mutual evaluations and their outcomes are tested in NISM IFSCA-01 as they drive national AML/CFT policy.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** FATF mutual evaluation findings directly shape regulatory requirements — a poor evaluation can result in a country being grey-listed, which increases compliance burden for financial institutions dealing with that jurisdiction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>