<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 8 of the PML Rules, the Suspicious Transaction Report (STR) must be furnished to the Director, FIU-IND within what time frame?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 3 working days on being satisfied that the transaction is suspicious]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not later than 7 working days on being satisfied that the transaction is suspicious]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 15 days of the month following the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 30 calendar days of detecting the suspicious activity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 8(2) requires the Principal Officer to furnish STR information promptly in writing or by fax or by electronic mail to the Director not later than seven working days on being satisfied that the transaction is suspicious. This is different from CTRs and CBWTRs which are furnished monthly by the 15th of the succeeding month.

**The Trap:** The 15-day-of-succeeding-month deadline applies to CTRs, CBWTRs, and NPO transactions (monthly reporting). The quarterly 15-day deadline applies to IPRs. Only STRs have the 7-working-day deadline. Also note it is 7 WORKING days, not calendar days.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the same 7-working-day STR deadline. The IFSCA exam emphasizes that each day of delay constitutes a separate violation under Rule 8(4).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The STR timeline is urgent: 7 working days from the date of satisfaction that the transaction is suspicious. Unlike other reports that follow a monthly schedule, STRs are event-driven and must be filed promptly. Each day of delay is a separate violation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>