<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Section 3 of the PMLA 2002, which of the following activities connected with proceeds of crime constitutes the offence of money laundering?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only concealment and possession of proceeds of crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only projecting proceeds of crime as untainted property]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only acquisition and use of proceeds of crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Concealment, possession, acquisition, use, projecting as untainted property, or claiming as untainted property]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 3 of PMLA defines money laundering broadly. A person is guilty if they directly or indirectly attempt to indulge or knowingly assist in any process connected with proceeds of crime including: (a) concealment, (b) possession, (c) acquisition, (d) use, (e) projecting as untainted property, or (f) claiming as untainted property. ALL six activities independently constitute the offence.

**The Trap:** Options A, B, and C each list only a subset of the activities. The correct answer includes all six. The exam tests whether you know the full scope of what constitutes money laundering under Section 3. Also note that the process is a continuing activity until the person stops enjoying the proceeds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests Section 3 in the context of securities intermediaries. The IFSCA exam tests it with emphasis on cross-border implications relevant to IFSC entities.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Section 3 is extremely broad -- even KNOWINGLY ASSISTING someone involved in any of these six activities makes you guilty. As an IFSC entity officer, this means facilitating suspicious transactions can make the entity liable.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>