<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 9 of the PML Rules, if a reporting entity relies on a third party for client due diligence, which condition must be met?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The third party can be based in any country regardless of risk level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The reporting entity is relieved of all CDD responsibility once it relies on the third party]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The reporting entity remains ultimately responsible for CDD and the third party must not be based in a high-risk country]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Third party reliance is not permitted under any circumstances]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 9(2) allows third-party reliance subject to conditions: (a) the reporting entity immediately obtains CDD information from the third party, (b) copies of identification data will be available on request, (c) the third party is regulated and has CDD measures in place, (d) the third party is NOT based in a high-risk country, and (e) the reporting entity remains ultimately responsible for CDD. Third-party reliance does NOT transfer the ultimate responsibility.

**The Trap:** The reporting entity is ALWAYS ultimately responsible -- third-party reliance does not transfer the obligation. The third party must not be in a high-risk jurisdiction. This is not a blank permission to outsource CDD without accountability.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests third-party reliance conditions. The IFSCA exam additionally covers the IFSCA Guidelines Chapter VI on Third Party Reliance with specific conditions for IFSC entities.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Third-party reliance is a convenience, not an escape from responsibility. Your entity remains liable for CDD quality. Always verify the third party's regulatory status and ensure they are not in a FATF high-risk jurisdiction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>