<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Scheduled Offences_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The offence of 'punishment for fraud' under Section 447 of the Companies Act, 2013 is categorized under which Part of the PMLA Schedule?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Part A]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Part B]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Part C]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is not listed as a scheduled offence under PMLA]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 447 of the Companies Act, 2013 (Punishment for fraud) is listed under Part A of the PMLA Schedule. This means corporate fraud generating proceeds of crime can trigger money laundering proceedings with no monetary threshold. This is significant because corporate fraud is one of the most common sources of laundered money flowing through financial systems.

**The Trap:** Part B is limited to Customs Act offences. Part C covers cross-border implications of Part A offences. Section 447 is in Part A with no monetary threshold. Candidates might think corporate fraud is a Part B offence because it involves monetary values, but it is listed under Part A.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV specifically tests Companies Act Section 447 as a scheduled offence because securities market fraud often involves corporate fraud. The IFSCA exam tests it because companies operating in IFSC can be subject to fraud proceedings under the Companies Act.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Corporate fraud under Section 447 is a Part A offence with NO monetary threshold. This means even small-scale corporate fraud generating proceeds of crime can trigger ML proceedings. IFSC entities must be vigilant about red flags indicating corporate fraud in client entities.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>