<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 3A, every reporting entity that is part of a group shall implement group-wide programmes against money laundering and terror financing. These programmes must include:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only information sharing across group entities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only client due diligence policies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Group-wide policies for information sharing, CDD, and risk management with safeguards against tipping-off]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only risk management measures for the Indian operations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 3A requires every reporting entity that is part of a group to implement group-wide programmes including: group-wide policies for sharing information required for CDD purposes, money laundering and terror finance risk management, and adequate safeguards on the confidentiality and use of information exchanged, including safeguards to prevent tipping-off. These must be implemented across the group, not just at the entity level.

**The Trap:** The answer must include ALL three elements: information sharing, CDD, AND risk management with confidentiality safeguards. Individual elements alone are incomplete. The tipping-off prevention requirement is particularly important.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests group-wide compliance for SEBI intermediaries. The IFSCA exam emphasizes this because many IFSC entities are subsidiaries or branches of larger financial groups.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Group-wide AML programmes are not optional -- they are a Rule 3A requirement. For IFSC entities that are part of larger groups, ensure your group's AML policies are consistent and include adequate safeguards against tipping-off when sharing information.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>