<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA AML CFT KYC Guidelines_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What does Clause 8.4 of the IFSCA (AML, CFT and KYC) Guidelines mandate regarding certification?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Officers and employees of Regulated Entities dealing with AML/CFT matters must obtain relevant NISM-IFSCA certification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Principal Officer needs to be certified by NISM]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Certification is optional and recommended but not mandatory]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Governing Body members need AML/CFT certification]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Clause 8.4 of the IFSCA (AML, CFT and KYC) Guidelines mandates that officers and employees of Regulated Entities who deal with AML/CFT matters must obtain the relevant NISM-IFSCA certification. This is the very certification (NISM-IFSCA-01) that this exam is for. Note: This requirement comes from the IFSCA Guidelines source document; the workbook references this mandate indirectly through its discussion of training and certification obligations.

**The Trap:** The certification is MANDATORY, not optional. It applies to all relevant officers and employees dealing with AML/CFT, not just the Principal Officer.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is unique to IFSCA-01 — the certification requirement is self-referential. Series XXIV has its own certification mandate under SEBI regulations. Understanding WHY you are taking this exam is itself an exam-worthy topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** You are taking the NISM-IFSCA-01 exam precisely because of Clause 8.4. This certification is a regulatory requirement for anyone dealing with AML/CFT matters in IFSC-regulated entities.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>