<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PML Rules, for the purpose of determining beneficial ownership of a company, 'controlling ownership interest' means ownership of more than what percentage of shares or capital or profits?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[10 percent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[15 percent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[25 percent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[51 percent]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the IFSCA AML, CFT and KYC Guidelines (referenced in Rule 9(3)(a)), for a company, the beneficial owner is the natural person(s) having a 'controlling ownership interest' which means ownership of or entitlement to more than 10% of shares or capital or profits. This is the threshold for companies and partnership firms. For unincorporated associations, the threshold is 15%.

**The Trap:** The 10% threshold applies to companies and partnership firms. The 15% threshold applies to unincorporated associations/bodies of individuals. Candidates must not confuse these two thresholds. The 25% threshold is used by some other jurisdictions but not in the IFSCA context.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV uses 10% as the threshold under SEBI's AML guidelines. The IFSCA exam uses the same 10% for companies/partnerships but 15% for unincorporated associations, following the IFSCA Guidelines.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Beneficial ownership thresholds: Companies and partnerships = more than 10%. Unincorporated associations = more than 15%. Trusts = identify author, trustee, beneficiaries with 10%+ interest. If no natural person is identified, the senior managing official is the beneficial owner.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>