<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 3 of the PML (Maintenance of Records) Rules, 2005, reporting entities are required to maintain records of which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Records of all cash transactions exceeding Rs. 10 lakh or its equivalent in any foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Records only of transactions reported as suspicious to FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Records of all transactions regardless of amount or nature]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Records only of cross-border wire transfers exceeding Rs. 5 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 3 of the PML (Maintenance of Records) Rules, 2005 requires every reporting entity to maintain records of all cash transactions of the value of more than Rs. 10 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency. In the IFSC context, since transactions are predominantly in foreign currency, the equivalent threshold in foreign currency applies. This threshold-based record-keeping is a cornerstone of AML compliance.

**The Trap:** Recording only suspicious transactions is insufficient — the Rules mandate recording ALL cash transactions above the threshold, whether suspicious or not. Recording all transactions regardless of amount is impractical and not what the Rules require. The Rs. 5 lakh threshold for wire transfers is a fabricated distractor.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The IFSCA AML/CFT Guidelines build upon these PML Rules. In IFSC, where transactions are in foreign currency, understanding the equivalent threshold is critical. This is frequently tested alongside the obligation to report Cash Transaction Reports (CTRs) to FIU-IND.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The Rs. 10 lakh threshold applies to cash transactions specifically. Additionally, reporting entities must also maintain records of all series of integrally connected cash transactions within a month that individually fall below Rs. 10 lakh but aggregate above it — a concept designed to catch structuring or smurfing.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
