<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the role of the 'Designated Director' in the context of PMLA compliance?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A person designated by the reporting entity to ensure overall compliance with PMLA obligations, including internal policies and procedures for AML/CFT]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A government official appointed by the Central Government to oversee all PMLA investigations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The CEO of a reporting entity who is personally liable for all financial transactions processed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An external auditor hired to conduct annual reviews of a reporting entity's financial statements]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Designated Director is a person designated by the reporting entity to ensure overall compliance with PMLA obligations. This role is in addition to the Principal Officer and focuses on ensuring the entity has effective internal policies, procedures, and controls for AML/CFT compliance.
**The Trap:** Option A confuses the Designated Director (internal to the reporting entity) with the Director of FIU-IND or Enforcement Directorate (government officials). The Designated Director is appointed within the organization.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Both Principal Officer and Designated Director roles are tested in NISM IFSCA-01 — candidates must understand the distinction between these two compliance roles.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Both the Principal Officer and Designated Director must be registered with FIU-IND through the FINGate 2.0 Portal — ensure your organization has both roles properly filled and registered.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>