<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA AML CFT KYC Guidelines_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the IFSCA Guidelines, what must a Regulated Entity do if records are kept outside the IFSC?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Take reasonable steps to ensure records comply with Guidelines, are easily accessible, and immediately available for inspection by the Authority]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Records cannot be kept outside the IFSC under any circumstances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only inform IFSCA of the location of records within 30 days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Appoint a local custodian in the country where records are stored]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When records are kept outside the IFSC, the Regulated Entity must: (a) take reasonable steps to ensure records are kept consistent with Guidelines; (b) ensure records are easily accessible; and (c) ensure records are immediately available for inspection by the Authority. They must also check for secrecy/data protection laws that might restrict access.

**The Trap:** Records CAN be kept outside IFSC — but accessibility and compliance cannot be compromised. If secrecy laws in the foreign jurisdiction restrict access, certified copies must be obtained and kept in a jurisdiction that allows access.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is unique to IFSCA-01 given the international nature of IFSC operations. Series XXIV doesn't address cross-border record storage since it deals with domestic intermediaries.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If there's a data protection law blocking access in the country where records are stored, get certified copies and keep them somewhere accessible. IFSCA must always be able to inspect records immediately.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>