<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under FATF Special Recommendation III (SR III), countries are required to freeze and confiscate terrorist assets in accordance with UN Security Council resolutions. What is the prescribed timeline for freezing such assets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Without delay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 48 hours of identification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 7 working days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only after obtaining a court order]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SR III mandates that countries must freeze and confiscate terrorist assets "without delay" in accordance with UN Security Council resolutions. The phrase "without delay" is deliberate -- it means immediate action is required to prevent terrorists from moving or dissipating funds before they can be seized.

**The Trap:** "Within 48 hours" or "within 7 working days" sound reasonable but introduce unacceptable delays that could allow terrorists to move funds. "After court order" would create procedural delays inconsistent with the urgency of counter-terrorism. The key principle is that administrative freezing must happen instantly, with judicial review available afterward.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This "without delay" standard is critical in IFSCA operations because entities in IFSC must comply with UN Security Council sanctions lists and freeze designated assets immediately upon listing, without waiting for domestic court orders.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SR III = Freeze terrorist assets WITHOUT DELAY. No grace period, no waiting for court orders. Freeze first, provide due process afterward.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>