<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Introduction to AML CFT and PF_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Financial Intelligence Unit - India (FIU-IND) reports directly to which body?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Reserve Bank of India (RBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The Economic Intelligence Council (EIC) headed by the Finance Minister]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The International Financial Services Centres Authority (IFSCA)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FIU-IND was established on November 18, 2004 as the central national agency for receiving, processing, analyzing, and disseminating information relating to suspected financial transactions. It is an independent body reporting directly to the Economic Intelligence Council (EIC), which is headed by the Finance Minister. This independence ensures FIU-IND can function without interference from any single regulator.

**The Trap:** Candidates may assume FIU-IND reports to RBI (being a financial body) or SEBI (being securities-related). FIU-IND is deliberately kept independent of all sectoral regulators to maintain its effectiveness as a central intelligence-gathering body.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests FIU-IND's role in the context of SEBI-regulated entities. The IFSCA exam tests FIU-IND in the broader context of IFSC entities that must mandatorily register on the FINGate 2.0 Portal.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** FIU-IND's independence is key to its effectiveness. As an IFSC entity officer, know that your STRs and CTRs go to FIU-IND (not to IFSCA or SEBI), and FIU-IND then disseminates actionable intelligence to relevant enforcement agencies.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>