<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the FATF IX Special Recommendations, SR I requires each country to ratify and implement a specific UN convention. Which convention is this?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The 1999 UN International Convention for the Suppression of the Financing of Terrorism]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The 1988 Vienna Convention against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The 2000 Palermo Convention against Transnational Organized Crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The 2005 Warsaw Convention on Laundering, Search, Seizure and Confiscation of Proceeds from Crime]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SR I of the IX Special Recommendations specifically requires each country to ratify and implement the 1999 UN International Convention for the Suppression of the Financing of Terrorism. This convention is the foundational legal instrument dedicated to criminalizing terrorist financing at the international level.

**The Trap:** The 1988 Vienna Convention deals with drug trafficking (not terrorist financing). The 2000 Palermo Convention focuses on transnational organized crime broadly. The 2005 Warsaw Convention deals with proceeds of crime. While all are important AML instruments, only the 1999 Convention specifically targets the financing of terrorism as required by SR I.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The IX Special Recommendations were developed post-9/11 to specifically address terrorist financing gaps. SR I anchors the entire framework by requiring states to adopt the core UN legal instrument on terrorist financing.

**Key Takeaway:** SR I = 1999 Convention on Suppression of Financing of Terrorism. Remember the year 1999 and the specific focus on "financing of terrorism" to distinguish it from other UN conventions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>