<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Why does FATF recommend that countries have measures to detect the physical cross-border transportation of currency and bearer negotiable instruments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Because physical movement of cash and bearer instruments is one of the primary methods criminals use to move illicit value across borders, bypassing the formal financial system]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because FATF wants to eliminate all physical cash from the global economy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because bearer instruments are illegal in all FATF member countries]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because cross-border cash transportation is only used by terrorist organizations and never by legitimate travelers]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FATF Special Recommendation IX addresses cash couriers because physical transportation of currency and bearer negotiable instruments is one of the three main methods used to move criminal value across borders. Detection measures (like declaration systems at borders) help identify suspicious movements that may indicate ML/TF without using the formal financial system.
**The Trap:** Option A is extreme — FATF does not seek to eliminate cash, but to ensure detection mechanisms exist for suspicious cross-border cash movements. Legitimate travelers routinely carry cash across borders.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Cash courier detection aligns with FATF SR IX and is tested in NISM IFSCA-01 Chapter 8.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients conduct large cash-based transactions or discuss cross-border cash movements, treat these as potential red flags — they may indicate attempts to bypass the formal financial system's AML controls.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>