<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA Related Cases_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What common theme emerges from the PMLA enforcement cases studied in the NISM IFSCA-01 curriculum?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Reporting entities face significant penalties for failing to implement effective AML/CFT systems including KYC verification, ongoing due diligence, record maintenance, and suspicious transaction reporting]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMLA enforcement actions are limited to warnings and no monetary penalties are ever imposed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only large multinational banks are subject to PMLA enforcement, while smaller entities are exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMLA enforcement cases are purely theoretical and have never resulted in actual penalties]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Across all cases discussed — Bybit (Rs 9.27 crore penalty), Paytm (multiple charges), Prowess (authorization cancelled), Way2Wealth (compliance deficiencies) — the common theme is that reporting entities face real, significant consequences for failing to implement effective AML/CFT systems covering KYC, ongoing CDD, record-keeping, and STR filing.
**The Trap:** Option A is flatly incorrect — substantial monetary penalties and even cancellation of authorizations have been imposed. Option B wrongly suggests size-based exemption — entities of all sizes face enforcement.
**Cross-Exam Context:** These case studies are tested in NISM IFSCA-01 to reinforce that AML compliance is not optional and has real consequences.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Invest proactively in robust AML/CFT infrastructure — the cost of compliance is always lower than the cost of enforcement actions, reputational damage, and business disruption.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>