<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 3 of the PML Rules, every reporting entity must maintain records of all cash transactions exceeding what value?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 5 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 15 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 3(A) requires every reporting entity to maintain records of all cash transactions of the value of more than ten lakh rupees or its equivalent in foreign currency. This is the Cash Transaction Report (CTR) threshold. Additionally, series of connected cash transactions individually below Rs. 10 lakh but with a monthly aggregate exceeding Rs. 10 lakh must also be recorded.

**The Trap:** Rs. 50 lakh is the threshold for immovable property transactions (Rule 3(F)), not cash transactions. Rs. 5 lakh is the threshold for cross-border wire transfers (Rule 3(E)). Candidates often confuse these three different thresholds: Rs. 10 lakh (cash), Rs. 5 lakh (cross-border wire), Rs. 50 lakh (immovable property).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the Rs. 10 lakh CTR threshold. The IFSCA exam adds the important note that no cash transactions are permitted in the IFSC domain, but the threshold knowledge is still tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remember the three thresholds: Rs. 10 lakh (cash/CTR), Rs. 5 lakh (cross-border wire transfers/CBWTR), Rs. 50 lakh (immovable property/IPR). For IFSC entities, the CBWTR threshold is most practically relevant since cash transactions are not permitted.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>