<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 9 of the PML Rules, what is the beneficial ownership threshold for an unincorporated association or body of individuals?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than 10 percent of property, capital, or profits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[More than 15 percent of property, capital, or profits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than 20 percent of property, capital, or profits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than 25 percent of property, capital, or profits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 9(3)(c) states that for an unincorporated association or body of individuals, the beneficial owner is the natural person(s) having ownership of or entitlement to more than 15% of the property, capital, or profits. This is higher than the 10% threshold applicable to companies and partnership firms.

**The Trap:** The threshold differs by entity type: Companies and partnerships = more than 10%; Unincorporated associations = more than 15%. For trusts, there is no percentage threshold -- you must identify the author, trustee, beneficiaries with 10%+ interest, and any person with ultimate effective control.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV uses 25% as the threshold under SEBI guidelines (different from IFSCA). The IFSCA exam follows the PMLA/IFSCA Guidelines which use 10% (companies/partnerships) and 15% (unincorporated associations) -- lower thresholds reflecting stricter IFSC standards.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Lower thresholds mean more beneficial owners to identify. For companies: anyone with more than 10%. For unincorporated bodies: anyone with more than 15%. If no one is identified, default to the senior managing official. This is stricter than many other jurisdictions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>