<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 8(4) of the PML Rules, delay in reporting a transaction or rectifying a mis-reported transaction constitutes:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A single violation regardless of the duration of delay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A separate violation for each day of delay beyond the specified time limit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A violation only if the delay exceeds 30 days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No violation if the delay is explained with reasonable cause]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 8(4) explicitly states that for the purpose of this rule, delay of each day in not reporting a transaction or delay of each day in rectifying a mis-reported transaction beyond the time limit specified in this rule shall constitute a separate violation. This strict provision means that a 10-day delay counts as 10 separate violations, not one.

**The Trap:** There is no grace period and no 'reasonable cause' defense mentioned in the rule. Each day is a separate violation automatically. This is designed to ensure prompt and accurate reporting and makes delayed or incorrect reporting very costly in terms of penalties.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the same penalty provision. The IFSCA exam emphasizes this to underscore the importance of timely and accurate reporting for IFSC entities.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is one of the strictest provisions in the PML Rules. A 30-day delay means 30 separate violations, each potentially attracting a separate penalty. Ensure your entity has robust systems for timely reporting and quality checks for accuracy of reported data.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>