<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the IFSCA Guidelines, can a Regulated Entity establish a business relationship before completing CDD verification?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, if deferral is essential for normal business conduct, ML/TF risk is low, adequate safeguards exist, and verification is completed within 30 business days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, CDD verification must always be completed before any business relationship is established]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, without any conditions as long as the customer signs an undertaking]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only for government entities and listed companies]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A RE may establish business relationship before completing verification subject to: (i) deferral is essential to not interrupt normal business; (ii) low ML/TF risk that can be managed; (iii) adequate safeguards for bank accounts (no transactions before verification); and (iv) verification completed within 30 business days.

**The Trap:** This is a conditional exception, not a blanket permission. All four conditions must be met. For bank accounts, the account cannot be used for transactions until verification is complete.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of establishing relationship before full verification exists in both IFSCA-01 and FATF standards. It recognizes the practical need to onboard clients efficiently while maintaining AML controls.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** 30 days to complete verification, 120 days to terminate if not completed. During the interim, manage risk through safeguards. This flexibility is important for IFSC's competitive positioning.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>