<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Who is a Politically Exposed Person (PEP) and why do they require enhanced due diligence?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A PEP is an individual who holds or has held a prominent public function; they require EDD because their position makes them more susceptible to corruption and the potential misuse of the financial system for laundering corrupt proceeds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A PEP is any person who has been convicted of a financial crime; they require EDD because they are known offenders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A PEP is a person who holds more than five bank accounts; they require EDD because multiple accounts indicate suspicious activity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A PEP is any person who has made political donations; they require EDD because political donations may be linked to money laundering]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A PEP is an individual entrusted with a prominent public function (e.g., heads of state, senior politicians, senior government officials, judicial officials, military officers). Their position of influence makes them more susceptible to involvement in corruption, and EDD is required to detect potential misuse of the financial system to launder corruptly obtained wealth.
**The Trap:** Option A confuses PEPs with convicted criminals. A PEP designation is based on their position, not criminal history — many PEPs are entirely legitimate, but the risk of corruption requires enhanced scrutiny.
**Cross-Exam Context:** PEP identification and EDD requirements are heavily tested in NISM IFSCA-01 and other AML-related certifications.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PEP status extends to family members and close associates — your screening should cover not just the direct customer but also related persons who may be conduits for corrupt funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>