<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Introduction to AML CFT and PF_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Vienna Convention of 1988 is significant in the context of AML because it:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Established the Financial Action Task Force]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Created an obligation for signatory states to criminalize laundering of money from drug trafficking]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Set up the Financial Intelligence Unit framework globally]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Introduced the concept of Know Your Customer for banks]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Vienna Convention, adopted in December 1988, laid the groundwork for combating money laundering by creating an obligation for signatory states to criminalize the laundering of money from drug trafficking. It promoted international cooperation in investigations and made extradition applicable between signatory states for money laundering offences. It also established the principle that domestic bank secrecy should not interfere with international criminal investigations.

**The Trap:** FATF was established in 1989 (not by the Vienna Convention). FIU frameworks came later. KYC norms were developed separately by regulators. The Vienna Convention specifically targeted drug trafficking proceeds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may not deeply test the Vienna Convention. The IFSCA exam includes it because IFSC entities operate in an international context where treaties and conventions form the basis of cross-border cooperation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The Vienna Convention established that bank secrecy cannot shield money launderers from international investigations -- a principle directly relevant to IFSC entities that handle cross-border financial flows.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>