<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What additional measures must a Regulated Entity undertake when a customer is determined to be a Politically Exposed Person (PEP)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All of the above]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Collect information about source of wealth and income of family members and close relatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtain Senior Management approval before opening an account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Increase the degree and nature of ongoing monitoring of the business relationship]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For PEPs, additional measures include: (i) collecting adequate information about source of wealth and income of family members, BOs, and close relatives; (ii) verifying identity before acceptance; (iii) obtaining Senior Management approval before opening account; (iv) if existing customer becomes PEP, obtaining Senior Management approval to continue; (v) increasing ongoing monitoring; and (vi) additional CDD before payouts under life insurance.

**The Trap:** PEP measures go beyond the customer themselves — they extend to family members, close associates, and beneficial owners. The monitoring must be INCREASED, not just standard.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PEP identification and management appears in IFSCA-01, Series XXIV, and FATF Recommendation 12. In IFSCA-01, the international PEP dimension is critical since IFSC deals with foreign public officials.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PEP measures cover: source of wealth, Senior Management approval, increased monitoring. Also applies to International Organisation PEPs and former PEPs (risk-based approach for stepped-down PEPs).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>