<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA AML CFT KYC Guidelines_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the IFSCA Guidelines, what is a 'Shell Financial Institution' in the context of correspondent banking?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A financial institution that has no physical presence in the country where it is incorporated and licensed, and is not affiliated with a regulated financial group]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A newly incorporated financial institution with less than one year of operations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A financial institution that only deals with shell companies as clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A subsidiary of a regulated bank operating under a different trade name]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Shell Financial Institution is one that has no physical presence in the jurisdiction where it is incorporated and licensed and is unaffiliated to a regulated financial group. The IFSCA Guidelines explicitly prohibit correspondent relationships with Shell Financial Institutions.

**The Trap:** A shell financial institution is about lack of physical presence and lack of affiliation to a regulated group — not about the age of the entity or its client base.

**Cross-Exam Context:** FATF Recommendation 13 on correspondent banking covers shell bank prohibition. Series XXIV covers domestic correspondent banking; IFSCA-01 extends this to the critical international correspondent banking context of IFSC.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Correspondent banking relationships must NEVER be established with shell financial institutions. Also ensure that correspondent banks don't permit their accounts to be used by shell financial institutions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>