<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Scheduled Offences_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Part C of the Schedule to the PMLA 2002 covers which type of offences?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only offences committed by foreign nationals in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only offences committed within the territory of India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Offences with cross-border implications as specified in Part A and offences against property under Chapter XVII of the IPC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only offences related to narcotics and psychotropic substances]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Part C covers offences with cross-border implications, specifically: (1) offences specified in Part A that have cross-border dimensions, (3) offences against property under Chapter XVII of the IPC, and (4) wilful attempt to evade tax/penalty/interest under Section 51 of the Black Money Act, 2015. No monetary threshold applies to Part C offences.

**The Trap:** Part C is not limited to foreign nationals or to offences committed only in India. It covers cross-border implications in both directions -- offences committed abroad with proceeds coming to India, AND offences committed in India with proceeds going abroad. The inclusion of Black Money Act offences is specific to Part C.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may not deeply focus on Part C. The IFSCA exam places significant emphasis on Part C because cross-border transactions are the core business of IFSC entities, making them potentially involved in offences with cross-border implications.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Part C is the most relevant Part for IFSC entities. Cross-border implications mean that proceeds of crime moving through the IFSC from any Part A offence can trigger ML proceedings under Part C. Enhanced due diligence on cross-border flows is essential.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>