<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[According to FATF Special Recommendation VIII (SR VIII), non-profit organisations (NPOs) are considered "particularly vulnerable" to terrorist financing abuse. Which of the following vulnerabilities must countries specifically address through their laws and regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All of: (i) terrorist organisations posing as legitimate NPOs, (ii) exploitation of legitimate NPOs as conduits for TF, and (iii) concealment of clandestine diversion of funds to terrorist organisations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only terrorist organisations posing as legitimate NPOs and exploitation of legitimate NPOs as conduits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only concealment of clandestine diversion of funds to terrorist organisations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only exploitation of legitimate NPOs as conduits for terrorist financing and tax evasion through NPOs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SR VIII identifies three specific vulnerabilities of NPOs to terrorist financing abuse that countries must address: (i) terrorist organisations posing as legitimate entities, (ii) exploitation of legitimate entities as conduits for TF, and (iii) concealment of clandestine diversion of funds intended for legitimate purposes to terrorist organisations. All three must be addressed comprehensively.

**The Trap:** Partial lists are tempting because each individual vulnerability sounds complete on its own. However, the FATF standard requires countries to address ALL THREE vulnerabilities. Tax evasion is not part of SR VIII -- it specifically deals with terrorist financing abuse, not tax offences.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In the IFSC context, entities dealing with NPO clients must apply enhanced scrutiny. Understanding the full scope of NPO vulnerabilities helps compliance officers identify red flags across all three categories, not just the most obvious one.

**Key Takeaway:** SR VIII = NPOs are "particularly vulnerable" to TF. Three vulnerabilities: (1) posing as legitimate, (2) conduit exploitation, (3) clandestine fund diversion. All three must be addressed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>