<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[How does IFSCA's AML/CFT framework differ from other Indian regulators like RBI, SEBI, and IRDAI?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[IFSCA guidelines are tailored to the unique global nature of IFSC operations and align closely with FATF standards, while other regulators focus on domestic operations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IFSCA guidelines are less stringent than those of RBI and SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IFSCA does not require KYC procedures as it deals only with institutional clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IFSCA follows exactly the same guidelines as SEBI without any modifications]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Key differences: IFSCA is a single-point regulator for diverse financial activities in IFSC (unlike sector-specific regulators); IFSCA guidelines align closely with FATF (global standard-setter); IFSC entities deal with international clients requiring global KYC/CDD/sanctions procedures; IFSCA aims for world-class regulatory environment with ease of doing business.

**The Trap:** IFSCA is NOT less stringent — it's differently focused. Its guidelines are globally aligned (FATF-based) rather than domestically aligned. The KYC/CDD procedures may be streamlined but are certainly not absent.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This comparison is unique to IFSCA-01 and won't appear in Series XXIV. Understanding why IFSCA has a separate AML/CFT framework is fundamental to this certification.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** IFSCA = single regulator, FATF-aligned, international clients, global KYC. Other regulators = sector-specific, Indian-law aligned, domestic clients, India-focused KYC. This distinction defines the IFSCA-01 exam.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>