<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PML Rules, the fact of maintenance of records and furnishing of information to the Director, FIU-IND must be:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Kept confidential by the reporting entity, its directors, officers, and all employees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Disclosed to the client for transparency purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Published in the annual report of the reporting entity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Shared with all regulatory authorities simultaneously]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 8(6) states that every reporting entity, its Directors, officers, and all employees shall ensure that the fact of maintenance of records and furnishing of information to the Director is kept confidential. This anti-tipping-off provision prevents subjects of suspicious activity reports from learning about the filing and potentially destroying evidence or fleeing.

**The Trap:** Confidentiality applies to everyone in the entity -- directors, officers, and ALL employees. There is a limited exception under Rule 3A for group-wide information sharing, but even that requires safeguards to prevent tipping-off. Never disclose to a client that an STR has been filed.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the same confidentiality requirement. The IFSCA exam additionally tests that group-wide sharing (Rule 3A) is permitted but must include tipping-off safeguards.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Tipping-off is a serious compliance breach. If a client asks whether a report has been filed about them, you must not confirm or deny it. Train all staff, not just compliance officers, on this requirement because Rule 8(6) applies to ALL employees.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>