<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Section 12 of the PMLA 2002, records of transactions between a client and the reporting entity must be maintained for a period of:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[3 years from the date of the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[5 years from the date of the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[7 years from the date of the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[10 years from the date of the transaction]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 12(3) of PMLA states that records of transactions shall be maintained for 5 years from the date of transaction. Separately, under Section 12(4), records of client identity documents and account files shall be maintained for 5 years after the business relationship has ended or the account has been closed, whichever is later. Both retention periods are 5 years but measured from different starting points.

**The Trap:** Both types of records have a 5-year retention period, but the measurement point differs: transaction records = 5 years from date of transaction; identity records = 5 years from end of relationship or account closure. Candidates often confuse these two starting points.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the same 5-year retention period for SEBI intermediaries. The IFSCA exam may test both subsections (12(3) and 12(4)) to check if you understand the different measurement points.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The universal rule is 5 years, but count from the right starting point. Transaction records: 5 years from transaction date. Client identity records: 5 years from end of relationship or account closure, whichever is LATER.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>