<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA FATF Recommendations_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the 'risk-based approach' as recommended by FATF, and why is it considered effective?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It requires countries and institutions to assess ML/TF risks and allocate resources proportionately, focusing enhanced measures on higher-risk areas while allowing simplified measures for lower-risk areas]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It requires all customers to undergo the same level of due diligence regardless of their risk profile]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It means applying the strictest possible measures to every transaction to eliminate all risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It allows financial institutions to avoid compliance measures entirely if they determine their risk is low]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FATF Recommendation 1 establishes the risk-based approach as the foundation of AML/CFT frameworks. It requires assessment of ML/TF risks and proportionate allocation of resources — enhanced measures for higher-risk situations and the possibility of simplified measures for lower-risk scenarios. This ensures effective and efficient use of compliance resources.
**The Trap:** Option C is dangerous — the risk-based approach never permits complete avoidance of compliance. Even low-risk situations require baseline measures. The approach is about proportionality, not exemption.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The risk-based approach is FATF Recommendation 1 and is foundational to all AML compliance frameworks tested in NISM IFSCA-01.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Implement the risk-based approach by developing a clear risk assessment methodology — document your risk categories and ensure measures are proportionate to the identified risks.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>