<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 3 of the PML Rules, what is the threshold for maintaining records of cross-border wire transfers where either the origin or destination of funds is in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than Rs. 1 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[More than Rs. 5 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than Rs. 10 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than Rs. 50 lakh or its equivalent in foreign currency]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 3(E) requires reporting entities to maintain records of all cross-border wire transfers of the value of more than five lakh rupees or its equivalent in foreign currency where either the origin or destination of fund is in India. This is reported through the Cross Border Wire Transfer Report (CBWTR).

**The Trap:** Rs. 5 lakh is specifically for cross-border wire transfers, not for cash transactions (Rs. 10 lakh) or immovable property (Rs. 50 lakh). Many candidates apply the Rs. 10 lakh cash threshold to wire transfers, which is incorrect.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests CBWTR thresholds for SEBI intermediaries. The IFSCA exam places greater emphasis on this because IFSC entities primarily deal with cross-border transactions, making CBWTR the most frequently triggered report.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For IFSC entities, CBWTR reporting at Rs. 5 lakh threshold is the most practically relevant reporting obligation since all transactions are cross-border by nature and no cash transactions are permitted in the IFSC.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>