<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Rule 4, records maintained under Rule 3 must contain information sufficient to permit reconstruction of individual transactions. Which of the following is NOT specifically required?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The nature of the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The amount and currency of the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The date on which the transaction was conducted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The credit rating of the parties to the transaction]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 4 requires records to contain: (a) the nature of the transactions, (b) the amount and currency, (c) the date of the transaction, and (d) the parties to the transaction. Credit rating is not one of the specified requirements under Rule 4. The records must permit reconstruction of individual transactions.

**The Trap:** All four specified elements are straightforward transaction details. Credit rating is a risk assessment metric, not a transaction record requirement. While reporting entities may assess client risk (which may include creditworthiness), it is not a Rule 4 requirement for transaction records.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests Rule 4 requirements similarly. The IFSCA exam additionally tests that records must be maintained as per the regulator's specifications (Rule 5).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remember the four elements of Rule 4: Nature, Amount/Currency, Date, and Parties. These are the minimum for reconstructing any transaction. Your entity's internal policies may require more, but these four are the regulatory minimum.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>