<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What are the Enhanced Due Diligence (EDD) measures under the IFSCA Guidelines when ML/TF risks are HIGH?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All of the above]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtaining additional customer information and updating identification data more frequently]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Examining source of wealth and source of funds of the customer or Beneficial Owner]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtaining Senior Management approval to commence or continue the business relationship]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** EDD measures include: (i) additional customer information and more frequent ID updates; (ii) examining source of wealth and funds; (iii) recording purpose behind transactions; (iv) Senior Management approval to start or continue relationship; (v) enhanced monitoring with increased controls; and (vi) requiring first payment through customer's own bank account.

**The Trap:** EDD is not just 'more documents' — it includes deeper analysis of wealth sources, transaction purposes, and requires Senior Management involvement. The first payment requirement through customer's own bank account is often overlooked.

**Cross-Exam Context:** EDD requirements are tested across IFSCA-01, Series XXIV, and III-A. IFSCA-01 specifically requires EDD for entities from FATF-identified countries, which is particularly relevant for IFSC's international clientele.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** EDD key elements: more info, source of wealth/funds, Senior Management approval, enhanced monitoring, and first payment from customer's own account at a regulated bank with equivalent AML standards.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>