<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the concept of 'reliance on third party' for client due diligence under the PML Rules?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A reporting entity may rely on CDD performed by a regulated third party, provided it can immediately obtain the identification data and is satisfied the third party is adequately regulated]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any person including an unregulated agent can conduct CDD on behalf of a reporting entity without any conditions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Third-party reliance eliminates the reporting entity's own liability for CDD compliance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only government agencies can serve as third parties for CDD verification purposes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Rule 9(2) of PML Rules, a reporting entity may rely on a third party for CDD, subject to conditions: it must immediately obtain the CDD information, ensure copies of identification data will be available on request, and the third party must be regulated and supervised for AML compliance.
**The Trap:** Option B is a critical trap — even when relying on a third party, the ultimate responsibility for CDD compliance remains with the reporting entity. Third-party reliance does not transfer liability.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Third-party reliance for KYC is tested in the context of both domestic and IFSC-based entities in NISM IFSCA-01.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you rely on a third party for CDD, ensure they are a regulated entity — the Paytm Payments Bank case showed penalties for relying on a non-compliant/unregulated entity for KYC.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>