<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PMLA, an 'offence of cross border implications' includes:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Conduct outside India constituting an offence there, which would be a scheduled offence if committed in India, and proceeds are transferred to India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only offences committed within India where proceeds remain in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only offences listed under Part C of the Schedule]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only offences committed by foreign nationals]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 2(ra) defines 'offence of cross border implications' in two scenarios: (i) conduct by a person at a place outside India which constitutes an offence there AND would be a scheduled offence if committed in India, where proceeds are transferred to India; OR (ii) any scheduled offence committed in India where proceeds have been transferred or attempted to be transferred outside India.

**The Trap:** The definition covers BOTH directions: proceeds coming INTO India from foreign crimes, and proceeds going OUT of India from domestic crimes. It is not limited to Part C offences or foreign nationals. The concept of 'dual criminality' applies -- the conduct must be an offence in both jurisdictions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may not deeply test cross-border implications. The IFSCA exam specifically tests this because IFSC entities are inherently cross-border in nature and this definition determines PMLA's jurisdictional reach.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This two-way definition is critical for IFSC entities. Money flowing in from overseas crimes OR flowing out from Indian crimes -- both are covered. Your enhanced due diligence must assess cross-border flows in both directions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>