<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the IFSCA Guidelines, what must be done when CDD verification cannot be completed within 30 business days of establishing a business relationship?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Document the reason, complete verification ASAP, and record the non-compliance for reporting to the Governing Body]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Immediately terminate the business relationship without exception]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Continue the business relationship without any restrictions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Report to IFSCA and await further instructions before taking any action]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If verification cannot be completed within 30 days, the RE must: (i) document the reason for non-compliance; (ii) complete verification as soon as possible; and (iii) record the non-compliance event for reporting to the Governing Body. If still uncompleted after 30 days, the relationship must be suspended. If uncompleted after 120 days, the relationship must be terminated.

**The Trap:** The 30-day breach doesn't automatically terminate the relationship — there's a documented process. But after 120 days, termination is MANDATORY. Two key thresholds: 30 days (suspend) and 120 days (terminate).

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 30/120-day framework is specific to IFSCA-01. Series XXIV has different timelines for domestic CDD completion. This dual-threshold approach accommodates the complexity of international client verification.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Timeline: 0-30 days = complete verification; 30 days breached = document, report to Governing Body, suspend; 120 days breached = TERMINATE. Return funds to source when suspending.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>