<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Principal Officer designated by a reporting entity under PMLA must be an officer at which level?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Junior management level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Management level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Board of Directors level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any level as decided by the entity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Principal Officer is an officer designated by a reporting entity who should be at the management level. The PO is designated for the purpose of Section 12 of PMLA and acts as a central reference point for facilitating onward reporting of suspicious transactions. Rule 7 requires the reporting entity to communicate the name, designation, and address of the PO to the Director, FIU-IND.

**The Trap:** The PO must be at 'management level' -- not too junior (which would lack authority) and not necessarily at the Board level (which is the Designated Director's domain). The distinction between Principal Officer (management level, operational reporting) and Designated Director (overall compliance) is important.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the PO role for SEBI intermediaries. The IFSCA exam adds the Designated Director requirement and specifically tests who qualifies as DD for IFSC entities (person heading the reporting entity in India if located in IFSC).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Principal Officer = operational reporting to FIU-IND. Designated Director = overall compliance oversight. Both must be registered on FINGate 2.0. For IFSC entities, the Designated Director is the person heading the entity in India.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>