<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PML Rules, which of the following types of suspicious transactions must be reported?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only suspicious transactions that are completed and are in cash]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only suspicious transactions exceeding Rs. 10 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only suspicious transactions involving cross-border wire transfers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All suspicious transactions, whether or not made in cash, including attempted transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rule 3(D) requires maintenance of records of ALL suspicious transactions whether or not made in cash and by way of various instruments and modes. There is no monetary threshold for suspicious transactions. Additionally, attempted transactions that are suspicious must also be reported. The scope covers deposits, credits, withdrawals, money transfers, loans, investments, and collection services in any currency.

**The Trap:** Unlike CTR (Rs. 10 lakh threshold) or CBWTR (Rs. 5 lakh threshold), suspicious transactions have NO monetary threshold. Even a Rs. 100 transaction can be suspicious and must be reported. The inclusion of ATTEMPTED transactions is also commonly missed by candidates.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the same no-threshold STR requirement. The IFSCA exam emphasizes that even electronic transactions within the IFSC (where no cash is used) can be suspicious and must be reported.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** There is no safe harbor based on transaction value for STRs. If something looks suspicious based on the four grounds (proceeds of crime, unusual complexity, no economic rationale, terrorism financing), report it regardless of amount. Better to over-report than to miss a genuinely suspicious transaction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>