<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What should a Regulated Entity do when it is unable to complete the required Customer Due Diligence for a customer?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It should not open an account, not carry out transactions, not establish a business relationship, and consider terminating any existing relationship and filing an STR if appropriate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It should proceed with the business relationship but limit the transaction amount to below the reporting threshold]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It should report the customer directly to the police as a suspected money launderer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It should grant a temporary 90-day grace period during which full CDD can be completed while allowing unrestricted transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under IFSCA Guidelines, when a Regulated Entity cannot complete CDD, it must: not open an account, not carry out transactions, not establish a business relationship, terminate or suspend existing relationships, and consider filing a suspicious transaction report. This strict approach ensures that unverified customers cannot access financial services.
**The Trap:** Option C (90-day grace period) is tempting because some entities informally allow temporary access, but the Guidelines are clear — no account or service should be provided without completed CDD.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The consequences of incomplete CDD are tested in NISM IFSCA-01 to ensure candidates understand the strict compliance obligations.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never allow business relationships to proceed without completed CDD — the regulatory consequences far outweigh any commercial benefit from the customer relationship.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>