<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA KYC Norms_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the difference between Customer Due Diligence (CDD) and Enhanced Due Diligence (EDD)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[CDD involves standard identity verification and risk assessment, while EDD requires additional measures such as verifying source of wealth, obtaining senior management approval, and enhanced monitoring for higher-risk customers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[CDD is performed only for individual customers, while EDD is performed only for corporate customers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[CDD requires physical document verification, while EDD only requires electronic verification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[CDD is mandatory for all customers, while EDD is optional and depends on the reporting entity's discretion]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** CDD is the baseline level of due diligence applied to all customers, involving identity verification and understanding business purpose. EDD goes beyond CDD and is required for higher-risk scenarios — it includes additional steps like verifying source of wealth and funds, obtaining senior management approval, and conducting enhanced ongoing monitoring.
**The Trap:** Option C is dangerous — EDD is not optional. It is mandatory when risk indicators warrant it, such as for PEPs, high-risk jurisdictions, or complex/unusual transactions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The CDD-EDD distinction is tested in NISM IFSCA-01, NISM Series V-A, and NISM Series VIII.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Apply EDD whenever you encounter PEPs, customers from high-risk jurisdictions, complex ownership structures, or unusually large transactions — failing to do so is a compliance violation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>