<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Maintenance of Records Rules_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Prevention of Money-laundering (Maintenance of Records) Rules, 2005 were framed in exercise of powers conferred by which section of PMLA?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Section 3 -- Offence of Money Laundering]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Section 12 -- Reporting entity to maintain records]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Section 73 -- Power to make Rules]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Section 56 -- Agreements with foreign countries]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The PML (Maintenance of Records) Rules, 2005 were made by the Central Government in exercise of powers conferred by Section 73 of the PMLA in consultation with the Reserve Bank of India. Section 73 is the rule-making power provision that enables the Central Government to prescribe detailed procedures and methods for implementing the Act's provisions.

**The Trap:** Section 12 requires reporting entities to maintain records, but the rules themselves are made under Section 73 (the rule-making power). Section 3 defines the offence and Section 56 deals with international cooperation. The distinction between the substantive obligation (Section 12) and the rule-making power (Section 73) is important.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may not specifically test which section enables the rules. The IFSCA exam tests the legal hierarchy: PMLA (Act) -> Section 73 (rule-making power) -> PML Rules 2005 (detailed procedures).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understanding the legal hierarchy is important: the Act sets the obligation (Section 12), the rules (made under Section 73) specify how to fulfill that obligation. This helps you understand why rules can be amended without changing the Act itself.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>