<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA AML CFT KYC Guidelines_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the IFSCA Guidelines, who are required to report suspicious transactions when they engage in financial transactions on behalf of clients?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Lawyers, notaries, accountants, and entities offering services]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only banks and financial institutions licensed by IFSCA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Principal Officer of the Regulated Entity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only designated non-financial businesses registered with FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Guidelines state that lawyers, notaries, accountants, and entities offering services shall report suspicious transactions when, on behalf of or for a client, they engage in financial transactions related to: buying/selling real estate, managing client money/securities/assets, management of bank/savings/securities accounts, organization of contributions for companies, and creation/management of legal persons.

**The Trap:** Reporting obligations extend beyond traditional financial institutions to include professional service providers when they facilitate financial transactions on behalf of clients.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This aligns with FATF Recommendations 22-23 on Designated Non-Financial Businesses and Professions (DNFBPs). Series XXIV focuses on SEBI-registered intermediaries; IFSCA-01 covers the broader IFSC ecosystem including professional service providers.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Key activities triggering reporting: real estate, managing client money, bank account management, company formation, and managing legal entities. If you facilitate it, you must report suspicious activity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>