<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA PMLA 2002_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the PMLA, 'proceeds of crime' means:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only cash derived directly from a criminal activity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only property held within India derived from scheduled offences]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Any property derived or obtained, directly or indirectly, as a result of criminal activity relating to a scheduled offence, or its value equivalent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only movable property connected with money laundering]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 2(u) defines 'proceeds of crime' very broadly as any property derived or obtained, directly or indirectly, by any person as a result of criminal activity relating to a scheduled offence or the value of any such property. Crucially, where such property is taken or held outside the country, the property equivalent in value held within the country or abroad is also covered. The definition also clarifies that proceeds include property indirectly derived from criminal activity relatable to the scheduled offence.

**The Trap:** The definition is extremely broad -- it covers direct AND indirect derivation, property held inside OR outside India, and includes value equivalents. It is not limited to cash, not limited to domestic property, and not limited to movable property.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV tests the same definition. The IFSCA exam emphasizes the cross-border aspect -- property equivalent in value held within or outside the country -- which is particularly relevant for IFSC transactions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The expansive definition of 'proceeds of crime' means that even indirectly connected property can be attached. For IFSC entities, this extends to assets held in any jurisdiction, making cross-border due diligence critical.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>