<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="IFSCA Scheduled Offences_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Part A of the Schedule to the PMLA, offences are drawn from which of the following legislations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Bharatiya Nyaya Sanhita (BNS) 2023]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Multiple legislations including BNS, NDPS Act, UAPA, Arms Act, Prevention of Corruption Act, and others]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Part A draws from a wide range of criminal legislations including: Bharatiya Nyaya Sanhita (BNS) 2023 (erstwhile IPC), Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act 1985, Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act 1967, Arms Act 1959, Prevention of Corruption Act 1988, Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, Copyright Act, Trademark Act, Wildlife Protection Act, Information Technology Act, Companies Act 2013, and others. No monetary threshold applies to Part A offences.

**The Trap:** Part A is not limited to any single legislation. It is an exhaustive compilation from many different laws. The broad scope ensures that proceeds from virtually any serious criminal activity can trigger money laundering proceedings.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XXIV may focus on specific IPC/BNS offences. The IFSCA exam tests the breadth of Part A to ensure candidates understand the wide range of predicate offences that can generate proceeds of crime flowing through IFSC entities.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The diversity of Part A means that proceeds from drug trafficking, terrorism, corruption, fraud, counterfeiting, wildlife crimes, IP theft, and many more can all trigger ML proceedings. IFSC entities must have broad-based due diligence covering all these risk categories.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>