<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Gopal took a housing loan for construction of a self-occupied property. Construction was completed on 1st March 2025. He paid pre-construction interest totalling Rs.5,00,000 over 3 years. How will this pre-construction interest be treated under the old tax regime?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire Rs.5,00,000 is deductible in the year of completion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.5,00,000 is deductible in 5 equal annual installments of Rs.1,00,000 each, starting from the year of completion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pre-construction interest is not deductible for self-occupied property]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.5,00,000 is deductible in 3 equal installments matching the years of payment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Pre-construction interest on a housing loan is deductible in 5 equal annual installments, starting from the year in which construction is completed. The total pre-construction interest of Rs.5,00,000 will be allowed as Rs.1,00,000 per year for 5 years. This is in addition to the current year's interest, but the combined deduction for self-occupied property is subject to the Rs.2 lakh cap under the old regime.
**The Trap:** Candidates often think pre-construction interest is deductible in the year it was paid, or that it is split based on the number of years of payment. The law mandates exactly 5 equal installments regardless of the actual payment period.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests this specific provision as it affects cash flow planning for clients with under-construction properties.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising clients buying under-construction properties, factor in that pre-construction interest gets spread over 5 years — this impacts the effective tax saving in early years and should be modeled in their financial plan.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
