<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ms. Neha, a Non-Resident, has the following incomes: (i) Salary received in India: Rs.6,00,000, (ii) Rental income from property in Mumbai: Rs.3,00,000, (iii) Agricultural income from land in Sri Lanka: Rs.2,00,000, (iv) Interest on UK bank deposit credited to UK account: Rs.1,50,000. What is her total taxable income in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.9,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.12,50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.6,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.11,00,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For a Non-Resident, only income received in India or accruing/arising in India is taxable. (i) Salary received in India = Rs.6,00,000 — taxable (received in India). (ii) Rental income from Mumbai property = Rs.3,00,000 — taxable (accrues in India). (iii) Agricultural income from Sri Lanka = Rs.2,00,000 — NOT taxable (foreign income, neither received nor accruing in India). (iv) UK bank interest credited to UK account = Rs.1,50,000 — NOT taxable (neither received nor accruing in India). Total taxable = Rs.6,00,000 + Rs.3,00,000 = Rs.9,00,000.
**The Trap:** Candidates may include Sri Lankan agricultural income thinking all agricultural income is exempt under section 10(1) — but that exemption applies only to agricultural income from land in India. For an NR, foreign agricultural income is simply outside the scope of Indian taxation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-A tests basic NR scope; X-B tests with multiple income streams requiring classification by source and receipt location.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For NR clients, always classify each income stream by two criteria: where is it received, and where does it accrue? Only India-linked income is taxable. This exercise is essential before recommending any investment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
