<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A speculative transaction in the context of PGBP (Profits and Gains of Business or Profession) is one where:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The transaction involves delivery-based purchase and sale of shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The transaction is settled otherwise than by actual delivery or transfer of the commodity or scrip]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The transaction results in a loss exceeding Rs.10 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The transaction involves trading in derivatives on a recognized stock exchange]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Income Tax Act, a speculative transaction is defined as one that is settled otherwise than by actual delivery or transfer of the commodity or scrip. The key factor is the mode of settlement — if no actual delivery takes place, it is speculative. Note: trading in derivatives on a recognized stock exchange is specifically excluded from the definition of speculative transaction.
**The Trap:** Candidates frequently confuse derivatives trading with speculative transactions. While derivatives are inherently "speculative" in the common sense, they are specifically carved out from the tax definition of speculative transactions when traded on recognized exchanges.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) tests what constitutes speculation from a regulatory angle; Series X-B tests the tax treatment. The distinction is critical for loss set-off rules.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Speculative losses can only be set off against speculative gains and carried forward for 4 years. Non-speculative business losses have much broader set-off options. Help clients understand this distinction when they trade in cash-settled instruments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
