<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following conditions makes a Resident individual an RNOR (Resident but Not Ordinarily Resident)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The individual has been resident in India for 9 out of 10 preceding previous years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The individual has been a non-resident in India in 9 out of the 10 preceding previous years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The individual has stayed 730 or more days in India during the 7 preceding previous years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The individual's Indian income exceeds Rs.15 lakh and he has stayed 182 days in India]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Resident qualifies as RNOR if ANY ONE of the following is satisfied: (a) NR in 9 out of 10 preceding previous years, OR (b) total stay in India ≤729 days in 7 preceding previous years, OR (c) deemed resident under s.6(1A). Option B correctly states the NR-in-9/10-years condition. Option A reverses it (resident in 9/10 — that would make them ROR, not RNOR). Option C states 730+ days — the threshold is ≤729 days (i.e., less than 730). Option D describes a residency condition, not an RNOR condition.
**The Trap:** The 9-out-of-10 test is frequently reversed by examiners — "resident in 9/10" vs "non-resident in 9/10" are opposites. Similarly, candidates confuse ≤729 with ≥730.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B frequently tests the precise RNOR conditions. The distinction between ROR and RNOR matters greatly for scope of taxable income.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** RNOR status is a valuable tax planning window for returning NRIs — their foreign income remains untaxed in India during RNOR years. Help clients track their year-count carefully.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
