<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A Hindu Undivided Family (HUF) has its business operations in Mumbai, but the karta makes all key management decisions from London. What is the residential status of this HUF?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Resident, since business operations are in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Non-Resident, since control and management is wholly outside India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RNOR, since partial control is in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Resident, since HUF is always treated as an Indian entity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For an HUF, the test is: Resident if control and management of affairs is not wholly outside India. NR if control and management is wholly outside India. Here, the karta makes ALL key decisions from London — control and management is wholly outside India. Hence the HUF is Non-Resident. Note: the location of business operations is irrelevant; what matters is where control and management decisions are made.
**The Trap:** Candidates confuse "business operations in India" with "control and management in India." The test for HUF is purely about where decisions are made, not where operations occur.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B specifically tests HUF residency. The "wholly outside India" standard is an absolute test — even partial management from India makes the HUF resident.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For HUF clients, if even one key management decision is taken from India, the HUF becomes Resident. Advise karta-level clients to be aware that conducting even a single board meeting from India can change the HUF's status.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
