<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A "Person of Indian Origin" (PIO) for the purposes of residential status under the Income Tax Act is defined as a person:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Whose parents were born in India after 15th August 1947]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Who holds an Overseas Citizen of India (OCI) card]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Whose parents or grandparents (any of them) were born in undivided India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Who has lived in India for at least 10 years at any point in their lifetime]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Income Tax Act, a Person of Indian Origin is defined as an individual who himself, or whose parent or grandparent (any one of them), was born in undivided India. The reference to "undivided India" means the territory of India as it existed before the partition on 15th August 1947, which includes present-day Pakistan and Bangladesh.
**The Trap:** Candidates often confuse the IT Act PIO definition with the immigration/OCI card definition. The IT Act definition is broader in one sense (includes birth in undivided India) and uses a specific legal test (self/parent/grandparent born in undivided India), not merely an OCI card.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B specifically tests the PIO definition as it impacts the day-count thresholds for residential status determination.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When onboarding NRI clients, always determine PIO status by checking birth records of their parents and grandparents — this can change the applicable day-count threshold and affect their residential status determination.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
