<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Income, Residential Status, Five Heads of Income_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Nitin receives a gift of Rs.60,000 from his friend (non-relative) on the occasion of his birthday. Under which head of income will this gift be taxed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Income from Salary]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is fully exempt from tax as it is a birthday gift]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Income from Other Sources, under section 56]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is exempt since the amount is below Rs.1,00,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under section 56(2)(x), any sum of money received without consideration from non-relatives exceeding Rs.50,000 in aggregate during a previous year is taxable as "Income from Other Sources." Mr. Nitin received Rs.60,000 from a friend (non-relative), which exceeds the Rs.50,000 threshold. The ENTIRE Rs.60,000 becomes taxable (not just the excess over Rs.50,000). The occasion of birthday does not provide any exemption — only gifts on the occasion of marriage are exempt.
**The Trap:** Candidates often think (a) only the excess over Rs.50,000 is taxable (wrong — the entire amount is taxable once the threshold is breached), or (b) birthday gifts are exempt like wedding gifts (wrong — only marriage is a specified exempt occasion).
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests gift taxation under section 56. This is also relevant for NISM V-A when advising on tax-efficient wealth transfer strategies.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients to be careful with gifts from non-relatives — keep aggregate gifts below Rs.50,000 per year, or the ENTIRE amount becomes taxable. Gifts from specified relatives are always exempt regardless of amount.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
