<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Industry Analysis_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Arjun Malhotra is analyzing the Indian pharmaceutical industry for a sector report. His PESTLE analysis reveals: Political: Government promoting generic drug manufacturing through production-linked incentive (PLI) schemes. The Jan Aushadhi scheme promotes affordable generic medicines. Economic: India is the world's largest supplier of generic drugs (60% of global supply). The industry exports to 200+ countries with exports worth $27 billion. Pharma is counter-cyclical — demand is inelastic to economic cycles. Socio-cultural: Rising health consciousness, increasing lifestyle diseases (diabetes, cardiovascular), and aging population driving demand. Technological: Digital health, telemedicine, and AI-driven drug discovery are creating new opportunities. Patent cliff — many blockbuster drugs losing patent protection, opening doors for generic manufacturers. Legal: Drug Price Control Order (DPCO) regulates prices of essential medicines. US FDA inspections are critical for export-oriented companies. Environmental: Growing emphasis on green chemistry and sustainable manufacturing. Effluent treatment requirements adding to operating costs.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Patent cliff creating opportunities for generic manufacturers is classified under:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Legal — as it relates to intellectual property law]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Political — as governments decide on patent policies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Technological — as it relates to technology and innovation cycles in drug development]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Socio-cultural — as it reflects societal preferences]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Patent cliff relates to the technology and innovation cycle — when patents on drugs expire, the technological barrier to entry is removed, allowing generic manufacturers to produce the same drug.
**The Trap:** While patents are a legal concept, the patent cliff phenomenon is about the technology/innovation lifecycle of drug development. It represents technological change.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Technology analysis in PESTLE tested in NISM Series XV Chapter 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Track upcoming patent expirations for blockbuster drugs — each represents a multi-billion-dollar opportunity for Indian generic manufacturers like Sun Pharma and Dr. Reddy's.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>