<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Industry Analysis_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunita Reddy, a research analyst at Alpha Research, is analyzing the Indian cement industry using Porter's Five Forces framework. Here are her findings: (1) The industry has 50+ players with the top 5 controlling 45% market share. Cement is a homogeneous commodity product. (2) Key raw materials (limestone, coal, pet coke) are sourced from limited mining operators, and government controls mining licenses. (3) Cement demand is driven by construction activity from government infrastructure projects (40%), housing (35%), and commercial real estate (25%). Large institutional buyers like real estate developers and government agencies purchase in bulk. (4) The industry requires minimum investment of Rs.500 crore for a new plant, along with mining licenses and environmental clearances. (5) Substitutes like prefabricated steel structures and AAC blocks are gaining market share in urban construction. Average industry EBITDA margin is 15-18%.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> The threat of new entrants is best assessed as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Very high because anyone can easily start a cement plant]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Moderate because significant capital (Rs.500 crore+), mining licenses, and environmental clearances create meaningful barriers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Non-existent because the government prohibits new cement plants]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Low but only because demand is declining]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rs.500 crore minimum investment, mining license requirements, and environmental clearance processes create meaningful entry barriers. But they are not insurmountable for large corporations.
**The Trap:** The barriers are real but not absolute — large players regularly add capacity. It is not true that new plants are prohibited.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Entry barrier analysis tested in NISM Series XV Chapter 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Entry barriers in cement are 'medium' — high enough to deter casual entrants but not enough to prevent determined large players from entering.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>