<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Industry Analysis_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Arjun Malhotra is analyzing the Indian pharmaceutical industry for a sector report. His PESTLE analysis reveals: Political: Government promoting generic drug manufacturing through production-linked incentive (PLI) schemes. The Jan Aushadhi scheme promotes affordable generic medicines. Economic: India is the world's largest supplier of generic drugs (60% of global supply). The industry exports to 200+ countries with exports worth $27 billion. Pharma is counter-cyclical — demand is inelastic to economic cycles. Socio-cultural: Rising health consciousness, increasing lifestyle diseases (diabetes, cardiovascular), and aging population driving demand. Technological: Digital health, telemedicine, and AI-driven drug discovery are creating new opportunities. Patent cliff — many blockbuster drugs losing patent protection, opening doors for generic manufacturers. Legal: Drug Price Control Order (DPCO) regulates prices of essential medicines. US FDA inspections are critical for export-oriented companies. Environmental: Growing emphasis on green chemistry and sustainable manufacturing. Effluent treatment requirements adding to operating costs.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Based on Arjun's analysis, the pharma industry can be classified as which type in terms of cyclicality?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Deep cyclical — revenues swing wildly with economic cycles]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Semi-cyclical — some decline during recessions but with a base demand]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Defensive — demand is inelastic to economic cycles as healthcare is essential]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Seasonal — demand follows weather patterns only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The workbook states pharma is counter-cyclical with inelastic demand. Healthcare is essential — people need medicines regardless of economic conditions. This makes pharma a defensive industry.
**The Trap:** Pharma demand doesn't swing with GDP. Healthcare is not seasonal (unlike agricultural inputs). It's defensive because demand persists through economic downturns.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Industry cyclicality classification tested in NISM Series XV Chapter 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Defensive sectors like pharma provide portfolio stability during economic downturns. They may underperform during strong recoveries but protect capital during crashes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>