<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Industry Analysis_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Arjun Malhotra is analyzing the Indian pharmaceutical industry for a sector report. His PESTLE analysis reveals: Political: Government promoting generic drug manufacturing through production-linked incentive (PLI) schemes. The Jan Aushadhi scheme promotes affordable generic medicines. Economic: India is the world's largest supplier of generic drugs (60% of global supply). The industry exports to 200+ countries with exports worth $27 billion. Pharma is counter-cyclical — demand is inelastic to economic cycles. Socio-cultural: Rising health consciousness, increasing lifestyle diseases (diabetes, cardiovascular), and aging population driving demand. Technological: Digital health, telemedicine, and AI-driven drug discovery are creating new opportunities. Patent cliff — many blockbuster drugs losing patent protection, opening doors for generic manufacturers. Legal: Drug Price Control Order (DPCO) regulates prices of essential medicines. US FDA inspections are critical for export-oriented companies. Environmental: Growing emphasis on green chemistry and sustainable manufacturing. Effluent treatment requirements adding to operating costs.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> The DPCO regulating prices of essential medicines falls under which PESTLE category?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Political]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Economic]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Socio-cultural]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Legal — as it is a specific regulatory order with legal force]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** DPCO is a legal/regulatory order with binding force on pharma companies. It dictates maximum retail prices for essential drugs, making it a Legal factor in PESTLE.
**The Trap:** While DPCO originates from government policy (Political), the question asks about the specific regulatory order which has legal force and compliance implications.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Regulatory analysis in PESTLE tested in NISM Series XV Chapter 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** DPCO-covered drugs have limited pricing power. Analysts should calculate what percentage of a company's revenue comes from price-controlled products.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>