<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Industry Analysis_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunita Reddy, a research analyst at Alpha Research, is analyzing the Indian cement industry using Porter's Five Forces framework. Here are her findings: (1) The industry has 50+ players with the top 5 controlling 45% market share. Cement is a homogeneous commodity product. (2) Key raw materials (limestone, coal, pet coke) are sourced from limited mining operators, and government controls mining licenses. (3) Cement demand is driven by construction activity from government infrastructure projects (40%), housing (35%), and commercial real estate (25%). Large institutional buyers like real estate developers and government agencies purchase in bulk. (4) The industry requires minimum investment of Rs.500 crore for a new plant, along with mining licenses and environmental clearances. (5) Substitutes like prefabricated steel structures and AAC blocks are gaining market share in urban construction. Average industry EBITDA margin is 15-18%.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> The bargaining power of suppliers (mining operators) in the cement industry is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Low because there are thousands of mining operators]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Moderate to High because limited mining operators exist and government controls licenses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Non-existent because cement companies own all mines]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Low because limestone is freely available everywhere]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Limited mining operators and government-controlled licenses create moderate to high supplier bargaining power. Cement companies depend on these critical inputs.
**The Trap:** Not all cement companies own mines. Mining licenses are limited resources, giving existing operators leverage.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Supplier power analysis tested in NISM Series XV Chapter 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Companies with captive mines (own limestone sources) have a significant cost advantage over those dependent on external suppliers.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>