<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Industry Analysis_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Arjun Malhotra is analyzing the Indian pharmaceutical industry for a sector report. His PESTLE analysis reveals: Political: Government promoting generic drug manufacturing through production-linked incentive (PLI) schemes. The Jan Aushadhi scheme promotes affordable generic medicines. Economic: India is the world's largest supplier of generic drugs (60% of global supply). The industry exports to 200+ countries with exports worth $27 billion. Pharma is counter-cyclical — demand is inelastic to economic cycles. Socio-cultural: Rising health consciousness, increasing lifestyle diseases (diabetes, cardiovascular), and aging population driving demand. Technological: Digital health, telemedicine, and AI-driven drug discovery are creating new opportunities. Patent cliff — many blockbuster drugs losing patent protection, opening doors for generic manufacturers. Legal: Drug Price Control Order (DPCO) regulates prices of essential medicines. US FDA inspections are critical for export-oriented companies. Environmental: Growing emphasis on green chemistry and sustainable manufacturing. Effluent treatment requirements adding to operating costs.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> India being the world's largest generic drug supplier represents which PESTLE factor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Political]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Economic — demonstrating India's competitive advantage and scale in global pharma trade]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Socio-cultural]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Environmental]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** India's position as the largest generic supplier with $27 billion exports to 200+ countries is an Economic factor showing competitive advantage, trade position, and economic contribution.
**The Trap:** While influenced by political decisions (trade agreements), the fact of being the largest supplier is fundamentally an economic position.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Economic analysis in PESTLE tested in NISM Series XV Chapter 6.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** India's pharma exports are a key source of foreign exchange. Disruptions (like US FDA import alerts) can affect both the companies and the rupee.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>