<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to Merchant Banking_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a key difference between investment banking and merchant banking?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investment banks only handle private placements while merchant banks handle public offers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Merchant banks risk their own capital in proprietary trading while investment banks do not]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Investment banking includes fund-based activities like stock trading and market making, while merchant banking is primarily fee-based]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Merchant banks provide corporate advisory services while investment banks do not]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The fundamental distinction is that investment banking has a wider connotation including both fund-based (proprietary trading, stock trading, market making) and non-fund-based activities, while merchant banking is primarily fee-based, focusing on issue management and intermediation.
**The Trap:** It is actually investment banks (not merchant banks) that risk their own capital in proprietary trading. Both types provide corporate advisory services. Private placement vs. public offers is not the distinguishing factor.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the MB vs. IB distinction is foundational for NISM Series IX and helps contextualize regulatory requirements for different intermediaries.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** UK model = merchant banking (fee-focused, advisory); US model = investment banking (capital at risk, trading + advisory). India's regulatory framework uses the term "merchant banker" but the activities increasingly resemble investment banking.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
