<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to the Capital Market_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The regulation of foreign investment in India involves multiple regulators. Which combination correctly identifies the regulators and the governing legislation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI and IRDAI under the Companies Act, 2013]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[RBI and Ministry of Finance through FEMA, 1999]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PFRDA and MCA under the SEBI Act, 1992]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI and SEBI under the Banking Regulation Act, 1949]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Foreign investment (including NRI investment) in India is regulated by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) and the Ministry of Finance (MOF) through the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (FEMA), which became effective in 2000. FEMA replaced the earlier Foreign Exchange Regulation Act (FERA).
**The Trap:** "RBI and SEBI under Banking Regulation Act" is tempting because RBI is correctly identified, but the governing law for foreign investment is FEMA, not the Banking Regulation Act. SEBI regulates FPIs' participation in the securities market but the overarching foreign investment framework is under FEMA.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) frequently tests regulatory overlap, especially in IPOs involving FPI participation. Understanding which regulator governs what aspect is critical for merchant bankers structuring cross-border transactions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising on an IPO with foreign investor participation, a merchant banker must ensure compliance with both SEBI regulations (for the offering) and FEMA/RBI rules (for the foreign investment component) — a dual compliance framework.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
