<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Introduction to AML, CFT and Proliferation Financing_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[In the context of money laundering, "shell companies" are used during the placement stage. These are best described as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Companies with complex multi-layered ownership structures designed to obscure the audit trail]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Companies that operate legitimate businesses but mix illegal funds with legal revenue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Inactive companies or corporations that exist only on paper and are used to place illegal funds into the financial system]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Companies established in foreign jurisdictions to integrate laundered money into the legitimate economy]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Shell companies, as used in the placement stage of money laundering, are inactive companies or corporations that exist only on paper. They have no real business operations and are used as vehicles to introduce illegal funds into the financial system by creating a veneer of legitimacy.

**The Trap:** The first option describes layering through complex ownership structures. The second option describes commingling, which is a different placement technique. The fourth option describes an integration technique using offshore entities. Each distractor represents a real money laundering method but from a different stage or technique.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Distinguishing between placement, layering, and integration methods is heavily tested in NISM XXIV. Shell companies specifically fall under placement — remember "placement = getting dirty money INTO the system."

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Shell companies = exist only on paper = placement tool. Do not confuse with front companies (which have some real business) or offshore entities used in layering/integration.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>