<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to the Capital Market_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[If a company has more than 1 lakh security holders, what is the requirement regarding its Registrar and Transfer Agent (RTA) function?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Even if the RTA function is handled by an internal department of the company, that department must be registered with SEBI as an RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The company must outsource the RTA function to a SEBI-registered external RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The company is exempt from RTA registration if it uses an internal department]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The company needs RBI approval instead of SEBI registration for its internal RTA department]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a company has more than 1 lakh (100,000) security holders, even if it maintains the registrar and transfer function through an internal department, that department must be registered with SEBI as a Registrar and Share Transfer Agent.
**The Trap:** The company is not required to outsource — it can keep the function internal. However, the internal department must still register with SEBI. There is no exemption for internal departments when the holder count exceeds 1 lakh.
**Cross-Exam Context:** RTA registration requirements are tested in NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) and Series VI (Depository Operations) exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The 1 lakh holder threshold is a key trigger. RTAs handle critical functions: collecting applications, maintaining holder records, handling transfers and redemptions. SEBI registration ensures accountability regardless of whether the function is internal or external.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
