<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to Research Analyst Profession_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following best describes the primary difference between sell-side and buy-side research analysts?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell-side analysts focus on equity while buy-side analysts focus on debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sell-side analysts publish reports for external clients while buy-side analysts generate research for internal use]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell-side analysts work independently while buy-side analysts work in teams]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell-side analysts cover only large-cap stocks while buy-side analysts cover small-cap stocks]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The primary distinction is the audience: sell-side analysts publish research reports in the public domain with buy/hold/sell recommendations for external clients, while buy-side analysts generate investment recommendations for internal consumption by fund managers within their organization.
**The Trap:** Option A incorrectly limits the asset class coverage. Both sell-side and buy-side analysts can cover equity, debt, or other asset classes. Options C and D create false distinctions about working style and coverage universe.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This distinction is fundamental to understanding the securities market ecosystem and is tested in multiple NISM exams including Series IX (Merchant Banking) and Series XII (Securities Markets Foundation).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A useful analogy: sell-side research is like a restaurant's public menu (available to all), while buy-side research is like a chef's private recipe book (proprietary and internal).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>