<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to the Capital Market_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In a private equity transaction, when an investment banker performs "Pre-Money Valuation," the primary purpose is to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Determine the tax liability of the investee company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Calculate the exit multiple for existing investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Arrive at a fair value that meets regulatory pricing requirements for preferential allotments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Prepare the company's financial statements for audit]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In a PE transaction, the investment banker performs pre-money valuation to determine the fair value of the company before the new investment. This valuation must meet regulatory pricing requirements, particularly for preferential allotments under SEBI's ICDR Regulations and Companies Act provisions, which prescribe minimum pricing based on specific formulas.
**The Trap:** "Calculate the exit multiple" relates to the investor's return analysis, not the regulatory pricing requirement. "Tax liability" and "financial statements for audit" are functions of accountants and tax advisors, not the investment banker's valuation role.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) specifically tests the investment banker's role in PE transactions, including valuation as part of the sell-side advisory function.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Pre-money valuation is critical because if the price is set below the regulatory minimum for preferential allotments, SEBI can reject the transaction. The merchant banker must ensure the valuation methodology is defensible and compliant.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
