<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to Research Analyst Profession_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A research analyst at a brokerage firm covers both the IT and pharmaceutical sectors. When publishing a report on a pharma company, the analyst's firm also has an investment banking relationship with the same company. This situation represents:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A normal business practice that requires no special action]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A potential conflict of interest that must be disclosed in the research report]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An illegal arrangement under SEBI regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A situation that only buy-side analysts encounter]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a research entity has investment banking or other business relationships with the subject company, it creates a potential conflict of interest. SEBI (Research Analyst) Regulations require that such conflicts be disclosed in the research report.
**The Trap:** Option A ignores the conflict management requirements. Option C overstates the situation — it's not illegal per se, but requires proper disclosure and management. Option D is wrong — this is specifically a sell-side issue where broking firms have multiple business lines.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Conflict of interest management is a critical topic across NISM Series XV, III-A, and X-A. The Chinese wall concept between research and investment banking divisions is frequently tested.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When reading research reports, always check the disclosure section at the end. It reveals whether the firm has business relationships with the subject company, which may influence the objectivity of the recommendation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>