<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Introduction to AML, CFT and Proliferation Financing_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI's Prohibition of Fraudulent and Unfair Trade Practices (PFUTP) Regulations, a "mule account" in the securities market refers to a trading account that is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An account opened under a fictitious name for the purpose of tax evasion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A dormant account that has not been used for more than two years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An account that is effectively controlled by another person who is not the account holder]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An account used exclusively for placing proceeds of crime into the financial system]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Per SEBI PFUTP Regulations, a "mule account" is defined as a trading account that is effectively controlled by another person who is not the registered account holder. This concept is critical in securities market manipulation where individuals lend their accounts to others for fraudulent trading.

**The Trap:** The last option confuses mule accounts with the "placement" stage of money laundering. The fictitious name option describes a different type of fraud. Dormant accounts are a separate regulatory concern. The key distinction is "effective control by another person."

**Cross-Exam Context:** Mule accounts are a relatively new addition to the AML/CFT syllabus, reflecting SEBI's evolving focus on market manipulation. This concept bridges NISM XXIV with the NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) and NISM Series XV (Research Analyst) exams.

**Key Takeaway:** A mule account is about control, not ownership on paper. If someone else is directing the trades in your account, your account is being used as a mule account — regardless of whose name it is registered under.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>