<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to the Capital Market_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The category of "sub-broker" has been discontinued by SEBI. Former sub-brokers were required to migrate to which of the following categories?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investment Adviser or Portfolio Manager]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Clearing Member or Custodian]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Authorized Person (AP) and/or Trading Member]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Depository Participant or Registrar to an Issue]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI discontinued the sub-broker category and required existing sub-brokers to migrate to either Authorized Person (AP) status or upgrade to full Trading Member registration. An Authorized Person acts as an agent of a stock broker and provides access to the trading platform, essentially performing the same client-facing role that sub-brokers previously performed.
**The Trap:** "Investment Adviser or Portfolio Manager" sounds plausible because sub-brokers dealt with investors, but these are entirely different SEBI registration categories with different eligibility criteria and functions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) and NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) both test the understanding of market intermediary categories. The AP concept is also tested in NISM Series V-A (Mutual Funds) for mutual fund distributors.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The migration from sub-broker to AP formalized the principal-agent relationship — an AP acts strictly as an agent of the stock broker, and the stock broker is responsible for the AP's conduct. This improved accountability in the system.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
