<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Introduction to AML, CFT and Proliferation Financing_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[How many Recommendations does the FATF currently have, and what areas do they cover?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[49 Recommendations covering only anti-money laundering measures]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[25 Recommendations covering AML and CFT only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[40 Recommendations covering AML, CFT, and countering proliferation financing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[30 Recommendations covering banking sector compliance only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FATF has issued 40 Recommendations that set the global standard for combating money laundering, terrorist financing, and the financing of proliferation of weapons of mass destruction. Originally focused on AML when first issued in 1990, they were revised in 2001 to include CFT (after 9/11) and further updated in 2012 to incorporate countering proliferation financing — reflecting the evolving threat landscape.

**The Trap:** The number 49 is a common confusion — FATF initially had 40 AML Recommendations plus 9 Special Recommendations on CFT, which were later consolidated into the current set of 40. The scope is not limited to banking — the Recommendations cover all designated non-financial businesses and professions (DNFBPs) as well.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XXIV frequently tests knowledge of the 40 Recommendations and their three-pillar coverage (AML, CFT, CPF). India's AML/CFT framework, including PMLA and RBI/SEBI guidelines, is built to comply with these FATF standards.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remember "40 Recommendations, 3 pillars" — AML, CFT, and CPF. The consolidation from 40+9 to 40 happened in 2012. FATF also conducts Mutual Evaluations of member countries to assess compliance with these Recommendations — India's latest evaluation is a frequently tested topic.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
