<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Introduction to AML, CFT and Proliferation Financing_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[The Palermo Convention (2000) expanded AML efforts beyond drug trafficking by:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Extending the criminalization of money laundering to proceeds from ALL serious crimes, not just drug trafficking]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Creating the Financial Action Task Force (FATF) as a permanent intergovernmental body]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Establishing the Egmont Group of Financial Intelligence Units]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Requiring all countries to set up dedicated Financial Intelligence Units]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The United Nations Convention against Transnational Organized Crime (UNTOC), known as the Palermo Convention (2000), was a landmark because it broadened the scope of money laundering beyond drug-related proceeds. While the Vienna Convention (1988) focused specifically on criminalizing laundering of drug trafficking proceeds, the Palermo Convention extended this to proceeds from ALL serious crimes, making AML frameworks far more comprehensive.

**The Trap:** FATF was established in 1989 at the G7 Summit in Paris — not by the Palermo Convention. The Egmont Group was informally created in 1995. While FIUs are important to AML infrastructure, the Palermo Convention did not mandate their creation — that evolved through FATF Recommendations and domestic legislation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The evolution from Vienna Convention (drug proceeds only) to Palermo Convention (all serious crimes) mirrors how India's PMLA covers a broad range of scheduled offences — not limited to drug trafficking. This progression is important for understanding the global AML framework tested in NISM Series XXIV.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remember the chronological expansion of AML scope: Vienna Convention (1988) covered drug trafficking proceeds -> Palermo Convention (2000) expanded to all serious crimes -> Post-9/11 measures added CFT. This evolution explains why PMLA's schedule of offences is so broad today.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
