<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to the Capital Market_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A company is planning an IPO. Its shares will be subscribed by domestic institutional investors, retail investors, and Foreign Portfolio Investors (FPIs). The company must comply with regulations from:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI only, as it is the sole regulator of the securities market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI and MCA only, under the SEBI Act and Companies Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI, MCA (Companies Act), and RBI (FEMA for foreign investors)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI only, since foreign investors are involved]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An IPO with FPI participation involves regulatory overlap: (1) SEBI regulates the issuance process under SEBI (ICDR) Regulations, (2) MCA governs corporate compliance under the Companies Act 2013, and (3) RBI regulates the foreign investment component through FEMA 1999 (sectoral caps, pricing guidelines, reporting requirements). The company and its merchant banker must navigate all three regulatory frameworks.
**The Trap:** "SEBI only" ignores the Companies Act requirements (prospectus filing, allotment rules) and FEMA compliance for FPIs. "SEBI and MCA only" misses the RBI/FEMA dimension when foreign investors participate. This multi-regulator reality is a core concept for merchant bankers.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX extensively tests regulatory overlap in capital market transactions. Understanding which regulator governs which aspect is fundamental to the merchant banker's advisory role.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In practice, merchant bankers maintain a compliance checklist mapping every step of an IPO to the relevant regulator — SEBI for the offer document and listing, ROC/MCA for prospectus filing and allotment, and RBI for FPI allotment reporting. Missing any one can delay the entire issue.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
