<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to Merchant Banking_71" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under delisting via SAST Regulation 5A, an acquirer wishing to delist must satisfy which of the following conditions?
(i) Must declare delisting intention upfront at the detailed public statement stage
(ii) Must not be a promoter or in control of the target company during the preceding 2 years
(iii) Must not hold more than 25% shares in the target company
(iv) Cannot acquire joint control with the existing promoter]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(i) and (ii) only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(i), (ii) and (iii) only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(ii) and (iv) only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All of (i), (ii), (iii) and (iv)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Delisting under SAST Regulation 5A requires ALL four conditions: (i) upfront declaration of delisting intent, (ii) acquirer must not have been promoter/in control for preceding 2 years, (iii) acquirer must not hold >25% shares, and (iv) cannot acquire joint control with existing promoter. These conditions ensure the delisting is by a genuinely new acquirer.
**The Trap:** Selecting only a subset of conditions is tempting because each condition individually seems sufficient. But the regulation imposes all four simultaneously to prevent backdoor delisting by existing insiders.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests SAST Regulation 5A as a specialized delisting pathway distinct from standard voluntary delisting.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising on a Regulation 5A delisting, create a compliance checklist for all four conditions at the engagement stage — failure on any one makes the entire pathway unavailable.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
