<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to Research Analyst Profession_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI (Research Analyst) Regulations, 2014, a Research Analyst is defined as a person who, for consideration, is engaged in which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing trading signals exclusively to institutional investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The business of providing research services]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Managing portfolio assets on behalf of clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Distributing mutual fund units to retail investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per the SEBI (Research Analyst) Regulations, 2014, a Research Analyst means a person who, for consideration, is engaged in the business of providing research services and includes a part-time research analyst. This is the verbatim definition from the regulations.
**The Trap:** Option A is tempting because research analysts do provide recommendations, but they are not limited to institutional investors or trading signals. Option C describes portfolio managers, and Option D describes mutual fund distributors — both distinct SEBI-registered categories.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This definition is foundational across all NISM exams that touch upon market intermediaries. In NISM V-A (Mutual Fund Distributors), the distinction between advisers, analysts, and distributors is frequently tested.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients confuse research analysts with investment advisers, remind them that RAs provide research reports and analysis, while IAs provide personalized advice. The regulatory registration requirements are different under SEBI.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>