<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Introduction to the Capital Market_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment banker advising a company seeking private equity capital prepares various documents for the "data room." Which of the following best describes the purpose of these documents?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To file with SEBI for regulatory approval of the PE investment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To enable prospective buyers/investors to conduct thorough due diligence before making an investment decision]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To publicly announce the PE deal on stock exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To calculate the brokerage commission payable to the investment banker]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The data room is a critical component of a PE transaction where the investment banker organizes and presents comprehensive information about the company — including financial models, corporate disclosures, legal documents, and operational data. This enables prospective investors to perform due diligence before committing capital. The documents include teasers, preliminary information memoranda, detailed information memoranda, and financial models.
**The Trap:** "File with SEBI" is incorrect because PE investments through preferential allotments typically do not require prior SEBI approval (though they must comply with SEBI regulations). "Publicly announce on exchanges" contradicts the private nature of PE deals.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the investment banker's role in leading PE transactions end-to-end. The data room concept is also relevant in M&A transactions covered in later chapters.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The quality of the data room directly impacts deal execution speed and valuation. A well-organized data room with clear disclosures builds investor confidence, reduces negotiation time, and often results in better pricing for the seller.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
