<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_58" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Mrs. Lakshmi's KYC was done 8 years ago with her old school address. She has moved to a new residence and her Aadhaar is not linked to her mutual fund accounts.

Question 2: What is the correct sequence of actions Mrs. Lakshmi should take to update her KYC and link Aadhaar?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only update Aadhaar on the UIDAI website and the mutual fund records will auto-update]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File a new KYC application as her old KYC is invalid after 8 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Submit a KYC modification request to update address, link Aadhaar through the KRA/CKYC system, and update address in her mutual fund folios as a non-financial transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No action needed — KYC is a one-time process and never needs updating]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mrs. Lakshmi needs to take multiple steps: (1) Update her address in the KRA/CKYC system by submitting a KYC modification form with proof of new address. (2) Link her Aadhaar to the KYC records for enhanced verification. (3) Submit a change of address request (non-financial transaction) to the AMC/RTA for each of her folios. While KYC is a one-time process, modifications to KYC details must be updated when there are changes.

**The Trap:** KYC is "one-time" for REGISTRATION, but details must be UPDATED when they change. An outdated address can cause issues with CAS delivery, communication from AMC, and even redemption processing if the AMC flags the account for address mismatch.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Aadhaar linking to mutual fund accounts helps in eKYC verification, ensures correct CAS delivery, and facilitates Aadhaar-based authentication for online transactions. SEBI has been encouraging Aadhaar-seeding of mutual fund folios for enhanced investor protection.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During portfolio reviews, always check if client details (address, bank, contact, nominee) are current. For elderly clients like Mrs. Lakshmi, offer to help with the paperwork. Proactive KYC maintenance prevents future transaction delays and demonstrates the ongoing service value you provide.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
