<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_56" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[During an NFO, an investor invests Rs. 1,00,000 at the face value of Rs. 10 per unit. After 6 months, the NAV of the scheme rises to Rs. 12. If the investor had instead invested in an existing fund with NAV of Rs. 100 that also rose by 20% in the same period, which investment would have generated higher returns?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The NFO investment would generate higher returns because units were bought at Rs. 10]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The existing fund would generate higher returns because it has a proven track record]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both investments would generate the same 20% return — the starting NAV does not determine returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The returns cannot be compared as the two funds have different NAVs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Calculation:
NFO Fund: Invested Rs. 1,00,000 at Rs. 10/unit = 10,000 units. NAV rises to Rs. 12.
Value = 10,000 x Rs. 12 = Rs. 1,20,000. Return = 20%.

Existing Fund: Invested Rs. 1,00,000 at Rs. 100/unit = 1,000 units. NAV rises 20% to Rs. 120.
Value = 1,000 x Rs. 120 = Rs. 1,20,000. Return = 20%.

Both investments yield exactly Rs. 1,20,000 — a 20% return on Rs. 1,00,000. The absolute NAV is irrelevant; what matters is the PERCENTAGE CHANGE in NAV.

**The Trap:** This is one of the most common misconceptions among mutual fund investors. Many believe buying at Rs. 10 (NFO) is "cheaper" and therefore better than buying at Rs. 100 or Rs. 500 NAV. In reality, you get more units at the lower NAV but each unit appreciates by the same percentage.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI and AMFI have repeatedly highlighted this in investor education campaigns. The NFO face value of Rs. 10 is not a discount — it is simply the starting point. An investor's return depends on the fund's future performance, not the starting NAV.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never use "low NAV" or "only Rs. 10" as a selling point for NFOs. This is a regulatory red flag and a sign of poor investor education. Instead, discuss the scheme's investment strategy, the fund manager's track record, and whether the scheme fills a gap in the client's portfolio. A well-informed investor makes better decisions and stays invested longer.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
