<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When a mutual fund scheme undergoes a fundamental attribute change (such as change in investment objective or scheme type), what right does the investor have?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to vote against the change at a unitholder meeting]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Right to exit the scheme without any exit load within a prescribed period after being notified of the change]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to switch to any other AMC's scheme at no cost]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to receive additional units as compensation for the change]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a scheme's fundamental attributes are changed (investment objective, type, asset allocation pattern, etc.), investors must be notified and given the right to exit the scheme without any exit load within a prescribed period (typically 30 days from the notice). This protects investors from being locked into a scheme that no longer matches their original investment thesis.
**The Trap:** While unitholders may vote on some changes through special resolution, the key RIGHT tested here is the exit-without-load option. Investors can't block the change but can leave without penalty.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers fundamental attribute changes; Series II-B tests the RTA's role in processing exit-load-free redemptions during the prescribed window.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Monitor fundamental attribute change notifications carefully — they're rare but significant. Proactively reach out to affected clients with your analysis of whether the changed scheme still suits their portfolio. The load-free exit window is time-limited, so quick action is essential.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
