<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In the context of the investment triangle (safety, liquidity, returns), which statement is most accurate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual funds score highest on all three dimensions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Bank fixed deposits offer high returns with high safety and high liquidity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No single investment can simultaneously maximize all three dimensions -- there is always a trade-off]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Government securities offer the best combination of safety, liquidity, and returns]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The investment triangle illustrates a fundamental principle: safety, liquidity, and returns are in a state of trade-off. An investment that excels in one or two dimensions must compromise on the third. For example, bank savings accounts are safe and liquid but offer low returns. Equity offers high return potential but lower safety. Real estate may appreciate well but lacks liquidity.

**The Trap:** Option B is tempting because FDs are perceived as "ideal" by many Indian investors, but they actually offer moderate returns (lower than equity and often barely above inflation), high safety, and moderate liquidity (early withdrawal attracts a penalty). No instrument is perfect on all three counts.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This trade-off concept is foundational in NISM V-A and drives the rationale for diversification and mutual fund product design. Each mutual fund category represents a different positioning on this triangle.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the triangle as a visual tool with clients. Draw it on paper, plot different investments, and show how mutual funds offer various positions on this triangle -- from liquid funds (high safety, high liquidity, low returns) to equity funds (high return potential, high liquidity, low safety) -- helping clients choose based on their priority.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
