<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The IEPF provides a special window for prioritized processing of claims. Which category of claimants is eligible for this benefit?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Claimants holding shares worth more than INR 5 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Claimants who are women investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Claimants who are 75 years of age or older]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Claimants who are first-time investors in the securities market]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The IEPF has established a special window for claimants who are 75 years of age or older. These senior citizen claims receive prioritized processing to ensure that elderly investors, who may have limited time and mobility, can recover their unclaimed amounts and shares expeditiously.

**The Trap:** While SEBI and various financial institutions often provide benefits based on investment value or gender, the IEPF special window is specifically age-based (75+ years). This is distinct from the general senior citizen category of 60+ used in banking and taxation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investor protection measures for vulnerable categories appear across NISM certifications. In Series V-A (Mutual Funds), there are specific suitability requirements for senior citizens. Understanding which protection applies to which age threshold is frequently tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a database of investors aged 70+ across your client companies. Proactively reach out to these investors about any unclaimed amounts before the 7-year IEPF transfer deadline. If shares have already been transferred, guide them through the expedited IEPF-5 claim process available under the special window.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
