<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following financial goals would typically be classified as a short-term goal?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Building a retirement corpus over 25 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Saving for a child's higher education in 15 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Accumulating funds for a vacation planned in 6 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Purchasing a house in 8 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Financial goals are classified by time horizon: short-term (up to 3 years), medium-term (3-7 years), and long-term (beyond 7 years). A vacation in 6 months clearly falls within the short-term category. Short-term goals require capital preservation and liquidity, making them suitable for low-risk instruments like liquid funds, ultra-short-duration funds, or bank deposits.

**The Trap:** Option D (8 years) might seem medium-term to some, but it is generally classified as long-term in financial planning frameworks. The exam tests precise classification boundaries. Options A and B are clearly long-term, making C the only short-term goal.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Goal classification drives the entire financial planning and product recommendation process tested in NISM V-A. Short-term goals require debt instruments, medium-term goals use balanced/hybrid funds, and long-term goals benefit from equity exposure.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always start client conversations by listing and classifying their goals. This automatically determines the appropriate product category. A client who says "I want to invest" without a specific goal is harder to advise than one who says "I need Rs. 5 lakh in 6 months for a trip."]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
