<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE about SIP (Systematic Investment Plan) in mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SIP is a separate mutual fund product with its own portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SIP guarantees minimum returns due to rupee cost averaging]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SIP can only be done in equity mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SIP is a method of investing a fixed amount at regular intervals through auto-debit from the investor's bank account]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SIP is an investment method, not a product. It is a facility that allows investors to invest a pre-determined amount at regular intervals (monthly, weekly, quarterly) through an auto-debit mandate from their bank account. SIP can be used to invest in any type of mutual fund scheme — equity, debt, hybrid, or any other category.

**The Trap:** SIP is NOT a guarantee of returns. Many marketing materials overemphasize the benefits of rupee cost averaging, leading investors to believe SIP eliminates risk. While SIP reduces the impact of market timing, the underlying scheme can still generate negative returns.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The minimum SIP amount is typically Rs. 500 per month (varies by AMC and scheme). SIP works through an ECS/NACH mandate, which automatically debits the investor's bank account on the specified date. The investor can stop, pause, or modify the SIP.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SIP is the most powerful tool for building long-term wealth for retail investors. Focus on starting SIPs early and increasing the amount annually (step-up SIP). The key is consistency — discourage clients from stopping SIPs during market downturns, which is exactly when rupee cost averaging works best.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
