<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Deepa discovers that her mutual fund account statement shows a different address than her current residence. What should she do?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Report it to SEBI as a data breach]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Update it only when she makes her next transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ignore it — the address doesn't affect her investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Submit an address change request to the RTA/AMC with the new Proof of Address document]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An outdated address in the folio means important communications (physical CAS, tax documents, scheme notices) may not reach the investor. Deepa should submit an address change request to the RTA/AMC with a new Proof of Address document (Aadhaar, passport, utility bill ≤2 months old, etc.). The change applies to all schemes under that folio with the same AMC.
**The Trap:** Ignoring an incorrect address is not harmless — it can lead to missed communications about fundamental attribute changes, IDCW notifications, tax documents, and even regulatory notices. It's not a data breach (it's likely her old address), but it does need prompt correction.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers the importance of updated KYC; Series II-B tests the process flow for address change requests at the RTA level.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During annual portfolio reviews, verify the client's address on record. Address changes are among the most common but neglected updates. A proactive check prevents missed communications and demonstrates attention to detail.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
