<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following activities does the IEPF undertake using its funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing direct financial subsidies to retail investors for purchasing securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Conducting education programs, media campaigns, seminars, and publishing multilingual booklets and films]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Funding the infrastructure costs of depositories and stock exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Paying salaries of SEBI officials involved in investor grievance handling]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The IEPF utilizes its funds for investor education and awareness activities including education programs, media campaigns, seminars, and publishing multilingual booklets and films. These activities aim to empower investors with knowledge to make informed financial decisions and protect themselves from fraud.

**The Trap:** The IEPF does not provide direct financial subsidies to investors, fund market infrastructure, or pay SEBI salaries. Its mandate is strictly limited to refunding unclaimed amounts, promoting investor awareness through educational activities, and protecting investor interests through knowledge dissemination.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investor education initiatives are relevant across all NISM certifications. SEBI, AMFI, stock exchanges, and depositories all run parallel investor education programs. Understanding which body funds which type of activity helps in answering cross-referencing questions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Leverage IEPF's multilingual educational materials when conducting investor awareness programs in regional languages. These resources are freely available and can supplement your own investor education initiatives. Partnering with IEPF for seminars in smaller cities demonstrates your commitment to financial literacy.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
