<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Priya works as a compliance officer at a Qualified RTA (QRTA) that services 3.5 crore folios. During a SEBI inspection, the regulator specifically examines certain enhanced compliance areas applicable to QRTAs. Which of the following is NOT an area of enhanced monitoring for QRTAs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Data security and business continuity planning]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Internal policy framework and periodic reporting on risk areas]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mandatory listing of the QRTA on a recognized stock exchange]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Governance, investor services, and insurance coverage]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** QRTAs are subject to enhanced monitoring in specific areas: internal policy framework, periodic reporting on risk areas, data security, business continuity planning, governance, investor services, and insurance. However, mandatory stock exchange listing is NOT a QRTA requirement — QRTAs are Critical Infrastructure Institutions but they are not required to be publicly listed companies.

**The Trap:** All three incorrect options list genuine QRTA enhanced monitoring areas. The stock exchange listing option sounds plausible for large entities handling crores of folios, but listing is a corporate governance choice, not a regulatory mandate for QRTAs. This "NOT" question format tests depth of knowledge.

**Cross-Exam Context:** "NOT" or "EXCEPT" format questions require thorough knowledge of all aspects of a regulation. In NISM Series VI (Depository Operations), similar questions test which compliance areas apply to depositories as systemically important infrastructure. The pattern of enhanced monitoring for critical infrastructure is consistent across SEBI's regulatory framework.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you lead compliance at a QRTA like Priya, maintain a comprehensive compliance dashboard covering all six enhanced monitoring areas. Conduct quarterly self-assessments against each area and document findings. This proactive approach ensures readiness for SEBI inspections and demonstrates a culture of compliance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
