<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What happens to unclaimed redemption proceeds and dividends in mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are transferred to the Investor Protection and Education Fund (IPEF)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are forfeited after 7 years and become AMC revenue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[They are deployed as per SEBI guidelines in specified instruments, and investors can claim them at any time with applicable returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are returned to the scheme's NAV pool after 3 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Unclaimed redemption proceeds and dividends are not forfeited — they are deployed by the AMC in specified instruments (typically liquid/overnight funds) as per SEBI guidelines. Investors can claim these amounts at any time, and they receive the returns earned on the deployed amount during the unclaimed period. The Instant Access Facility for overnight/liquid funds further facilitates quick access.
**The Trap:** Unlike some other financial products, unclaimed MF proceeds are NOT transferred to any government fund or forfeited. They remain claimable indefinitely, earning returns for the investor.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers unclaimed amounts; Series II-B tests the RTA's role in tracking and facilitating claims on unclaimed amounts.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Periodically review your client base for unclaimed amounts — the RTA/AMC websites and SEBI's unclaimed amounts dashboard can help identify such amounts. Helping clients recover unclaimed money is a valuable service that builds loyalty and demonstrates your proactive approach.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
