<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the Investor Charter, which of the following is an investor's RIGHT in the mutual fund context?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Right to receive timely account statements, NAV disclosure, and redemption proceeds within prescribed timelines]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to access the fund manager's personal investment portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to change the scheme's investment objective at will]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to guaranteed minimum returns from the scheme]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Investor Charter explicitly lists several rights including: access to scheme information (SID, KIM), timely account statements (CAS/individual), daily NAV disclosure, redemption proceeds within T+1/T+2/T+3 timelines, notification of fundamental attribute changes with exit option, and grievance redressal through SCORES. Guaranteed returns are NOT a right — mutual funds are market-linked.
**The Trap:** 'Guaranteed minimum returns' is not a right in any market-linked investment. The Investor Charter focuses on information transparency, timely service, and grievance mechanisms — not on investment outcomes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers the Investor Charter; Series II-B tests the RTA's role in ensuring these rights are operationally fulfilled.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Print the Investor Charter and keep it accessible during client meetings. When clients understand their rights (and responsibilities), they become better investors. It's also a trust-building tool — showing that the regulatory framework protects their interests.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
