<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Vikram invested his entire Rs. 30 lakh inheritance in a mid-cap sectoral fund focused on the IT sector because his colleague told him it gave 40% returns last year. Which behavioral biases is Vikram most likely exhibiting?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Anchoring bias and loss aversion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Herd mentality and recency bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overconfidence bias and anchoring bias]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Loss aversion and recency bias]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Vikram displays two distinct biases: (1) Herd mentality -- he is following his colleague's recommendation without independent analysis ("my colleague told me"), and (2) Recency bias -- he is making his investment decision based solely on last year's exceptional 40% return, assuming recent past performance will continue. Additionally, he exhibits concentration risk by putting all Rs. 30 lakh in a single sectoral fund.

**The Trap:** Option A includes anchoring bias, which would involve fixating on a specific price point (like a purchase price), not applicable here. Option C includes overconfidence, which involves excessive faith in one's OWN abilities, but Vikram is relying on someone else's tip, not his own analysis. Option D includes loss aversion, which involves reluctance to book losses -- not relevant to Vikram's initial investment decision.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Application questions combining multiple biases are increasingly common in NISM V-A and X-A exams. Candidates must identify the SPECIFIC biases at play, not just recognize that "something is wrong" with the investor's behavior.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client comes with a "hot tip" and wants to invest a lump sum, this is a red flag for both herd mentality and recency bias. Slow down the conversation: (1) Conduct a proper risk assessment, (2) Diversify across asset classes, (3) Use STP (Systematic Transfer Plan) to stagger entry, (4) Show long-term rolling returns, not just last year's performance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
