<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the process of 'Transmission' in mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer of units from one scheme to another within the same AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer of units between two different investors through a market transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Transfer of units to the nominee or legal heir upon the death of the unitholder]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conversion of physical unit certificates to demat form]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Transmission refers to the transfer of mutual fund units from a deceased unitholder to the surviving nominee(s) or legal heir(s). It is a non-financial transaction that changes the ownership of units without involving any purchase or sale. The nominee or legal heir must submit the death certificate, relevant KYC documents, and transmission request form.

**The Trap:** Transmission is different from a "transfer." Transfer is a voluntary sale/gift of units between living individuals, while transmission occurs specifically upon the death of the unitholder. Transfer of mutual fund units is generally restricted (except between family members in certain cases).

**Cross-Exam Context:** If the deceased had nominated, transmission to the nominee is straightforward. Without nomination, legal heirs must produce a succession certificate, probate of will, or letter of administration, which is a longer process.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is where your nomination advice pays off. Help the surviving family members with the transmission process — they are often unfamiliar with mutual fund procedures during a difficult time. Having nomination in place significantly reduces the documentation burden.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
