<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Government securities (G-Secs) are considered to have virtually zero credit risk because:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are traded on stock exchanges with high liquidity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They offer the highest returns among all fixed-income instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[They are backed by the sovereign guarantee of the government]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are insured by the Deposit Insurance Corporation]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Government securities carry sovereign guarantee, meaning the government stands behind the repayment of principal and interest. Since the government has the power to tax and print currency, the probability of default is considered negligible. This is why G-Secs are treated as "risk-free" instruments for credit risk purposes.

**The Trap:** Option D is a clever distractor because DICGC (Deposit Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation) does insure bank deposits up to Rs. 5 lakh, but this applies to bank deposits, not government securities. Option A confuses liquidity with creditworthiness -- while G-Secs are indeed traded, their low credit risk comes from the sovereign guarantee, not exchange trading.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of sovereign guarantee and risk-free rate is foundational for NISM V-A, V-B, and XII. G-Sec yields serve as the benchmark risk-free rate in the Sharpe ratio and CAPM calculations.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When conservative clients want "zero risk," explain that even G-Secs carry interest rate risk and inflation risk -- only credit risk is virtually zero. Gilt mutual funds, which invest in G-Secs, can show negative returns in rising interest rate environments despite holding "risk-free" securities.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
