<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ravi is dissatisfied with his mutual fund scheme's performance and wants to complain. What should you advise him?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sue the AMC for not meeting promised returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Complain to the fund manager directly about the underperformance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Explain that scheme performance is market-linked and not a valid grievance; however, if there are operational issues (delayed statements, wrong NAV application, etc.), those can be escalated through the proper grievance mechanism]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File a complaint on SEBI SCORES immediately — poor performance is a valid grievance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Investment performance is market-linked and subject to market risks — poor returns are NOT a valid grievance under the investor charter or SCORES framework. However, operational issues (delayed redemption proceeds, incorrect NAV application, statement errors, non-receipt of IDCW, etc.) are legitimate grievances that can be escalated through RTA → AMC → SEBI SCORES.
**The Trap:** SCORES is not a platform for investment performance complaints — it handles service and process failures. Filing a performance complaint wastes the investor's time and SEBI's resources.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A clearly distinguishes between valid and invalid grievances; this understanding is critical for distributor/RTA professionals.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use this conversation as an opportunity for investor education — explain that mutual fund returns reflect market movements, not AMC/distributor promises. If the client's risk profile doesn't match the scheme, suggest a switch to a more suitable scheme rather than filing a complaint.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
