<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meena Sharma, a 55-year-old retired school teacher from Jaipur, has mutual fund investments across 3 schemes of PQR Mutual Fund. She visits the Investor Service Centre (ISC) with the following requests:

Request 1: She has recently moved from Jaipur to Udaipur and wants to update her address. She carries her new Aadhaar card showing the Udaipur address.

Request 2: She has opened a new bank account with a different bank (Bank of Rajasthan) and wants all future redemption proceeds and IDCW payouts to go to this new account. She carries a cancelled cheque of the new account and her old bank's passbook.

Request 3: She wants to add her daughter (Priya, age 28) and son (Rahul, age 32) as nominees with 60% and 40% allocation respectively. Currently, no nominee is registered.

Request 4: She has not received her CAS for the last 6 months and wants to understand why and get it reissued.

Request 5: She wants to know if she can consolidate her 3 folios — Folio 1 is in her single name, Folio 2 is joint with her husband (Meena + Suresh), and Folio 3 is in her single name with a different bank account.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> For Request 3 (nomination addition), what must the RTA verify about Meena's nomination request?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the nominee names and PAN numbers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[That the nominees are immediate family members of Meena]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[That both nominees are above 18 and have completed MF KYC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[That the percentage allocation totals 100% (60% + 40% = 100%), both nominees are individuals, and the nomination form is properly witnessed]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The RTA must verify: (1) percentage allocation totals exactly 100% (Priya 60% + Rahul 40% = 100% — correct), (2) nominees are individuals (not institutions/trusts), (3) the nomination form is properly filled and witnessed (signatures of witness required). Nominees do NOT need to be family members — any individual can be a nominee. Nominees also don't need their own MF KYC at the time of nomination.
**The Trap:** There's no requirement that nominees be family members — Meena could even nominate a friend or charity. The percentage must total exactly 100%, and the form must be properly witnessed. Nominee KYC becomes relevant only at the time of transmission, not at nomination.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers nomination rules; Series II-B tests the RTA's validation checklist for nomination forms.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Double-check the percentage allocation — it's the most common error in nomination forms. If the percentages don't add to 100%, the form will be rejected. Also ensure the witness (who is NOT a nominee) signs the form — missing witness signatures cause unnecessary delays.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
