<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_57" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Mrs. Lakshmi, a 62-year-old retired school teacher, has accumulated a mutual fund corpus of Rs. 30 lakh across three equity diversified schemes of the same AMC (Rs. 10 lakh each). She needs a monthly income of approximately Rs. 20,000 to supplement her pension. Her KYC was done 8 years ago with her school address; she has since moved to a new residence. She has no nominee registered in any of her folios. Her Aadhaar is not linked to her mutual fund accounts. She recently redeemed Rs. 5 lakh from one scheme but has not received the proceeds even after 5 working days.

Question 1: Mrs. Lakshmi wants a reliable monthly income of Rs. 20,000 from her mutual fund corpus. Which of the following is the MOST suitable recommendation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Switch all holdings to IDCW Payout option as dividends provide regular income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Switch to IDCW Re-investment option to grow the corpus and then withdraw as needed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Set up an SWP of Rs. 20,000 per month from the Growth option of one or more schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Redeem the entire Rs. 30 lakh and deposit in a fixed deposit for monthly interest]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SWP from the Growth option is the most suitable for Mrs. Lakshmi because: (1) It provides a fixed, predictable monthly income of Rs. 20,000 — unlike IDCW where the amount and timing are uncertain. (2) It is tax-efficient — only the capital gains component of each SWP withdrawal is taxed, not the entire amount. (3) The remaining corpus stays invested and continues to grow. (4) The annual withdrawal rate is Rs. 2.4 lakh from Rs. 30 lakh = 8%, which is sustainable if the equity fund earns more than this over time.

**The Trap:** IDCW Payout sounds like "income" but is unreliable — the AMC decides if, when, and how much to distribute. Mrs. Lakshmi cannot plan her monthly expenses around IDCW. IDCW Re-investment defeats the purpose as no cash flow is generated. Complete redemption to FD would trigger large capital gains tax and lose equity growth potential.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For a retiree like Mrs. Lakshmi, the combination of Growth option + SWP provides: predictable cash flow, tax efficiency, inflation protection (corpus remains in equity), and control over withdrawal amount. This is widely considered the best practice for generating retirement income from equity mutual funds.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When setting up SWP for retirees, calculate the withdrawal rate carefully. Mrs. Lakshmi's Rs. 20,000/month (Rs. 2.4 lakh/year) from Rs. 30 lakh is an 8% withdrawal rate. While this is on the higher side, equity funds have historically delivered higher long-term returns. Review and adjust the SWP amount annually based on corpus value and her income needs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
