<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_51" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[SEBI renamed the "Dividend" option in mutual funds to "IDCW" in 2021. What does IDCW stand for?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Income Distribution and Capital Wealth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investment Distribution cum Capital Worth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Interim Dividend cum Capital Withdrawal]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated the renaming from "Dividend" to "IDCW — Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal" in April 2021. This was done to address the widespread misconception that mutual fund "dividends" were additional income similar to stock dividends. The new name explicitly indicates that distributions may include a capital withdrawal component, not just income.

**The Trap:** The acronym IDCW must be remembered precisely. "Income Distribution CUM Capital Withdrawal" — the "cum" means "along with" or "combined with." It indicates the distribution is a combination of income and capital return, clarifying that the investor may be receiving back their own capital.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This renaming was part of SEBI's broader investor education initiative. Mutual fund distributors were also required to explain the NAV impact of IDCW distributions to investors. All scheme documents, fact sheets, and marketing materials were updated to reflect the new terminology.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the IDCW terminology consistently in all client communications. When discussing distribution options, always explain that IDCW reduces the NAV — the money comes from the scheme's assets, not from external sources. A simple illustration comparing pre and post-IDCW NAV is very effective in explaining this concept.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
