<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Loss aversion bias implies that investors:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tend to ignore losses and focus only on gains]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Feel the pain of losses more intensely than the pleasure of equivalent gains]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Always sell losing investments immediately to cut losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Prefer investments with zero possibility of loss regardless of return potential]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Loss aversion, identified by Kahneman and Tversky in Prospect Theory, states that the psychological pain of losing Rs. 1,000 is approximately twice as intense as the pleasure derived from gaining Rs. 1,000. This asymmetry leads investors to hold losing investments too long (hoping to avoid realizing the loss) and sell winning investments too quickly (to "lock in" gains).

**The Trap:** Option C is the opposite of what loss-averse investors typically do -- they actually HOLD losing investments (reluctant to book the loss) rather than selling immediately. Option A reverses the bias entirely. Option D describes extreme risk aversion, not loss aversion specifically.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Loss aversion and its consequences are tested in NISM V-A and X-A. The "disposition effect" (selling winners too early, holding losers too long) is a direct consequence of loss aversion and may be tested separately.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client refuses to redeem a poorly performing fund because "I don't want to book a loss," recognize this as loss aversion. Reframe the conversation: "The question is not what you paid, but whether this fund is the best place for your money going forward." Help them evaluate future potential, not past prices.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
