<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Who can be appointed as the Nodal Officer for IEPF-related matters in a company?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any employee designated by the Human Resources department]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A Director, Chief Financial Officer, or Company Secretary of the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The statutory auditor of the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any external consultant appointed by the Board of Directors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The IEPF rules mandate that the Nodal Officer must be a Director, Chief Financial Officer (CFO), or Company Secretary (CS) of the company. This ensures the person responsible for IEPF compliance holds a position of statutory authority and accountability within the corporate governance structure.

**The Trap:** The "any employee" option sounds reasonable but lacks the statutory backing required. External consultants and auditors cannot serve as Nodal Officers because the role requires an internal officer with fiduciary responsibility. The Nodal Officer's details must be displayed on the company website, and any change must be communicated to the IEPF Authority within 7 days via Form IEPF-2.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Corporate governance roles are tested extensively in NISM Series II-A and NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking). Understanding who holds specific statutory responsibilities — like the Nodal Officer, Compliance Officer, or KMP — is a cross-cutting competency.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As an RTA, maintain an updated directory of Nodal Officers and Deputy Nodal Officers for all client companies. When processing IEPF claims, direct claimants to the correct Nodal Officer at the company's registered office for faster resolution.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
