<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_59" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Mrs. Lakshmi has no nominee registered in any of her three mutual fund folios. She has two children — a son and a daughter — and wants to split her holdings equally between them in case of her death.

Question 3: What should Mrs. Lakshmi do regarding nomination, and what are the implications if she does not nominate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nomination is optional for senior citizens, so she can ignore it without any consequences]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She can nominate only one person per folio, so she must choose either her son or daughter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[She should nominate both children with 50% allocation each in all folios; without nomination, her children will need a succession certificate or probate to claim the investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should create a joint holding with her children instead of nomination]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mrs. Lakshmi can nominate up to 3 persons in each folio with a specified percentage split. She should nominate her son (50%) and daughter (50%) in all three folios. Without nomination, upon her death, her children would need to obtain a succession certificate from court or probate of will (if she has one), which is a lengthy, expensive legal process that could take months or even years.

**The Trap:** Nomination does not override a will. If Mrs. Lakshmi makes a will that specifies a different distribution than the nomination, the will prevails. The nominee acts as a custodian until the legal heirs claim their rightful share. However, nomination GREATLY simplifies the immediate transmission process.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Since Mrs. Lakshmi has no nominee, her folios may already be flagged by the AMC as non-compliant with the mandatory nomination disclosure requirement. She should update all three folios immediately. The nomination is a non-financial transaction processed by the AMC/RTA.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For elderly clients, nomination and estate planning discussions are critical but sensitive. Approach it professionally — explain the practical difficulties families face without nomination. Offer to help Mrs. Lakshmi complete the nomination forms for all folios in a single sitting. This is exactly the kind of value-added service that sets a good distributor apart.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
