<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which form must an investor file online at iepf.gov.in to claim shares and unclaimed amounts transferred to the IEPF?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Form IEPF-2]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Form IEPF-5]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Form IEPF-1]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Form IEPF-7]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An investor who wishes to claim shares or unclaimed amounts that have been transferred to the IEPF must file Form IEPF-5 online at the IEPF website (iepf.gov.in). Along with the form, the claimant must submit an indemnity bond and supporting documents to the company's Nodal Officer at the registered office.

**The Trap:** Form IEPF-2 is used by companies to report unclaimed amounts and Nodal Officer changes — it is a company-filed form, not an investor-filed form. Mixing up IEPF-2 and IEPF-5 is the most common error. Remember: IEPF-2 = Company reporting, IEPF-5 = Investor claiming.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Form-specific questions appear frequently in NISM exams. In Series II-A, knowing which forms are filed by companies versus investors is critical. Similarly, in NISM Series V-A, understanding which forms mutual fund distributors versus investors file is equally important.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When guiding investors through the IEPF claim process, prepare a step-by-step checklist: (1) File IEPF-5 online, (2) Take printout with SRN, (3) Execute indemnity bond, (4) Gather identity documents, (5) Submit physical documents to Nodal Officer at company's registered office. The refund will be credited to the claimant's Aadhaar-linked bank account.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
