<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the Instant Access Facility in the context of mutual fund investor services?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A facility to invest in any mutual fund scheme instantly through UPI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A facility enabling instant redemption of limited amounts from overnight/liquid fund unclaimed amounts without waiting for standard processing timelines]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A feature that allows instant KYC verification for new investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A service that provides instant NAV calculation before market closure]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Instant Access Facility is specifically designed for unclaimed redemption/dividend amounts that have been deployed in overnight or liquid funds as per SEBI guidelines. It allows investors (or their nominees/heirs) to access these unclaimed amounts instantly, without going through the standard redemption processing timelines, facilitating quick recovery of unclaimed assets.
**The Trap:** This is NOT the same as the general instant redemption facility available in liquid/overnight funds (which has its own limits). The Instant Access Facility is specifically for unclaimed amounts deployed in these schemes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B specifically tests this facility as part of the unclaimed amounts framework; understanding the distinction from regular instant redemption is important.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When helping clients recover unclaimed amounts, mention the Instant Access Facility — it eliminates the usual waiting period and provides immediate liquidity. This is especially valuable for nominees/heirs who may have urgent financial needs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
