<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Priya, age 17, has mutual fund investments made by her father as guardian. She turns 18 next month. What happens to her SIP if no action is taken?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The SIP continues normally as her father remains the guardian]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The SIP amount doubles since she is now an adult]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The SIP and all transactions will be frozen until she completes fresh KYC in her own name and the status is changed from minor to major]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The SIP will be automatically transferred to her father's account]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a minor turns 18, the guardian's authority to operate the account ceases. The account is frozen — no financial or non-financial transactions (including SIP installments) can be processed. To reactivate, Priya must complete fresh KYC in her own name, submit a status change request from minor to major, and provide her own bank account details.

**The Trap:** This is not an automatic process. Many families are unaware of this requirement and are surprised when SIP bounces or transactions are rejected after the minor turns 18. The freeze applies to ALL transactions, not just new purchases.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The minor-to-major status change is a critical non-financial transaction that has financial implications (frozen SIPs, inability to redeem). AMCs/RTAs typically send advance notifications, but the onus is on the investor/guardian to complete the process on time.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is a high-value service opportunity. Reach out to families with minor accounts 2-3 months before the child turns 18. Help them complete the KYC and status change process seamlessly. This earns client loyalty and demonstrates proactive service that justifies your commission.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
