<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Meena, a 55-year-old retiree with a pension of Rs. 40,000 per month and savings of Rs. 80 lakh, approaches you for investment advice. She needs regular income to supplement her pension and cannot afford to lose her capital. Which asset allocation would be MOST suitable for her?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[80% equity mutual funds, 10% debt funds, 10% gold]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% equity mutual funds, 30% debt funds, 20% real estate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[20% equity mutual funds, 60% debt funds, 10% liquid funds, 10% gold]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in bank fixed deposits for maximum safety]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Meena's profile indicates: (1) Conservative risk profile (retiree, cannot afford capital loss), (2) Need for regular income (pension supplement), (3) Capital preservation is primary goal. The appropriate allocation is debt-heavy (60%) for stability and income, with modest equity (20%) to beat inflation over time, liquid funds (10%) for emergency needs, and gold (10%) as a hedge. This balances income generation with inflation protection.

**The Trap:** Option A is an aggressive allocation completely unsuitable for a retiree. Option D (100% FDs) seems safe but fails to protect against inflation and misses better after-tax efficiency of debt mutual funds (indexation benefit for funds held over 3 years). Option B includes real estate which is illiquid and inappropriate for someone needing regular income.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Suitability-based recommendation questions are high-weightage in NISM V-A. The exam tests whether candidates can match investor profiles to appropriate asset allocation. Key variables: age, income needs, risk tolerance, time horizon, and liquidity requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For retirees, the "bucket strategy" works well: Bucket 1 (1-2 years' expenses in liquid/ultra-short funds for immediate needs), Bucket 2 (3-7 years' expenses in short-term debt funds), Bucket 3 (remaining in balanced/equity funds for long-term inflation protection). This provides income certainty while maintaining growth potential.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
