<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Patel invested Rs.5,00,000 in DEF Equity Fund on March 15. He submitted his redemption request for the entire holding on April 5 (a Monday, working day) before the 3:00 PM cutoff. The following events occurred:

Event 1: By April 9 (Thursday, T+3 working days, with no holidays in between), Vikram had not received his redemption proceeds in his bank account.

Event 2: He called the AMC's customer care on April 9 and was told the delay was due to 'technical issues at the RTA' and that the proceeds would be credited within 2 more working days.

Event 3: By April 13 (Tuesday), the proceeds were still not received. Vikram sent an email complaint to the AMC.

Event 4: The AMC responded on April 16 (Friday) saying the RTA has been instructed to process the payment and it should arrive by April 20.

Event 5: On April 20, Vikram received only Rs.4,85,000 instead of the expected Rs.4,97,500 (based on the redemption NAV and units held). He was not given any explanation for the shortfall of Rs.12,500.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Was the AMC's customer care response on April 9 (attributing the delay to 'RTA technical issues') adequate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, RTA issues are a valid reason for redemption delay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, as long as the AMC provided a revised timeline]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because the AMC cannot control the RTA's operations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, the AMC is responsible for ensuring timely redemption regardless of RTA issues — the AMC cannot transfer its regulatory obligation to the RTA's operational difficulties]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AMC is ultimately responsible for ensuring timely redemption payouts — this regulatory obligation cannot be delegated or excused by citing RTA operational issues. The AMC-RTA relationship is contractual, and the AMC must ensure its service providers meet regulatory timelines. From the investor's perspective, the AMC is the counterparty, not the RTA.
**The Trap:** While the RTA may be operationally responsible for the delay, the regulatory accountability lies with the AMC. 'RTA technical issues' may explain the cause but does not excuse the violation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers AMC responsibilities; Series II-B highlights that while RTAs process transactions, the AMC bears regulatory responsibility for investor-facing timelines.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client faces a redemption delay, hold the AMC accountable — not the RTA. The AMC chose its RTA and is responsible for their performance. Document the delay and the AMC's response, as this creates a record for potential SCORES complaint and interest claim.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
