<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[How does the centralised demise reporting mechanism benefit the investor's family?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It cancels all SIP and STP instructions immediately upon reporting]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It freezes all investments permanently until court intervention]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It automatically distributes the deceased investor's assets to nominees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A single report through the KRA blocks unauthorized transactions across all financial intermediaries, protecting the deceased's assets while the claim process is initiated]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The centralised mechanism allows a single report through the KRA to protect the deceased investor's assets across ALL linked financial intermediaries simultaneously. It blocks debit (withdrawal) transactions to prevent unauthorized access while allowing the claim/transmission process to proceed through individual intermediaries. This is much more efficient than reporting to each AMC/intermediary separately.
**The Trap:** The mechanism blocks unauthorized transactions — it doesn't permanently freeze or automatically distribute assets. The claim process still needs to be pursued through each intermediary, but the protection is immediate and universal.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B tests this mechanism as a key investor protection feature; understanding its scope and limitations is important for RTA professionals.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Educate your clients' families about this mechanism now — don't wait for an emergency. A quick report through the KRA immediately protects all investments. Then, the family can proceed with transmission at each AMC/intermediary at their own pace, knowing the assets are secure.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
