<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the primary purpose of the Investor Education and Protection Fund (IEPF) established under the Companies Act, 2013?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To refund unclaimed amounts, promote investor awareness, and protect investor interests]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To fund stock exchange infrastructure development across India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To provide guaranteed returns on equity investments to retail investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To compensate investors for losses arising from stock market volatility]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The IEPF was created by the Ministry of Corporate Affairs under Section 125(3) of the Companies Act, 2013, with three core objectives: refunding unclaimed amounts to rightful owners, promoting investor awareness through education programs, and protecting overall investor interests. It was established on September 7, 2016.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse IEPF with a compensation fund or a market stabilization fund. The IEPF does not compensate for trading losses or guarantee returns — it specifically deals with unclaimed corporate amounts and investor education.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This concept appears in NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) and Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) exams when discussing investor protection mechanisms. Understanding the distinction between IEPF and Investor Protection Fund (IPF) of stock exchanges is critical.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As an RTA professional, educate your corporate clients about their IEPF obligations. Many companies face penalties for non-compliance with IEPF transfer timelines. Proactively identifying unclaimed amounts helps both the company and its investors.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
