<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is CKYC (Central KYC) in the context of mutual fund investments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A KYC process specific to corporate investors only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A centralized KYC registry maintained by CERSAI where one-time KYC is valid across all financial institutions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A KYC process conducted only by the Central Government]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A KYC verification method using only credit bureau data]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** CKYC (Central KYC) is a centralized repository maintained by CERSAI (Central Registry of Securitisation Asset Reconstruction and Security Interest of India). Once an investor completes KYC with any financial institution (bank, mutual fund, insurance company), the KYC record is uploaded to CKYC, and a 14-digit KIN (KYC Identification Number) is generated. This KIN can be used across all financial institutions, eliminating the need for repeated KYC.

**The Trap:** CKYC is different from KRA-KYC. KRA (KYC Registration Agency) was the earlier system specific to capital markets (mutual funds, shares). CKYC is a broader system covering all financial services sectors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The CKYC system was introduced to implement the "one KYC" vision across financial services, reducing paperwork and improving investor convenience. Both individual and non-individual investors can use CKYC.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help clients complete CKYC when they do their first mutual fund investment. This saves them from repeated KYC when they open bank accounts, buy insurance, or invest in other financial products. The KIN number should be preserved for future use.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
