<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the role of RTAs in providing investor education?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs are not involved in investor education; it's solely the AMC's responsibility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[RTAs provide educational materials and support investor awareness initiatives to help investors make informed decisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs offer certified financial planning courses to investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs conduct mandatory investor awareness workshops every quarter]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** RTAs contribute to investor education by providing educational materials, supporting AMC-driven investor awareness initiatives, and making information accessible to investors through their platforms. While the primary investor education responsibility lies with AMCs and AMFI, RTAs play a supporting role given their direct touchpoint with investors through ISCs and digital platforms.
**The Trap:** RTAs are not educational institutions — they don't conduct formal courses or workshops. Their role is supportive, providing materials and information that help investors understand processes and their rights.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers the broader investor education ecosystem; Series II-B specifically tests the RTA's contribution to this effort.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Leverage RTA-provided educational materials in your client interactions — they're neutral, authoritative, and compliant. Using AMC-neutral educational content (instead of sales material from a specific AMC) builds trust and positions you as an unbiased adviser.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
