<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[According to the Investor Charter for RTAs, which of the following is listed as a right of investors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Right to approach the RTA, Depository, Company, Stock Exchange, or SEBI for grievance redressal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to appoint the company's auditor at the AGM]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to receive guaranteed minimum returns on their investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Right to demand physical share certificates even after mandatory dematerialization]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Investor Charter for RTAs (Annexure 13.5) explicitly lists the right of investors to approach multiple forums for grievance redressal — including the RTA, Depository, Company, Stock Exchange, or SEBI. This multi-layered escalation framework ensures investors are never without recourse.

**The Trap:** Guaranteed returns are never a right in the securities market — this is a fundamental principle tested across all NISM exams. Appointing auditors is the right of shareholders at AGM but is not part of the RTA Investor Charter. Demanding physical certificates contradicts mandatory demat requirements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investor rights under various charters are tested in NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund Charter), Series VI (Depository Charter), and Series II-A (RTA Charter). The common thread is the right to fair treatment, information access, and multi-level grievance escalation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Display the complete Investor Charter prominently on your website and at all investor service centres. Train front-desk staff to guide investors through the escalation matrix: first approach the RTA, then the Company, then the Depository/Exchange, and finally SEBI. Document each escalation step for compliance records.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
