<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Mr. Iyer passes away with Rs. 15 lakh in mutual fund holdings. He had nominated his wife with 100% allocation. Which of the following is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The mutual fund units are automatically transferred to the wife's demat account on death]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The wife must submit a transmission request with death certificate and KYC documents to claim the units]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The units are automatically redeemed and proceeds deposited in the wife's bank account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The nomination becomes void if the amount exceeds Rs. 10 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Even with valid nomination, the transmission is not automatic. The nominee (wife) must submit a formal transmission request to the AMC/RTA along with: (1) death certificate of Mr. Iyer, (2) her own KYC documents, (3) transmission request form, and (4) cancelled cheque/bank details. The AMC then transfers the units to her name or redeems and pays proceeds as per her instructions.

**The Trap:** Nomination makes the process EASIER, not AUTOMATIC. Without nomination, the legal heirs would need to submit a succession certificate or probate of will, which involves a court process and significantly more time and expense.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The nominee receives the units as a trustee for the legal heirs, not as the absolute owner (as per Supreme Court rulings). If there is a will that specifies a different beneficiary, the will takes precedence over the nomination. However, the AMC transfers to the nominee — disputes between nominees and legal heirs are civil matters.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During this difficult time, be the guide the family needs. Help the surviving spouse with all documentation for transmission. Have a checklist ready: death certificate (multiple copies), nominee's KYC, bank details, and the transmission form. Your support during such times builds lifelong loyalty with the family.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
