<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Anchoring bias in investing refers to the tendency of an investor to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Follow the investment decisions of other investors in the market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rely heavily on the first piece of information encountered when making investment decisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overestimate their ability to predict market movements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Give more weight to recent events while ignoring historical data]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Anchoring bias occurs when investors fixate on a specific reference point (the "anchor") and make subsequent decisions based on that anchor rather than on objective analysis. For example, an investor who bought a stock at Rs. 500 may refuse to sell at Rs. 400, anchoring to their purchase price rather than evaluating the stock's current fundamentals.

**The Trap:** Option A describes herd mentality, Option C describes overconfidence bias, and Option D describes recency bias. Each is a distinct behavioral bias, and the exam frequently tests the ability to distinguish between them. The key identifier for anchoring is the fixation on a specific reference point.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Behavioral biases are increasingly featured in NISM V-A and X-A (Investment Adviser). Common exam anchoring examples include: fixating on a stock's 52-week high, the IPO price, or the NAV at which a fund was purchased.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients often say "I'll sell when my investment gets back to the price I bought it at." This is classic anchoring. Help them evaluate whether the investment has future potential based on current fundamentals, not their historical purchase price.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
