<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following investor risk profiles is most likely to have the highest allocation to equity in their portfolio?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Moderate investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Aggressive investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk-averse investor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An aggressive investor has a high risk tolerance, a long investment horizon, and seeks capital appreciation. Their portfolio typically has the highest allocation to equity (70-80% or more) because they can withstand short-term volatility in pursuit of higher long-term returns. Conservative investors prioritize capital preservation and favor debt/fixed income, while moderate investors balance between the two.

**The Trap:** Option D (Risk-averse investor) is essentially synonymous with conservative investor and would have the LOWEST equity allocation. The question tests whether candidates can correctly map risk profiles to asset allocation strategies. "Risk-averse" and "conservative" both indicate low risk tolerance.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Risk profiling is a key regulatory requirement under SEBI guidelines for mutual fund distributors (NISM V-A) and investment advisers (X-A). Distributors must assess client risk profiles before recommending products -- this is a compliance and suitability requirement.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always conduct a formal risk assessment before recommending funds. A young, high-earning professional MIGHT be aggressive, but if they have low emotional tolerance for losses, they may actually be moderate. Risk profiling must consider both risk capacity (financial ability) and risk tolerance (emotional comfort).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
