<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the primary benefit of Rupee Cost Averaging achieved through a Systematic Investment Plan (SIP)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It guarantees positive returns over any time period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It eliminates the risk of investing in equity markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It averages out the purchase cost by buying more units when NAV is low and fewer when NAV is high]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It ensures the investor always buys at the lowest NAV]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** With SIP, a fixed amount is invested at regular intervals. When the NAV is low, more units are purchased; when the NAV is high, fewer units are purchased. Over time, this averages out the per-unit cost, typically resulting in a lower average cost than the average NAV during the period. This is called Rupee Cost Averaging.

**The Trap:** Rupee Cost Averaging does NOT guarantee profits. In a consistently declining market, the average cost will keep falling but the investment value may still be lower than the total amount invested. SIP reduces timing risk but does not eliminate market risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SIP is a method of investing, not a product. The underlying scheme still carries its inherent risks. SIP works best in volatile markets where NAV fluctuates, giving the investor the benefit of buying at various price points.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use actual examples to show clients how SIP works in volatile markets. Show how investing Rs. 10,000 monthly across fluctuating NAVs results in a lower average cost than investing a lump sum. But always disclose that SIP does not guarantee returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
