<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Recency bias in investing causes an investor to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Give excessive importance to recent events and trends while underweighting long-term historical data]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fixate on the purchase price of an investment as a reference point]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overestimate their own ability to pick winning investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Avoid making any investment decisions due to fear of recent market crashes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Recency bias is the cognitive tendency to weigh recent events and experiences more heavily than earlier ones. In investing, this means an investor might chase recently outperforming funds or avoid asset classes that have recently underperformed, without considering longer-term performance patterns or fundamentals.

**The Trap:** Option B describes anchoring bias (fixating on a reference point), Option C describes overconfidence bias, and Option D describes a possible consequence of fear but not recency bias itself. The key distinguishing feature of recency bias is the disproportionate emphasis on RECENT data over HISTORICAL patterns.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Recency bias is tested alongside other behavioral biases in NISM V-A and X-A. A classic example: investors pouring money into small-cap funds after two years of stellar small-cap performance, ignoring that such outperformance is often followed by mean reversion.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Combat recency bias with long-term data. When clients want to invest solely in the "hot" sector of the last quarter, show them 10-year rolling return data. Sectors rotate, and last year's winner is often this year's laggard. SIP across diversified funds neutralizes this bias.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
