<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the IDCW Re-investment option, what happens when an income distribution is declared by the scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The distribution amount is paid out to the investor's bank account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The existing units are split to reflect the distribution]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The distribution amount is used to purchase additional units of the same scheme at ex-IDCW NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The distribution is automatically transferred to a liquid fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In the IDCW Re-investment option, the declared distribution is not paid to the investor in cash. Instead, it is used to buy additional units of the same scheme at the prevailing ex-IDCW NAV. The investor ends up with more units but at a lower NAV per unit. The total investment value remains the same (pre-tax).

**The Trap:** IDCW Re-investment is NOT the same as Growth option. In Re-investment, the IDCW is first declared (triggering tax liability) and then reinvested. In Growth, no distribution is declared at all, so no tax event occurs until redemption.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Tax treatment differs significantly: IDCW Re-investment is taxed at the time of distribution (TDS applicable), while Growth option defers tax until actual redemption. This makes Growth option generally more tax-efficient for long-term investors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The IDCW Re-investment option creates unnecessary tax events. Unless the client has specific reasons, the Growth option is usually preferable. Help clients understand that reinvestment does not mean tax-free compounding.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
