<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is listed as a "Don't" in the Investor Charter for RTAs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Don't register a nomination for your securities holdings]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Don't share security details with unknown persons]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Don't update your KYC details with the RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Don't encash dividend warrants before the expiry date]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Investor Charter explicitly advises investors not to share their security details (such as folio numbers, transaction PINs, login credentials) with unknown persons. This is a basic investor protection guideline aimed at preventing fraud and unauthorized transactions. Other "Don'ts" include: keeping folios without PAN, keeping folios without nomination, and dealing with unauthorized persons.

**The Trap:** Registering a nomination and updating KYC are listed as "Do's" in the Investor Charter, not "Don'ts." Encashing dividend warrants promptly is also a "Do" — investors should encash them regularly to avoid IEPF transfer. The question tests whether candidates can distinguish between the Do's and Don'ts lists.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investor awareness guidelines and Do's/Don'ts are tested in NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) and Series VI (Depository Operations) as well. The underlying principle of protecting personal financial information is universal across all securities market certifications.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Create awareness materials listing the Do's and Don'ts prominently at all investor service centres. Conduct periodic investor awareness workshops highlighting real-world fraud cases that resulted from sharing security details with unknown persons. Prevention is more effective than grievance redressal after the fact.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
