<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_62" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) is sent to mutual fund investors on a monthly basis for months with transactions. For folios with no transactions during a half-year period, the CAS is sent ________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Half-yearly (once every six months)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Quarterly (once every three months)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annually (once a year)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only on specific request by the investor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** CAS (Consolidated Account Statement) consolidates an investor's mutual fund holdings and transactions across all AMCs into a single statement. The dispatch frequency follows two rules: (1) Monthly CAS is sent for every month in which there is a financial transaction (purchase, redemption, switch, dividend). (2) For folios with no transactions during a half-year period, CAS is sent on a half-yearly basis (for the periods ending September and March). Additionally, investors can register up to 5 bank accounts with their mutual fund folios.

**The Trap:** "Quarterly" (Option B) overstates the frequency for non-transaction folios. "Annually" (Option C) understates it -- investors with no transactions still receive CAS twice a year. "Only on request" (Option D) is wrong -- the half-yearly CAS is sent automatically without any request. The monthly vs. half-yearly distinction based on transaction activity is the key exam point.

**Cross-Exam Context:** CAS is generated by depositories (CDSL/NSDL) in coordination with RTAs. It includes both mutual fund holdings and demat holdings, providing a comprehensive view of the investor's securities portfolio.

**Key Takeaway:** CAS frequency: monthly for months with transactions, half-yearly for non-transaction folios. Sent automatically, not on request.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
