<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a characteristic feature of equity shares as an asset class?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteed fixed returns at regular intervals]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Senior claim over bondholders during liquidation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Ownership stake in the company with potential for capital appreciation and dividends]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maturity date on which the face value is returned to the investor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Equity shares represent ownership in a company. Shareholders participate in the company's profits through dividends (which are not guaranteed) and benefit from capital appreciation if the company's value grows. Unlike debt instruments, equity does not have a maturity date or guaranteed returns.

**The Trap:** Option A describes fixed deposits or bonds with guaranteed interest, not equity. Option B reverses the priority -- equity holders are the LAST to be paid in liquidation, after secured creditors and bondholders. Option D describes bonds/debentures which have a maturity date, not equity shares which are perpetual.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the risk-return characteristics of equity vs. debt is fundamental to NISM V-A. Equity offers the highest long-term return potential but with the highest short-term volatility -- this trade-off drives the entire mutual fund product spectrum.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining equity to new investors, emphasize that "ownership" means sharing in both profits and losses. Unlike FDs where the bank bears all risk, equity investors directly participate in the company's fortunes. This is why equity has historically delivered 12-15% CAGR over long periods in India.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
