<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Priya, aged 32, IT professional, monthly investable surplus of Rs. 40,000. Her daughter Ananya's higher education currently costs Rs. 25,00,000 and is needed in 15 years. Assume education inflation is 10% per annum.

Question 3: What is the approximate inflation-adjusted amount Priya will need for Ananya's education in 15 years?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 62,50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 75,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1,04,43,000 (approximately Rs. 1.04 crore)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50,00,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Using the compound interest formula for inflation adjustment: FV = PV x (1 + inflation)^years = Rs. 25,00,000 x (1.10)^15. Calculating step by step: (1.10)^15 = 4.177. Therefore FV = Rs. 25,00,000 x 4.177 = Rs. 1,04,43,000, approximately Rs. 1.04 crore. Education inflation at 10% more than quadruples the cost in 15 years.

**The Trap:** Option A (Rs. 62.5 lakh) results from using simple interest: 25 lakh + (25 lakh x 10% x 15) = 25 + 37.5 = Rs. 62.5 lakh. This dramatically underestimates the actual need because it ignores the compounding effect of inflation. Option D (Rs. 50 lakh) simply doubles the current cost, which is an arbitrary estimate ignoring any calculation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Future value calculations with education inflation are directly tested in NISM V-A. Remember: education inflation (8-12%) is typically higher than general inflation (5-6%) in India. The exam may provide different inflation rates for different goal categories.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This calculation is the single most impactful conversation tool. Parents are shocked when they see Rs. 25 lakh becoming Rs. 1.04 crore. Then show: "To accumulate Rs. 1.04 crore in 15 years at 12% expected equity return, you need a SIP of approximately Rs. 20,800/month." Starting now makes the goal achievable; delaying 5 years nearly doubles the required SIP.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
