<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rajesh, a 78-year-old retired government officer from Pune, discovers that his shares in ABC Ltd were transferred to the IEPF because his dividends remained unclaimed for 7 years. He wants to reclaim his shares. What is the correct procedure he should follow?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[File Form IEPF-5 online at iepf.gov.in along with an indemnity bond and submit documents to the company's Nodal Officer, with eligibility for prioritized processing under the special window for claimants aged 75 and above]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Write a letter to the Managing Director of ABC Ltd requesting return of shares and wait for a Board resolution]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File a complaint on SEBI SCORES against ABC Ltd for unauthorized transfer of his shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Approach the nearest consumer court and file a complaint against both ABC Ltd and the IEPF Authority]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Rajesh must file Form IEPF-5 online at iepf.gov.in, execute an indemnity bond, and submit supporting documents (Aadhaar, PAN, bank details) to the Nodal Officer at ABC Ltd's registered office. Being 78 years old, he qualifies for the IEPF's special window for claimants aged 75 and above, which ensures prioritized processing of his claim. The refund will be credited to his Aadhaar-linked bank account via electronic transfer.

**The Trap:** Writing to the MD is insufficient — there is a formal process through IEPF-5. Filing on SCORES is inappropriate because the IEPF transfer is a statutory requirement, not an unauthorized act by the company. Consumer court proceedings are unnecessary when a specific regulatory claim mechanism exists.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Scenario-based questions combining multiple concepts (IEPF-5, special window for 75+, Aadhaar-linked refund) are common in NISM exams. Candidates must synthesize procedural knowledge with the specific facts of each scenario.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For elderly claimants like Rajesh, offer end-to-end assistance with the IEPF-5 filing. Help them navigate the online portal, prepare the indemnity bond, and coordinate with the company's Nodal Officer. The special window for 75+ claimants means faster processing — set expectations of quicker turnaround for these investors.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
