<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Priya, aged 32, is an IT professional in Bengaluru earning a monthly salary of Rs. 1,20,000. After monthly expenses of Rs. 60,000 and existing EMIs of Rs. 20,000, she has Rs. 40,000 available for investment. She has the following financial goals: (1) Build an emergency fund of Rs. 3,60,000 (6 months' expenses) -- needed within 1 year; (2) Save for her 3-year-old daughter Ananya's higher education (current cost Rs. 25,00,000) -- needed in 15 years; (3) Build a retirement corpus -- she plans to retire at age 60 (28 years away); (4) Down payment of Rs. 15,00,000 for a house -- needed in 5 years. She currently has Rs. 2,00,000 in a savings account and no other investments. She is comfortable with moderate market fluctuations but panics during sharp market corrections.

Question 1: Based on Priya's goals, which of the following correctly classifies her financial goals by time horizon?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Emergency fund: Short-term; House down payment: Medium-term; Child's education: Long-term; Retirement: Long-term]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Emergency fund: Short-term; House down payment: Short-term; Child's education: Medium-term; Retirement: Long-term]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Emergency fund: Immediate; House down payment: Medium-term; Child's education: Medium-term; Retirement: Long-term]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Emergency fund: Short-term; House down payment: Long-term; Child's education: Long-term; Retirement: Long-term]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Goal classification by time horizon: (1) Emergency fund (1 year) = Short-term (up to 3 years); (2) House down payment (5 years) = Medium-term (3-7 years); (3) Child's education (15 years) = Long-term (beyond 7 years); (4) Retirement (28 years) = Long-term. The standard classification is: Short-term (0-3 years), Medium-term (3-7 years), Long-term (7+ years).

**The Trap:** Option B incorrectly classifies the house down payment (5 years) as short-term and education (15 years) as medium-term. Option C invents an "Immediate" category and misclassifies education as medium-term. Option D incorrectly classifies the 5-year house goal as long-term. The exam tests precise application of standard time horizon classifications.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Goal classification is the first step in financial planning tested in NISM V-A and X-A. Correct classification directly determines the appropriate asset class and product category for each goal.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Create a visual "goal timeline" for clients like Priya. Plot each goal on a horizontal timeline with the target amount. This makes the abstract concept of goal classification tangible and helps prioritize investment allocation. Clients immediately see why different goals need different investment strategies.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
