<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Market risk is also known as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Systematic risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Unsystematic risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Specific risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Idiosyncratic risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Market risk is the risk of losses due to factors that affect the entire market, such as economic recessions, interest rate changes, political events, or pandemics. It is also called systematic risk because it systematically affects all securities in the market and cannot be diversified away. It is measured by beta.

**The Trap:** Options B, C, and D are all terms for the SAME concept -- unsystematic risk, specific risk, and idiosyncratic risk all refer to risk unique to a particular company or sector that CAN be diversified away. The exam tests whether candidates can correctly pair market risk = systematic risk and company-specific risk = unsystematic risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The systematic vs. unsystematic risk distinction is tested in NISM V-A, X-A, and XII. Key exam point: diversification reduces unsystematic risk to near zero, but systematic risk remains even in a perfectly diversified portfolio. This is why the market demands a risk premium for bearing systematic risk.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask "why did my diversified fund fall during a crash?" explain systematic risk. A diversified equity fund reduces company-specific risk but cannot protect against market-wide downturns. Only asset allocation across equity, debt, and gold can mitigate the impact of systematic risk on the overall portfolio.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
