<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Suresh wants to update his address, change his bank account, add a nominee, and request a CAS — all in one visit to the ISC. How should the RTA process these requests?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only two changes can be processed per visit; the rest must wait]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Each request is processed separately with its own documentation requirements and verification process]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All requests are processed through a single combined form]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Address and bank change need AMC approval; nominee and CAS can be processed by RTA]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Each service request has its own documentation requirement and verification process: address change needs new PoA, bank change needs old and new account proof, nominee addition needs the nomination form with witness, and CAS can be generated as an immediate service. While all can be initiated in one visit, each follows its own processing workflow and timeline.
**The Trap:** There's no limit on the number of requests per visit, but they cannot be combined into a single form — each has distinct documentation and compliance requirements. The RTA processes each independently.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B tests the RTA's ability to handle multiple service requests simultaneously while maintaining separate compliance processes for each.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client visits for multiple changes, prepare ALL documentation in advance. Create a master checklist covering: address change (new PoA), bank change (old + new account proof), nominee (form + witness signatures), and any other requests. One well-prepared visit is better than three incomplete ones.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
