<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What happens to the voting rights attached to shares transferred to the IEPF demat account?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The IEPF Authority exercises the voting rights on behalf of the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The voting rights are permanently extinguished]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The company's Board of Directors exercises the voting rights]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The voting rights remain frozen until the rightful owner claims the shares]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When shares are transferred to the IEPF demat account, the voting rights attached to those shares are frozen — they cannot be exercised by anyone. The rights remain suspended until the rightful owner files a claim through Form IEPF-5 and the shares are returned. This protects the original investor's ownership interest.

**The Trap:** The option suggesting IEPF Authority exercises voting rights sounds plausible but would create a conflict of interest and is legally incorrect. The rights are not extinguished — they are merely frozen, preserving the investor's entitlement upon successful claim.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Voting rights and their restrictions are tested in NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) and Series XII (Securities Markets Foundation). Understanding when voting rights can be frozen, restricted, or suspended is a core competency across capital market certifications.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When communicating with investors about IEPF transfers, reassure them that their voting rights are preserved. This encourages timely claims and reduces investor anxiety. The IEPF transfer is not a forfeiture — it is a protective custody mechanism with full restoration upon claim.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
