<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is pledging of mutual fund units?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Selling mutual fund units at a premium to another investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Using mutual fund units as collateral/security for a loan without transferring ownership]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Converting mutual fund units from one AMC to another]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transferring mutual fund units to a trust for estate planning]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Pledging allows unitholders to offer their mutual fund units as collateral/security against a loan from a bank or financial institution. The ownership of units remains with the investor, but a lien is marked on the units in favor of the lender. The investor cannot redeem pledged units without the lender's consent.

**The Trap:** Pledging does not transfer ownership. The investor continues to be the unitholder and receives all benefits (IDCW, bonus) except the right to redeem the pledged units. If the investor defaults on the loan, the lender can invoke the pledge and redeem the units.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The pledging process involves the investor submitting a pledge request to the AMC/RTA, which marks a lien on the specified units. De-pledging (removal of lien) requires consent from the pledgee (lender).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Pledging is a useful facility for clients who need short-term liquidity but do not want to redeem their mutual fund investments. It avoids redemption-related capital gains tax and keeps the investment growth potential intact. Guide clients to explore this option before suggesting redemption for emergency needs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
