<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Phase II of online grievance processing for RTAs, what key development was mandated from July 1, 2024?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Each RTA must develop its own mobile application for grievance filing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All RTAs must integrate their systems with the SEBI SCORES platform directly]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs must appoint dedicated grievance officers in every district of India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Qualified RTAs (QRTAs) must establish a common website for online grievance processing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The online processing framework was rolled out in two phases. Phase I required each RTA to have a functional website with RTA information and an online mechanism for grievance filing. Phase II, effective from July 1, 2024, mandated that Qualified RTAs (QRTAs) establish a common website for streamlined online grievance processing, creating a unified platform for investors.

**The Trap:** Phase II is specifically about a "common website by QRTAs" — not individual mobile apps, direct SCORES integration, or physical office requirements. The concept of a shared platform among QRTAs is unique and tests whether candidates understand the phased implementation approach.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Phased implementation of regulatory requirements is a common approach by SEBI, seen in KYC centralization, T+1 settlement rollout, and now online grievance processing. Understanding the timeline and scope of each phase is frequently tested in NISM exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If your organization is a QRTA, ensure your technology team is aligned with the common website specifications. If you are a smaller RTA, monitor the common website framework as it may eventually extend to all RTAs. Either way, ensure your internal grievance tracking system can interface with the common platform.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
