<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the Investor Charter, what must an AMC do before changing a scheme's fundamental attributes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Simply notify investors through the next CAS]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtain prior approval from SEBI only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Notify investors and provide an exit option without exit load for a prescribed period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conduct a mandatory unitholder meeting and obtain 100% consent]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Before changing fundamental attributes (investment objective, scheme type, asset allocation, etc.), the AMC must: (1) notify investors in writing about the proposed change, (2) provide a period (typically 30 days) during which investors can exit the scheme without any exit load. This protects investors from being forced to stay in a scheme whose character has fundamentally changed from what they originally signed up for.
**The Trap:** 100% consent is not required — unitholders can be overruled if the regulatory process is followed. The protection is the right to exit, not the right to veto. Also, the AMC may need SEBI approval depending on the nature of the change, but the investor-facing requirement is notification + exit option.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers fundamental attribute changes; this is a key investor protection mechanism tested across multiple NISM certifications.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a fundamental attribute change notification arrives, contact affected clients IMMEDIATELY — the exit window is time-limited. Assess whether the changed scheme still fits the client's portfolio and risk profile. Don't wait for the client to notice the communication in their email.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
