<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[When a minor investor attains majority (turns 18), what is required to continue operating the mutual fund account?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No action is required; the account automatically converts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the guardian needs to submit a request letter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Fresh KYC in the minor's own name is required, and the guardian is removed from the account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The guardian must continue to operate the account until the investor turns 21]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a minor turns 18, the mutual fund account cannot be operated by the guardian anymore. The now-adult investor must complete fresh KYC in their own name (re-KYC), update the account status from minor to major, and provide their own bank details. The guardian's association with the account is removed. Until this process is completed, all transactions in the account are frozen.

**The Trap:** The account does NOT automatically convert. There is an active process required, and during the transition period, no transactions can be processed. Many families miss this deadline, leading to frozen accounts and missed SIP installments.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is classified as a non-financial transaction but has significant operational impact. The AMC/RTA flags accounts of minor investors approaching 18 and sends reminders to complete the status change.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a tracker of minor client accounts with their dates of birth. Proactively reach out to families 2-3 months before the minor turns 18 to initiate the status change process. This prevents account freezing and demonstrates excellent client servicing.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
