<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meena Sharma, a 55-year-old retired school teacher from Jaipur, has mutual fund investments across 3 schemes of PQR Mutual Fund. She visits the Investor Service Centre (ISC) with the following requests:

Request 1: She has recently moved from Jaipur to Udaipur and wants to update her address. She carries her new Aadhaar card showing the Udaipur address.

Request 2: She has opened a new bank account with a different bank (Bank of Rajasthan) and wants all future redemption proceeds and IDCW payouts to go to this new account. She carries a cancelled cheque of the new account and her old bank's passbook.

Request 3: She wants to add her daughter (Priya, age 28) and son (Rahul, age 32) as nominees with 60% and 40% allocation respectively. Currently, no nominee is registered.

Request 4: She has not received her CAS for the last 6 months and wants to understand why and get it reissued.

Request 5: She wants to know if she can consolidate her 3 folios — Folio 1 is in her single name, Folio 2 is joint with her husband (Meena + Suresh), and Folio 3 is in her single name with a different bank account.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> For Request 1 (address change), what will the RTA require from Meena?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a verbal request since she's visiting the ISC in person]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A signed letter requesting the change; no document proof needed for existing KYC-compliant investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A signed request letter along with the new Aadhaar card (or its copy) as Proof of Address, with In-Person Verification at the ISC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She must complete fresh KYC since her address has changed]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Address change requires: (1) a signed written request from the investor, (2) a valid Proof of Address document showing the new address — Meena's new Aadhaar card with the Udaipur address is an acceptable PoA. Since she's visiting the ISC in person, IPV can be completed on the spot. She does NOT need to redo her entire KYC — this is a profile update, not a fresh KYC.
**The Trap:** Fresh KYC is not required for address changes — KYC remains valid, only the address field is updated. However, merely requesting verbally or without PoA is insufficient — documentary proof is mandatory.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers KYC update vs fresh KYC; Series II-B tests the RTA's document requirements for various profile changes.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Aadhaar with updated address is the most efficient PoA for address changes — it's universally accepted and can be verified electronically. Advise clients to update their Aadhaar first (at UIDAI), then use the updated Aadhaar for all financial address changes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
