<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) and how frequently is it issued?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A physical certificate of holdings issued annually by each AMC separately]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A single statement covering all mutual fund holdings across AMCs, issued monthly if there are transactions and half-yearly otherwise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A statement issued only on redemption showing capital gains and losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A quarterly portfolio disclosure statement required by SEBI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** CAS is a consolidated statement that shows all mutual fund holdings and transactions of an investor across all AMCs in a single document. It is generated by the RTAs (CAMS and KFin Technologies). CAS is issued monthly if any financial transaction has occurred during the month, and half-yearly (September and March) even if there are no transactions.

**The Trap:** CAS is not the same as individual AMC account statements. CAS covers holdings across ALL AMCs linked to the investor's PAN. It provides a complete picture of the investor's mutual fund portfolio in one document.

**Cross-Exam Context:** CAS also includes details of demat holdings alongside mutual fund holdings, giving investors a comprehensive view of their investment portfolio. It serves as the primary record of mutual fund holdings since physical unit certificates are no longer issued.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Encourage clients to review their CAS regularly. It is the best tool for portfolio review meetings — it shows everything in one place. Help clients register their email for eCAS delivery, which is faster and more accessible than physical statements.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
