<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_52" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, which of the following is the correct frequency for issuing Consolidated Account Statements (CAS) to investors with no transactions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monthly]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Quarterly]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Half-yearly (for the periods ending September and March)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annually]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates two frequencies for CAS: (1) Monthly CAS for investors who have had any financial transaction during the month, and (2) Half-yearly CAS (for periods ending September 30 and March 31) for all investors with mutual fund holdings, even if there were no transactions during the period. This ensures every investor receives at least two statements per year.

**The Trap:** The half-yearly CAS is not for the calendar half-year (January-June, July-December). It follows the periods ending September and March, aligned with the Indian financial reporting calendar. Monthly CAS is sent only for months with transactions, not every month regardless.

**Cross-Exam Context:** CAS includes holdings across all mutual fund AMCs and demat accounts linked to the investor's PAN. It provides a comprehensive portfolio view and serves as an important document for financial review and tax computation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remind clients about the half-yearly CAS even if they have not transacted recently. It is an excellent opportunity for a portfolio review call. Use the CAS as a conversation starter to discuss rebalancing, additional investments, or changes in financial goals. This proactive outreach keeps you relevant in the client's financial life.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
