<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the Growth option in a mutual fund scheme is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Growth option invests in a different portfolio than the IDCW option]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Growth option guarantees capital appreciation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The Growth option does not declare any income distribution and all gains are reflected in the NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Growth option has a higher expense ratio than the IDCW option]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Growth option and IDCW option of the same scheme invest in an identical portfolio. The difference is that the Growth option does not declare any IDCW — all earnings (interest, dividends, capital gains) remain within the scheme and are reflected in a rising NAV over time. No tax event occurs until the investor redeems.

**The Trap:** "Growth" does not guarantee growth or positive returns. It simply means no distributions will be made. The NAV can still fall if the underlying portfolio loses value. The name refers to the compounding structure, not guaranteed capital appreciation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Growth option typically shows a higher NAV than the IDCW option of the same scheme over time because all earnings remain invested. However, total returns (NAV + distributions received) should be comparable before taxes.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Recommend the Growth option for wealth accumulation goals with a long time horizon. The tax deferral benefit of Growth option compounds significantly over time. For clients needing regular cash flows, combine Growth option with SWP for tax efficiency.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
