<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Priya, aged 32, moderate risk profile, monthly investable surplus of Rs. 40,000. Goals: emergency fund (1 year, Rs. 3,60,000), house down payment (5 years, Rs. 15,00,000), daughter's education (15 years), and retirement (28 years). She has Rs. 2,00,000 in savings and no other investments.

Question 4: As Priya's mutual fund distributor, which of the following is the most appropriate FIRST step in her investment plan?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Start SIPs in equity mutual funds immediately for maximum long-term compounding benefit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest the entire Rs. 2,00,000 savings and Rs. 40,000 monthly surplus into a diversified equity fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Prioritize building the emergency fund first by allocating her existing Rs. 2 lakh savings and initial monthly surplus to a liquid fund until the Rs. 3,60,000 target is met]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buy a term insurance plan and health insurance before making any investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The first priority in financial planning is building an emergency fund (typically 3-6 months of expenses). Priya needs Rs. 3,60,000 as emergency reserve. She already has Rs. 2,00,000 in savings, so she needs Rs. 1,60,000 more. By allocating her initial surplus to a liquid fund, she can complete the emergency fund in about 4 months. Only after this safety net is in place should she allocate surplus to medium and long-term goals through equity and hybrid funds.

**The Trap:** Option A (start equity SIPs immediately) sounds logical for long-term goals but ignores the foundational step of emergency fund creation. Without an emergency fund, Priya might be forced to redeem equity investments at a loss during emergencies. Option D (insurance first) is important but is a separate financial planning step -- the question asks about the investment plan specifically, and the emergency fund takes precedence as the first investment action.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The priority sequence in financial planning is tested in NISM V-A and X-A: (1) Emergency fund, (2) Adequate insurance, (3) Short-term goals, (4) Medium-term goals, (5) Long-term goals. Exam questions test whether candidates understand this sequencing, not just individual product knowledge.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Many new distributors skip the emergency fund step because it earns low commissions (liquid fund trail is minimal). But this is the foundation of a long-term client relationship. If Priya faces an emergency without reserves, she will blame you for putting all her money in equity. Build trust first, earn commissions over a 20-year relationship, not a 20-day transaction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
