<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The transfer of shares to the IEPF demat account is legally treated as which type of transaction?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Deemed transmission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Regular transfer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Off-market trade]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gift transaction]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When shares are transferred to the IEPF demat account due to unclaimed dividends for 7 years, the transaction is legally classified as a "deemed transmission" — not a transfer. This distinction is crucial because transmission typically occurs by operation of law (like inheritance), whereas transfer involves a voluntary act between parties.

**The Trap:** Most candidates instinctively select "regular transfer" because shares are moving from one account to another. However, since the shareholder has not voluntarily initiated this movement, and it occurs by operation of law under Section 124(6) of the Companies Act, it is classified as transmission. This also means no stamp duty applies.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The transfer vs. transmission distinction is heavily tested in NISM Series VI (Depository Operations) and Series II-B (Registrars to Mutual Fund). Understanding the legal implications of each — especially regarding stamp duty, documentation, and reversibility — is essential.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining IEPF provisions to investors, emphasize that their shares are not "sold" or "transferred" to a third party. The shares remain available for claim, and this deemed transmission preserves the investor's underlying ownership rights, which can be restored through the IEPF-5 claim process.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
