<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is MF Central, and who operates it?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A regulatory portal operated by SEBI for mutual fund compliance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A mobile app operated by AMFI for NAV information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A government platform for tracking mutual fund taxes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A common transaction platform operated jointly by CAMS and KFintech for all mutual fund transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** MF Central is a common digital platform jointly operated by the two major RTAs — CAMS (Computer Age Management Services) and KFintech (formerly Karvy/KFIN Technologies). It provides investors a single platform to execute transactions, view holdings, and manage their mutual fund investments across ALL AMCs, regardless of which RTA services them.
**The Trap:** MF Central is NOT a regulatory or government platform — it's an industry initiative by the two RTAs. It's also different from MFU (Mutual Fund Utility) which was an earlier attempt at a common platform.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B specifically tests MF Central as a key service infrastructure; it represents the evolution of RTA services beyond back-office processing to direct investor servicing.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Direct tech-savvy clients to MF Central (mfcentral.com) for self-service transactions across all AMCs. It reduces dependence on individual AMC platforms and provides consolidated access. For clients who prefer human assistance, you remain the interface — but knowing about MF Central adds to your credibility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
