<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is a CAS (Consolidated Account Statement) in the context of mutual fund investments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A statement showing only mutual fund holdings from a single AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A single statement consolidating an investor's mutual fund and demat holdings across all AMCs, sent monthly if transactions occurred or half-yearly otherwise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A statement issued only on investor request through the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A statement showing only the capital gains and tax details of investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** CAS is a Consolidated Account Statement that provides a unified view of an investor's mutual fund holdings across ALL AMCs, along with demat holdings, in a single document. It is generated by the RTAs (CAMS and KFintech) and sent monthly if any transaction occurred during the month, or half-yearly if no transactions took place. It can be sent via email and/or physical copy.
**The Trap:** CAS is not AMC-specific — that's an individual account statement from each AMC. CAS consolidates across ALL AMCs, making it a powerful portfolio-level document.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers CAS features; Series II-B tests the RTA's role in generating and distributing CAS as a key investor service.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the CAS as a portfolio review tool during client meetings — it shows the complete MF picture in one place. If a client says 'I don't know all my investments,' the CAS is the answer. Ensure clients have updated email addresses for timely CAS delivery.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
