<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[How many nominees can a mutual fund investor appoint, and can the percentage be split among them?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only 1 nominee can be appointed with 100% allocation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Up to 2 nominees can be appointed with equal split only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Up to 10 nominees can be appointed with percentage split as desired by the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Up to 3 nominees can be appointed with percentage split]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Per the January 2025 SEBI circular, a mutual fund investor can now nominate up to 10 persons (increased from the earlier limit of 3). The investor can specify the percentage of units/proceeds each nominee will receive, and these percentages can be unequal. For example, Nominee A: 50%, Nominee B: 30%, Nominee C: 20%. If percentages are not specified, equal distribution is assumed.

**The Trap:** Nomination is mandatory disclosure — investors must either nominate or explicitly opt out of nomination. Simply leaving the nomination field blank is not acceptable. The form requires either a nominee name or a declaration that the investor does not wish to nominate.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Nomination simplifies the transmission process upon the investor's death — the nominee can claim the units/proceeds without going through a lengthy legal process. However, nomination does not override a valid will. The nominee acts as a trustee for the legal heirs.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always complete the nomination section in every application form. Explain to clients that nomination is not succession planning — it merely facilitates quick transfer. For estate planning, they should create a proper will that specifies how mutual fund holdings should be distributed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
