<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[In a mutual fund scheme, the NAV of the Direct Plan is typically _______ compared to the Regular Plan of the same scheme over time.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lower, because Direct Plan has fewer investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Higher, because Direct Plan has a lower expense ratio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equal, because both plans invest in the same portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Variable, depending on market conditions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Since both Direct and Regular Plans invest in the identical portfolio, the gross returns are the same. However, the Direct Plan has a lower Total Expense Ratio (TER) because no distributor commission is charged. This lower expense deduction means more returns remain in the scheme, leading to a higher NAV for the Direct Plan compared to the Regular Plan over time.

**The Trap:** At the start (Day 1), both plans may have the same NAV. But from Day 2 onwards, the NAV diverges because different expense ratios are deducted daily. The longer the holding period, the greater the NAV difference. This is why the answer is "higher" not "equal" even though the portfolio is identical.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The NAV difference between Direct and Regular Plans of the same scheme represents the cumulative commission paid to distributors. This transparency helps investors make informed choices about the value of distributor services.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Do not shy away from discussing this NAV difference with clients. Instead, justify your commission by demonstrating the value you add: financial planning, portfolio construction, behavioral coaching during market downturns, and ongoing service. A well-served investor in a Regular Plan can outperform a poorly-guided Direct Plan investor.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
