<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Patel invested Rs.5,00,000 in DEF Equity Fund on March 15. He submitted his redemption request for the entire holding on April 5 (a Monday, working day) before the 3:00 PM cutoff. The following events occurred:

Event 1: By April 9 (Thursday, T+3 working days, with no holidays in between), Vikram had not received his redemption proceeds in his bank account.

Event 2: He called the AMC's customer care on April 9 and was told the delay was due to 'technical issues at the RTA' and that the proceeds would be credited within 2 more working days.

Event 3: By April 13 (Tuesday), the proceeds were still not received. Vikram sent an email complaint to the AMC.

Event 4: The AMC responded on April 16 (Friday) saying the RTA has been instructed to process the payment and it should arrive by April 20.

Event 5: On April 20, Vikram received only Rs.4,85,000 instead of the expected Rs.4,97,500 (based on the redemption NAV and units held). He was not given any explanation for the shortfall of Rs.12,500.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Given that the AMC hasn't resolved the issue by April 13, what is Vikram's next recourse?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He can file a complaint on SEBI SCORES since the AMC has failed to resolve the issue — the redemption is already delayed beyond the T+3 regulatory timeline]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He should file a police complaint for misappropriation of funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He should approach the stock exchange where the scheme is listed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He must wait for the AMC's response to his email complaint before taking any further action]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AMC has failed to deliver redemption proceeds within T+3, and even after Vikram's direct complaint, the issue remains unresolved. At this point, Vikram can escalate to SEBI SCORES. While the standard escalation is RTA → AMC → SCORES, Vikram has already approached the AMC directly, and the regulatory violation (T+3 breach) is clear. Filing on SCORES is appropriate at this stage.
**The Trap:** A police complaint would be premature — this is a regulatory/operational issue, not a criminal matter (unless fraud is suspected). Also, DEF Equity Fund may not be exchange-traded, and even if it were, exchange complaints are for trading-related issues.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers the SCORES escalation process; knowing when an investor has exhausted internal remedies and should approach SCORES is a key skill.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help Vikram draft a clear SCORES complaint: state the facts (redemption date, amount, T+3 violation), attach evidence (transaction confirmation, bank statement showing non-receipt), and specify the desired resolution (immediate payment + interest for delay). Well-structured complaints get faster resolution.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
