<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_60" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Mrs. Lakshmi redeemed Rs. 5 lakh from one of her equity schemes on Monday at 2 PM. It is now Friday (5 working days later) and she has not received the redemption proceeds in her bank account.

Question 4: What is the correct course of action for Mrs. Lakshmi regarding her delayed redemption proceeds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should wait for 10 working days as that is the standard turnaround time for equity fund redemptions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She should redeem additional units to check if the payment system is working]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[She should complain to the AMC first, as the 3 working day deadline has been breached, and the AMC is liable to pay her interest at 15% per annum for the delay period; if unresolved, she can escalate to SEBI SCORES]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[She cannot complain as the delay is within the acceptable 7 working day limit]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mrs. Lakshmi's redemption request was accepted on Monday at 2 PM (before the 3 PM cut-off), so Monday's NAV applies. The redemption proceeds must be dispatched within 3 working days — by Thursday at the latest (Monday = T, Tuesday = T+1, Wednesday = T+2, Thursday = T+3). Since it is Friday and she has not received the proceeds, the AMC has breached the 3-working-day deadline by at least 1 day.

Action steps: (1) Contact the AMC's investor service/grievance cell immediately and lodge a formal complaint. (2) Demand interest at 15% per annum for the period of delay as mandated by SEBI. (3) If the AMC does not resolve within a reasonable time, lodge a complaint on SEBI SCORES. (4) If still unresolved, approach the Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) mechanism.

**The Trap:** The turnaround time for equity fund redemption is 3 working days, NOT 5 or 7. By Day 5, the AMC is already 2 days late. Some students confuse this with the NFO allotment timeline (5 business days) or assume a longer processing period.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 15% per annum interest for delay is calculated from the 4th working day (the day after the deadline) until the date of actual payment. For Rs. 5 lakh delayed by 2 days, the interest would be approximately Rs. 5,00,000 x 15% x 2/365 = Rs. 411. While the amount seems small, it is a regulatory right.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As Mrs. Lakshmi's distributor, take ownership of this complaint. Contact the AMC on her behalf, get a clear timeline for payment, and ensure the delay interest is credited. Document everything. This proactive problem-solving during a stressful situation builds deep client trust. Also, check if the delay is due to her outdated bank details — this would explain the failed payment and reinforces why KYC updates are important.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
