<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_50" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, what is the status of nomination in mutual fund investments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nomination is completely optional and the investor can leave the field blank]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nomination is mandatory and the investor must name at least one nominee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Nomination disclosure is mandatory — the investor must either nominate or explicitly opt out of nomination]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nomination is required only for investments exceeding Rs. 5 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI requires mandatory disclosure regarding nomination. This means the investor cannot simply leave the nomination field blank. They must either: (a) provide nominee details (name, address, relationship, percentage allocation for up to 3 nominees), OR (b) explicitly declare that they do not wish to nominate anyone by signing the opt-out section of the form.

**The Trap:** "Mandatory disclosure" is different from "mandatory nomination." The investor is not forced to nominate — they are forced to make a choice and declare it. This ensures the application form is complete and the investor has consciously considered the nomination decision.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This regulation was strengthened to address the large number of unclaimed mutual fund investments after the death of investors. By mandating disclosure, SEBI ensures that either a nominee is in place or the investor has made an informed choice to opt out.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always encourage nomination. Explain to clients that without a nominee, their family will face a lengthy legal process to claim the investments. For joint holders, nomination is equally important as it provides clarity after the death of all holders. Never let a client opt out without understanding the consequences.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
