<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Strategic asset allocation differs from tactical asset allocation in that strategic allocation:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sets a long-term target mix of asset classes based on the investor's goals and risk profile]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Involves frequent rebalancing based on short-term market conditions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Focuses exclusively on equity investments for maximum returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is only suitable for aggressive investors with high risk tolerance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Strategic asset allocation establishes a long-term, policy-level target mix (e.g., 60% equity, 30% debt, 10% gold) based on the investor's financial goals, time horizon, and risk tolerance. It is reviewed periodically but not changed frequently. Tactical asset allocation, by contrast, involves short-term deviations from the strategic mix to exploit perceived market opportunities.

**The Trap:** Option B describes tactical allocation, not strategic -- this is the most common confusion tested in exams. Option C incorrectly limits strategic allocation to equities, when it actually involves multiple asset classes. Option D wrongly restricts it to aggressive investors, when all investor profiles need strategic allocation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Asset allocation concepts are central to NISM V-A and X-A (Investment Adviser). Studies show that over 90% of portfolio return variation is explained by asset allocation rather than individual security selection (Brinson, Hood & Beebower study).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Start every client conversation with asset allocation before discussing specific funds. A 60:40 equity-debt split for a moderate investor is more impactful than choosing between two large-cap funds. Get the asset allocation right first, and fund selection becomes secondary.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
