<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is an advantage of seeking professional financial help over a DIY (Do-It-Yourself) approach to investing?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Professional help guarantees higher returns than self-managed portfolios]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Professional advisers eliminate all investment risks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Professional advisers bring expertise in goal-based planning, product selection, and behavioral coaching]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Professional help is always cheaper than managing investments independently]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Professional financial advisers and mutual fund distributors add value through structured goal-based planning, appropriate product selection based on risk profiling, periodic portfolio rebalancing, and behavioral coaching that prevents emotional decision-making. They do not guarantee returns or eliminate risk, but they bring discipline, knowledge, and objectivity to the investment process.

**The Trap:** Option A is the most dangerous distractor -- no professional can guarantee returns, and suggesting otherwise would violate SEBI regulations. Option B is equally incorrect because risk is inherent to investing and cannot be eliminated, only managed. Option D is wrong because professional help involves fees/commissions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The role and value proposition of mutual fund distributors is central to NISM V-A. SEBI regulations prohibit guaranteeing returns. The exam tests whether candidates understand what legitimate value a distributor adds vs. what constitutes mis-selling.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Your value as a distributor is not stock-picking or timing the market. It is keeping clients invested during downturns, ensuring proper asset allocation, and preventing behavioral mistakes. Studies show that "adviser alpha" (value added by advisers) comes primarily from behavioral coaching, not portfolio construction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
