<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the significance of providing one's own email and mobile number (not the distributor's) for mutual fund investments, as per the Investor Charter?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is merely a suggestion, not a requirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It allows the distributor to communicate more efficiently]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It ensures the investor receives direct communication from the AMC/RTA including transaction alerts, account statements, and regulatory notifications without intermediary dependency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It qualifies the investor for a discount on the expense ratio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Investor Charter mandates that investors should provide their OWN email and mobile number (not the agent's/distributor's) to ensure direct communication from AMC/RTA. This includes transaction confirmations, CAS, scheme notifications, IDCW alerts, and regulatory communications. This reduces dependency on intermediaries and prevents information asymmetry.
**The Trap:** This is a requirement, not a suggestion. SEBI has specifically addressed the practice of distributors providing their own contact details in investor forms, which creates a dependency and potential conflict of interest.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers this as part of investor responsibility; Series II-B tests the RTA's verification of contact details during onboarding.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Providing your own email/mobile in client forms may seem convenient, but it's a compliance violation that puts YOUR license at risk. Instead, help clients set up their own email if needed, and maintain a separate communication system for your advisory services. Transparent communication builds long-term trust.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
