<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Currency risk is most relevant for an Indian investor who invests in:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nifty 50 Index Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A gilt fund investing in government securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A fund of funds investing in a US-based equity ETF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A corporate bond fund investing in AAA-rated Indian companies]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Currency risk (also called exchange rate risk) arises when investments are denominated in a foreign currency. An Indian investor in a US equity ETF faces the risk that the Indian Rupee may appreciate against the US Dollar, reducing the value of returns when converted back to Rupees. Conversely, a depreciating Rupee would enhance returns.

**The Trap:** Option A is tempting because many Nifty 50 companies earn revenue in foreign currencies, but the investment itself is denominated in Rupees, so there is no direct currency risk for the investor. The exam tests direct currency exposure, not indirect business exposure.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Currency risk is tested in NISM V-A and XII. With increasing interest in international funds (Nasdaq 100, S&P 500 feeder funds), this concept has become more exam-relevant. The Rupee's depreciation trend historically has added 3-4% annually to international fund returns for Indian investors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When recommending international funds, explain the dual return -- asset return plus currency return. A US fund returning 10% in USD terms could yield 13-14% in INR if the Rupee depreciates by 3-4%. But this works both ways, so clients must understand both dimensions of return.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
