<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes eKYC (Electronic KYC) using Aadhaar for mutual fund investments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[eKYC allows unlimited investment without any restrictions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Aadhaar-based eKYC enables paperless KYC verification using biometric or OTP authentication]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[eKYC is mandatory and cannot be substituted with physical KYC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[eKYC is only available for NRI investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** eKYC using Aadhaar allows paperless KYC verification through biometric authentication (fingerprint/iris scan) or OTP (One Time Password) sent to the Aadhaar-linked mobile number. It eliminates the need for physical documents and in-person verification, making the KYC process faster and more convenient.

**The Trap:** eKYC through OTP-based Aadhaar verification may have investment limits. Biometric-based Aadhaar eKYC provides full KYC status, while OTP-based eKYC may restrict the annual investment amount. The specific limits can change based on regulatory updates.

**Cross-Exam Context:** eKYC is an alternative to physical KYC, not a replacement. Investors can choose between eKYC and traditional physical KYC. Both result in KYC-compliant status, though the verification process and documentation differ.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** eKYC is a game-changer for onboarding new investors quickly. Guide clients through the Aadhaar OTP process for instant KYC completion. However, ensure their Aadhaar-linked mobile number is active, as OTP delivery is critical for the process.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
