<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Meera, an investor from Bengaluru, submitted a request to her RTA for updation of her bank account details 18 days ago but has not received any response. She is considering escalation. What is the most appropriate escalation path under the investor charter framework?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Directly file a criminal complaint with the police against the RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File a PIL in the High Court against SEBI for failure of regulatory oversight]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[First approach the RTA using its escalation matrix, then if unresolved, escalate to the Company, then the Depository or Stock Exchange, and finally SEBI through SCORES]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Immediately file on SEBI SCORES without attempting any resolution with the RTA first]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Investor Charter establishes a structured escalation path. Meera should first use the RTA's own escalation matrix (which the RTA is required to provide access to). If the RTA does not resolve her issue, she can escalate to the Company, then to the Depository or Stock Exchange, and finally to SEBI through the SCORES platform. The 21-day RTA deadline has not been breached yet (18 days), but she can begin the escalation process.

**The Trap:** Going directly to SEBI SCORES without first attempting resolution with the RTA is premature and inefficient. Criminal complaints and PILs are disproportionate responses to a service delay. The exam tests whether candidates understand the sequential escalation framework.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Escalation matrices are tested across all NISM certifications. The principle of "first approach the immediate service provider, then the regulator" is universal in financial services. This mirrors the Mutual Fund complaint escalation (AMC, then AMFI, then SEBI) tested in Series V-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Publish your escalation matrix with clear contact details, timelines, and escalation triggers on your website and in all investor communications. Internally, ensure that when a complaint reaches Level 2 of escalation, the compliance officer is automatically notified. This prevents regulatory escalation and preserves investor trust.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
