<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under LODR Regulation 13(3), the quarterly statement submitted by a company to the stock exchange regarding investor complaints must include which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Names and addresses of all complainants along with their folio numbers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Complaints pending at the beginning of the quarter, received during the quarter, disposed of, and remaining unresolved]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The total compensation paid to investors for delayed services during the quarter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Details of all legal proceedings initiated by investors against the company]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under LODR Regulation 13(3), listed companies must submit a quarterly statement to the stock exchange with four specific data points about investor complaints: (1) complaints pending at the beginning of the quarter, (2) complaints received during the quarter, (3) complaints disposed of during the quarter, and (4) complaints remaining unresolved at the end of the quarter.

**The Trap:** Individual complainant details (names, addresses) are confidential and not disclosed in the quarterly statement. The statement is a statistical summary, not a detailed case-by-case report. Compensation details and legal proceedings are separate disclosures with different reporting requirements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** LODR regulations are extensively tested in NISM Series II-A and Series IX (Merchant Banking). The quarterly complaint reporting requirement ensures continuous disclosure and transparency about a company's investor servicing quality. Stock exchanges monitor these statements for early warning signs.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help your client companies prepare the quarterly statement well before the submission deadline. Reconcile your internal complaint tracking system with the stock exchange reporting format. A company that consistently shows zero pending complaints at quarter-end demonstrates strong investor servicing capability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
