<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_48" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE regarding SEBI SCORES (SEBI Complaint Redress System)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only investors with investments above Rs. 10 lakh can file complaints on SCORES]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCORES can only be used after filing a police complaint]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It is an online platform where investors can lodge, track, and view resolution of their complaints against SEBI-registered entities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCORES automatically awards monetary compensation to the investor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI SCORES is a web-based centralized grievance redressal system. Any investor can lodge a complaint online, track its progress, and view the resolution. SEBI-registered entities (including AMCs, distributors, RTAs) are required to respond to complaints on SCORES within 30 days.

**The Trap:** SCORES facilitates complaint resolution but does not automatically award compensation. It is not a court or arbitration body. If the investor is not satisfied with the resolution on SCORES, they can escalate to the Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) mechanism or approach appropriate legal forums.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Before approaching SCORES, investors should first try to resolve the complaint directly with the AMC/entity. SCORES is the second level of escalation. The entire process is online, making it accessible to investors across the country.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Treat a complaint on SCORES as a serious matter — it creates a regulatory record. Proactively resolve client issues before they reach SCORES. If a complaint is filed, cooperate fully and respond within the 30-day timeline. A pattern of SCORES complaints can invite SEBI scrutiny of your distribution practices.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
