<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[If there is no nominee registered for a deceased unitholder's mutual fund investments, how does the transmission process work?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC distributes the units equally among all family members]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Legal heirs must submit a succession certificate, probate of will, or letter of administration along with the death certificate for transmission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The units become part of the unclaimed amounts pool]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The units are automatically transferred to the spouse]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Without a nominee, the transmission process requires legal documentation — the legal heir(s) must produce a succession certificate (from civil court), probate of the will (if a will exists), or letter of administration. Along with the death certificate, KYC of the claimant, and an indemnity bond, these documents establish the rightful claimant(s). This process is significantly longer and more expensive than nominee-based transmission.
**The Trap:** There is no automatic transfer to spouse or equal distribution among family — the legal heir process must be followed. The AMC cannot make assumptions about who the rightful heir is without legal documentation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers the complexity of non-nominee transmission; this is a key reason why nomination completion is strongly encouraged.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use this as a powerful example when encouraging clients to nominate. Without nomination, the family faces: court procedures (months), legal fees (Rs.5,000-50,000+), emotional stress during bereavement, and potential family disputes. A simple nomination form prevents all of this.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
