<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What happens when an investor does not specify the plan (Direct/Regular) while submitting a mutual fund application?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The application is rejected]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The investment is made in the Regular Plan by default]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The investment is routed to the Direct Plan by default]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC contacts the investor to clarify before processing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI guidelines, if an investor does not specify the plan in the application form, the investment is processed under the Direct Plan by default. This rule protects investors by defaulting to the lower-cost option. Similarly, if the option (Growth/IDCW) is not specified, Growth is the default.

**The Trap:** This default to Direct Plan has implications for distributors. If a distributor submits an application without specifying the Regular Plan, the investment goes to Direct Plan and the distributor receives no commission. This emphasizes the importance of careful form filling.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The default to Direct Plan and Growth option reflects SEBI's investor-first approach — lower cost and tax-efficient compounding are the defaults. Any deviation requires an explicit choice by the investor.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always double-check that the plan is marked as "Regular" on every application you process. A single oversight can result in lost commission with no recourse. Conversely, never change a client's explicit choice of Direct Plan to Regular Plan — this is a regulatory violation and a breach of trust.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
