<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the defining criterion for a Registrar and Transfer Agent to be classified as a Qualified RTA (QRTA)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Having a minimum net worth of INR 50 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Being registered with SEBI for at least 10 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Servicing more than 2 crore folios]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Having offices in all state capitals of India]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Qualified RTA (QRTA) is defined as an RTA that services more than 2 crore (20 million) folios. Due to the systemic importance of handling such a large volume of investor records, QRTAs are classified as Critical Infrastructure Institutions and are subject to enhanced regulatory monitoring and compliance requirements.

**The Trap:** Net worth, years of registration, and geographical presence are plausible criteria but incorrect. The sole defining criterion is the folio count exceeding 2 crore. This makes the classification purely volume-based, reflecting the systemic risk associated with large-scale operations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of systemically important entities appears in banking (SIBs), insurance (SIIs), and now in the RTA space (QRTAs). NISM Series II-A tests candidates on the specific threshold and its regulatory implications for enhanced governance, data security, and business continuity requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If your organization is approaching the 2-crore folio threshold, start preparing for QRTA compliance proactively. This includes strengthening your internal policy framework, periodic risk reporting, data security infrastructure, business continuity plans, and investor services — all areas subject to enhanced monitoring.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
