<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[How does the transmission process work for mutual fund units when the unitholder dies and there is a registered nominee?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Units are compulsorily redeemed and proceeds are paid to the nominee's bank account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The nominee submits a transmission request with death certificate and identity proof to the RTA/AMC, which then transfers the units after verification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Units are automatically transferred to the nominee on the date of demise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The nominee must obtain a court order before units can be transmitted]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a unitholder dies and a nominee is registered, the transmission process is relatively straightforward: the nominee submits a transmission request along with the death certificate (original or notarized copy), KYC documents, and identity proof to the RTA/AMC. After verification, the units are transmitted to the nominee's folio. No court order or legal heir certificate is typically required when a valid nomination exists.
**The Trap:** Transmission is NOT automatic — the nominee must actively submit a request with documents. Also, units are transmitted (not compulsorily redeemed) — the nominee can choose to continue holding or redeem later.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers transmission basics; Series II-B tests the RTA's specific document checklist and processing workflow for transmission cases.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The nominee should approach the RTA/AMC as soon as possible after the demise. The centralised demise reporting through KRA blocks debit transactions for protection, but the nominee needs to initiate the transmission for gaining control. Keep a ready checklist of documents required to guide families during a difficult time.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
