<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI Regulations 2023, which Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR) mechanisms are available for resolving investor disputes with market intermediaries?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mediation, conciliation, and arbitration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only arbitration conducted through stock exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Civil court litigation and criminal prosecution only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only mediation conducted by SEBI-appointed mediators]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI Regulations 2023 provide for all three ADR mechanisms — mediation, conciliation, and arbitration — for resolving disputes between investors and market intermediaries. These mechanisms offer faster, less expensive, and more accessible alternatives to traditional court litigation.

**The Trap:** While arbitration through stock exchanges has been a traditional mechanism, the 2023 regulations expand the ADR toolkit to include mediation and conciliation as well. Candidates who are familiar with the older framework may incorrectly select "only arbitration." Civil court litigation is not an ADR mechanism — it is the formal judicial process.

**Cross-Exam Context:** ADR mechanisms are tested in NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) regarding exchange-level arbitration, in Series V-A (Mutual Funds) regarding AMFI conciliation, and in Series II-A regarding RTA-level dispute resolution. The three-tier ADR framework is a recent regulatory development.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Familiarize your team with all three ADR processes. Mediation is ideal for relationship-preserving resolutions, conciliation works well when parties need a neutral third-party recommendation, and arbitration is appropriate when a binding decision is required. Guide investors to the most suitable mechanism based on the nature of their dispute.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
