<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A daily wage worker without PAN wants to start investing in mutual funds. He can save Rs. 1,000 per month. What is the best advice for him?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He cannot invest in mutual funds without PAN under any circumstances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He should first earn enough to obtain PAN and then start investing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He can start a micro-SIP of Rs. 1,000 per month without PAN as long as total annual investment does not exceed Rs. 50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He must invest through a corporate or trust account instead]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI allows micro-SIP investments without PAN, provided the aggregate investment across all mutual funds does not exceed Rs. 50,000 per year per investor. At Rs. 1,000 per month, the annual investment would be Rs. 12,000, which is well within the Rs. 50,000 limit. The investor will need alternative KYC documents (Aadhaar, voter ID, etc.).

**The Trap:** The Rs. 50,000 limit is per year per investor across ALL mutual fund investments, not per scheme. If the investor has other mutual fund investments, those must be included in the calculation. Also, while PAN is not required, basic KYC with alternative documents is still mandatory.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The micro-SIP provision was introduced to promote financial inclusion and bring the lower-income segment into the formal investment ecosystem. It recognizes that not everyone has PAN but everyone should have access to mutual fund investing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is a huge opportunity for financial inclusion. Many daily wage workers, domestic helpers, and small traders can start micro-SIPs. While the ticket size is small, the volume potential is large. Help them start with Rs. 500-1,000 monthly SIPs and gradually increase as their income grows. Also encourage them to apply for PAN for future flexibility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
