<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the Trigger Facility in mutual fund investing?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A facility that automatically executes transactions (purchase, redemption, or switch) when pre-set NAV or index levels are reached]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A facility that sends SMS alerts when NAV changes by more than 1%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A facility that automatically starts an SIP when the market falls by 10%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A facility that triggers KYC verification when transaction amounts exceed Rs. 50,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Trigger Facility allows investors to set pre-defined conditions (NAV levels, index levels, or dates) that automatically trigger a transaction such as purchase, redemption, or switch. When the trigger condition is met, the transaction is executed without requiring manual intervention.

**The Trap:** The Trigger Facility is different from alerts or notifications. It actually EXECUTES a transaction, not just informs the investor. Also, it is different from SIP/STP/SWP which operate on fixed time intervals — triggers are based on price/index conditions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Not all AMCs offer the Trigger Facility, and its availability may vary across schemes. It is an optional feature that tries to automate investment timing decisions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While the Trigger Facility sounds appealing, advise clients cautiously. Setting triggers based on short-term market movements can lead to frequent transactions, increased tax events, and may work against the discipline of staying invested. It is best suited for experienced investors with clear strategies.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
