<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a source of funds credited to the Investor Education and Protection Fund (IEPF)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Brokerage fees collected by stock exchanges from trading members]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Unpaid dividends and matured deposits unclaimed for 7 years along with interest thereon]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annual listing fees paid by companies to stock exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Securities Transaction Tax collected by the government]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The IEPF receives funds from multiple sources including contributions from central/state governments, companies, and institutions. The primary sources are unclaimed/unpaid dividends, matured debentures, matured deposits, application money, call money due for refund, and the interest accrued on all these amounts — all unclaimed for 7 years.

**The Trap:** Brokerage fees and listing fees go to stock exchanges, not the IEPF. Securities Transaction Tax goes to the government exchequer. These are common distractors designed to test whether candidates understand the specific funding sources of the IEPF versus other market infrastructure fees.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the flow of unclaimed amounts is important for NISM Series VI (Depository Operations) as well, where similar concepts about unclaimed benefits exist in the depository system.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When processing corporate actions, maintain a meticulous tracker of all unclaimed amounts by investor folio. This helps companies comply with the IEPF-2 filing requirements and gives RTAs visibility into amounts approaching the 7-year threshold.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
