<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_47" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, what is the penalty if an AMC fails to dispatch redemption proceeds within the stipulated timeframe?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A flat penalty of Rs. 10,000 per day of delay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Interest at the rate of 15% per annum for the period of delay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suspension of the scheme for 30 days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cancellation of the AMC's license]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If an AMC fails to dispatch redemption proceeds within the stipulated timeframe (3 working days for equity/debt, 1 working day for liquid/overnight), it is liable to pay interest at 15% per annum for the period of delay. This penalty is borne by the AMC from its own funds, not from the scheme's assets, protecting other investors.

**The Trap:** The 15% interest is per ANNUM, not per month or per day. For a 5-day delay on Rs. 1 lakh, the penalty would be approximately Rs. 1 lakh x 15% x 5/365 = Rs. 205. While it seems small, it adds up for AMCs with multiple delayed redemptions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This penalty provision applies to both the refund of NFO money (if allotment is delayed) and regular redemption proceeds. The same 15% per annum rate is specified for both scenarios, providing a uniform penalty framework.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a client's redemption proceeds are delayed beyond the stipulated time, file a formal complaint with the AMC requesting the delay interest. Most AMCs will voluntarily pay it to avoid escalation to SEBI SCORES. Knowing this regulation empowers you to advocate effectively for your clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
