<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor who holds bonds is concerned that when interest rates rise, the market value of their existing bonds will decline. This concern relates to which type of risk?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Reinvestment risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Interest rate risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Inflation risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Interest rate risk is the risk that changes in prevailing interest rates will negatively affect the market value of fixed-income securities. Bond prices and interest rates have an inverse relationship -- when interest rates rise, existing bond prices fall (because new bonds offer higher coupons, making existing lower-coupon bonds less attractive).

**The Trap:** Option B (Reinvestment risk) is a strong distractor because it is also related to interest rates, but it works in the opposite direction -- reinvestment risk is the concern that coupon payments may have to be reinvested at LOWER rates when rates fall. The question specifically mentions rates RISING and bond values DECLINING, which is interest rate risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The inverse relationship between bond prices and interest rates is one of the most tested concepts in NISM V-A, especially when discussing debt mutual funds. Duration is the measure that quantifies this sensitivity.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Explain to clients that longer-duration debt funds carry more interest rate risk. In a rising rate environment, recommend short-duration or ultra-short-duration funds. In a falling rate environment, longer-duration funds (gilt funds) can generate capital appreciation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
