<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What role does the RTA play in the complaint handling process?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs only forward complaints to the AMC without any processing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[RTAs process complaints received through emails, letters, and SCORES, resolve operational issues directly, and escalate unresolved matters to the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs handle complaints only from institutional investors, not retail investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RTAs are not involved in complaint handling — it's entirely the AMC's responsibility]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** RTAs are the first line of complaint resolution for many operational issues — they process complaints received through multiple channels (emails, letters, SCORES) and can directly resolve issues related to transaction processing, statement discrepancies, NAV application errors, and other operational matters. Only complaints beyond their authority (scheme-related, policy decisions) are escalated to the AMC.
**The Trap:** RTAs are not mere forwarding agents — they have the authority and capability to resolve many operational complaints independently. This is because most complaints relate to transaction processing, which is the RTA's core function.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B specifically emphasizes the RTA's active role in complaint resolution; understanding the scope of RTA-resolvable vs AMC-escalatable complaints is important.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For operational complaints (wrong NAV, missing units, statement errors), go directly to the RTA rather than the AMC — they own the data and can fix it faster. For scheme-related issues (performance, load structure, scheme changes), the AMC is the right entity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
