<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Ravi receives a bonus of Rs. 10 lakh and wants to invest in an equity fund. He is worried about investing the entire amount at market peak. Which facility would best address his concern?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest the entire amount via lump sum in the equity fund immediately]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Set up a Trigger Facility to buy when the market falls 10%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Park in a liquid/debt fund and set up an STP to the equity fund over 6-12 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Wait in his bank account for the market to correct before investing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** STP is ideal for Ravi's situation. He can park the Rs. 10 lakh in a liquid or short-duration debt fund (earning returns while waiting) and set up an STP to systematically transfer a fixed amount to the equity fund over 6-12 months. This provides rupee cost averaging while keeping idle money productive.

**The Trap:** Keeping money in a savings account while waiting for a "correction" is suboptimal because: (a) savings account interest is lower than liquid fund returns, (b) market timing rarely works, and (c) there is no discipline to actually invest. STP solves all three issues.

**Cross-Exam Context:** STP from a liquid fund to an equity fund is operationally a combination of SWP from the source and SIP into the target. Each transfer is a taxable event (redemption from liquid fund), but the short holding period and small gains typically result in minimal tax impact.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** STP is the perfect solution for clients with lump sums who are nervous about market levels. Position it as "the best of both worlds" — money earns returns in a liquid fund while being gradually deployed into equity. It provides emotional comfort and investment discipline simultaneously.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
