<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is SEBI SCORES in the context of investor grievance redressal?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A rating system used by SEBI to evaluate the financial performance of intermediaries]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A scoring methodology for ranking mutual fund schemes based on investor satisfaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A software used internally by SEBI for monitoring stock exchange trading volumes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An online platform maintained by SEBI where investors can lodge and track their complaints against market intermediaries]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redress System) is an online platform maintained by SEBI that enables investors to lodge complaints against listed companies and SEBI-registered intermediaries. Investors can file complaints online, track the status, and receive updates on resolution. It centralizes the grievance redressal process and ensures accountability.

**The Trap:** The name "SCORES" might lead candidates to think it involves scoring or rating mechanisms. It is purely a complaints handling platform — not a rating system, ranking methodology, or internal monitoring tool.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SCORES is referenced across virtually all NISM certifications — Series V-A (Mutual Funds), Series VIII (Equity Derivatives), Series X-A (Investment Adviser), and others. Every SEBI-registered intermediary must address complaints filed through SCORES within stipulated timelines.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Train your client servicing team to monitor SCORES regularly. Set up internal alerts for any new complaint filed against your company on the platform. Quick acknowledgment and resolution of SCORES complaints prevents escalation and demonstrates regulatory compliance to SEBI during inspections.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
