<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Services and Transaction Processing_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is listed as an investor's RESPONSIBILITY under the Investor Charter?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ensure the scheme's returns match the benchmark index]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monitor the fund manager's daily investment decisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Report daily NAV to SEBI through the SCORES platform]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Read the Scheme Information Document before investing, update KYC, and provide own email/mobile for communication]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Investor responsibilities under the Charter include: reading the SID before investing, keeping KYC updated, providing their own (not agent's) email and mobile for direct communication, checking statements regularly, reading AMC communications, completing nomination, investing only through SEBI-registered entities, and keeping login credentials confidential.
**The Trap:** Monitoring fund manager decisions and ensuring benchmark performance are NOT investor responsibilities — those are the AMC's domain. The investor's role is informed participation and engagement, not fund management oversight.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers investor responsibilities alongside rights; understanding both sides creates a balanced framework for investor education.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Emphasize the 'own email/mobile' responsibility — SEBI wants direct communication with investors, not through intermediaries. Ensure clients register their personal email/mobile, not yours. This protects both you and the client from communication gaps and compliance issues.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
