<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investment Landscape_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Priya, aged 32, IT professional, monthly investable surplus of Rs. 40,000. Goals: emergency fund (1 year), house down payment (5 years), daughter's education at current cost of Rs. 25,00,000 (15 years), and retirement (28 years). She is comfortable with moderate fluctuations but panics during sharp corrections.

Question 2: Based on the information provided, what is Priya's most likely risk profile?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Aggressive -- because she is young and has a long time horizon for most goals]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Moderate -- because she can tolerate normal fluctuations but panics during sharp corrections, despite having a long time horizon]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative -- because she panics during sharp market corrections]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Very Aggressive -- because her income is high and she has multiple long-term goals]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Risk profiling considers both risk capacity (financial ability to take risk) and risk tolerance (emotional comfort with risk). Priya has high risk capacity (young age, good income, long time horizons) but limited risk tolerance (panics during sharp corrections). The combination of high capacity but moderate tolerance results in a MODERATE risk profile. Risk profiling must consider the lower of the two dimensions.

**The Trap:** Option A focuses only on risk capacity (age, income, time horizon) while ignoring her stated emotional response to market corrections. This is a critical exam concept -- a person's financial profile might suggest "aggressive," but their psychological profile may override this. Option C overweights the panic response while ignoring her stated comfort with moderate fluctuations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between risk capacity and risk tolerance is heavily tested in NISM V-A and X-A (Investment Adviser). SEBI mandates that distributors assess both dimensions before recommending products. Recommending aggressive funds to a person who panics during corrections is a suitability violation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always probe deeper than the questionnaire. Ask clients: "How did you react during the March 2020 COVID crash?" or "If your portfolio dropped 30% in a month, would you add more, hold, or sell everything?" Their instinctive answer reveals true risk tolerance better than any checkbox form.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
