<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Investor Grievance Handling and Redressal_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Amit, an RTA operations manager in Mumbai, receives a claim from a person named Vikram who presents forged documents to claim unclaimed shares from the IEPF. The company verifies the claim using Aadhaar, PAN, and signature matching and discovers the fraud. Under IEPF rules, what is the legal consequence for Vikram?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Vikram will receive a warning letter from the IEPF Authority and be barred from future claims for 5 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Vikram's claim will simply be rejected with no further action]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The RTA will impose a monetary penalty of INR 1 lakh on Vikram for filing a false claim]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The fraudulent claim is treated as fraud under law, and Vikram is liable for prosecution and legal consequences]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under IEPF rules, filing a fraudulent claim is explicitly classified as fraud. The claimant becomes liable for prosecution under applicable laws including the Companies Act, 2013 and the Indian Penal Code. The verification process uses Aadhaar, PAN, Passport, or other government-issued ID along with signature and photo matching to detect fraudulent claims. This is not merely an administrative rejection — it carries serious criminal consequences.

**The Trap:** A simple warning or claim rejection without further action would undermine the integrity of the IEPF claim process. The RTA itself does not have the authority to impose monetary penalties — that is a regulatory or judicial function. The IEPF rules are deliberately stringent to deter fraud and protect the interests of genuine claimants.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Fraud and its consequences are tested across NISM certifications. In Series VIII (Equity Derivatives), fraudulent trading practices carry severe penalties. In Series V-A (Mutual Funds), forged redemption requests have similar legal consequences. The principle that fraud in financial services invites criminal prosecution is universal.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Implement robust verification protocols for all IEPF claims. Cross-verify Aadhaar details with UIDAI, match PAN with the Income Tax database, and use signature verification technology. If fraud is detected, immediately escalate to the company's legal team and cooperate with law enforcement. Document the entire verification trail for evidentiary purposes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
