<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - Process and Underwriting_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE regarding the monetary assets condition under Regulation 6(1) for IPO eligibility?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monetary assets must not exceed 25% of net tangible assets in any of the 3 preceding years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The monetary asset condition applies equally to fresh issue and pure OFS IPOs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not more than 50% of net tangible assets should be in monetary assets, unless utilized or committed; this condition does not apply to pure OFS IPOs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monetary assets include only cash and bank deposits, not investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Regulation 6(1), not more than 50% of the net tangible assets should be held in monetary assets. However, this condition is relaxed if the monetary assets are being utilized or are committed to specific purposes. Importantly, this condition does not apply to IPOs that are purely an Offer for Sale (no fresh issue component).
**The Trap:** The pure OFS exemption is a critical nuance that candidates often miss. In a pure OFS, no new money is being raised by the company, so the end-use restriction on monetary assets is irrelevant.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the distinction between fresh issue and OFS components is fundamental across NISM Series IX and is also relevant in Series V-A when mutual funds participate in IPOs.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If an issuer has high monetary assets and cannot demonstrate utilization plans, consider structuring the IPO as a pure OFS to sidestep this condition — but ensure there are enough eligible selling shareholders to meet the issue size.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
