<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - Process and Underwriting_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A company has an average operating profit of Rs. 20 crore over the past 3 years, but incurred a loss in one of those years. Is it eligible for an IPO under Regulation 6(1)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because the average exceeds Rs. 15 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because operating profit must be positive in each of the 3 years, not just on average]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, if the loss year was the earliest of the three years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because the average operating profit must be at least Rs. 25 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 6(1) requires both conditions to be met: (a) average operating profit of at least Rs. 15 crore over 3 years, AND (b) the company must have earned an operating profit in each of the 3 preceding years. A loss in any single year disqualifies the company, regardless of how high the average may be.
**The Trap:** The average exceeding Rs. 15 crore may seem sufficient, but the "profit in each year" requirement is a separate, conjunctive condition. This is a classic exam trap that tests whether candidates read both parts of the regulation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This type of conjunctive regulatory condition — where ALL criteria must be met simultaneously — is a pattern seen across NISM certifications.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When evaluating IPO readiness, do not rely on averages alone. Review each year's financials individually. If one year shows a loss, the company must either wait or use the alternative QIB route (book building with 75% QIB allotment).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
