<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What must the offer document on the websites of SEBI, lead managers, and stock exchanges match?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The summary version submitted to the stock exchanges for listing purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The latest amended version incorporating all SEBI observations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The printed copies filed with the RoC, SEBI, and stock exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The draft version originally filed, without any subsequent modifications]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The offer document made available on websites must be an exact match of the printed copies filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC), SEBI, and stock exchanges. This ensures consistency — an investor reading the online version gets the same information as one reading the physical copy.

**The Trap:** "Latest amended version incorporating all SEBI observations" sounds logical but is imprecise — the regulation specifically requires matching the filed printed copies, which would already incorporate SEBI's observations if they were addressed before filing.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the concept of document consistency across platforms. This principle extends to mutual fund offer documents (SID/SAI) that must be consistent across AMFI/AMC websites and physical copies.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before the issue opens, download the offer document from each website (SEBI, lead manager, exchanges) and verify page counts and key sections match the RoC-filed copy. Any discrepancy is a compliance risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
