<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - Process and Underwriting_51" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the distinction between 'expertise' and 'non-expertise' portions of an offer document?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Expertise portions are drafted by SEBI, non-expertise portions by the issuer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Expertise portions include financial statements and technical reports where lead managers rely on expert reports, while non-expertise portions are guided by materiality analysis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Expertise portions are optional disclosures, non-expertise portions are mandatory]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no such distinction recognized under SEBI ICDR Regulations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Offer documents contain "expertise" portions (financial statements, technical reports, valuation reports) where lead managers rely on reports from qualified experts like auditors and technical consultants. "Non-expertise" portions are areas where lead managers apply materiality analysis to determine what should be included.
**The Trap:** This distinction is real and recognized — it is not an imaginary classification. It determines the standard of verification expected from lead managers for different parts of the offer document.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of reliance on expert reports is also relevant in NISM Series XV (Research Analyst) when analysts cite expert opinions in their research.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When reading an offer document, note which sections rely on expert reports versus management representations. Expert-certified portions carry more reliability, but always check for qualifications in those expert reports.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>