<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[If a promoter's contribution exceeds Rs. 100 crore, what is the requirement regarding the timing of bringing in the funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire amount must be brought in at least 7 days before the issue opens]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire amount must be brought in at least 1 day before the issue opens]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[At least Rs. 100 crore must be brought before opening, and the rest pro-rata before calls are made to the public]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% must be brought before opening and 50% within 30 days of allotment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When the promoter's contribution exceeds Rs. 100 crore, at least Rs. 100 crore must be brought in before the issue opens (1 day prior), and the balance is required to be brought in pro-rata before calls are made to the public. This staggered approach recognizes the practical difficulty of arranging very large sums at once.

**The Trap:** Option B is the general rule for contributions up to Rs. 100 crore, making it a strong distractor. But the question specifically asks about amounts exceeding Rs. 100 crore, where the staggered provision applies.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests nuances of promoter contribution mechanics. The Rs. 100 crore threshold is a frequently tested boundary condition.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In mega-IPOs, the merchant banker must structure the escrow arrangement to accommodate this staggered schedule, coordinating with the escrow bank and the registrar to ensure compliance at each tranche.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
