<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Securities acquired in the preceding 3 years through revaluation of assets are ineligible for promoters' contribution. What is the rationale behind this restriction?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Revaluation of assets indicates poor financial management by the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Revalued assets are always overpriced and mislead investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI prohibits all non-cash transactions for shares held by promoters]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The consideration did not involve actual cash outflow, so the promoter's real financial commitment is questionable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When securities are acquired through revaluation of assets or capitalization of intangible assets, there is no actual cash outflow from the promoter. SEBI wants to ensure the promoter's contribution reflects genuine financial commitment — not paper transactions. The 3-year look-back period gives a reasonable window for this safeguard.

**The Trap:** "SEBI prohibits all non-cash transactions" is too absolute — SEBI only restricts specific types of non-cash acquisitions within the 3-year window, not all non-cash transactions in perpetuity.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the logic behind regulatory provisions, not just the rules. Understanding the "why" helps in application-type questions across NISM exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In practice, merchant bankers must trace the consideration for each tranche of promoter shares during due diligence. Shares acquired via asset revaluation within 3 years are flagged and excluded from the eligible pool.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
