<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An issuer company wants to include financial data in its issue advertisement. Which of the following is MANDATORY to include as per SEBI ICDR norms?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cash flow statement, EBITDA margins, and return on equity for the last 5 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Revenue, net profit, and working capital ratio for the last 2 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Revenue, net profit, share capital, reserves, EPS, dividends, and book value for the last 5 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Revenue, net profit, share capital, reserves, EPS, dividends, and book value for the last 3 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When an issue advertisement includes financial data, SEBI ICDR Schedule IX requires that it must include seven specific items — revenue, net profit, share capital, reserves, EPS, dividends, and book value — for the last THREE years. The period is 3 years, and all seven parameters are mandatory if any financial data is included.

**The Trap:** The "5 years" distractor with the same seven parameters is a classic exam trap. Remember: 3 years, not 5. Similarly, the "2 years" option uses too short a period and includes a non-mandated metric (working capital ratio).

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XV (Research Analyst) tests requirements for financial data disclosure in research reports — a parallel concept but with different specific rules.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If an issuer wants to highlight only its revenue growth, you cannot allow cherry-picking. Either include all seven parameters for three years, or include no financial data at all.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
