<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When issue highlights are displayed in an advertisement, how must risk factors be presented?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk factors may be placed on a separate page with a reference link in the highlights section]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk factors must be listed but can be in a smaller font to differentiate from highlights]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk factors need not be shown if the advertisement directs readers to the offer document]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Risk factors must be shown with equal prominence as the highlights, in a minimum point seven font size]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI ICDR regulations mandate that whenever issue highlights are presented in an advertisement, the risk factors must also be displayed with EQUAL prominence. Additionally, the minimum font size for risk factors is point seven (7 pt). This ensures investors receive a balanced view.

**The Trap:** "Smaller font to differentiate" is tempting because in many commercial contexts, disclaimers are indeed in fine print. But SEBI explicitly requires equal prominence — not just presence, but equal visual weight.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund Distributors) tests similar norms — mutual fund advertisements must show risk factors with equal prominence and include the standard disclaimer about market risks.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In print ads, measure the font size of your risk factors section. If the highlights are in 12-point font and risk factors are in 7-point, the "equal prominence" test likely fails. Match the formatting as closely as possible.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
