<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_63" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A promoter acquired shares at Rs. 80 per share 8 months ago. The IPO price is Rs. 100 per share. Can the promoter use these shares towards minimum contribution? What is the remedy if they wish to?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, they can be used without any additional payment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, they are ineligible unless the promoter pays the difference of Rs. 20 per share to the issuer company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, they are permanently ineligible regardless of any payment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, provided the promoter holds them for at least 12 months from allotment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Shares acquired in the preceding 1 year at a price lower than the IPO price are ineligible for promoters' minimum contribution. However, they CAN become eligible if the promoter pays the difference (Rs. 100 - Rs. 80 = Rs. 20 per share) to the issuer company.
**The Trap:** The option saying they are permanently ineligible is too absolute — SEBI provides a remedy through payment of the price difference. The option about holding for 12 months confuses the 1-year lookback with a holding period requirement.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This pricing remedy for ineligible shares is a nuanced topic tested in NISM Series IX. It demonstrates SEBI's approach of providing practical solutions rather than outright prohibitions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The pay-the-difference remedy exists because SEBI wants to prevent promoters from getting a cheap entry relative to public investors, not to permanently exclude shares from contribution.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
