<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What must the lead manager submit to SEBI regarding news reports published between the filing of the offer document and issue closure?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A compilation of all news reports with annotations identifying factual errors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A rebuttal document correcting any misleading news coverage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A compliance certificate certifying that the news reports are in compliance with SEBI regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A request for SEBI to issue directions to media outlets publishing non-compliant reports]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The lead manager is required to submit a compliance certificate to SEBI regarding news reports published between the filing of the offer document and issue closure. This certificate confirms that the news reports are in compliance with SEBI regulations — essentially certifying that the lead manager has monitored media coverage and it does not contain misleading or non-compliant content.

**The Trap:** "Compilation with annotations" and "rebuttal document" sound like proactive monitoring activities, but the specific regulatory requirement is a compliance certificate — a formal attestation, not a detailed report.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the lead manager's gatekeeper role extensively. The compliance certificate for news reports is one of several certifications the lead manager must provide to SEBI.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Set up a media monitoring service from the day of filing. Track all news mentions of the issuer and the issue. This becomes the basis for your compliance certificate — you need to be able to stand behind it.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
