<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - Process and Underwriting_58" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under Regulation 109, what happens if a holder of optionally convertible debentures does not respond (remains silent) when given the option to convert?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Silence is treated as consent to convert]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Positive consent is required; silence does NOT equal consent, and non-exercisers are redeemed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The debentures are automatically rolled over for another term]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lead manager decides on behalf of the silent holder]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 109 explicitly provides that silence does NOT equal consent for optional CDI conversion. Positive consent is required from holders who wish to convert. Those who do not exercise the conversion option (non-exercisers) must be redeemed within 1 month at not less than face value.
**The Trap:** In many corporate actions, silence or non-response is treated as deemed consent. Regulation 109 is a notable exception — it protects investors by requiring affirmative action for conversion, ensuring no one is converted against their will.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of opt-in versus opt-out mechanisms is tested across NISM exams, including Series V-A (mutual fund systematic plan renewals) and Series X-A (client consent requirements).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always advise clients holding optional CDIs to actively respond — whether converting or not. Non-response leads to redemption at face value, which might be disadvantageous if the underlying equity has appreciated significantly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>