<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_46" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the minimum annualized trading turnover requirement for Fast Track Issue eligibility?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[At least 2% of the weighted average number of listed shares during the 6 months before the reference date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At least 5% of total listed shares during the preceding 12 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At least 10% of the weighted average public shareholding in the preceding year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At least 1% of total market capitalization during the preceding 6 months]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For Fast Track Issue eligibility, the annualized trading turnover on any nationwide terminal exchange must be at least 2% of the weighted average number of listed shares during the 6 months before the reference date. If public shareholding is less than 15%, this threshold is computed as 2% of free float weighted average instead.

**The Trap:** "10% of weighted average public shareholding" confuses two separate FTI criteria — 10% is the threshold for delivery-based turnover as a proportion of total annualized turnover, not the trading turnover requirement.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests multiple quantitative thresholds for Fast Track Issues. Candidates must remember the distinct percentages and their respective bases (trading turnover vs. delivery turnover).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The 2% trading turnover threshold ensures sufficient market liquidity. Companies with low trading volumes — even if large — may fail this test, which protects investors from illiquid fast-track issues.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
