<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A material development occurs between the filing of the offer document and allotment. How must this be disclosed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[By filing a supplementary document with SEBI within 7 days of the development]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Promptly, through public notices in the same newspapers used for the pre-issue advertisement, with true and fair disclosure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[By updating the offer document on the SEBI website and notifying the stock exchanges by email]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[By issuing a press release through two national news agencies within 48 hours]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Any material development between filing and allotment must be disclosed promptly, in a true and fair manner, through public notices published in the SAME newspapers that were used for the pre-issue advertisement. This ensures the information reaches the same audience that saw the original issue announcement.

**The Trap:** "Filing a supplementary document with SEBI" is a separate requirement under certain circumstances but is not the primary disclosure mechanism for material developments. The immediate obligation is public notice in the same newspapers.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) and NISM Series XII (Securities Markets Foundation) test material event disclosure requirements for listed companies under LODR regulations — a parallel concept for post-listing disclosures.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a list of the newspapers used for the pre-issue advertisement. When a material development occurs, you need to act fast — identify the same publications and place the notice without delay.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
