<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under what condition can locked-in securities forming part of minimum promoters' contribution be pledged?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They can be pledged to any lender for any purpose as long as the lock-in continues]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum promoters' contribution can never be pledged during the lock-in period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Only if the loan is granted to the issuer or its subsidiary for the objects of the issue, and the pledge is a term of the sanction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only if the pledge is approved by a special resolution of shareholders]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Locked-in securities forming part of minimum promoters' contribution (under Reg 16(a)) can be pledged ONLY as collateral for a loan granted to the issuer company or its subsidiary, where the loan is for the objects stated in the offer document and the pledge is one of the terms of the sanction. This is a very narrow exception.

**The Trap:** "They can never be pledged" is too absolute — SEBI does allow pledging under specific, restrictive conditions. The key restriction is that the loan must benefit the issuer (not the promoter personally) for issue objects.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX distinguishes between pledge conditions for minimum contribution (Reg 16(a)) versus excess holdings (Reg 16(b)), which have different requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The distinction is crucial — minimum contribution can only be pledged for the issuer's benefit, while excess holdings have a broader pledge permission. In either case, the lock-in continues even after pledge invocation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
