<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_50" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In a Fast Track Issue involving a rights issue, what restriction applies to promoters regarding their rights entitlement?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Promoters must renounce their entire rights entitlement in favor of public shareholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Promoters must subscribe to at least 50% of their rights entitlement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Promoters must subscribe to their full rights entitlement and cannot renounce except within the promoter group or for minimum public shareholding compliance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There are no restrictions on promoters regarding rights entitlement in Fast Track Issues]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In a Fast Track Issue involving rights, promoters are required to subscribe to their full rights entitlement. They cannot renounce their rights except in two specific cases: (1) renunciation to other members within the promoter group, or (2) renunciation necessary to comply with minimum public shareholding (MPS) requirements. This ensures promoters maintain their commitment to the company.

**The Trap:** "No restrictions" is incorrect — the Fast Track route comes with stricter governance expectations, not fewer. The renunciation restriction is a key safeguard that prevents promoters from diluting their stake through a rights issue while enjoying the FTI's streamlined process.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the specific conditions attached to Fast Track Issues comprehensively. The promoter renunciation restriction is a distinctive feature of the FTI framework.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The MPS exception is practical — if promoter holding would exceed the maximum permissible level after subscribing to the full rights entitlement, renunciation is allowed to ensure LODR compliance. Merchant bankers must verify this calculation before the issue.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
