<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What information is permitted on a BILLBOARD advertisement for a public issue?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Full issue highlights along with risk factors in equal prominence]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Only information as specified in Part D of Schedule X, along with advice to refer to the offer document]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any information from the offer document, provided the lead manager has approved it]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Company name, issue size, price band, and lead manager details only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Billboard advertisements for public issues are restricted to displaying ONLY the information specified in Part D of Schedule X of SEBI ICDR Regulations. Additionally, the billboard must advise viewers to refer to the offer document for complete details. This is because billboards have limited space and cannot provide the balanced, comprehensive information that investor protection requires.

**The Trap:** "Full issue highlights along with risk factors" would be appropriate for a newspaper advertisement but is too much for a billboard. "Any information from the offer document with lead manager approval" overstates what is permitted — even with approval, only Schedule X Part D content is allowed.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests medium-specific advertisement rules — different rules apply to TV, billboards, print, and digital media. Each has its own permitted content and restrictions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Billboard space is expensive and limited. Knowing exactly what Part D of Schedule X permits helps you design compliant billboards without wasted iterations with legal teams.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
