<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Between the filing of the draft offer document and the date of allotment, what must be prominently disclosed in the issuer's public communications?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The expected listing date and projected market price]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The proposed issue and the availability of the draft offer document on websites of SEBI, lead managers, and stock exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The names of all intermediaries involved and their SEBI registration numbers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A summary of the risk factors section from the offer document]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Once the draft offer document is filed and until allotment, all public communications by the issuer must prominently disclose: (a) the proposed issue of securities, and (b) that the draft offer document is available for viewing on the websites of SEBI, the lead managers, and the stock exchanges.

**The Trap:** "Expected listing date and projected market price" sounds like useful investor information but is actually speculative and not mandated. The regulation focuses on directing investors to the official document, not on providing trading-related projections.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) tests the concept of material disclosure in the context of listed securities, reinforcing the principle of full and fair disclosure.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always include the exact URLs where the draft offer document can be accessed. Merely saying "available on SEBI website" without the specific link may not meet the "prominent disclosure" standard in practice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
