<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Between the date of the board resolution approving the issue and the filing of the draft offer document, what are the communication rules for the issuer company?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The issuer must cease all public communications until the draft offer document is filed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The issuer may only communicate through the lead manager's official channels]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Communications must be consistent with past practices, or the issuer must disclose the upcoming issue in such communications]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The issuer must publish a public notice about the upcoming issue within 48 hours of the board resolution]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Between the board resolution and filing of the draft offer document, there is no blanket communication ban. The issuer can continue communications consistent with its past practices. However, if the communication departs from past patterns (e.g., suddenly issuing promotional content), the issuer must disclose that it is planning an upcoming issue.

**The Trap:** "Cease all public communications" is an over-reading of the regulation. SEBI does not impose a blackout — it imposes a consistency test. This distinction is critical for the exam.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series XV (Research Analyst) tests "quiet period" restrictions that apply to research analysts during IPOs — a related but distinct set of communication restrictions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Document the issuer's communication history for 6-12 months before the board resolution. This becomes your benchmark for what constitutes "consistent with past practices."]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
