<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the maximum age of financial information at the time of filing the DRHP/RHP AND at the time of issue opening?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not more than 6 months old at BOTH the time of filing and the time of issue opening]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not more than 3 months old at filing and 6 months old at issue opening]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not more than 6 months old at filing; no restriction at issue opening]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not more than 12 months old at both filing and issue opening]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Financial information included in the offer document must be not more than 6 months old at TWO checkpoints: (1) at the time of filing the DRHP/RHP, AND (2) at the time of opening of the issue. This dual requirement ensures that investors always see reasonably current financial data.

**The Trap:** "6 months at filing; no restriction at opening" is tempting because candidates may think the document review at filing is the final check. But the regulation imposes a SECOND freshness test at the issue opening date, which may require updating financials if there has been a long gap between filing and opening.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Companies Act rules impose a related but different standard — audited financials must be not more than 120 days old from the prospectus date. Both rules can apply simultaneously.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If the gap between DRHP filing and issue opening exceeds a few months, proactively update financial statements. Getting caught with stale financials at issue opening can delay or derail the entire issue.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
