<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A promoter acquired shares at Rs. 80 per share 10 months ago. The IPO price is fixed at Rs. 120. Under what condition can these shares be counted toward promoters' contribution?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[If the promoter pays the difference of Rs. 40 per share to the issuer company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[These shares can never be counted as they were acquired within 1 year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[If the promoter holds them for at least 6 more months before the issue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[If the promoter provides an undertaking to not sell for 3 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Securities acquired in the preceding 1 year at a price lower than the IPO price are normally ineligible. However, an exception exists: if the promoter pays the difference between the acquisition price and the IPO price to the issuer, those shares become eligible. Here, the promoter pays Rs. 40 per share (Rs. 120 - Rs. 80) to the issuer.

**The Trap:** "These shares can never be counted" sounds definitive and safe, but ignores the specific exception carved out in the regulations. SEBI allows a cure mechanism through price top-up.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a classic application-type question tested in NISM Series IX. Understanding exceptions to general rules is critical for merchant banking practice.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In live transactions, merchant bankers must calculate the price differential and ensure the promoter deposits the difference with the issuer before the contribution deadline. This is documented in the offer document.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
