<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_41" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Can locked-in shares held by a promoter be transferred to another promoter within the promoter group?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, locked-in shares cannot be transferred under any circumstances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, and the lock-in is released upon such transfer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but the transferee must hold them for the remaining lock-in period and cannot further transfer until lock-in expires]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only with prior SEBI approval and payment of a transfer fee]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Locked-in securities held by promoters CAN be transferred to another promoter, a member of the promoter group, or a new promoter. However, the lock-in travels with the shares — the transferee must hold them for the remaining lock-in period and cannot transfer them further until the lock-in expires.

**The Trap:** "Lock-in is released upon transfer" would completely undermine the purpose of the lock-in. SEBI ensures continuity by making the lock-in attach to the securities, not the person.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the transferability rules for both promoter and non-promoter locked-in shares. The rules differ slightly — promoters can transfer only to other promoters, while non-promoters can transfer to any person holding locked-in securities.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This provision facilitates family restructuring or promoter group reorganization without violating lock-in norms. Merchant bankers must ensure the transferee qualifies as a promoter or promoter group member.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
