<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_38" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What happens to the lock-in status of shares lent by a pre-issue shareholder to the stabilizing agent under a green shoe option?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lock-in is permanently waived for those shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lock-in continues to run during the lending period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The shares are NOT subject to lock-in during the lending period; lock-in resumes for the remaining period when returned]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lock-in period is doubled to compensate for the lending period]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When pre-issue shares are lent to the stabilizing agent under a green shoe option arrangement, these shares are exempt from lock-in during the lending period. Once the shares are returned to the lender, the lock-in resumes for the remaining period. This is a practical exception — the shares need to be freely tradeable for price stabilization purposes.

**The Trap:** "The lock-in continues to run during the lending period" sounds logical and conservative, but this would defeat the purpose of the green shoe option since the stabilizing agent needs to sell these shares in the market.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Green shoe options and price stabilization mechanisms are tested in NISM Series IX. Understanding how lock-in interacts with these mechanisms is a nuanced topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The green shoe option typically covers up to 15% of the issue size. Merchant bankers must carefully document the lending arrangement and track the lock-in resumption date when shares are returned.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
