<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A lead merchant banker discovers that an issue advertisement reproduces only selected positive extracts from the offer document's management discussion section. What is the compliance issue?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no issue as long as the extracts are factually accurate and sourced from the offer document]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is permitted if the advertisement also includes the SEBI disclaimer statement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is only a violation if the omitted portions contain material risk factors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It violates the rule that information reproduced from the offer document must be reproduced in FULL, not as selective extracts]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI ICDR regulations require that if information from the offer document is reproduced in an advertisement, it must be reproduced in FULL — not as selective or cherry-picked extracts. This prevents issuers from creating a misleadingly positive impression by extracting only favorable portions.

**The Trap:** "No issue as long as extracts are factually accurate" is a dangerous trap. Even 100% factually accurate extracts can be misleading if they are selectively chosen. The regulation addresses the completeness of reproduction, not just accuracy.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This principle parallels the "fair and balanced" communication requirements tested in NISM Series XV (Research Analyst) and NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund Distributors), where selective presentation of data is considered misleading.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When reviewing ad copy, any quotation marks or phrases like "as stated in the offer document" should trigger a full-text comparison. Verify that the full section is reproduced, not just the flattering parts.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
