<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Who is responsible for handling allotment, refund, and dispatch of certificates in the post-issue process?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The registrar to the issue, independently and without merchant banker supervision]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The issuer company's board of directors through its company secretary]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The post-issue lead merchant banker, who also gives instructions to syndicate members and SCSBs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI, through its Division of Issues and Listing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The post-issue lead merchant banker is responsible for ensuring proper handling of allotment, refund, and dispatch of certificates. This merchant banker also issues instructions to syndicate members and Self Certified Syndicate Banks (SCSBs). Additionally, the post-issue lead MB monitors investor grievance redressal.

**The Trap:** While the registrar performs the operational work of allotment processing, the regulatory responsibility and oversight lies with the post-issue lead merchant banker. The registrar acts under the MB's supervision, not independently.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the distinction between the "post-issue lead merchant banker" role and other intermediaries. Understanding who bears ultimate responsibility is a recurring exam theme.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In practice, the post-issue lead MB should maintain a daily status tracker covering application processing, allotment, refund initiation, and demat credit — with clear escalation paths for delays.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
