<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Issue Management - General Obligations and Due Diligence_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What happens if the dispatch of refund orders or allotment letters is delayed beyond the prescribed timeline?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI imposes a flat penalty of Rs. 1 lakh per day of delay on the lead merchant banker]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The issuer company must pay interest to the applicants for the period of delay]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The stock exchange suspends the listing approval until all dispatches are completed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The lead merchant banker's SEBI registration is placed under review for non-compliance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If dispatch of refund orders or allotment letters is delayed beyond the prescribed timeline, the issuer company is required to pay interest to the applicants for the period of delay. This serves as both compensation to investors and a financial deterrent against delays. The dispatch must be made by registered post or certificate of posting.

**The Trap:** "SEBI imposes a flat penalty" sounds authoritative but the prescribed consequence is specifically interest payment to applicants, not a regulatory penalty. While SEBI may separately take enforcement action, the direct regulatory requirement is interest payment.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the consequences of non-compliance at multiple points. Interest for delayed dispatch is one of the few instances where the regulation prescribes a specific financial remedy for investors rather than just a penalty for the intermediary.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Factor the potential interest cost into the issue timeline planning. If a holiday season or operational bottleneck could delay dispatch, plan the issue timeline accordingly to avoid both the financial and reputational cost of paying delay interest.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
