<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="IV Regulatory Framework_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A mid-sized corporate wants to hedge its floating rate loan exposure using exchange-traded interest rate derivatives. The company has no existing exchange membership. What steps must it take to participate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Open a trading account with a SEBI-registered broker who is a member of the IRD segment, provide documentation of underlying exposure, and trade through the broker]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Apply directly to the exchange for membership and start trading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtain RBI permission and then approach any bank for execution]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Corporates are not allowed to participate in ETIRD]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A corporate without exchange membership must trade through a registered broker (TM) who is a member of the IRD segment. The corporate opens a trading account, provides documentation of underlying exposure (floating rate loan), and the broker executes trades on their behalf.

**The Trap:** Direct membership requires significant capital and infrastructure - most corporates trade through brokers. RBI permission is not needed for exchange-traded products. Corporates ARE allowed to participate.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The client-broker relationship is standard across all exchange-traded segments. The additional requirement for IRD is documentation of underlying exposure for hedging.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For corporates, the broker should ensure suitability - that the IRD product actually hedges the corporate's risk and the corporate understands the product. This is both a regulatory requirement and good business practice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>