<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC and Compliance Requirements_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[How does the KYC process accommodate persons with disabilities who cannot complete standard liveness tests?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Persons with disabilities are exempt from digital KYC and must complete paper-based KYC only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No special provisions exist; standard procedures apply to all investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A family member can complete liveness tests on behalf of the person with disability]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Alternative liveness tests such as facial expressions, head nods, or OTP display on screen are permitted]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For persons with disabilities who cannot complete standard video KYC liveness tests (like reading random numbers, blinking, etc.), alternative tests are permitted — including facial expressions, head nods, displaying OTP on screen, and other accessible methods. This ensures digital KYC inclusion without compromising verification integrity.
**The Trap:** The provision is for alternative liveness tests within digital KYC, not an exemption from digital KYC itself. Persons with disabilities can and should access digital KYC through these accommodations.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B specifically tests accessibility provisions in KYC; this reflects SEBI's commitment to financial inclusion for all categories of investors.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When assisting clients with disabilities through digital KYC, inform the KYC platform/KRA about the disability type beforehand so appropriate alternative liveness tests can be configured. Patience and sensitivity during this process builds lasting client relationships.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
