<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC Guidelines_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[If a client's officially valid document does not contain an updated address, which of the following can be accepted as proof of address on a temporary basis?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Utility bill not more than two months old, property tax receipt, pension payment order, or employer accommodation letter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any document regardless of date, as long as it shows an address]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a bank statement not more than one year old]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A self-declaration by the client on plain paper]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Rule 9(18) of PML Rules, when the OVD does not have an updated address, the following can be accepted as temporary PoA: (i) utility bill not more than 2 months old, (ii) property/municipal tax receipt, (iii) pension/family pension payment orders, or (iv) employer accommodation allotment letter. However, the client must submit an updated OVD within 3 months.

**The Trap:** The utility bill must be NOT MORE THAN 2 MONTHS OLD. A bank statement is not in this list. Self-declaration alone is not accepted. The 3-month deadline for submitting updated OVD is critical.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-A, mutual fund distributors frequently encounter this situation where a client has moved but hasn't updated their OVD. The temporary acceptance provision helps onboard such clients.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When accepting a utility bill as temporary PoA, note the 2-month validity limit and set a reminder for the 3-month deadline to collect the updated OVD. Document the acceptance in the client file with the expected date for updated documents.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
