<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC Guidelines_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under KYC guidelines, if a client's proof of address document is in a foreign language, what additional requirement must be fulfilled?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Translation of the document into English is required]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Translation of the document into Hindi is required as it is the official language]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A notarized copy of the original document is sufficient without any translation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Attestation by the respective country's embassy or consulate is required in lieu of translation]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** KYC guidelines specify that if a proof of address document is in a foreign language, a translation into English is required. This ensures that the intermediary's compliance team can verify and understand the document contents for due diligence purposes.

**The Trap:** Candidates may assume Hindi is acceptable since it is an official language of India, but the KYC requirement specifically mandates English translation. A notarized copy without translation does not resolve the language barrier. Embassy attestation, while it may authenticate the document, does not substitute for the translation requirement.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This requirement is particularly relevant for Non-Resident Indians (NRIs), Foreign Portfolio Investors (FPIs), and foreign nationals opening accounts with Indian intermediaries, where address proof documents are commonly issued in non-English languages.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Foreign language proof of address documents must be translated into English for KYC purposes - notarization, embassy attestation, or Hindi translation are not acceptable substitutes for English translation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
