<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC and Compliance Requirements_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A company wants to invest in mutual funds. Which of the following documents is NOT typically required from the company?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[List of authorized signatories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Personal bank statements of all directors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Board Resolution authorizing the investment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Memorandum of Association (MoA) and Articles of Association (AoA)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For company investments, the required documents typically include: MoA/AoA (establishing identity and investment powers), Board Resolution (authorizing the specific investment), list of authorized signatories (for transaction processing), PAN of the company, and KYC of the company and authorized signatories. Personal bank statements of directors are NOT required — the investment is in the company's name from the company's bank account.
**The Trap:** Directors' personal financial information is irrelevant for the company's investment — the company is a separate legal entity. Some candidates confuse company KYC with individual director KYC.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers institutional investor documentation; Series II-B tests the RTA's document verification checklist for different entity types.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Company investments have the most documentation — maintain a comprehensive checklist and verify all documents before submission. The most common rejection reasons are: expired Board Resolution, unsigned signatory list, or MoA without investment clause. Pre-verify everything.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
