<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC and Compliance Requirements_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[How does DigiLocker contribute to reducing unclaimed mutual fund assets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[DigiLocker stores mutual fund account statements and enables nominee notification on the investor's demise, making it easier for nominees/heirs to trace investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[DigiLocker automatically redeems unclaimed investments and credits them to the investor's bank]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[DigiLocker sends daily reminders to investors about their pending mutual fund investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[DigiLocker prevents investments from becoming unclaimed by blocking redemptions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** DigiLocker helps reduce unclaimed mutual fund assets by: (1) storing account statements digitally so investors and their families can access them, and (2) enabling a mechanism for nominee notification upon the investor's demise. This ensures that nominees/legal heirs are aware of and can claim the mutual fund investments, reducing the pool of unclaimed assets.
**The Trap:** DigiLocker doesn't process any transactions — it's a document storage and access platform. It helps in discovery of investments, not in their automatic processing.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-B covers DigiLocker's role in the MF ecosystem; the unclaimed assets problem is a significant industry issue that DigiLocker helps address.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Encourage ALL clients to link their mutual fund statements to DigiLocker and inform their family members about it. In the unfortunate event of the investor's demise, this single step can save nominees months of searching for investment records across multiple AMCs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
