<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC and Compliance Requirements_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What additional information is required from investors whose birth country, citizenship, or tax residency is outside India, under FATCA/CRS requirements?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A letter from their employer confirming overseas posting]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A certificate from the Indian embassy in their country of residence]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Self-declaration of all countries of tax residency, Tax Identification Numbers, and the nature of their tax obligations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only their overseas bank account details]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FATCA/CRS requires investors with foreign tax residency indicators to provide: a self-declaration form listing all countries where they are tax residents, their Tax Identification Numbers (TIN) for each country, and details about the nature of their tax status. This information is then reported to CBDT for exchange with the relevant foreign tax authorities.
**The Trap:** It's not just about having an overseas connection — the requirement is specifically about tax residency. An Indian citizen working abroad may have dual tax residency obligations that must be declared.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers FATCA/CRS basics; Series II-B tests the RTA's role in collecting, validating, and reporting FATCA/CRS data.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** FATCA/CRS compliance is not optional — missing or incomplete declarations can result in the folio being frozen. When onboarding any investor, ask about overseas connections upfront. The FATCA self-certification form should be completed at the time of initial investment, not as an afterthought.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
