<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC Guidelines_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the consequence if a Permanent Account Number (PAN) is not linked with Aadhaar as required under the Income-tax Act, 1961?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The PAN becomes inoperative]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The PAN is permanently cancelled and a new PAN must be applied for]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A monetary fine is imposed on the PAN holder but the PAN remains functional]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no consequence as Aadhaar linkage with PAN is optional]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Income-tax Act, 1961, if a PAN is not linked with Aadhaar, the PAN becomes inoperative. This means it cannot be used for financial transactions that require PAN quotation, such as opening demat accounts, securities trading, or mutual fund investments. The PAN is not cancelled - it becomes inoperative, which is a distinct legal status.

**The Trap:** "Permanently cancelled" sounds severe and plausible but is incorrect - an inoperative PAN can be made operative again by completing the Aadhaar linkage. The "fine imposed" option confuses the consequence with penalty provisions. The "no consequence" option is flatly wrong as linkage is mandatory.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For KYC in securities markets, an inoperative PAN creates significant practical problems. Intermediaries cannot accept an inoperative PAN for account opening or transaction purposes, making this a critical KYC checkpoint.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PAN becomes inoperative (not cancelled) if not linked with Aadhaar - this directly impacts a client's ability to transact in securities markets and is a key KYC verification point for intermediaries.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
