<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="KYC and Compliance Requirements_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ananya has NRE and NRO accounts. She invested Rs.10,00,000 in an equity fund through her NRE account and wants to redeem after 2 years. What is the key implication of the NRE account route?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[LTCG rate is lower for NRE account investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NRE account investments are exempt from capital gains tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Redemption proceeds are fully repatriable outside India since the original investment was from an NRE account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No TDS is deducted on NRE account investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Investments made through an NRE account have the key benefit of full repatriability — both the principal and gains can be freely remitted outside India. This is because NRE accounts hold foreign earnings already subject to exchange control clearance. NRO account investments have restricted repatriability (subject to $1M per year limit). Tax treatment (LTCG/STCG rates) is the same regardless of the account type used.
**The Trap:** NRE route does NOT provide any tax benefit — LTCG/STCG rates and TDS obligations are identical for NRE and NRO routes. The difference is purely about repatriation rights.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers NRI investment repatriation rules; Series II-B tests the RTA's responsibility in tagging the investment source (NRE vs NRO) for redemption processing.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For NRI clients who may want to take money back abroad, ALWAYS recommend the NRE route. Once invested through NRO, converting to repatriable is complex and requires CA certification. Getting the account choice right at the investment stage saves significant hassle later.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
