<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_54" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Mrs. Patel notices in her Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) that Ravi earned a commission of Rs. 25,000 on her investment. She is upset and asks Ravi: "Why didn't you tell me about this commission? And why is your commission so high?"

Question 4: Which of the following statements about commission disclosure is CORRECT as per SEBI regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Distributors are not required to disclose commissions to investors — the CAS should not have shown this information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Commission disclosure in CAS is optional and depends on the AMC's policy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI mandates commission disclosure in the CAS. Ravi should have proactively disclosed his commission structure upfront. The commission is paid by the scheme (from TER), not separately by the investor, and is already factored into the NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The commission shown is incorrect — distributors only earn trail commission, never upfront commission, so the CAS is in error]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated commission disclosure in the Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) as part of its transparency initiative. The commission paid to distributors comes from the Total Expense Ratio (TER) charged to the scheme — it is NOT a separate charge to the investor. The commission is already reflected in the NAV difference between Direct Plan (lower TER) and Regular Plan (higher TER due to distributor commission). While SEBI mandates disclosure in CAS, good practice (and AMFI Code of Conduct) requires distributors to proactively inform clients about their commission structure upfront.

**The Trap:** Commission disclosure is MANDATORY, not optional (Options A and B). Both upfront and trail commissions can exist depending on the AMC's payout structure (Option D is incorrect in claiming only trail exists). The key understanding is that the commission is embedded in TER and reflected in NAV — the investor does not pay it separately, but transparency requires disclosure.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Commission transparency is a major SEBI reform tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-C. The distinction between upfront commissions (now restricted) and trail commissions (preferred model) is important. Series III-C (Investment Adviser) compares fee-only advice vs commission-based distribution.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients question your commission (as Mrs. Patel did), be transparent and confident. Explain: (1) the commission is paid from the scheme's TER, not from their pocket, (2) it compensates you for ongoing service — portfolio reviews, tax reporting help, and behavioral guidance during market volatility, (3) they can always invest through the Direct Plan if they prefer to manage their investments independently. Transparency builds trust.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
