<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_46" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly distinguishes the minimum investment requirement between Mutual Funds, Portfolio Management Services (PMS), and Alternative Investment Funds (AIFs)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MF: Rs. 5,000 minimum; PMS: Rs. 25 lakh; AIF: Rs. 25 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MF: Rs. 500 minimum; PMS: Rs. 50 lakh; AIF: Rs. 50 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[MF: As low as Rs. 100-500 (no regulatory minimum for lump sum; SIPs from Rs. 100); PMS: Rs. 50 lakh; AIF: Rs. 1 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MF: Rs. 1,000 minimum; PMS: Rs. 1 crore; AIF: Rs. 50 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mutual Funds have the lowest entry barrier with SIPs available from as low as Rs. 100 (SEBI does not prescribe a regulatory minimum for lump sum investments; AMCs set their own minimums, typically Rs. 100-5,000). PMS requires a minimum investment of Rs. 50 lakh (raised from Rs. 25 lakh by SEBI in 2020). AIFs require a minimum investment of Rs. 1 crore (except for employees/directors of the AIF or fund manager). This tiered structure reflects the different risk profiles and investor sophistication expected for each product.

**The Trap:** Candidates commonly confuse PMS (Rs. 50 lakh) and AIF (Rs. 1 crore) minimums, especially since PMS was Rs. 25 lakh before 2020. Option A uses the OLD PMS minimum. Option D incorrectly swaps PMS and AIF minimums. The MF minimum is effectively set by AMCs, not SEBI regulation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This comparison is a classic "cluster confusion" question that could appear in Series V-A (MF), Series III-A (Securities Intermediaries), or AIF/PMS-specific certifications. Understanding the product hierarchy (MF → PMS → AIF) by minimum investment, regulation, and investor type is critical.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This comparison is valuable when positioning mutual funds against PMS and AIF for different client segments. For clients with Rs. 50 lakh+, you can discuss PMS as an alternative. For those with Rs. 1 crore+, AIFs become relevant. But for most retail clients, mutual funds remain the most accessible and well-regulated vehicle.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
