<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[AMFI (Association of Mutual Funds in India) functions as a:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Self-regulatory organization of the mutual fund industry]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Statutory regulator with enforcement powers over mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Government body under the Ministry of Finance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Subsidiary of SEBI responsible for mutual fund oversight]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** AMFI is a self-regulatory organization (SRO) of the mutual fund industry. It is an industry association of all SEBI-registered mutual funds. AMFI works under the overall supervision of SEBI but is not a government body, nor a statutory regulator, nor a SEBI subsidiary. AMFI has established a Code of Conduct for intermediaries (including distributors) and works to promote best practices in the industry.

**The Trap:** The "statutory regulator" option is the most dangerous distractor because AMFI does issue guidelines and codes of conduct. However, the statutory regulator of mutual funds is SEBI, not AMFI. AMFI's powers are self-regulatory and industry-driven, not backed by statute in the way SEBI's powers are under the SEBI Act, 1992.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM V-B and III-C, understand the hierarchy: SEBI is the statutory regulator, AMFI is the self-regulatory body, and stock exchanges provide the trading platform. AMFI's Code of Conduct is directly testable in the NISM V-A exam and is a critical document for distributors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As an AMFI-registered distributor (with an ARN number), you are bound by AMFI's Code of Conduct. Violations can lead to suspension of your ARN. Treat AMFI guidelines as seriously as SEBI regulations — they directly affect your livelihood.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
