<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[XYZ Financial Services wants to become the sponsor of a new mutual fund. The company has been in financial services for 7 years, has maintained positive net worth for 6 consecutive years, and has earned an average net profit of Rs. 12 crore over the past 5 years. However, the company's net worth was negative in one year, 4 years ago. Is XYZ eligible to sponsor a mutual fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because the company meets the experience, profit, and current net worth criteria]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because having positive net worth for 6 out of the last 7 years exceeds the minimum requirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because the sponsor must have positive net worth in ALL of the immediately preceding five years, and the company had a negative net worth year within that window]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because the minimum average net profit required is Rs. 15 crore, not Rs. 12 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The question requires applying all four sponsor eligibility criteria: (1) 5+ years in financial services — MET (7 years), (2) positive net worth in ALL immediately preceding 5 years — NOT MET (negative in one year, 4 years ago, which falls within the 5-year window), (3) average net profit of Rs. 10 crore over 5 years — MET (Rs. 12 crore), (4) fit and proper person — assumed met. Since the positive net worth criterion requires ALL five years to be positive and one year within that window was negative, XYZ is NOT eligible.

**The Trap:** Option A is the most tempting wrong answer because three out of four criteria are clearly met, and the net worth IS positive now. But the regulation says "all of the immediately preceding five years" — not "currently positive." Option B tries to mislead by making 6 out of 7 sound impressive, but the rule has no averaging or "most years" provision. Option D cites a fictional Rs. 15 crore threshold.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Application questions on sponsor eligibility appear in NISM V-A and V-B. The key skill is checking EACH criterion independently. In NISM III-C, compliance officers must verify all eligibility conditions before recommending sponsor applications — missing one criterion means the entire application fails.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This question teaches a valuable professional lesson: in regulatory compliance, "almost qualifying" is the same as "not qualifying." When evaluating fund houses for your clients, understand that every sponsor had to clear ALL these hurdles, not just most of them.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
