<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations 1996, a mutual fund in India is constituted as a:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trust under the Indian Trusts Act, 1882]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Company under the Companies Act, 2013]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Limited Liability Partnership under the LLP Act, 2008]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Body corporate under the Indian Partnership Act, 1932]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations 1996 explicitly define a mutual fund as a "trust" set up under the Indian Trusts Act, 1882. The trust raises money by selling units to the public and invests the pooled corpus in securities, gold, silver, or real estate as permitted.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse the legal structure of a mutual fund (Trust) with the legal structure of the AMC (Company). The AMC that manages the fund is a company, but the mutual fund itself is a trust. Similarly, Alternative Investment Funds (AIFs) can be set up as trusts, companies, or LLPs — but mutual funds can ONLY be trusts.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This distinction is critical for NISM Series III-C (Compliance) where you must differentiate between how MFs, AIFs, and PMS are legally structured. PMS operates under a portfolio manager registered with SEBI, not as a trust.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining to clients why their MF investment is safe, highlight that the trust structure creates a legal separation between the fund's assets and the AMC's assets. Even if the AMC faces financial trouble, the investors' money in the trust remains protected.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
