<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_43" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An AMC wants to launch a new "ESG Thematic Fund" while it already operates an existing "Infrastructure Thematic Fund." Under SEBI's scheme categorization rules, is this permitted?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because Sectoral/Thematic is one category but different themes (ESG vs Infrastructure) are treated as different sub-categories allowing multiple schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because the one-scheme-per-category rule prohibits having two thematic funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only if the existing Infrastructure Fund is merged into the ESG Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because ESG is not a recognized SEBI category for mutual funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI's categorization norms, Sectoral/Thematic is listed as one category, but AMCs are permitted to have multiple schemes under this category as long as each scheme covers a different sector or theme. ESG (Environmental, Social, and Governance) and Infrastructure are distinct themes, so an AMC can operate both simultaneously. SEBI specifically recognized ESG as a valid thematic category and issued guidelines for ESG-related schemes including disclosure requirements and third-party ESG rating mandates.

**The Trap:** The "one scheme per category" rule has exceptions, and Sectoral/Thematic is one of them. Similarly, Index Funds/ETFs tracking different indices and Fund of Funds with different underlying funds can have multiple schemes. Option D is wrong because SEBI has specifically recognized and regulated ESG funds. Option C's forced merger is unnecessary given the exception.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The exceptions to the one-scheme-per-category rule are frequently tested in Series V-A and V-B. ESG fund regulations are a newer topic that reflects SEBI's evolving product framework. Understanding which categories allow exceptions is critical for the exam.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ESG investing is a growing trend in India. Understand the difference between ESG integration, ESG exclusion, and ESG thematic approaches. When recommending ESG funds, explain to clients that ESG funds have additional disclosure requirements including third-party ESG ratings and Business Responsibility and Sustainability Reports (BRSR) of investee companies.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
