<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Statement of Additional Information (SAI) of a mutual fund primarily contains information about:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Scheme-specific investment objectives and asset allocation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Statutory information about the AMC, sponsors, trustees, and legal/operational details]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A summary of the scheme for quick investor reference]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The daily NAV and portfolio holdings of the scheme]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The SAI (Statement of Additional Information) contains statutory and legal information common to all schemes of a mutual fund, including details about the AMC, sponsors, trustees, Board of Directors, auditors, tax provisions, and legal/operational framework. It is a companion document to the SID and does not contain scheme-specific investment details.

**The Trap:** Option A describes the SID (Scheme Information Document), and Option C describes the KIM (Key Information Memorandum). Option D describes factsheets/portfolio disclosures. The hierarchy is: SID (scheme-specific) + SAI (AMC/statutory) together form the complete offer document, while KIM is the abridged version of SID.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The SID-SAI distinction is tested frequently in Series V-A and V-B. Series III-A tests similar document hierarchies for other securities (prospectus, abridged prospectus, etc.). Understanding which information goes where is critical for compliance.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While clients rarely read the full SAI, you should review it for critical information about the AMC's governance structure, key personnel changes, and tax implications. The SAI is updated periodically and is available on the AMC's website alongside the SID.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
