<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_50" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following features is UNIQUE to Mutual Funds and NOT available in PMS or AIFs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Professional fund management]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI regulation and oversight]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Daily NAV disclosure, mandatory TRI benchmarking, and standardized scheme categorization by SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tax benefits on investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** While all three products (MF, PMS, AIF) offer professional management and SEBI regulation, certain features are unique to the mutual fund framework: (1) Daily NAV disclosure providing transparent, real-time valuation; (2) Mandatory TRI (Total Return Index) benchmarking for performance comparison; (3) SEBI's standardized 36-category scheme categorization ensuring clarity and comparability across AMCs. PMS portfolios are individually valued (not through a standardized NAV), and AIFs report NAV less frequently. Neither PMS nor AIF has SEBI-mandated scheme categorization.

**The Trap:** Professional management (Option A) applies to all three. SEBI regulation (Option B) also applies to all three (under different regulation sets). Tax benefits (Option D) are available for specific MF schemes (ELSS), but PMS and AIF investments also have tax implications (not a unique MF feature). The combination of daily NAV + TRI benchmarking + categorization is what makes the MF regulatory framework uniquely transparent and standardized.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This "unique features" comparison is a sophisticated cluster confusion question. It requires understanding what is common across products vs what is MF-specific. Series V-A, III-A, and V-B all test this level of product differentiation. The answer requires combining multiple MF-specific regulatory features.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** These unique features are your selling points for mutual funds: (1) clients can check their portfolio value daily through NAV, (2) performance is compared against a fair benchmark (TRI), and (3) SEBI's categorization makes it easy to compare similar schemes across AMCs. No other investment product offers this combination of transparency and standardization.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
