<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI's categorization and rationalization of mutual fund schemes (October 2017), how many categories were permitted for equity schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5 categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[8 categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[10 categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[16 categories]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's landmark circular on categorization and rationalization of mutual fund schemes (October 2017) defined 10 equity categories: Multi Cap, Large Cap, Large & Mid Cap, Mid Cap, Small Cap, Dividend Yield, Value/Contra, Focused, Sectoral/Thematic, and ELSS. The total across all categories was 36 (10 equity + 16 debt + 6 hybrid + 2 solution-oriented + 2 other). Each AMC was allowed only one scheme per category (with limited exceptions).

**The Trap:** The number 16 refers to debt scheme categories (not equity). 5 is too few, and 8 is a common miscounted number. The "one scheme per category" rule is the key regulatory principle — candidates often remember the rule but not the exact number of categories.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI categorization is heavily tested in Series V-A and V-B. It also appears in Series III-A when discussing the regulatory framework for securities. The Flexi Cap category was later added (November 2020), making it 11 equity categories — but the original 2017 circular had 10.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understanding the 36-category framework helps you explain to clients why an AMC may have only one Large Cap fund versus multiple thematic funds (thematic is one category but can have multiple themes). This categorization also guides scheme selection for clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
