<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_53" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): After proper suitability assessment, Ravi helps Mrs. Patel invest her Rs. 25 lakh across diversified schemes matching her conservative risk profile. Three months later, Mrs. Patel is unhappy because her equity allocation has declined 8% in a market correction. She calls Ravi saying she was promised "safe returns" and wants to file a formal complaint.

Question 3: What is the correct escalation path for Mrs. Patel's complaint as per SEBI's investor grievance mechanism?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File a civil suit directly in the consumer court against Ravi and the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[First approach the AMC's investor grievance cell → If unresolved within 30 days, file complaint on SEBI's SCORES portal → If still unresolved, escalate to Online Dispute Resolution (ODR)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[File a First Information Report (FIR) with the local police station]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Directly approach SEBI's Chairman for immediate resolution]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI has established a structured complaint escalation mechanism: Step 1 — approach the AMC's investor grievance/customer service cell directly. Step 2 — if the complaint is not resolved satisfactorily within 30 days, file a complaint on SEBI's SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redressal System) portal. Step 3 — if SCORES resolution is unsatisfactory, escalate to Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) through SEBI-empaneled ODR institutions for conciliation and arbitration. Litigation (consumer courts) remains an option but is typically pursued after the regulatory mechanisms are exhausted.

**The Trap:** Jumping directly to courts (Option A) or police (Option C) without exhausting the regulatory grievance mechanism is not the correct first step. SEBI's Chairman does not personally handle individual complaints (Option D). The structured escalation path ensures efficient resolution at each level before moving to the next.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The complaint escalation hierarchy (AMC → SCORES → ODR) is tested in Series V-A, V-B, III-A, and XXIV. Understanding that each level has a defined resolution timeline is important. Series XXIV (Compliance) tests the AMC's obligations at each stage of the complaint process.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A complaint against you or your recommended schemes is an opportunity, not a threat. Respond promptly to Mrs. Patel's concern — explain that short-term market corrections are normal, review the portfolio's suitability documentation, and demonstrate that the original recommendation was appropriate for her risk profile. Documenting your suitability analysis protects you in case the complaint escalates to SCORES or ODR.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
