<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, what is the minimum number of investors required in a mutual fund scheme after the initial NFO period to avoid winding up?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[20 investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50 investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100 investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[10 investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations require that every scheme must have a minimum of 20 investors at all times after the initial subscription period (NFO). If the number falls below 20, the AMC must report it to SEBI, and the scheme may face winding up if the situation is not rectified. This rule ensures that mutual fund schemes serve a reasonably broad investor base and do not become de-facto portfolio management services for a handful of investors.

**The Trap:** 50 and 100 are commonly guessed numbers but are too high. 10 is too low. The 20-investor minimum is also linked to another rule: no single investor should hold more than 25% of the scheme's corpus. Together, these rules prevent concentration risk and ensure the "mutual" nature of the fund.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 20-investor minimum is tested in Series V-A and V-B. It connects to governance norms and is part of SEBI's broader framework to distinguish mutual funds from PMS (which can have even a single client). Series III-A may test this as a comparison point.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Be cautious when recommending niche schemes (sectoral, thematic, or newer AMC schemes) to clients — if the scheme struggles to maintain 20 investors, it could face winding up. Always check the scheme's AUM and investor count in the monthly portfolio disclosure.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
