<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The proportion of independent directors required on the board of an Asset Management Company (AMC) is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[At least 50% (half) of the directors must be independent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At least two-thirds of the directors must be independent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At least 75% of the directors must be independent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[At least one-third of the directors must be independent]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations require that at least 50% (half) of the directors on an AMC's board must be independent directors. This ensures a balance between management representation and independent oversight within the company that manages the fund's assets.

**The Trap:** The two-thirds (2/3rd) requirement applies to the Board of TRUSTEES, not the AMC board. This is the single most frequently confused pair of numbers in Chapter 3. Candidates who remember "two-thirds independent" but forget which board it applies to will pick the wrong answer. The one-third option mirrors general Companies Act requirements for listed companies, which do not apply here.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C, being able to distinguish between trustee board composition (2/3rd independent) and AMC board composition (50% independent) is a must. Also compare with SEBI LODR requirements for listed companies (1/3rd independent directors) to see how MF regulations impose a stricter standard.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remember the simple rule: Trustees have the HIGHER independence bar (2/3rd) because they are the ultimate fiduciaries. The AMC board has a LOWER but still significant bar (50%). This dual-layer governance is what makes the MF structure robust.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
