<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the SEBI-mandated process for merger of two mutual fund schemes within the same AMC?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC can merge schemes at its discretion without any approval]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only SEBI approval is required; unitholder consent is not needed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Unitholders of the merging scheme must be given an exit option without any exit load during the notice period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A simple majority vote of unitholders present at a meeting is sufficient]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI regulations, when schemes are merged/consolidated, unitholders of the merging (transferor) scheme must be given adequate notice and a no-load exit option. The AMC must send a written communication to all unitholders at least 30 days before the effective date, allowing them to exit without any exit load if they disagree with the merger. This protects investors who may not want their money in the surviving (transferee) scheme.

**The Trap:** The AMC cannot merge schemes unilaterally — investor protection mechanisms must be followed. The process is not a "vote" but an "exit option" — the merger proceeds unless SEBI objects, but dissenting investors can leave without penalty. This is different from company mergers where shareholder voting is required.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Scheme mergers became especially relevant post-2017 categorization when AMCs had to consolidate multiple schemes into one per category. Series V-A and V-B test this process. Series III-A tests merger/consolidation of other intermediaries. The no-load exit option is a recurring investor protection principle.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a scheme merger is announced, proactively reach out to affected clients. Explain the merger rationale, compare the surviving scheme's mandate with what they originally invested in, and help them decide whether to stay or exit (load-free). This proactive service builds client trust and retention.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
