<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A person serving as a trustee of one mutual fund wishes to also become a trustee of another mutual fund. Under SEBI regulations, this is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not permitted — no person can be a trustee of two different mutual funds simultaneously]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Permitted only if the person is an independent trustee in both funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Permitted with prior SEBI approval on a case-by-case basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Permitted if both mutual funds have the same sponsor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations explicitly prohibit any person from acting as a trustee of two different mutual funds simultaneously. This rule prevents conflicts of interest that could arise if the same person were overseeing competing funds, ensuring each fund's trustees are dedicated solely to protecting that fund's unitholders.

**The Trap:** The "prior SEBI approval" distractor is clever because many MF regulations do require SEBI approval for various appointments. However, for dual trusteeship, there is no exception or approval mechanism — it is an absolute prohibition. The "same sponsor" option is also misleading because even fund houses under the same financial group must have distinct trustees.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Compare this with the AIF framework where the same trustee or investment manager can manage multiple AIF schemes. This strict prohibition for MF trustees reflects the higher standard of fiduciary care expected in the mutual fund industry, which pools retail investor money.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This regulation reinforces the message that each mutual fund house has a dedicated set of guardians. When clients compare MFs with less regulated products, the exclusivity of trusteeship is a governance advantage worth highlighting.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
