<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_58" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Celebrity endorsement of mutual funds is permitted only at the industry level (not for individual AMCs or schemes). For such endorsement, ________ is required.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Prior approval of SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No regulatory approval is needed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Approval of the AMC's board of directors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Approval of AMFI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations on mutual fund advertising are very strict about celebrity endorsements. Celebrities cannot endorse individual mutual fund schemes or AMCs. Celebrity endorsement is permitted ONLY at the mutual fund industry level (e.g., promoting mutual funds as an investment category), and this requires prior approval from SEBI. This rule prevents celebrity influence from misleading retail investors into specific products based on star power rather than investment merit.

**The Trap:** "No approval needed" (Option B) is wrong -- SEBI approval is mandatory even for industry-level endorsement. "AMC board approval" (Option C) is irrelevant since individual AMC-level celebrity endorsement is itself prohibited. "AMFI approval" (Option D) is close but incorrect -- while AMFI may coordinate industry campaigns, the regulatory approval must come from SEBI.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This restriction is part of SEBI's advertising code for mutual funds. Related rules include: no guaranteed returns in advertisements, mandatory risk disclaimers ("Mutual Fund investments are subject to market risks"), and no misleading performance claims.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Celebrity endorsement = industry level only + prior SEBI approval required. No celebrity endorsement for individual AMCs or schemes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
