<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_57" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the AMFI Code of Conduct enforcement framework, when an intermediary commits a second proven violation after an initial warning, the consequence is ________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Cancellation of registration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A monetary fine]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Temporary suspension for 6 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A second warning with enhanced monitoring]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AMFI Code of Conduct breach escalation follows a three-step process: Step 1 -- Upon receiving a complaint, AMFI writes to the intermediary requesting an explanation within 3 weeks. Step 2 -- If the explanation is unsatisfactory, AMFI issues a warning. Step 3 -- If there is a second proven violation, the consequence is cancellation of the intermediary's registration (ARN). This escalation framework ensures due process while maintaining strict enforcement.

**The Trap:** "Monetary fine" (Option B) is not part of the AMFI escalation framework -- AMFI issues warnings and cancellations, not fines. "Temporary suspension" (Option C) sounds moderate but is not the prescribed penalty for a second violation. "Second warning" (Option D) would weaken enforcement -- the framework deliberately escalates from warning to cancellation on the second offense.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 3-step escalation (explanation request within 3 weeks, warning, cancellation) is a frequently tested sequence. Candidates must know that cancellation -- not fine or suspension -- is the consequence of a second violation.

**Key Takeaway:** AMFI Code breach: Step 1 = seek explanation (3 weeks). Step 2 = warning. Step 3 (second violation) = cancellation of ARN registration.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
