<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The three primary objectives of SEBI, as stated in the SEBI Act, 1992, include all of the following EXCEPT:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Protection of the interests of investors in securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Promotion of the development of the securities market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Regulation of the securities market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteeing minimum returns to investors in securities]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's three statutory objectives under the SEBI Act, 1992 are: (1) protect the interests of investors in securities, (2) promote the development of the securities market, and (3) regulate the securities market. SEBI does NOT guarantee returns — this would fundamentally contradict the market-based nature of securities investing.

**The Trap:** The word "guaranteeing" is the giveaway, but under exam pressure, candidates may read it as "safeguarding" or "ensuring protection." SEBI protects investor interests through regulation and disclosure — not through return guarantees. Any guarantee of returns in the securities market context is a red flag.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a high-frequency question across NISM Series III-A, V-B, and XII. The distinction between "protection" and "guarantee" is critical — it also links to the SEBI Advertisement Code which prohibits assured/guaranteed return claims by mutual funds.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask "Is my investment guaranteed by SEBI?", clearly explain that SEBI ensures fair practices and transparency, but does NOT guarantee investment returns. This is both a regulatory requirement and an ethical obligation under the AMFI Code of Conduct.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
