<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Board of Trustees of a mutual fund is required to file reports with SEBI on:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A half-yearly basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A quarterly basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A monthly basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An annual basis]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations, the Board of Trustees is required to file half-yearly reports with SEBI on the activities and compliance of the mutual fund. This reporting frequency strikes a balance between ensuring regulatory oversight and allowing operational efficiency.

**The Trap:** Candidates often confuse this with the trustees' quarterly review of AMC transactions — the trustees review AMC activities quarterly (internal oversight), but file reports with SEBI half-yearly (external reporting). The quarterly option is the most popular wrong answer because it conflates internal review frequency with SEBI reporting frequency.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C, the reporting timelines across different entities are heavily tested. AMCs have their own reporting obligations (monthly CAS statements, daily NAV declarations). Distinguishing between internal review cycles and external SEBI reporting is a core compliance skill.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As a distributor, you won't directly handle trustee reports, but knowing these timelines demonstrates your professional knowledge to clients and helps you understand when governance reviews happen. If a client raises a concern, you can explain that trustees review the AMC every quarter and report to SEBI every six months.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
