<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's scheme categorization norms (2017), what is the key rule regarding the number of schemes an AMC can offer in a single category?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Only one scheme per category is permitted (with specified exceptions)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A maximum of three schemes per category is permitted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no limit on the number of schemes per category]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only two schemes per category — one for retail and one for institutional investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's scheme categorization circular (October 2017) mandated that each AMC can have only one scheme per category. This was introduced to reduce confusion among investors caused by multiple similarly-positioned schemes from the same AMC. Exceptions exist for index funds/ETFs tracking different indices, Fund of Funds with different underlying schemes, and sectoral/thematic funds covering different sectors/themes.

**The Trap:** The "one for retail, one for institutional" option sounds logical but is incorrect. SEBI's approach was simplification through strict one-per-category rule, not differentiation by investor type. AMCs had to merge or consolidate overlapping schemes, which was a massive industry exercise in 2018.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The one-scheme-per-category rule is a cornerstone of SEBI's MF regulation reform, tested in Series V-A and V-B. The consolidation/conversion process itself (requiring unitholder approval through exit option) is also examinable. Series III-A may reference this as an example of regulatory intervention for investor protection.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This rule benefits you as a distributor because it simplifies scheme selection. Instead of comparing 5-6 large-cap funds from the same AMC, you now compare one per AMC. Guide clients to compare across AMCs rather than within the same AMC's lineup.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
