<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which regulator oversees the regulation of money market instruments such as Commercial Paper (CP) and Certificates of Deposit (CD) that mutual fund schemes invest in?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Reserve Bank of India (RBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ministry of Corporate Affairs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Association of Mutual Funds in India (AMFI)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** RBI regulates the banking system, money market, and foreign exchange market in India. Money market instruments like Commercial Paper (CP), Certificates of Deposit (CD), Treasury Bills (T-Bills), and CBLO/Tri-party repo fall under RBI's regulatory purview. While SEBI regulates mutual funds as investment vehicles, the underlying money market instruments they invest in are RBI-regulated.

**The Trap:** AMFI is an industry body (not a regulator) — it is the Association of Mutual Funds in India. Candidates sometimes elevate AMFI's role to that of a regulator. Ministry of Corporate Affairs deals with company law, not financial market regulation. SEBI regulates the MF scheme but not the money market instruments themselves.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This dual-regulation concept (SEBI for the fund, RBI for certain underlying instruments) is tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. Understanding this helps explain why liquid funds and money market funds have specific investment restrictions set by both SEBI and RBI guidelines.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining liquid or money market fund investments to clients, understand that these instruments are among the safest because they are RBI-regulated. However, credit risk still exists (as seen in cases of CP defaults), which is why SEBI introduced the Potential Risk Class (PRC) matrix for debt schemes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
