<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a mandatory eligibility criterion for a sponsor of a mutual fund in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Positive net worth in all of the immediately preceding five years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Positive net worth of at least Rs. 50 crore in the preceding three years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Average net profit of Rs. 50 crore in the preceding five years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 10 years of experience in financial services]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations require a sponsor to have: (a) at least 5 years in financial services, (b) positive net worth in ALL of the immediately preceding 5 years, (c) average net profit of at least Rs. 10 crore in the preceding 5 years, and (d) the person must be fit and proper. The correct answer focuses on positive net worth across all 5 years.

**The Trap:** Rs. 50 crore is the minimum net worth requirement for the AMC, not the sponsor. The exam often swaps sponsor criteria with AMC criteria. Also, the experience requirement is 5 years, not 10. The average net profit threshold is Rs. 10 crore, not Rs. 50 crore.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM V-B (Mutual Fund Distributors — Advanced), these sponsor eligibility criteria are tested more granularly. In Series III-C, the focus shifts to comparing sponsor eligibility for MFs versus eligibility for AIF managers.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Knowing sponsor credentials helps you assess fund house quality. A sponsor with a long track record in financial services signals institutional strength, which can be a selling point when pitching funds to cautious investors.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
