<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's Advertisement Code, when a mutual fund advertisement shows past performance, which of the following rules must be followed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the best-performing period can be highlighted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Performance must be shown only for the last 1 year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Performance must be shown for standardized periods (1 year, 3 years, 5 years, since inception) on a CAGR basis, compared against the TRI benchmark]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Performance can be shown for any cherry-picked period chosen by the AMC]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's Advertisement Code requires that performance in advertisements must be disclosed for standardized periods — typically 1 year, 3 years, 5 years, and since inception — calculated on a compounded annualized (CAGR) basis. The performance must be compared with the Total Return Index (TRI) benchmark and must include the performance of both the direct and regular plans. Cherry-picking favorable periods or showing only the best timeframe is prohibited.

**The Trap:** "Only the best-performing period" and "any cherry-picked period" are explicitly prohibited practices. "Only 1 year" is too narrow — SEBI requires multiple standardized periods to give investors a comprehensive performance picture. The mandatory TRI benchmark comparison ensures that outperformance claims are verified against the right yardstick.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Performance advertising rules are tested in Series V-A, V-B, and Series XXIV. The shift to TRI benchmarking (2018) made performance comparisons more stringent. Series III-C tests performance presentation standards for investment advisers, which have similar principles.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When presenting scheme performance to clients, follow the same standardized format as the Advertisement Code — show 1/3/5/since inception returns vs TRI benchmark. This not only keeps you compliant but also provides clients with a complete picture rather than cherry-picked good periods that may not represent the full story.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
