<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The minimum net worth requirement for an Asset Management Company (AMC) under SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 100 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 25 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates that an AMC must maintain a positive net worth of at least Rs. 50 crore at all times. This ensures the AMC has adequate financial strength to manage investor assets professionally and absorb operational risks. The trustees are required to periodically review the AMC's net worth to ensure ongoing compliance.

**The Trap:** Rs. 10 crore is the average net profit threshold for the SPONSOR (not the AMC). Rs. 100 crore may sound plausible for a large financial institution but is not the regulatory requirement. Rs. 25 crore was a historical figure that has since been revised upward. Candidates who confuse sponsor criteria with AMC criteria often pick Rs. 10 crore.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B and Series III-C, compare the AMC net worth requirement (Rs. 50 crore) with PMS minimum net worth (Rs. 5 crore) and AIF manager net worth requirements. This comparison highlights the higher capital threshold for managing public money through mutual funds.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The Rs. 50 crore net worth floor means your clients' money is managed by well-capitalized entities. When comparing MFs with unregulated investment products, this capital adequacy requirement is a significant differentiator for investor protection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
