<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a key responsibility of the Board of Trustees of a mutual fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Entering into an investment management agreement with the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Making day-to-day investment decisions for the mutual fund schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Directly handling investor complaints and grievance redressal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Appointing fund managers and the Chief Investment Officer]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** One of the primary responsibilities of the Board of Trustees is to enter into an investment management agreement (IMA) with the AMC. This agreement defines the terms under which the AMC manages the fund's assets. Other trustee responsibilities include reviewing service contracts, ensuring regulatory compliance, quarterly review of AMC transactions, reviewing AMC net worth, handling investor complaints oversight, and filing half-yearly reports to SEBI.

**The Trap:** Day-to-day investment decisions are made by the AMC (through fund managers under the CIO), not the trustees. While trustees oversee investor complaint handling, they do not directly handle complaints — the AMC's operational team does. Appointing fund managers is an AMC function, not a trustee function. The trustees appoint the AMC itself, not its internal staff.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C, the IMA is a critical document that defines the legal relationship between trustees and the AMC. Understanding what goes into this agreement (fee structure, investment restrictions, compliance obligations) is essential for compliance officers.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The investment management agreement essentially sets the guardrails for the AMC. If a client ever questions whether the AMC can do "whatever it wants" with their money, you can explain that the trustees have a binding agreement that constrains and defines the AMC's authority.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
