<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a permitted activity for an Asset Management Company (AMC) under SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Managing mutual fund schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing portfolio management services (with separate SEBI registration)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing investment advisory services (with separate SEBI registration)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Lending money to any person or corporate body in the AMC's own name]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations explicitly prohibit AMCs from lending money in their own name. AMCs can manage mutual fund assets (their primary function), and with separate SEBI registrations, they can also provide PMS and investment advisory services. However, lending activity would create conflicts of interest and is inconsistent with an AMC's role as a fiduciary manager of investors' money.

**The Trap:** Options B and C are activities that AMCs commonly undertake but with SEPARATE SEBI registrations — this "with separate registration" qualifier makes them permitted. Many candidates correctly identify that AMCs provide PMS but wrongly conclude that lending (which sounds like a legitimate financial activity) should also be permitted.

**Cross-Exam Context:** AMC activity restrictions are tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. The prohibition on lending connects to the broader fiduciary obligation of AMCs. Series III-C may test how AMCs offering advisory services must manage conflicts between their MF and advisory businesses.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understanding what an AMC can and cannot do helps you explain the regulatory safeguards to clients. The prohibition on lending ensures that the AMC doesn't use its position or investors' funds for unauthorized purposes. This adds to the structural safety of the mutual fund vehicle.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
