<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redressal System) is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An online platform where investors can file and track complaints against SEBI-registered entities including mutual funds and their intermediaries]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A credit scoring system for mutual fund investors similar to CIBIL]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A performance scoring system that ranks mutual fund schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A training and certification platform for mutual fund distributors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redressal System) is SEBI's online grievance mechanism that allows investors to file complaints against SEBI-registered entities, including mutual fund AMCs, distributors, and other intermediaries. Complaints can be filed online, tracked through the system, and SEBI monitors resolution timelines. SEBI-registered entities are required to resolve complaints within 30 days. SCORES was upgraded to SCORES 2.0 with enhanced features.

**The Trap:** The word "SCORES" can mislead candidates into thinking it is a scoring/rating system. It is NOT a credit score (CIBIL), scheme ranking (like Morningstar ratings), or a training platform (NISM). The correct interpretation is Complaints Redressal System — focusing on investor grievance resolution.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SCORES is tested across multiple NISM exams — Series V-A, V-B, III-A, III-C, XXIV, and XII. It is a universal investor protection mechanism. The complaint resolution process (complaint → entity response → SEBI review → resolution/escalation) is a common exam topic. Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) is a newer mechanism that complements SCORES.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A complaint against you on SCORES can impact your AMFI registration and future business. Resolve client grievances proactively before they escalate to SCORES. Maintain proper documentation of all client interactions, disclosures, and transactions to defend yourself if a complaint is filed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
