<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the concept of "segregated portfolio" (side-pocketing) introduced by SEBI for mutual fund debt schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Separating distressed/downgraded securities into a separate portfolio to protect existing investors from forced redemption losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Creating a separate portfolio exclusively for high-net-worth investors within the same scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maintaining a separate portfolio of liquid assets to meet redemption demands]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dividing the scheme portfolio into equity and debt segments for balanced funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI introduced the segregated portfolio (side-pocketing) framework in December 2018 following the IL&FS credit crisis. When a debt security in a mutual fund portfolio is downgraded to below investment grade or faces a credit event, the AMC can create a segregated portfolio for that distressed asset. Existing unitholders get proportionate units in both the main and segregated portfolios. This prevents panic redemptions from destroying value for long-term investors while the distressed asset undergoes recovery/resolution.

**The Trap:** Option C describes a liquidity buffer (not segregated portfolio). Option B wrongly introduces investor-type segregation, which is prohibited under SEBI's principle of fair treatment. Option D describes asset allocation, not side-pocketing. The trigger for segregation is a credit event — not a routine portfolio management decision.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Segregated portfolios are tested in Series V-A (regulatory framework) and V-B (scheme types). Series III-A may test this as a risk management tool. This concept was born from the IL&FS/DHFL credit crises and represents SEBI's response to systemic debt market risks.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a scheme in your client's portfolio creates a segregated portfolio, explain that it actually protects their interests by preventing fire-sale losses. The segregated units are listed on exchanges for price discovery, and recovery proceeds are distributed proportionately.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
