<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the Prevention of Money Laundering Act (PMLA), mutual fund AMCs are required to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only verify the investor's PAN card]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Report suspicious transactions only if the amount exceeds Rs. 50 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Maintain records of transactions, verify client identity through KYC, and report suspicious transactions to the Financial Intelligence Unit (FIU-IND)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Block all investments from NRI investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the PMLA, 2002, mutual fund AMCs (as reporting entities) must: (1) verify client identity through robust KYC procedures, (2) maintain records of all transactions for a specified period, (3) report suspicious transactions (STRs) to the Financial Intelligence Unit-India (FIU-IND) irrespective of the transaction amount, and (4) report cash transactions above Rs. 10 lakh. PMLA compliance is a critical obligation that applies to all financial intermediaries including mutual fund entities.

**The Trap:** PAN verification alone is insufficient — full KYC including identity, address, and risk categorization is required. Suspicious transaction reporting has NO minimum threshold — even small suspicious transactions must be reported. NRI investments are permitted (with specific rules), not blocked. PMLA compliance is broader than just one or two requirements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PMLA/AML is tested across Series V-A, V-B, III-A, XXIV, and XII. It is one of the highest-overlap topics across NISM certifications. Series XXIV (Compliance Officers) tests PMLA in depth including the role of the Principal Officer, STR filing procedures, and record maintenance requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As a distributor, you are the first line of defense against money laundering. Be alert to red flags: unusually large cash transactions, frequent purchases and immediate redemptions, investments that don't match the client's profile, or clients who are reluctant to provide KYC documents. Report concerns to the AMC's compliance team — do not ignore them.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
