<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_51" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Ravi Sharma has recently obtained his NISM Series V-A certification and AMFI Registration Number (ARN). He has set up his office and started approaching potential clients. His first client, Mrs. Meena Patel (age 58, retired school teacher), walks in wanting to invest her retirement corpus of Rs. 25 lakh. Mrs. Patel has a PAN card but has never invested in mutual funds before and has no KYC on record. She wants to invest everything in a single small-cap fund because her neighbor told her it gave 80% returns last year.

Question 1: What is the FIRST regulatory step Ravi must complete before processing Mrs. Patel's investment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Submit the investment application to the AMC with Mrs. Patel's PAN card copy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtain Mrs. Patel's risk profile assessment and recommend schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Complete Mrs. Patel's KYC (Know Your Customer) verification through CKYC/KRA registration, as no mutual fund transaction can be processed without valid KYC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Check if Mrs. Patel's neighbor's claim about 80% returns is accurate]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** KYC is a mandatory pre-condition for ALL mutual fund investments (except micro-SIPs up to Rs. 50,000 per year per MF). Since Mrs. Patel has no KYC on record, Ravi must first complete her KYC verification through CKYC (Central KYC) or KRA (KYC Registration Agency) before any transaction can be processed. PAN alone is not sufficient. No AMC will accept an application without valid KYC compliance. This is both a SEBI regulatory requirement and a PMLA obligation.

**The Trap:** While risk profiling (Option B) is important, it comes AFTER KYC is completed — you cannot assess suitability for a client whose identity is not yet verified. Submitting the application with just PAN (Option A) will be rejected. Checking the neighbor's claims (Option D), while sensible, is not a regulatory step.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The KYC-first principle is tested across Series V-A, V-B, III-A, and XXIV. The case study tests the correct sequence: KYC → Risk Profiling → Suitability Assessment → Investment. This sequence is a regulatory and professional best practice.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Have a KYC checklist ready for walk-in clients: Aadhaar, PAN, passport-size photograph, address proof, and bank account details. Offer to help them complete eKYC (if Aadhaar-based) or physical KYC on the spot. The faster you complete KYC, the sooner you can process their investment and earn your first commission.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
