<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) mechanism introduced by SEBI for mutual fund investor grievances?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A replacement for SCORES that handles all SEBI-related complaints]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A digital mechanism for resolution of investor complaints and disputes through conciliation and arbitration via SEBI-empaneled ODR institutions, accessible after initial complaint resolution attempts fail]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An internal complaint mechanism within each AMC for employee grievances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A court-based system for filing civil suits against mutual fund AMCs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI introduced the Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) mechanism as a digital platform for resolving investor grievances through conciliation and online arbitration. ODR complements (does not replace) SCORES. The typical escalation path is: (1) complaint to the entity directly, (2) if unresolved, file on SCORES, (3) if still unresolved, escalate to ODR for conciliation/arbitration through SEBI-empaneled ODR institutions like SMARTODR. The ODR process is technology-driven, cost-effective, and faster than traditional litigation.

**The Trap:** ODR does NOT replace SCORES — it is an additional escalation layer. It is NOT an internal AMC mechanism or a court system. ODR uses conciliation and arbitration (alternative dispute resolution methods), not judicial proceedings. The digital nature makes it accessible to investors across India without needing to travel.

**Cross-Exam Context:** ODR is a relatively recent regulatory development tested in Series V-A and increasingly in other NISM exams. The complaint escalation hierarchy (entity → SCORES → ODR) is the complete grievance resolution framework. Series XXIV tests the operational aspects of handling complaints at each level.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Be aware of the ODR mechanism as it represents the final escalation before litigation. If a client complaint reaches ODR, it indicates a serious breakdown in the resolution process. Proactive complaint resolution at the first stage (direct communication) saves time, reputation, and potential regulatory consequences.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
