<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the AMFI Registration Number (ARN) in the context of mutual fund distribution?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A registration number issued by SEBI directly to mutual fund distributors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A unique identification number issued by AMFI to individuals/entities who have passed the NISM Series V-A certification and completed KYD (Know Your Distributor) requirements]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A number assigned to each mutual fund scheme for identification purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A code used by stock exchanges to identify mutual fund transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AMFI Registration Number (ARN) is a unique identification number assigned by the Association of Mutual Funds in India (AMFI) to mutual fund distributors. To obtain an ARN, a distributor must: (1) pass the NISM Series V-A: Mutual Fund Distributors Certification Examination, (2) complete the KYD (Know Your Distributor) process including identity verification and background checks, and (3) pay the applicable registration fees. The ARN must be quoted in all mutual fund transactions facilitated by the distributor.

**The Trap:** ARN is issued by AMFI, NOT by SEBI directly (though SEBI prescribes the framework). It is for distributors, not for schemes. Stock exchange codes are separate identifiers. The ARN-NISM-KYD trinity is the complete distributor registration framework — missing any component makes the ARN invalid.

**Cross-Exam Context:** ARN and distributor registration are core topics in Series V-A (this is essentially "your own license exam"). Series V-B also covers ARN requirements. Series III-A tests the broader intermediary registration framework where ARN is one type of registration.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Your ARN is your professional identity. Keep it active by renewing NISM certification before expiry (validity is 3 years, with CPE requirements). An expired ARN means you cannot earn commissions on new transactions. Also ensure your EUIN (Employee Unique Identification Number) is linked to every transaction you facilitate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
