<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A client approaches a mutual fund distributor to invest Rs. 60,000 in a liquid fund. The client provides a PAN card but says KYC is not yet completed. What should the distributor do?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Process the investment immediately since PAN is sufficient for mutual fund investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Process the investment using the micro-SIP exemption since the amount is below Rs. 2 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Complete the KYC process first before processing the investment, as KYC is mandatory for all mutual fund investments (except micro-SIP up to Rs. 50,000 per year per mutual fund)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Reject the investment entirely since liquid funds require enhanced KYC beyond standard norms]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** KYC (Know Your Customer) is mandatory for all mutual fund investments in India. PAN alone is not sufficient — full KYC verification (identity, address, in-person verification or equivalent) must be completed before any investment is processed. The only exception is for micro-SIPs where the annual investment per mutual fund is up to Rs. 50,000, which has a simplified KYC requirement. A Rs. 60,000 lump sum in a liquid fund does NOT qualify for the micro-SIP exemption, so full KYC is required.

**The Trap:** PAN is necessary but not sufficient — it is one component of KYC, not a substitute. The micro-SIP exemption applies to SIPs (not lump sums) with an annual limit of Rs. 50,000 per mutual fund. Liquid funds do NOT require "enhanced KYC" — the standard KYC process applies. The distributor's obligation is to ensure KYC compliance before transaction processing.

**Cross-Exam Context:** KYC requirements and exemptions are tested in Series V-A, V-B, III-A, and XXIV. The micro-SIP KYC relaxation was introduced to encourage financial inclusion. The distinction between PAN requirement and KYC requirement is a classic trap across all NISM exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never process a transaction without ensuring KYC compliance — this is your regulatory and legal obligation. Help the client complete KYC quickly through Aadhaar-based eKYC (where available) or in-person verification. Explain that KYC is a one-time process (through CKYC) that benefits them across all financial products.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
