<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which entity in the mutual fund structure is responsible for the day-to-day management of mutual fund schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Asset Management Company (AMC)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Board of Trustees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sponsor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Custodian]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AMC is appointed by the sponsor or trustees with SEBI's approval and is responsible for the day-to-day management of mutual fund schemes. This includes investment decisions, portfolio management, investor servicing, and scheme operations. The AMC acts under the supervision of the Board of Trustees.

**The Trap:** The Board of Trustees provides oversight but does NOT manage the schemes on a daily basis — their role is supervisory and fiduciary. The Sponsor sets up the mutual fund trust but does not manage schemes directly. The Custodian holds securities but makes no investment decisions. Candidates often confuse the trustee's oversight role with the AMC's operational management role.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In PMS, the portfolio manager directly manages the portfolio (similar to the AMC's role). In AIFs, the investment manager handles day-to-day operations. Understanding which entity "manages" in each structure is a frequent cross-exam comparison point for NISM III-C.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask "who manages my money?", the accurate answer is the AMC through its fund managers (who report to the Chief Investment Officer). Knowing this hierarchy helps you explain the investment process credibly and build client confidence.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
