<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Potential Risk Class (PRC) matrix introduced by SEBI for debt mutual fund schemes classifies risk on which two dimensions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Market risk and liquidity risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk and interest rate risk (duration)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Concentration risk and default risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Currency risk and reinvestment risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI introduced the Potential Risk Class (PRC) matrix (effective December 2021) for all open-ended debt schemes. The PRC matrix has two dimensions: (1) Credit Risk — classified as Class A (Sovereign/AAA), B (AA), or C (A and below), and (2) Interest Rate Risk (Duration) — classified as Class I (up to 1 year Macaulay Duration), II (1-3 years), or III (above 3 years). This creates a 3x3 matrix of 9 possible risk classes (e.g., A-I is lowest risk, C-III is highest risk).

**The Trap:** Liquidity risk and concentration risk, while real risks in debt funds, are not the two axes of the PRC matrix. Currency risk is relevant only for international funds. The PRC matrix was specifically designed to give investors a simple two-dimensional risk assessment tool for debt fund selection.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The PRC matrix is a recent regulatory innovation tested in Series V-A and V-B. It also connects to Series III-A (risk management) and Series III-C (investment advisory suitability). The matrix helps match a debt fund's risk profile to an investor's risk appetite.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the PRC matrix as a client communication tool. A conservative client should be in A-I or A-II funds (sovereign/AAA, low duration). An aggressive client seeking higher yield might consider B-II or B-III. Never recommend C-III class funds to risk-averse clients — this is a suitability and compliance essential.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
