<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, what is the requirement regarding uniformity of NAV applicable to all investors on a given day?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All investors must get the same NAV for purchase or redemption on a given business day, subject to cut-off timing rules]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Institutional investors get a preferential NAV compared to retail investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The AMC can offer a discounted NAV to large investors as a volume benefit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Different NAVs can apply to different investors based on the channel of investment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates NAV uniformity — all investors purchasing or redeeming on a given day, subject to the same cut-off time rules, must receive the same NAV. There can be no preferential pricing based on investor size, type, or channel. This is a fundamental principle of fair treatment in mutual fund regulation. The sale price and repurchase price must be derived from the same NAV using a uniform formula.

**The Trap:** In some financial products, large investors or institutional buyers get preferential pricing. This does NOT apply to mutual funds. The only NAV differentiation is between Regular Plan NAV and Direct Plan NAV (due to different TERs), which is a scheme-level difference, not investor-level discrimination.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NAV uniformity is tested in Series V-A and V-B. This principle distinguishes mutual funds from PMS (where each client's portfolio is individually managed with different entry/exit prices). Series III-A may compare this with share market pricing where different investors can buy at different prices.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This uniformity principle is actually a selling point for mutual funds — your client gets the same price as a billionaire investing in the same scheme on the same day. Use this to build trust with smaller investors who may feel disadvantaged compared to large investors.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
