<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, what is the maximum Total Expense Ratio (TER) permitted for an equity-oriented mutual fund scheme on the first Rs. 500 crore of daily net assets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1.50%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1.75%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[2.25%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2.50%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI's TER structure (effective April 1, 2019), the maximum TER for equity-oriented schemes on the first Rs. 500 crore of daily net assets is 2.25%. The TER follows a declining slab structure: 2.25% on first Rs. 500 crore, 2.00% on next Rs. 250 crore, 1.75% on next Rs. 1,250 crore, and so on, decreasing as AUM increases. For debt/other schemes, the corresponding maximum on the first Rs. 500 crore is 2.00%.

**The Trap:** 2.50% was the old TER limit before SEBI's 2018 rationalization. 1.75% and 1.50% are TER slabs applicable at higher AUM levels. The declining slab structure rewards scale economies — as AUM grows, the percentage expense decreases, benefiting investors in larger schemes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** TER limits are heavily tested in Series V-A and V-B. Series III-A may test expense ratio concepts for other products. The distinction between equity TER (2.25% max) and debt TER (2.00% max) is a common trap question. Additional 30 bps was permitted for inflows from B30 cities (beyond top 30).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** TER directly impacts net returns — a lower TER means more of the gross return reaches the investor. When comparing similar schemes, a lower TER can be a significant advantage over the long term due to compounding. Direct plans always have a lower TER than regular plans because they exclude distributor commissions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
