<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, mutual fund schemes are required to benchmark their performance against which type of index?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Price Return Index (PRI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Total Return Index (TRI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Net Asset Value Index (NAVI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk-Adjusted Return Index (RARI)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated (effective February 1, 2018) that all mutual fund schemes must use the Total Return Index (TRI) variant of their benchmark index for performance comparison. TRI includes both price appreciation and dividend/income reinvestment, providing a more accurate and fair comparison. Previously, schemes used the Price Return Index (PRI) which only captured price changes, making fund performance appear artificially superior.

**The Trap:** The Price Return Index (PRI) was the old benchmark standard and some candidates may still select it. "Net Asset Value Index" and "Risk-Adjusted Return Index" are fabricated terms designed to sound plausible. The key distinction is that TRI accounts for dividends reinvested, making it a higher bar for fund managers to beat.

**Cross-Exam Context:** TRI benchmarking is a significant regulatory change tested in Series V-A and V-B. It also connects to Series III-C (Investment Adviser) where performance reporting standards are discussed. The shift from PRI to TRI represents SEBI's investor-first approach.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When showing scheme performance to clients, always use TRI-benchmarked comparisons. If a fund consistently outperforms its TRI benchmark, it demonstrates genuine alpha generation by the fund manager — this is more meaningful than beating a PRI benchmark.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
