<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_52" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): After completing Mrs. Patel's KYC, Ravi wants to create a marketing flyer for his office that reads: "Invest with Ravi Sharma — Our recommended XYZ Small Cap Fund gave 80% returns last year! Invest now for guaranteed wealth creation!" He plans to distribute this at a local community event.

Question 2: How many SEBI Advertisement Code violations does Ravi's proposed flyer contain?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1 violation — only the guaranteed returns claim is problematic]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2 violations — guaranteed returns and cherry-picked performance period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[At least 4 violations: (1) guaranteed wealth creation claim, (2) showing only 1-year returns instead of standardized periods (1/3/5/since inception), (3) no TRI benchmark comparison, (4) missing mandatory risk disclaimer "Mutual Fund investments are subject to market risks..."]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No violations — distributors creating their own marketing material are exempt from SEBI Advertisement Code]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Ravi's flyer contains multiple SEBI Advertisement Code violations: (1) "Guaranteed wealth creation" — any guarantee or assurance of returns is prohibited; (2) Showing only last year's return (80%) without providing standardized period returns (1, 3, 5 years, since inception) on a CAGR basis; (3) No comparison with the scheme's TRI benchmark performance; (4) Missing the mandatory disclaimer "Mutual Fund investments are subject to market risks, read all scheme related documents carefully." Additionally, the flyer may need to show both direct and regular plan performance.

**The Trap:** Option D is the most dangerous trap — distributors are NOT exempt from the Advertisement Code. Any marketing material created by a distributor is subject to the same SEBI advertising norms as AMC-created advertisements. Identifying only 1 or 2 violations means the candidate missed other requirements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This scenario tests the practical application of SEBI's Advertisement Code, a high-frequency topic in Series V-A and V-B. Series XXIV tests compliance monitoring of such materials. The comprehensive nature of the Code (covering content, format, disclaimers, and performance presentation) means multiple violations can exist in a single communication.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before creating ANY marketing material, run it through the SEBI Advertisement Code checklist: (1) No guaranteed/assured return claims, (2) Standardized performance periods with CAGR, (3) TRI benchmark comparison, (4) Mandatory risk disclaimer, (5) Both direct and regular plan performance, (6) Risk-o-meter of the scheme. Many AMCs offer co-branded, pre-approved marketing materials — use those instead of creating your own to avoid compliance risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
