<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_49" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly compares the net worth requirements across Mutual Fund AMCs, PMS providers, and AIF Managers?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMC: Rs. 50 crore; PMS: Rs. 50 crore; AIF Manager: Rs. 50 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[AMC: Rs. 50 crore; PMS: Rs. 5 crore; AIF Manager: Rs. 5 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMC: Rs. 10 crore; PMS: Rs. 25 crore; AIF Manager: Rs. 50 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMC: Rs. 100 crore; PMS: Rs. 50 crore; AIF Manager: Rs. 25 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The minimum net worth requirements reflect the scale and systemic importance of each entity: AMC requires Rs. 50 crore (managing public money from millions of retail investors), PMS provider requires Rs. 5 crore (managing individual client portfolios with higher minimums), and AIF Manager requires Rs. 5 crore (managing pooled capital from sophisticated/institutional investors). The AMC's significantly higher net worth requirement reflects the higher fiduciary responsibility and systemic risk given the retail investor base.

**The Trap:** The equal amounts for PMS and AIF Manager (both Rs. 5 crore) can cause confusion — candidates may expect different amounts. The AMC's Rs. 50 crore is 10x higher, reflecting the difference in scale and regulatory burden. Options with Rs. 10 crore, Rs. 25 crore, or Rs. 100 crore for AMCs are fabricated distractors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Net worth comparisons across product types are high-value "cluster confusion" questions appearing in Series V-A, III-A, and product-specific exams. Memorizing the three-way comparison (AMC Rs. 50 cr, PMS Rs. 5 cr, AIF Manager Rs. 5 cr) is essential for eliminating distractors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The high net worth requirement for AMCs (Rs. 50 crore) is part of the robust regulatory framework that makes mutual funds suitable for retail investors. When comparing investment options for clients, the regulatory rigor (including capital requirements) behind mutual funds is a significant advantage over less-regulated alternatives.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
