<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_48" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Regarding concentration/diversification norms, which statement correctly compares Mutual Funds with PMS?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mutual Funds have strict diversification limits (max 10% in a single stock per scheme) while PMS can create concentrated portfolios based on individual client mandates without such rigid limits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both Mutual Funds and PMS have the same 10% single-stock concentration limit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMS has stricter diversification requirements than Mutual Funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Neither Mutual Funds nor PMS have any concentration limits — fund managers have full discretion]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mutual Funds are subject to strict SEBI-mandated diversification norms: a single scheme cannot invest more than 10% of NAV in a single company's equity (extendable to 15% with trustee approval). PMS, being an individualized portfolio management service, allows portfolio managers to create concentrated portfolios tailored to each client's investment mandate — there are no rigid per-stock concentration limits equivalent to the MF framework. This is a fundamental structural difference between the two products.

**The Trap:** PMS does NOT have the same concentration limits as MFs — this is a key differentiator. PMS is NOT stricter than MFs on diversification — it is actually more flexible. Neither product has "zero limits" — MFs have explicit limits, and PMS portfolio managers still have fiduciary obligations even without rigid concentration caps.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This MF vs PMS comparison on concentration limits is a classic cluster confusion question appearing in Series V-A and III-A. It tests understanding of why mutual funds are considered "safer" for retail investors (mandatory diversification) vs PMS (higher risk tolerance, higher minimum investment, more flexibility).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This distinction helps when advising HNI clients. If a client wants concentrated exposure to 5-6 stocks they believe in strongly, a mutual fund cannot provide that — but PMS can (subject to Rs. 50 lakh minimum). For most retail clients, the mandatory diversification in mutual funds is a protective feature they should appreciate.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
