<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations, 1996, which of the following documents provides scheme-specific information to potential investors, including investment objective, asset allocation, and risk factors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Scheme Information Document (SID)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Statement of Additional Information (SAI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Key Information Memorandum (KIM)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annual Information Memorandum (AIM)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Scheme Information Document (SID) is the primary scheme-specific disclosure document under SEBI MF Regulations. It contains the investment objective, asset allocation pattern, risk factors, benchmark details (Total Return Index), and scheme-specific information. The SAI contains statutory information about the AMC, sponsors, and trustees (common across all schemes of the AMC). The KIM is a summary/abridged version of the SID for quick reference.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse SID with SAI. Remember: SID = Scheme-specific, SAI = AMC-specific (Statutory Additional Information). KIM is a summary, not the primary document. "Annual Information Memorandum" (AIM) does not exist in this context — it is a fabricated distractor.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The SID-SAI-KIM hierarchy is tested extensively in Series V-A and V-B. Series III-A tests similar offer document concepts for other securities. Since SEBI mandated Total Return Index (TRI) benchmarking in SIDs (from February 2018), this is a frequently updated topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always ensure your client has access to the SID before investing. The SID is the legal document that defines the scheme's promise. If a client complaint arises, the SID serves as the reference document for what was disclosed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
