<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the relationship between AMC directors and the Board of Trustees is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No director of the AMC can serve as a trustee of the same mutual fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Up to one-third of AMC directors may simultaneously serve as trustees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMC directors can serve as trustees provided they are classified as independent directors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The CEO of the AMC is an ex-officio member of the Board of Trustees]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations create a strict firewall between the AMC and the Board of Trustees. No person who is a director of the AMC can be appointed as a trustee of the same mutual fund. This ensures that trustees maintain independent oversight of the AMC's activities without any conflict of interest.

**The Trap:** The distractor about "independent directors being allowed" is particularly dangerous because it sounds reasonable — after all, independent directors are supposed to be unbiased. However, SEBI's prohibition is absolute regardless of the director's classification. The "ex-officio" option borrows language from corporate governance concepts but has no basis in MF regulations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM III-C, this separation is examined in the broader context of Chinese walls and conflict-of-interest management in financial services. Compare this with PMS where the portfolio manager and compliance officer roles have different separation requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This governance separation is your strongest argument when clients worry about fund mismanagement. The trustees are legally barred from being AMC insiders, making them genuine watchdogs over the fund management company.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
