<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, mutual fund schemes must disclose their portfolio holdings to the public at what frequency?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annually]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Quarterly]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Monthly (within 10 days of month-end) on their website and fortnightly (within 5 days of fortnight-end) to AMFI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Daily along with NAV disclosure]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated enhanced portfolio disclosure norms for mutual funds. Schemes must disclose their complete portfolio on their website within 10 days of the end of each month. Additionally, they must disclose portfolio to AMFI on a fortnightly basis (within 5 days of the end of the fortnight). This was a significant enhancement from the earlier requirement of half-yearly disclosure, aimed at improving transparency and enabling investors to make informed decisions.

**The Trap:** Annual and quarterly are outdated frequencies — SEBI progressively increased disclosure frequency over the years. Daily disclosure is too frequent and operationally impractical (though NAV is disclosed daily). The distinction between monthly (on website) and fortnightly (to AMFI) timelines is a common exam trap.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Disclosure norms are tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. The progressive tightening of disclosure requirements reflects SEBI's evolving approach to transparency. Series XXIV (Compliance Officers) tests the operational aspects of meeting these disclosure timelines.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Monthly portfolio disclosure is a powerful tool for you. Review your recommended schemes' portfolios regularly to ensure they are investing as per the stated mandate. If you spot style drift (e.g., a large-cap fund holding significant mid-cap stocks), it may warrant a discussion with the AMC or a scheme switch for your clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
