<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations, the Board of Trustees of a mutual fund must have a minimum of:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[4 trustees, of which at least two-thirds must be independent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[3 trustees, of which at least half must be independent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5 trustees, of which at least two-thirds must be independent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[4 trustees, of which at least half must be independent]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates a minimum of 4 trustees on the Board of Trustees, and at least two-thirds (2/3rd) of these trustees must be independent — meaning they are not associated with the sponsor or the AMC in any material way. This ensures governance independence.

**The Trap:** The "half must be independent" distractor mirrors the AMC board composition rule (at least 50% independent directors on the AMC board). Candidates who mix up trustee board rules with AMC board rules often pick this wrong answer. The number "5" is also a common confusion with sponsor eligibility (5 years).

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C (Compliance), compare this with AIF trustee requirements and SEBI listing regulations for independent directors. The 2/3rd independence threshold for MF trustees is stricter than the 50% requirement for AMC boards, reflecting the fiduciary importance of trustees.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask about governance safeguards, explain that the two-thirds independence requirement for trustees ensures that the people overseeing their money are not controlled by the fund house management. This is a structural protection unique to the mutual fund industry.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
