<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the maximum exposure limit that a single mutual fund scheme can have to a single company's equity shares, as per SEBI regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[10% of the NAV of the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[15% of the NAV of the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5% of the NAV of the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[25% of the NAV of the scheme]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations, a single scheme cannot invest more than 10% of its NAV in equity shares or equity-related instruments of a single company. This can be extended to 15% with prior approval of the Board of Trustees. For the entire mutual fund (all schemes combined), the limit is 10% of a company's paid-up capital carrying voting rights. These limits ensure diversification and prevent concentration risk.

**The Trap:** 15% is the extended limit with trustee approval, not the standard limit. 5% is sometimes confused from the minimum diversification requirements for certain categories. 25% is the maximum single-investor concentration limit (not single-stock limit). The standard answer for exam purposes is 10%, with 15% as the exception.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investment restrictions are tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. Compare with PMS where concentration limits are different, and AIFs (Category III) where leverage and exposure norms differ significantly. Series XII may test general portfolio concentration concepts.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This 10% limit is why even the most conviction-driven fund manager cannot create an overly concentrated portfolio in a mutual fund. When clients ask why their "best idea" fund doesn't hold 20% in their favorite stock, explain this regulatory safeguard that protects against single-stock blowups.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
