<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE regarding exit load on mutual fund schemes as per SEBI regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exit load collected by the scheme is credited to the AMC's profit and loss account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Exit load collected is credited back to the scheme, benefiting remaining unitholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI has prohibited all exit loads on mutual fund schemes since 2018]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exit load is paid by the scheme to the distributor as commission]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI regulations, exit load collected from redeeming investors must be credited back to the scheme's corpus. This benefits the remaining investors in the scheme because it compensates for any costs or market impact of the redemption. SEBI abolished entry loads in August 2009, but exit loads continue to be permitted as a mechanism to discourage premature withdrawals and protect long-term investors.

**The Trap:** The most common trap is Option A — candidates assume the AMC keeps the exit load as revenue. Pre-2012, a portion of exit load could be used to pay commissions, but SEBI stopped this practice. Exit loads are now entirely for the scheme's benefit. SEBI has NOT abolished exit loads (it abolished entry loads in 2009).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Load structures are tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. The abolition of entry loads (2009) and the subsequent move to trail-based commission models is a landmark regulatory change. Series III-C (Investment Adviser) also tests the impact of loads on net returns.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always disclose exit load structures to clients before investment. A 1% exit load on a large redemption can be significant. For SIP investors, remember that each installment has its own holding period for exit load calculation — early SIP installments may be exit-load-free while later ones may still attract the load.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
