<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An AMC wishes to undertake a business activity unrelated to fund management. Under SEBI regulations, this is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Permitted only with prior approval from SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Permitted freely as long as it does not impair fund management]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Absolutely prohibited under all circumstances]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Permitted with approval from the Board of Trustees only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations, an AMC cannot undertake any business activity other than asset management and advisory services for mutual funds UNLESS it obtains prior approval from SEBI. This restriction ensures the AMC remains focused on its primary fiduciary duty of managing investor assets.

**The Trap:** "Absolutely prohibited" sounds strict enough to be correct, but SEBI does allow diversification of AMC activities — subject to its prior approval. "Trustee approval only" is wrong because this decision requires SEBI's approval, not just the trustees'. The "freely permitted" option ignores the regulatory gating requirement entirely.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In practice, many AMCs have obtained SEBI approval to offer PMS, AIF management, and offshore fund advisory services. For NISM III-C, understanding when SEBI approval versus trustee approval is required for AMC activities is a critical compliance distinction.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When an AMC you distribute for launches a PMS or AIF product, know that it required separate SEBI approval. These are distinct business lines with different risk-return profiles. Never confuse a client by suggesting an AMC's mutual fund track record automatically applies to its PMS or AIF offerings.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
