<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[SEBI requires mutual fund AMCs to disclose the commission paid to distributors in which of the following formats?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only in the annual report of the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only in the SID of each scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In the Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) sent to investors, showing the commission and expenses for each scheme invested in through the distributor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI does not require commission disclosure to investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated that the commission paid to mutual fund distributors must be disclosed in the Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) sent to investors. This includes the total commission and expenses charged to the scheme for each investor's holdings. The CAS is generated by the RTAs (CAMS/KFintech) and provides a consolidated view of all MF investments with commission transparency. This was a key SEBI initiative to enhance distributor commission transparency.

**The Trap:** While commission structures may be mentioned in scheme documents, the specific disclosure to individual investors happens through the CAS. "SEBI does not require disclosure" is clearly wrong — commission transparency has been a major SEBI reform agenda. The annual report also discloses commissions but in aggregate, not investor-specific.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Commission disclosure is tested in Series V-A and V-B. It connects to Series III-C (Investment Adviser) where the fee-only vs commission model is discussed. Series XXIV (Compliance) tests the operational aspects of ensuring accurate commission disclosures.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Embrace commission transparency rather than fearing it. When clients see your commission in the CAS, be prepared to justify your value — the advice, service, and handholding you provide. Distributors who add genuine value through financial planning, portfolio reviews, and behavioral coaching can justify their commission with confidence.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
