<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements is MANDATORY in all mutual fund advertisements as per SEBI's Advertisement Code?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA["Past performance is a guarantee of future results"]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA["Mutual Fund investments are subject to market risks, read all scheme related documents carefully"]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA["This scheme guarantees capital protection to all investors"]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA["Invest only through SEBI-registered distributors for assured returns"]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's Advertisement Code for Mutual Funds mandates that every advertisement must carry the standard risk disclaimer: "Mutual Fund investments are subject to market risks, read all scheme related documents carefully." This must appear prominently and in a legible manner. The code prohibits any guarantee of returns, assured performance claims, or misleading statements about past performance guaranteeing future results.

**The Trap:** All three wrong options contain words like "guarantee," "assured," or "guarantee of future results" — these are expressly PROHIBITED by SEBI's Advertisement Code. The correct option is the only one that warns about risk rather than promising outcomes. This distinction between risk disclosure and return promises is fundamental to SEBI's investor protection philosophy.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The SEBI Advertisement Code is tested in Series V-A, V-B, and Series XXIV (Compliance). The standard disclaimer is one of the most recognizable regulatory requirements in Indian financial markets. Series III-C (Investment Adviser) tests similar advertising restrictions for advisory services.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As a distributor, you are also bound by the Advertisement Code. Any marketing material, social media post, or client communication that promises guaranteed returns or makes misleading performance claims can result in regulatory action against you and the AMC. Always include the mandatory disclaimer in your communications.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
