<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Registrar and Transfer Agent (RTA) of a mutual fund is primarily responsible for:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Maintaining investor records, unit-holding details, and processing investor transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Holding custody of the mutual fund's securities and physical assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Making investment decisions and managing the fund's portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conducting statutory audits and certifying the fund's financial statements]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The RTA (Registrar and Transfer Agent) is responsible for maintaining investor records, processing subscriptions and redemptions, updating unit-holding details, managing folio-level data, and handling investor service transactions. Major RTAs in India include CAMS and KFin Technologies (formerly Karvy).

**The Trap:** Holding custody of securities is the custodian's role, not the RTA's. Making investment decisions is the AMC's responsibility. Conducting audits is the role of the fund's auditors. The RTA versus custodian confusion is especially common because both are "back-office" functions that candidates lump together.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B and III-C, the RTA's role becomes critical when discussing investor servicing timelines (e.g., processing redemption requests within specific timeframes) and data integrity. The SEBI-mandated Consolidated Account Statement (CAS) is generated using data maintained by RTAs.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As a distributor, the RTA is your primary operational touchpoint. When clients have issues with folio consolidation, address changes, bank mandate updates, or transaction statements, the RTA is the entity that resolves these. Building a good working relationship with your RTA contact saves enormous time.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
