<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, an Infrastructure Debt Fund (IDF) mutual fund scheme can be set up ONLY as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An open-ended equity scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A closed-ended debt scheme investing primarily in debt securities of infrastructure companies or infrastructure capital companies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An interval fund with quarterly redemption windows]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An exchange-traded fund tracking an infrastructure index]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI introduced the Infrastructure Debt Fund (IDF) as a new product category for mutual funds. An IDF-MF must be set up as a closed-ended debt scheme with a minimum tenure of 5 years. It invests primarily in debt securities or securitized debt instruments of infrastructure companies or infrastructure capital companies (project SPVs). The closed-ended nature matches the long-term nature of infrastructure debt, where assets have limited liquidity.

**The Trap:** IDF is a DEBT product (not equity) and must be CLOSED-ENDED (not open-ended or interval). An infrastructure ETF tracking an index would be a different product category altogether. The closed-ended requirement is critical because infrastructure debt instruments are illiquid and long-duration — open-ended structures would create asset-liability mismatches.

**Cross-Exam Context:** IDF is tested in Series V-A as a new product innovation under SEBI regulations. It may also appear in Series III-A (securities market products). IDFs can also be set up as NBFCs under RBI regulation — the exam may test the distinction between IDF-MF (SEBI-regulated) and IDF-NBFC (RBI-regulated).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** IDFs are suitable for sophisticated investors (institutions, HNIs) looking for long-term infrastructure debt exposure with potential tax benefits. As a distributor, recommend IDFs only to clients who understand the lock-in nature and have a sufficiently long investment horizon. These are not suitable for clients needing liquidity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
