<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, what is the validity period of the NISM Series V-A: Mutual Fund Distributors Certification, and what is required for renewal?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[3 years validity; renewal through CPE (Continuing Professional Education) or re-examination before expiry]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5 years validity; no renewal required — lifetime certification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1 year validity; annual re-examination is mandatory]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[10 years validity; renewal through a simple online test]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The NISM Series V-A certification has a validity period of 3 years from the date of passing the examination. To renew, distributors must either: (1) complete the required Continuing Professional Education (CPE) credits before the certification expires, or (2) re-take and pass the NISM exam. If the certification lapses, the ARN also becomes invalid, and the distributor cannot earn commissions on new transactions until renewal is completed.

**The Trap:** It is NOT a lifetime certification — the 3-year renewal ensures distributors stay updated with regulatory changes. Annual re-examination is too frequent and not the actual requirement. The CPE route is the more common renewal path, as it does not require re-examination but involves attending approved training programs and accumulating the requisite CPE credits.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Certification requirements are tested in Series V-A (meta-question about your own exam!), V-B, and III-A. The CPE framework applies to all NISM certifications, not just Series V-A. Series XXIV (Compliance) tests the monitoring of certification validity for registered intermediaries.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Set a reminder at least 6 months before your certification expiry. CPE programs are offered by NISM, AMFI, and other approved providers. Treat CPE as a professional development opportunity, not just a compliance checkbox — the regulatory landscape changes frequently, and staying updated is essential for providing good service.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
