<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_37" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the AMFI Code of Conduct for Mutual Fund Intermediaries, which of the following is a prohibited practice for distributors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Recommending suitable schemes based on the investor's risk profile]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Disclosing all material information about the scheme to the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Inducing investors to churn their portfolio frequently to generate higher commissions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Providing after-sales service including account statements and portfolio reviews]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The AMFI Code of Conduct explicitly prohibits distributors from engaging in churning — frequently inducing investors to switch between schemes or redeem and reinvest to generate higher commissions at the investor's expense. Churning is a form of mis-selling that prioritizes distributor income over investor interest. Suitable recommendations, full disclosure, and after-sales service are all REQUIRED (not prohibited) practices under the code.

**The Trap:** Options A, B, and D are all positive practices that distributors SHOULD do — the question asks for the prohibited practice. Under exam pressure, candidates may misread the question and select a "good" practice. Churning is one of the most commonly cited distributor malpractices and is a key focus area for SEBI and AMFI enforcement.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The AMFI Code of Conduct is tested in Series V-A and V-B. Churning is also examined in Series III-C (Investment Adviser) and Series III-A (Securities Intermediaries) where similar prohibitions apply. Series XXIV (Compliance) tests the detection and prevention of churning.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Build your business on trail commissions rather than upfront commissions — this naturally aligns your interests with long-term investor wealth creation. If an AMC or product switch is genuinely beneficial for the client, document the rationale. Regular portfolio reviews are good practice, but each switch recommendation should have a clear, documented investor benefit.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
