<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The trustees of a mutual fund are required to review the transactions of the AMC on a:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Quarterly basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Half-yearly basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monthly basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annual basis]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI regulations require the Board of Trustees to conduct a quarterly review of the AMC's transactions and activities. This includes reviewing whether the AMC is operating within the investment mandate, whether there are any conflicts of interest, and whether the fund's operations comply with SEBI regulations and the trust deed.

**The Trap:** This question is the mirror image of Q8 (trustee reports to SEBI). The trustees REVIEW AMC transactions quarterly (internal oversight) but REPORT to SEBI half-yearly (external reporting). The half-yearly option is the most popular wrong answer because candidates who remember the half-yearly frequency often assign it to the wrong activity.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C, the distinction between internal review frequency (quarterly) and external reporting frequency (half-yearly to SEBI) is fundamental to compliance frameworks. Compliance officers must ensure both cycles are maintained without confusing one for the other.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use this memory aid: "Q for Quarterly, Q for Quality check" (internal AMC review) and "H for Half-yearly, H for Headquarters (SEBI) reporting." The quarterly review is the more frequent and operationally critical cycle that keeps the AMC accountable between SEBI reporting periods.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
