<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The appointment of the Board of Trustees of a mutual fund requires prior approval from:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Reserve Bank of India (RBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMFI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ministry of Finance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations, the appointment of every trustee to the Board of Trustees requires prior approval from SEBI. This ensures that SEBI can vet the suitability and independence of each trustee before they assume the fiduciary responsibility of overseeing investor assets.

**The Trap:** RBI regulates banks and NBFCs, not mutual fund trustees. AMFI is a self-regulatory body without statutory appointment approval authority. The Ministry of Finance oversees SEBI at a policy level but does not directly approve MF trustee appointments. Candidates who confuse the regulatory hierarchy often pick RBI (because banks are involved in MF operations) or Ministry of Finance.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C, the chain of approvals is crucial: SEBI approves trustees, trustees appoint the AMC and custodian, and the AMC appoints fund managers internally. Each layer of appointment has its own approval mechanism, and understanding this chain is essential for compliance professionals.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a mutual fund announces a change in its Board of Trustees, it means SEBI has already vetted and approved the new trustee. This pre-vetting by the regulator is another layer of protection for your clients' investments that you can highlight during client conversations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
