<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following regulators operates under the Ministry of Finance and is responsible for regulating the securities market in India, including mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Reserve Bank of India (RBI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority (PFRDA)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI is the statutory regulator for the securities market in India, established under the SEBI Act, 1992. Mutual funds, being collective investment vehicles that invest in securities, fall squarely under SEBI's regulatory jurisdiction. All four regulators — RBI, SEBI, IRDAI, and PFRDA — operate under the Ministry of Finance, Government of India, but each has distinct domains.

**The Trap:** All four options are legitimate regulators under the Ministry of Finance. Candidates often confuse RBI (which regulates banking, money markets, and forex) with SEBI. While RBI regulates money market instruments that mutual funds invest in, it does not regulate mutual funds themselves.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This fundamental regulatory structure question appears across NISM Series III-A (Securities Intermediaries), Series V-B (Mutual Fund Foundation), and Series XII (Securities Markets Foundation). Understanding the four-regulator framework is foundational.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As a mutual fund distributor, your primary regulatory relationship is with SEBI (through AMFI). However, understand that the products MFs invest in may be regulated by RBI (debt instruments, money market) or other regulators. This multi-regulator awareness helps you explain product risks to clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
