<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund distributor creates a social media post stating: "Invest in XYZ Equity Fund — it has given 45% returns in the last 6 months! Guaranteed to double your money in 2 years!" Which SEBI Advertisement Code violations are present in this post?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the guarantee claim violates the code; showing 6-month returns is acceptable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only showing past performance for a non-standard period is a violation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Multiple violations: (1) guarantee/assured returns claim, (2) non-standard performance period (6 months instead of 1/3/5 years), (3) no mandatory risk disclaimer, (4) no benchmark comparison]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There are no violations as distributors are exempt from the Advertisement Code]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** This social media post has multiple SEBI Advertisement Code violations: (1) "Guaranteed to double your money" — guaranteeing or assuring returns is strictly prohibited; (2) "45% returns in the last 6 months" — performance must be shown for standardized periods (1, 3, 5 years, since inception) on CAGR basis, not cherry-picked periods; (3) No mandatory disclaimer "Mutual Fund investments are subject to market risks..."; (4) No benchmark (TRI) comparison alongside the performance claim. Distributors ARE covered by the Advertisement Code — they are not exempt.

**The Trap:** Some candidates may identify only one violation when multiple exist. The most dangerous trap is Option D — distributors are absolutely NOT exempt from the Advertisement Code. Any person involved in the distribution or marketing of mutual funds must comply with SEBI's advertising guidelines.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Advertisement Code violations are scenario-based questions common in Series V-A and V-B. Series XXIV tests compliance monitoring of advertisements. Series III-C tests similar advertising restrictions for investment advisers. Social media posts are specifically covered under SEBI's advertising framework.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Social media is a powerful marketing tool, but every post about mutual funds is considered an "advertisement" under SEBI rules. Before posting, check: (1) no guaranteed return claims, (2) standard performance periods with CAGR, (3) TRI benchmark comparison, (4) mandatory disclaimer included. Several distributors have faced AMFI/SEBI action for non-compliant social media posts.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
