<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the minimum proportion of independent directors required on the Board of Directors of an Asset Management Company (AMC) under SEBI regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[One-fourth of the board]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[One-third of the board]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[50% (half) of the board]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Two-thirds of the board]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations require that at least 50% of the directors on the AMC Board must be independent directors. Similarly, at least two-thirds of the trustees must be independent of the sponsor. These governance norms ensure that the AMC's decision-making is not dominated by sponsor interests and that unitholder interests are adequately represented and protected.

**The Trap:** One-third is the Companies Act requirement for listed companies, not the SEBI MF-specific requirement. The MF regulations set a higher bar (50%) because of the fiduciary nature of fund management. Two-thirds applies to trustee boards (not AMC boards). Don't confuse AMC board independence requirements with trustee independence requirements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Governance norms are tested in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. Series XXIV (Compliance Officers) also tests governance frameworks extensively. The 50% AMC independence and two-thirds trustee independence are frequently tested together as a comparison pair.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Strong governance at the AMC level protects your clients' interests. When evaluating AMCs, look at the quality and independence of their board. AMCs with robust governance frameworks tend to have better risk management practices, which matters during market crises.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
