<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_47" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about regulatory oversight is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mutual Funds, PMS, and AIFs are all regulated under the SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations, 1996]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMS is regulated by RBI while Mutual Funds are regulated by SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Mutual Funds are regulated under SEBI MF Regulations 1996, PMS under SEBI (Portfolio Managers) Regulations 2020, and AIFs under SEBI (AIF) Regulations 2012 — all under SEBI but different regulation sets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AIFs are self-regulated with no SEBI oversight, unlike Mutual Funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** While all three — Mutual Funds, PMS, and AIFs — are regulated by SEBI, each operates under its own distinct set of regulations: MFs under SEBI (Mutual Fund) Regulations, 1996 (as amended); PMS under SEBI (Portfolio Managers) Regulations, 2020 (replacing the earlier 1993 regulations); and AIFs under SEBI (Alternative Investment Funds) Regulations, 2012. Each regulation has different provisions regarding registration, operations, disclosure, and investor protection suited to the product's nature.

**The Trap:** The most common confusion is that all pooled investment vehicles fall under one regulation — they don't. Each has a separate regulatory framework reflecting its unique characteristics. PMS is NOT regulated by RBI (Option B). AIFs are NOT self-regulated (Option D) — they are fully under SEBI's supervision. The year of each regulation is a frequent exam question.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This regulatory framework comparison is tested across Series V-A, III-A, and product-specific NISM certifications. Understanding that SEBI is the common regulator but with different regulation sets is foundational. The PMS regulation year change (1993 → 2020) is a recent update candidates must note.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients with larger portfolios ask about PMS or AIF, explain that while SEBI regulates all three, the regulatory protections differ. Mutual funds offer the highest level of investor protection (mandatory diversification, NAV transparency, daily liquidity for open-ended funds). PMS and AIF offer more flexibility but with higher risk and less regulatory handholding.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
