<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Within the organizational structure of an AMC, fund managers directly report to the:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Chief Investment Officer (CIO)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Chief Executive Officer (CEO)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Compliance Officer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Chief Operating Officer (COO)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In the AMC's organizational hierarchy, fund managers report to the Chief Investment Officer (CIO). The CIO is responsible for the overall investment strategy and oversees all fund managers. The CEO heads the AMC overall, the COO handles operations, and the Compliance Officer ensures regulatory adherence — but the direct reporting line for fund managers runs through the CIO.

**The Trap:** The CEO is the overall head of the AMC, so candidates may assume fund managers report to the CEO. While the CEO has ultimate authority, the direct functional reporting for investment decisions goes through the CIO. The Compliance Officer monitors investment compliance but does not direct investment decisions or manage fund managers.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For NISM III-C, the role delineation within an AMC is important for understanding accountability. The Compliance Officer's independence from the investment team (CIO/fund managers) is critical for effective compliance oversight. In SEBI enforcement actions, the CIO and individual fund managers have been held accountable for investment process failures.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When evaluating a fund for your clients, look at the CIO's track record and investment philosophy, not just the individual fund manager's. Fund managers may change, but if the CIO and the investment process are strong, the fund's character tends to remain consistent.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
