<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following entities is responsible for holding mutual fund assets in trust for the benefit of unitholders?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Asset Management Company (AMC)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trustees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sponsor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Custodian]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations, 1996, the mutual fund is constituted as a trust. The Trustees (Board of Trustees or Trustee Company) hold the assets of the mutual fund in trust for the benefit of unitholders. The Sponsor sets up the mutual fund trust, the AMC manages the investments, and the Custodian holds the securities in safe custody — but the legal ownership/trusteeship vests with the Trustees.

**The Trap:** Candidates frequently confuse the Custodian's role (physical/electronic safekeeping of securities) with the Trustees' role (legal oversight and trusteeship). The AMC manages but does not own the assets. The three-tier structure — Sponsor, Trustee, AMC — is fundamental to Indian mutual fund regulation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The trust structure of mutual funds is a core topic in Series V-A, V-B, and III-A. Series XII tests the broader concept of trust-based financial structures. The trustee's supervisory role over the AMC is a frequently examined governance concept.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients worry about "what if the AMC goes bankrupt?", explain the trust structure — unitholder assets are held by Trustees, separate from the AMC's own assets. This structural protection is a key selling point of the mutual fund framework.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
