<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Legal and Regulatory Framework_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, how is the IDCW (Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal) option in a mutual fund scheme different from the erstwhile "Dividend" option?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[IDCW is a nomenclature change to clarify that distributions may include capital withdrawal and are not guaranteed — the underlying mechanism remains the same]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW provides tax-free distributions unlike the old dividend option which was taxable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW guarantees a fixed periodic payout unlike the old dividend option which was discretionary]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW is available only for debt schemes while the old dividend option was available for all schemes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated (effective April 2021) the renaming of "Dividend" option to "Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal (IDCW)" option. This was a nomenclature change to address investor misconception that mutual fund "dividends" were similar to company dividends (which come from profits). In reality, MF distributions come from the NAV (which may include unrealized gains or even principal) and are not guaranteed. The mechanism of distribution remains unchanged.

**The Trap:** Many candidates assume IDCW introduced a new tax treatment or payout mechanism — it did not. It was purely a disclosure/nomenclature reform. IDCW distributions are still taxable in the hands of investors (post-2020 budget abolishing DDT). The word "Capital Withdrawal" is deliberately included to remind investors that payouts may erode their invested capital.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The IDCW nomenclature change is tested in Series V-A and V-B. It connects to SEBI's broader investor education mandate. Series III-C (Investment Adviser) tests the taxation implications of IDCW vs Growth option for different investor profiles.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always explain to clients that IDCW is NOT like a fixed deposit interest payout. The NAV falls by the distribution amount after each payout. Many retirees choose IDCW expecting regular "income" — educate them that SWP (Systematic Withdrawal Plan) from Growth option may be more tax-efficient for regular cash flows.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
