<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A life insurance policy taken under Section 6 of the Married Women's Property Act (MWPA) has which of the following characteristics?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It creates a trust in favour of the wife and/or children, and the policy proceeds cannot be attached by any court for the debts of the insured]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It allows the insured to change the beneficiary at any time and the proceeds can be used to settle outstanding debts of the insured]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It provides tax-free maturity benefits but the death benefit is taxable under the Income Tax Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is available only for policies with a sum assured above Rs. 50 lakhs and requires annual renewal of the trust deed]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 6 of the MWPA mandates that a life insurance policy taken under this act creates a statutory trust. The beneficiaries (wife and/or children) have a direct claim on the proceeds. Critically, these proceeds are ring-fenced from creditors -- no court can attach them for the insured's debts.
**The Trap:** The ability to "change beneficiary at any time" is incorrect -- MWPA policies have irrevocable beneficiary designations. There is no minimum sum assured requirement and no annual renewal of the trust deed.
**Cross-Exam Context:** MWPA is tested in NISM X-B as a key estate planning and creditor-protection tool that investment advisers must understand.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** MWPA policies are essential for business owners and professionals with potential liability exposure. The creditor protection makes them superior to regular policies for family financial security.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
