<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A businessman with significant personal liabilities purchases a life insurance policy worth Rs. 2 crore. He later faces bankruptcy and his creditors obtain court orders to attach his assets. Under which circumstance would the life insurance proceeds be completely protected from the creditors' claims?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[If the policy was taken under Section 6 of the Married Women's Property Act (MWPA) with his wife and/or children as beneficiaries]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[If the policy was a regular endowment plan with his wife nominated as the beneficiary]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[If the policy was a ULIP with a 5-year lock-in period that has already been completed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[If the policy was assigned to a bank as collateral for a business loan]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Only a policy taken under Section 6 of the MWPA creates a statutory trust that is completely ring-fenced from creditors. The proceeds go directly to the wife and/or children and cannot be attached by any court for the debts of the insured. A regular nomination (even in favour of the wife) does not provide this level of protection -- creditors can still claim against the policy proceeds.
**The Trap:** Nomination alone does not create creditor protection -- it only directs who receives the proceeds. The nominee in a regular policy holds the proceeds as a trustee for the legal heirs, and creditors can stake a claim. ULIP lock-in is about liquidity, not creditor protection. Assignment to a bank actually gives the bank priority claim.
**Cross-Exam Context:** MWPA and its creditor-protection feature is a high-value topic in NISM X-B estate planning and asset protection modules.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For business owners, professionals, and anyone with contingent liability exposure, MWPA policies are non-negotiable. The cost is the same as a regular policy, but the legal protection is vastly superior. Always recommend MWPA endorsement at policy inception.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
