<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a key distinguishing feature of term insurance compared to other life insurance products?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It provides only a death benefit with no survival/maturity benefit, making it the most affordable form of life insurance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It provides both death and maturity benefits, making it the most comprehensive form of life insurance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It builds cash value over time that can be borrowed against, similar to a savings account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It guarantees a minimum annual bonus irrespective of the insurance company's performance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Term insurance is a pure risk cover product -- it pays the sum assured ONLY if the insured dies during the policy term. There is no survival/maturity benefit. Because the insurer does not need to set aside money for maturity payouts, term insurance offers the highest cover at the lowest premium, making it the most affordable life insurance product.
**The Trap:** "Death and maturity benefits" describes endowment policies, not term plans. Cash value accumulation is a feature of whole life and endowment policies. Guaranteed annual bonuses are a feature of participating traditional policies, not term plans.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The fundamental distinction between term, endowment, whole life, and ULIP is foundational knowledge tested across NISM X-A and X-B exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Term insurance should be the foundation of every client's insurance portfolio. The "buy term, invest the rest" strategy is the most cost-efficient way to ensure adequate life cover while maximizing investment returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
