<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Whole life insurance policies were originally popular in India primarily for which of the following reasons?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[They helped in estate duty avoidance by providing liquidity to pay estate taxes, though estate duty has since been abolished in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They offered the highest investment returns among all life insurance products due to lifelong compounding]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They were the only type of policy that offered tax benefits under Section 80C of the Income Tax Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They were mandatory for all government employees as part of their employment benefits package]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Whole life policies provide coverage for the entire life of the insured (or up to an upper age limit). They were originally popular because they helped families manage estate duty obligations by providing a guaranteed payout at death to cover the tax liability. However, estate duty was abolished in India, reducing their primary appeal.
**The Trap:** "Highest investment returns" is incorrect -- whole life policies typically have lower returns than endowment plans of equivalent premium due to longer coverage periods and higher cumulative mortality charges. They were never mandatory for government employees.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the historical context of whole life products and their diminished relevance is tested in NISM X-B product comparison modules.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Despite the abolition of estate duty, whole life policies still serve a purpose for legacy planning, charitable giving, and ensuring dependents with lifelong needs (such as special-needs children) are protected.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
