<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When evaluating two competing term insurance policies for a client, which combination of criteria is MOST comprehensive for an investment adviser to use?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Coverage amount, premium cost, available riders, claim settlement ratio, and company credit rating]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the premium cost and sum assured, as term insurance is a commodity product with no other differentiators]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the claim settlement ratio and company brand reputation, since all policies are regulated by IRDAI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the maturity value and bonus track record, as these determine the long-term wealth creation potential]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NISM recommends evaluating life insurance policies across five key criteria: (1) coverage/sum assured, (2) premium affordability, (3) riders (accidental death, critical illness, waiver of premium), (4) claim settlement ratio (percentage of claims settled vs received), and (5) company rating/financial strength. All five together provide a comprehensive evaluation framework.
**The Trap:** Term insurance does NOT have maturity value or bonuses -- those are endowment product features. While premium and sum assured are important, ignoring riders and claim settlement ratio can lead to recommending a cheap but unreliable policy. Claim settlement ratio alone without premium comparison is incomplete.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This multi-criteria evaluation framework is explicitly tested in NISM X-B as part of the investment adviser's due diligence obligations.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Claim settlement ratio above 95% should be the minimum threshold. A cheap policy with a low claim settlement ratio is a false economy -- the premium saved is meaningless if the claim is not paid.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
