<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following best describes the difference between a guaranteed bonus and a reversionary bonus in a traditional life insurance policy?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A guaranteed bonus is a fixed percentage of sum assured declared for the first few years at policy inception, while a reversionary bonus is discretionary and depends on the insurance company's investment performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A guaranteed bonus is declared annually based on company profits, while a reversionary bonus is fixed at the time of policy purchase]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both bonuses are identical in nature but differ only in the timing of payment -- guaranteed is paid yearly while reversionary is paid at maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A guaranteed bonus applies only to ULIPs, while a reversionary bonus applies only to endowment plans]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A guaranteed bonus is pre-committed by the insurer for the initial years of the policy as a percentage of sum assured -- it is contractually fixed. A reversionary bonus, however, is declared at the discretion of the insurance company based on its investment performance and overall profitability. It is not guaranteed and can vary from year to year.
**The Trap:** Swapping the definitions is a classic exam trap. Candidates must remember: guaranteed = fixed upfront; reversionary = discretionary and performance-linked. ULIPs do not have bonuses -- they have NAV-based returns.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Bonus structures in traditional policies are compared against ULIP NAV-based returns in NISM X-B product comparison questions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When presenting policy illustrations, clearly distinguish between guaranteed and non-guaranteed components. Clients often mistake illustrated reversionary bonuses as guaranteed returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
