<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Life Insurance Products_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A ULIP policyholder wants to surrender the policy after 3 years of investment. What is the regulatory position on this?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The policyholder cannot surrender before completing the 5-year lock-in period; the fund will be moved to a discontinuation fund with a maximum charge of Rs. 6,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The policyholder can surrender at any time and will receive the full fund value minus a 2% exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The policyholder can surrender after 3 years with a minimum guaranteed surrender value of 30% of premiums paid]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The policyholder must wait for the full policy term to complete before any withdrawal is permitted]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ULIPs have a mandatory 5-year lock-in period as per IRDAI regulations. If a policyholder discontinues before 5 years, the fund value (after deducting a discontinuation charge of maximum Rs. 6,000) is moved to a discontinuation fund. The proceeds are paid out only after the lock-in period of 5 years is completed.
**The Trap:** The 30% minimum surrender value applies to traditional policies, not ULIPs. ULIPs have their own discontinuation framework. There is no "2% exit load" concept -- the charge is capped at Rs. 6,000 in absolute terms. The funds are not locked until the full policy term, only until 5 years.
**Cross-Exam Context:** ULIP discontinuation rules are heavily tested in both NISM X-B and NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) exams for comparison purposes.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The Rs. 6,000 cap on discontinuation charges is the maximum -- actual charges vary by year of discontinuation and are typically lower in later years. Always check the policy document.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
