<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mergers, Acquisitions and Takeovers_50" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When an acquirer states upfront intent to retain the listing of the target company but the post-offer shareholding may exceed maximum permissible non-public shareholding, what can the acquirer do?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cancel the open offer and renegotiate the underlying agreement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Request SEBI for a temporary exemption from minimum public shareholding norms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Delist the company immediately after the open offer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Proportionately reduce the shares acquired under the underlying agreement to stay within the maximum non-public shareholding limit]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If the acquirer has stated upfront intent to retain listing, they may proportionately reduce the number of shares acquired under the underlying agreement to ensure the post-offer shareholding does not exceed maximum permissible non-public shareholding. This balances the acquisition with listing compliance.
**The Trap:** "Delist immediately" contradicts the stated intent to retain listing. "SEBI exemption" is not available as a standard mechanism — the acquirer must manage shareholding within existing rules.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests the interplay between SAST and SCRR 1957 minimum public shareholding requirements. This is a nuanced area where merchant bankers add significant value.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This proportionate reduction mechanism is elegant — it allows acquirers to complete the deal while maintaining listing compliance. As a merchant banker, model multiple scenarios of tendering acceptance to ensure the acquirer can stay within limits under all outcomes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
