<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mergers, Acquisitions and Takeovers_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI SAST Regulations 2011, bonus issues and stock splits received by an acquirer in the preceding 52 weeks are treated how for the purpose of voluntary offer eligibility?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They count as acquisitions and disqualify the acquirer from making a voluntary offer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They count only if the bonus ratio exceeds 1:1]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[They are excluded from the 52-week disentitlement check and do not affect eligibility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are counted at 50% of their face value for disentitlement purposes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Regulation 6, bonus issues and stock splits are explicitly excluded from the 52-week disentitlement provision. Since these are non-discretionary corporate actions that apply to all shareholders proportionately, they do not represent the kind of strategic acquisition that the disentitlement rule aims to prevent.
**The Trap:** "They count as acquisitions" would penalize acquirers for corporate actions they cannot control. The regulation recognizes that bonus and split shares increase everyone's holdings proportionately without changing voting rights percentages.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX tests exceptions to SAST provisions carefully. NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) also covers corporate action adjustments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When planning a voluntary offer timeline, segregate corporate action shares from market purchases in the 52-week lookback. Only market purchases and preferential allotments create disentitlement risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
