<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mutual Funds_58" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the minimum investment amount required from investors for SEBI's newly introduced Specialized Investment Fund (SIF) category under mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10 lakhs across all investment strategies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1 lakh across all investment strategies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50 lakhs across all investment strategies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 5 lakhs per scheme]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI introduced a new product line under mutual funds known as Specialized Investment Fund (SIF) through a recent amendment to SEBI (Mutual Funds) Regulations. SIFs are sophisticated mutual funds where the minimum required investment amount is Rs. 10 lakhs from investors across all investment strategies. This higher threshold reflects the sophisticated nature of these products.

**The Trap:** Rs. 50 lakhs is the threshold for Accredited Investors under AIF regulations, not SIF. Rs. 1 lakh is too low for a specialized product. Students may confuse SIF with regular mutual fund minimum investments of Rs. 500 to Rs. 5,000.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SIF is a recent regulatory development tested in updated versions of NISM V-A and NISM XII. As a December 2024 amendment, this represents the latest evolution in mutual fund regulation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SIFs bridge the gap between regular mutual funds and alternative investment funds (AIFs). The Rs. 10 lakh minimum ensures that only investors with adequate financial capacity and presumably greater sophistication access these products. Ensure client suitability before recommending SIF products.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>