<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mutual Funds_57" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI's mutual fund categorization, what is the minimum investment that an Equity Linked Savings Scheme (ELSS) must make in equity and equity-related instruments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[80 percent of total assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[65 percent of total assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[75 percent of total assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[90 percent of total assets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI's mutual fund categorization norms, an ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Scheme) must invest a minimum of 80 percent of total assets in equity and equity-related instruments, in accordance with the Equity Linked Saving Scheme, 2005 notified by the Ministry of Finance. ELSS comes with a statutory lock-in period of 3 years and provides tax benefits under section 80C of the Income Tax Act.

**The Trap:** The 65 percent threshold applies to several other equity fund categories like Flexi Cap, Value, and Dividend Yield funds. Students may apply the general equity fund threshold to ELSS. The 80 percent is the same as Large Cap funds and Sectoral/Thematic funds, but ELSS has the added feature of tax benefit and lock-in.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's mutual fund categorization norms are extensively tested in NISM V-A and NISM XII. ELSS-specific rules combine tax law and securities regulation knowledge.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ELSS is the only mutual fund category offering income tax deduction under section 80C. The 3-year lock-in is the shortest among tax-saving instruments under 80C. Note that the tax benefit under section 80C is available only under the old income tax regime.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>