<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mutual Funds_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund registered with SEBI is classified as a "pass-through" entity for tax purposes, which means:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The income of the mutual fund is completely exempt from tax and taxed only in the hands of the investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The mutual fund pays tax on behalf of the investors at a flat rate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both the mutual fund and the investor pay tax on the same income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The investor is exempt from all taxes on mutual fund income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** To prevent double taxation, mutual funds registered with SEBI are classified as pass-through entities. The income earned by the fund on behalf of investors is completely exempt from tax at the fund level. The income is "passed through" to investors and taxed only in their hands when they earn it (through IDCW payouts or capital gains on redemption).

**The Trap:** The fund does NOT pay tax on behalf of investors. Income is NOT taxed at both levels (that would be double taxation, which the pass-through status prevents). Investors are NOT exempt from tax — they must pay tax on their MF income per applicable tax laws.

**Cross-Exam Context:** MF topics overlap with Series V-A, V-B. The tax treatment of mutual funds is also relevant in financial planning exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The pass-through status is an important tax efficiency feature. Explain to clients that the fund itself does not pay tax — this means no tax leakage at the fund level. Tax is paid only when the investor receives income or books gains.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
