<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mutual Funds_52" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's mutual fund categorization, a Corporate Bond Fund must invest a minimum of __________ of its total assets in corporate bonds rated AA+ and above.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[80% in AA+ and above rated corporate bonds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[65% in AA+ and above rated corporate bonds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[90% in AAA rated corporate bonds only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[70% in AA and above rated corporate bonds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI's mutual fund categorization norms, a Corporate Bond Fund must invest a minimum of 80% of its total assets in corporate bonds with a credit rating of AA+ and above. This ensures the fund maintains a high credit quality portfolio. In contrast, a Credit Risk Fund invests minimum 65% in corporate bonds rated AA and below (excluding AA+), deliberately taking on higher credit risk for potentially higher returns.

**The Trap:** The 65% threshold applies to Credit Risk Fund, not Corporate Bond Fund. Students often confuse the two categories. The rating threshold is also important: Corporate Bond Fund = AA+ and above; Credit Risk Fund = AA and below. The 90% in AAA is too restrictive and 70% in AA is a fabricated threshold.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Mutual fund debt categories are tested in NISM Series XII and V-A (Mutual Fund). The Corporate Bond Fund vs Credit Risk Fund distinction is a frequently tested topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Corporate Bond Fund = 80% in AA+ and above. Credit Risk Fund = 65% in AA and below. Remember: higher credit quality fund (Corporate Bond) has a higher allocation threshold (80%).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>