<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Mutual Funds_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Diversification in a mutual fund portfolio means:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Creating a well-balanced portfolio across multiple sectors and securities to smoothen price volatility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing all money in the single best-performing sector for maximum returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Splitting the investment equally between equity and debt regardless of objectives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buying units of multiple mutual fund schemes from the same AMC]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Diversification means creating a portfolio of securities such that the overall portfolio is well balanced across multiple sectors and securities. Since not all prices rise and fall together, diversification smoothens the impact of individual stock or sector movements. Mutual funds allow investors to access a diversified portfolio even with small investments of Rs. 5,000.

**The Trap:** Concentrating in one sector is the opposite of diversification. Equal split between equity and debt is an asset allocation decision, not diversification. Buying multiple schemes from one AMC may still result in overlapping portfolios without true diversification.

**Cross-Exam Context:** MF topics overlap with Series V-A, V-B. Diversification as a risk management tool is a fundamental concept in all investment-related NISM exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Diversification is one of the strongest advantages of mutual funds for small investors. A single equity diversified fund may hold 40-60 stocks across sectors — something impossible to replicate with a Rs. 5,000 direct investment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
