<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_38" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following best describes the "distributable surplus" from which IDCW can be declared by a mutual fund scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It includes realized gains and income received by the scheme, but excludes unrealized appreciation (valuation gains)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is limited only to the interest income and dividend income received by the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It includes only the realized capital gains from the sale of securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is the total NAV appreciation since the scheme's inception]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The distributable surplus from which IDCW can be declared includes: (a) realized gains from sale of investments, and (b) income received (interest, dividends from underlying securities). Importantly, unrealized appreciation (valuation gains) is EXCLUDED from distributable surplus per the workbook. The scheme can distribute IDCW only to the extent of this distributable surplus.

**The Trap:** It is not limited to just interest and dividend income — capital gains (realized) and unrealized appreciation are also included. It is not limited to only realized capital gains — income is also part of it. It is not total NAV appreciation since inception — it has specific components defined by regulations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The concept of distributable surplus is tested in NISM V-A. SEBI has clarified that IDCW can only be paid from distributable surplus, preventing schemes from paying IDCW in excess of available surplus, which would erode capital.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a scheme declares a large IDCW, check whether it has adequate distributable surplus. A scheme that consistently pays large IDCW without corresponding gains may be returning capital to investors. Monitor the scheme's performance relative to IDCW declarations — if the total return is lower than cumulative IDCW, the scheme is effectively returning invested capital.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
