<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE about the relationship between the TER of a direct plan and a regular plan of the same mutual fund scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The TER of the direct plan must be lower than the regular plan by at least the distributor commission component]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The TER of both direct and regular plans must be identical as per SEBI regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The direct plan TER is always exactly 1% lower than the regular plan TER]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The regular plan TER is lower than the direct plan TER because it has more investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates that direct plans must have a lower TER than regular plans. The difference must be at least equal to the distribution/commission expenses included in the regular plan TER. Since direct plans have no distributor involvement, the distributor commission is eliminated, resulting in a lower TER.

**The Trap:** TER is not identical for both plans — that would defeat the purpose of having separate plans. The difference is not a fixed 1% — it varies by scheme based on the distributor commission component. Regular plan TER is HIGHER (not lower) than direct plan TER because it includes distributor commission.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The direct vs. regular plan TER difference is a key concept in NISM V-A. Direct plans were introduced by SEBI in January 2013 to give investors a choice to invest without distributor intermediation at a lower cost. The NAV of direct plans is always higher than regular plans for the same scheme.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Acknowledge the TER difference transparently with clients. Your value proposition should go beyond just executing transactions. Provide financial planning, regular portfolio reviews, behavioral coaching during market volatility, and goal-based advice. Clients who value these services will willingly invest through the regular plan.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
