<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the face value at which units of a new mutual fund scheme are typically offered during a New Fund Offer (NFO)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10 per unit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 100 per unit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1 per unit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The face value is determined by the AMC based on market conditions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Units of a new mutual fund scheme are typically offered at a face value of Rs. 10 per unit during the NFO period. After the NFO closes and the scheme begins operations, the NAV starts from Rs. 10 and then fluctuates based on the performance of the underlying investments.

**The Trap:** Rs. 100 is the face value of most shares/debentures, not mutual fund units. Rs. 1 is too low and not the standard. The face value is not at the AMC's discretion — Rs. 10 is the industry standard for new schemes. Some ETFs may have different face values, but Rs. 10 is the standard for open-ended schemes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The Rs. 10 face value for NFO is important in NISM V-A. After the NFO, NAV will deviate from Rs. 10 based on market movements and expenses. A common investor misconception is that a fund with NAV of Rs. 10 (new fund) is "cheaper" than one with NAV of Rs. 100 (established fund).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never sell an NFO to clients by saying "you get more units at Rs. 10." This is a misleading sales pitch. A Rs. 1 lakh investment in a Rs. 10 NAV fund gets 10,000 units, while in a Rs. 100 NAV fund it gets 1,000 units — but the value is the same Rs. 1 lakh. What matters is the percentage return, not the number of units or the absolute NAV level.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
