<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV Calculations and Fund Valuation_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Horizon Mutual Fund manages the Horizon Corporate Bond Fund, a debt scheme with AUM of Rs.5,000 crore and 200 crore units outstanding. The fund held Rs.250 crore worth of bonds issued by Delta Industries Ltd, which constituted 5% of the portfolio. On March 15, Delta Industries was downgraded from BBB to BB- (below investment grade) by a credit rating agency. The fund manager, after obtaining trustee approval, decided to create a segregated portfolio for the Delta Industries holding.

Before segregation:
- Total portfolio: Rs.5,000 crore
- Delta Industries bonds: Rs.250 crore (now valued at Rs.100 crore post-downgrade)
- Other holdings: Rs.4,750 crore
- Total liabilities: Rs.50 crore
- Units outstanding: 200 crore

After segregation, the main portfolio contains Rs.4,750 crore of performing assets with Rs.47.50 crore of proportionate liabilities, and the segregated portfolio contains Rs.100 crore of impaired assets with Rs.2.50 crore of proportionate liabilities. Six months later, Delta Industries makes a partial recovery payment of Rs.80 crore on the bonds.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> What was the NAV of the Horizon Corporate Bond Fund immediately BEFORE segregation (but after the downgrade mark-down)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.25.0000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.23.7500]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.24.0000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.24.7500]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** After the downgrade, Delta bonds are marked down from Rs.250 crore to Rs.100 crore. Total portfolio = Rs.4,750 crore (other holdings) + Rs.100 crore (marked-down Delta) = Rs.4,850 crore. NAV = (4,850 - 50) / 200 = 4,800 / 200 = Rs.24.0000 (4 decimal places for debt fund).
**The Trap:** Rs.24.7500 uses the original Rs.5,000 crore portfolio without the mark-down. The credit downgrade immediately impacts NAV through mark-to-market before segregation occurs. Always use post-downgrade values.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Mark-to-market valuation means NAV reflects current reality, not historical cost. The Rs.150 crore loss on Delta reduces NAV by Rs.0.75 per unit (from Rs.24.7500 to Rs.24.0000).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The NAV drop of ~3% (Rs.0.75 per unit) happened because 5% of the portfolio lost 60% of its value. This demonstrates why diversification and credit quality monitoring matter. A concentrated bet on one issuer magnifies credit event impact.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>