<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_49" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): Mr. Rajesh holds 10,000 units of the "Sunrise Equity Growth Fund" with current NAV of Rs. 9.87. The scheme declares an IDCW of Rs. 1.50 per unit.

Question 3 of 4: What is the value of Mr. Rajesh's holding after the IDCW is paid out, and what is the total IDCW amount he receives?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Holding value: Rs. 83,700 and IDCW received: Rs. 15,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Holding value: Rs. 98,700 and IDCW received: Rs. 15,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Holding value: Rs. 83,700 and IDCW received: Rs. 9,870]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Holding value: Rs. 1,13,700 and IDCW received: Rs. 15,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Ex-IDCW NAV = Rs. 9.87 - Rs. 1.50 = Rs. 8.37. Holding value after IDCW = 10,000 units x Rs. 8.37 = Rs. 83,700. IDCW received = 10,000 units x Rs. 1.50 = Rs. 15,000. Total wealth = Rs. 83,700 + Rs. 15,000 = Rs. 98,700 (same as before IDCW, before tax).

**The Trap:** Rs. 98,700 holding value assumes NAV does not change after IDCW — the most common misconception. Rs. 9,870 IDCW amount incorrectly calculates IDCW as a percentage of NAV rather than a flat per-unit amount. Rs. 1,13,700 adds the IDCW to the holding value instead of recognizing it as a separate cash receipt that reduces NAV.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This case study demonstrates the fundamental IDCW-NAV relationship: NAV drops by exactly the IDCW per unit, total wealth (before tax) remains unchanged. This is tested extensively in NISM V-A and V-B. Note that IDCW is now taxable in the investor's hands, so post-tax wealth decreases.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In Mr. Rajesh's case, his total wealth before tax is unchanged at Rs. 98,700. But after tax on IDCW of Rs. 15,000 (taxed at his income tax slab rate), his actual wealth decreases. This is why the growth option is generally more tax-efficient — no taxable event occurs until redemption. Show clients this math to guide them toward appropriate option selection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
