<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV Calculations and Fund Valuation_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Horizon Mutual Fund manages the Horizon Corporate Bond Fund, a debt scheme with AUM of Rs.5,000 crore and 200 crore units outstanding. The fund held Rs.250 crore worth of bonds issued by Delta Industries Ltd, which constituted 5% of the portfolio. On March 15, Delta Industries was downgraded from BBB to BB- (below investment grade) by a credit rating agency. The fund manager, after obtaining trustee approval, decided to create a segregated portfolio for the Delta Industries holding.

Before segregation:
- Total portfolio: Rs.5,000 crore
- Delta Industries bonds: Rs.250 crore (now valued at Rs.100 crore post-downgrade)
- Other holdings: Rs.4,750 crore
- Total liabilities: Rs.50 crore
- Units outstanding: 200 crore

After segregation, the main portfolio contains Rs.4,750 crore of performing assets with Rs.47.50 crore of proportionate liabilities, and the segregated portfolio contains Rs.100 crore of impaired assets with Rs.2.50 crore of proportionate liabilities. Six months later, Delta Industries makes a partial recovery payment of Rs.80 crore on the bonds.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> What is the NAV of the MAIN portfolio after segregation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.24.7500]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.23.5125]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.24.0000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.23.7500]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Main portfolio NAV = (Main assets - Main liabilities) / Units = (4,750 - 47.50) / 200 = 4,702.50 / 200 = Rs.23.5125 (4 decimals for debt fund).
**The Trap:** Using total liabilities (Rs.50 crore) instead of proportionate main portfolio liabilities (Rs.47.50 crore) gives a different answer. Liabilities are split proportionately between main and segregated portfolios.
**Cross-Exam Context:** After segregation, all calculations must use the split assets and liabilities, not the pre-segregation totals.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The main portfolio NAV of Rs.23.5125 is lower than the pre-segregation Rs.24.0000 because the performing assets now bear their proportionate liabilities without the Delta holding. Explain to clients that this NAV represents only the healthy, performing portion of the fund.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>