<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is the correct formula for calculating Net Asset Value (NAV) of a mutual fund scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[(Total Assets - Total Liabilities) / Total Units Outstanding]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total Assets / Total Units Outstanding]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[(Total Assets - Total Liabilities) / Face Value per Unit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total Assets / (Total Liabilities x Total Units Outstanding)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NAV = (Total Assets - Total Liabilities) / Total Units Outstanding. This gives the per-unit value of the scheme's net assets. Total Assets include market value of investments, receivables, accrued income, and other assets. Total Liabilities include accrued expenses, payables, and other liabilities.

**The Trap:** "Total Assets / Total Units" forgets to subtract liabilities — the most common exam error. "Divided by Face Value" confuses NAV with a ratio-based calculation. The fourth option creates a nonsensical formula. Always remember: NAV = NET assets (after deducting liabilities) per unit.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is the most fundamental formula in mutual fund knowledge, tested across NISM V-A, V-B, II-B, and XII. The formula may be presented in expanded form (listing individual asset and liability components) or compact form.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** NAV represents the true per-unit value of an investor's holding. Unlike stock prices which are driven by demand-supply, NAV is purely a mathematical computation based on underlying asset values minus liabilities. This is an important distinction to explain to clients transitioning from equity investing to mutual funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
