<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_54" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Open-ended debt mutual fund schemes (excluding liquid and overnight funds) are required to maintain a ________ of their net assets in liquid assets such as cash, government securities, treasury bills, and repo on government securities.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 10%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 5%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 15%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 20%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates that open-ended debt fund schemes must maintain a minimum of 10% of their net assets (corpus) in liquid assets. Qualifying liquid assets include cash, government securities (G-Secs), treasury bills (T-bills), and repo on government securities. This requirement ensures that debt funds have sufficient liquidity to meet redemption requests without being forced to sell illiquid securities at distressed prices. Liquid funds and overnight funds are exempt from this requirement as they inherently invest in highly liquid instruments.

**The Trap:** 5% (Option B) understates the requirement and may be confused with other minimum thresholds. 15% (Option C) and 20% (Option D) overstate the requirement. The 10% figure is a specific SEBI mandate designed to balance liquidity needs with return optimization for debt funds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This liquidity requirement was strengthened after the 2020 credit crisis in debt mutual funds. It is part of SEBI's broader framework to improve liquidity risk management in open-ended debt schemes, alongside swing pricing and stress testing requirements.

**Key Takeaway:** Open-ended debt funds (except liquid/overnight) must hold minimum 10% in liquid assets (cash, G-Secs, T-bills, repo on G-Secs).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
