<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV Calculations and Fund Valuation_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunrise Mutual Fund operates an equity scheme called Sunrise Growth Fund and a liquid scheme called Sunrise Cash Fund. The following events occur during a particular week:

Monday: Portfolio value of Sunrise Growth Fund is Rs.800 crore with liabilities of Rs.20 crore and 40 crore units outstanding. Mr. Amit Kumar submits a purchase application for the Growth Fund at 2:45 PM with Rs.5 lakh via RTGS (credited same day). Mrs. Rekha Joshi submits a purchase application for the Cash Fund (liquid) at 1:15 PM with Rs.10 lakh via RTGS (credited same day).

Tuesday: The Growth Fund's portfolio rises to Rs.820 crore (same liabilities and units outstanding as Monday for simplicity). Mr. Vikash Patel submits a redemption request for 10,000 units of the Growth Fund at 3:20 PM.

Wednesday: The Growth Fund's portfolio value is Rs.810 crore. Mr. Vikash's redemption is processed using the applicable NAV.

The Growth Fund's closing NAV on Friday of the previous week was Rs.19.40. All days mentioned are business days.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Mr. Amit Kumar submitted his Growth Fund purchase at 2:45 PM on Monday with RTGS credited. What NAV is applicable for his purchase?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Monday's closing NAV of Rs.19.50 since both the application and funds were received before the 3 PM cut-off]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tuesday's closing NAV since equity fund purchases are processed on T+1]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Friday's closing NAV of Rs.19.40 since it was the last available NAV at the time of application]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The average of Friday's and Monday's NAV, i.e., Rs.19.45]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Amit submitted before 3 PM (equity cut-off) on Monday and funds were available (RTGS credited same day). Both conditions are met, so Monday's closing NAV of Rs.19.50 applies.
**The Trap:** T+1 processing does NOT mean T+1 NAV. The NAV is determined by when the application and funds are received, not when the units are allotted in the system.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The 'funds available for utilisation' concept is critical. RTGS provides same-day availability, unlike cheques which may take days to clear.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Amit's choice of RTGS ensured he got Monday's NAV. Had he used a cheque that cleared Wednesday, he would have gotten Wednesday's NAV of Rs.19.75 (from the caselet data) -- Rs.0.25 higher per unit, meaning fewer units for the same Rs.5 lakh.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>