<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_43" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which SEBI regulation governs the exit load on ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Schemes) mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ELSS schemes cannot charge any exit load because of the mandatory 3-year lock-in period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS schemes can charge a maximum exit load of 1% if redeemed within 5 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS schemes can charge exit load only during the first year at a rate of 2%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS schemes must charge a mandatory exit load of 0.50% on all redemptions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Schemes) have a mandatory lock-in period of 3 years as they offer tax deduction under Section 80C. Since investors cannot redeem during the lock-in period, there is no exit load applicable. After the 3-year lock-in, investors can redeem freely without any exit load.

**The Trap:** There is no exit load for ELSS — the lock-in period itself serves as a commitment mechanism. The 5-year period is for tax-saving fixed deposits, not ELSS. No mandatory exit load exists for ELSS. The lock-in replaces the need for exit load as a deterrent against early withdrawal.

**Cross-Exam Context:** ELSS exit load rules are tested in NISM V-A. Key ELSS features: 3-year lock-in, no exit load, tax deduction under Section 80C (up to Rs. 1.5 lakh), and equity-oriented portfolio. ELSS has the shortest lock-in among Section 80C tax-saving instruments.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ELSS is an excellent product to recommend during January-March (tax planning season). Highlight that it has the shortest lock-in (3 years) compared to PPF (15 years), NSC (5 years), and tax-saving FDs (5 years). After the 3-year lock-in, there is zero exit load — clients can redeem freely. This makes ELSS one of the most liquid tax-saving instruments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
