<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about TER (Total Expense Ratio) is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[TER is deducted from the scheme's assets on a daily basis and is reflected in the daily NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TER is charged as a separate fee to the investor's bank account at the end of each quarter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TER is deducted only at the time of redemption along with exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TER is charged annually in one lump sum on the scheme anniversary date]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** TER is computed and accrued on a daily basis. The daily TER (annual TER / 365) is deducted from the scheme's assets each day, which means the NAV already reflects the TER deduction. Investors do not receive a separate bill or see a separate charge — it is built into the NAV.

**The Trap:** TER is not charged separately to investors' bank accounts — it is embedded in NAV. It is not a one-time redemption charge like exit load. It is not an annual lump sum — it is a daily accrual. This is why comparing NAV returns already accounts for TER differences between schemes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The daily accrual nature of TER is tested in NISM V-A. This means that when you compare NAV-based returns of two schemes, the TER impact is already reflected. The scheme with lower TER, all else being equal, will show higher NAV growth.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Since TER is already deducted from NAV, the returns you quote to clients are net-of-expense returns. This is unlike PMS (Portfolio Management Services) where management fees may be charged separately. When comparing MF returns with PMS or direct equity returns, remember that MF returns are already net of TER while others may need expense adjustment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
