<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the current status of entry load in Indian mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Entry load has been abolished by SEBI since August 2009, so sale price equals NAV for open-ended schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Entry load of 2.25% is permitted for equity schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Entry load is optional and can be charged at the discretion of the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Entry load of 1% is mandatory for all mutual fund schemes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI abolished entry load for mutual fund schemes effective August 1, 2009. Since then, units of open-ended mutual fund schemes are sold at NAV (Sale Price = NAV). The formula Sale Price = NAV + Entry Load is now effectively Sale Price = NAV + 0 = NAV.

**The Trap:** 2.25% was the pre-2009 maximum entry load for equity schemes — this is outdated. Entry load is not optional or discretionary — it is completely abolished. No mandatory entry load exists. This is a factual regulatory question that tests whether candidates know the current regulation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The abolition of entry load is a landmark SEBI regulation tested in NISM V-A and V-B. After this abolition, SEBI allowed AMCs to use a portion of TER to pay distributor commissions. This shifted the cost from a one-time upfront charge to an ongoing expense through TER.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before 2009, distributors earned upfront commission through entry load. Post-abolition, distributor compensation comes from TER (trail commission model). This shift encouraged long-term relationship building with clients rather than one-time transaction-based selling. Embrace the trail commission model — it rewards you for assets retained, not just new sales.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
