<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What happens to the exit load amount collected by a mutual fund scheme when an investor redeems units?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It is credited back to the scheme, benefiting the remaining unitholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is retained by the AMC as additional revenue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is paid to SEBI as a regulatory fee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is distributed equally among all unitholders including the redeeming investor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI regulations, exit load collected on redemptions must be credited back to the scheme. This means the exit load amount increases the scheme's assets and benefits the remaining unitholders. The AMC cannot retain the exit load as its own revenue.

**The Trap:** Many candidates assume the AMC keeps the exit load — this was partially true before SEBI's regulation change, but now the entire exit load goes back to the scheme. It is not a regulatory fee to SEBI either. The exit load protects remaining investors from the impact of frequent redemptions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a critical regulatory point tested in NISM V-A. SEBI mandated that exit load be credited to the scheme to protect long-term investors from the transaction costs caused by frequent trading/redemptions. The AMC can charge additional 5 bps TER to compensate.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is a great selling point for long-term investors — explain that when short-term investors pay exit load, it actually benefits those who stay invested. This mechanism aligns the interests of long-term investors with the fund structure. Use this to encourage clients to stay invested beyond the exit load period.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
