<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Why is it incorrect for an investor to consider a mutual fund with a lower NAV as "cheaper" or a better value compared to a fund with a higher NAV?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Because NAV only reflects the per-unit value of assets, and investment returns depend on percentage growth of NAV, not its absolute level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because funds with lower NAV always have higher expense ratios making them more expensive]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because SEBI does not allow comparison of NAVs across different schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because lower NAV funds always carry higher risk than higher NAV funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NAV is simply (Total Assets - Total Liabilities) / Units Outstanding. A lower NAV does not mean the fund is cheaper or undervalued. What matters for investment returns is the percentage change in NAV over time, not the absolute level. A fund with NAV Rs. 10 growing at 12% and a fund with NAV Rs. 500 growing at 12% both deliver the same 12% return to the investor.

**The Trap:** Lower NAV funds do not necessarily have higher TER. SEBI does not prohibit NAV comparisons. Lower NAV does not imply higher or lower risk. The critical insight is that NAV is a mathematical construct, not a price signal like stock prices where "cheap" might have meaning.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a conceptual question tested in NISM V-A and V-B to check whether candidates can debunk common investor myths. The "low NAV is cheap" misconception is one of the most prevalent myths in Indian mutual fund investing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is perhaps the single most important misconception to address with clients. Use this analogy: if you invest Rs. 1 lakh in a Rs. 10 NAV fund (10,000 units) or a Rs. 100 NAV fund (1,000 units), and both grow 20%, your Rs. 1 lakh becomes Rs. 1.20 lakh in both cases. The number of units is irrelevant — only percentage return matters.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
