<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, what is the cut-off time for purchase applications in equity and debt schemes to get the same day's NAV?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[3:00 PM on a business day, provided both application and funds are received before this time]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1:30 PM on a business day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2:00 PM on a business day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[12:00 Noon on a business day]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For purchase applications in equity and debt schemes, the cut-off time is 3:00 PM on a business day. Both the application AND funds must be received by the mutual fund before 3:00 PM to get the same day's NAV. If either is received after 3:00 PM, the next business day's NAV applies. Note: The earlier Rs. 2 lakh threshold distinction was abolished by SEBI from February 2021 — now all purchase amounts follow the same 3:00 PM rule requiring funds realization.

**The Trap:** 1:30 PM is the cut-off time for certain liquid fund transactions, not for equity/debt schemes. 2:00 PM and 12:00 Noon are not the correct cut-off times for any standard scheme category. The critical condition is that BOTH application and funds must be received before 3:00 PM.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Cut-off timings are heavily tested in NISM V-A. Different rules apply for: (a) equity/debt schemes below Rs. 2 lakh — same-day NAV if received before 3 PM, (b) equity/debt schemes Rs. 2 lakh and above — same-day NAV only if funds also received before 3 PM, (c) liquid/overnight funds — different timings.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always advise clients to submit applications well before the 3:00 PM cut-off, especially for large investments. For amounts of Rs. 2 lakh or more, ensure the payment mode allows same-day credit (RTGS, NEFT, or local cheque). If using a demand draft or outstation cheque, the funds may not be credited by 3:00 PM, resulting in next-day NAV applicability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
