<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the significance of the term "IDCW" in mutual funds, and how does it differ from the earlier term "dividend"?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[IDCW (Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal) replaces the term "dividend" to clarify that the distribution comes from the scheme's assets, not from external profits like company dividends]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW is a new type of distribution that is tax-free, unlike the old dividend which was taxable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW means the fund distributes only capital gains, while earlier dividends included income as well]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW is only applicable to debt schemes, while the dividend option continues for equity schemes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI renamed the "dividend option" to "Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal (IDCW)" to make investors aware that mutual fund distributions are not like company dividends. Company dividends come from profits, but mutual fund IDCW comes from the scheme's own assets (including capital), which is why NAV falls by the distribution amount.

**The Trap:** IDCW is not tax-free — it is taxable in the investor's hands. IDCW can include both income and capital components, not just capital gains. The renaming applies to all schemes, not just debt schemes. The key insight is that IDCW is a naming change to prevent investor confusion.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The renaming from dividend to IDCW is a recent SEBI initiative tested in NISM V-A. This came after observations that many retail investors believed mutual fund "dividends" were similar to company dividends — extra income from profits. The new name clarifies that it is a withdrawal from the investor's own investment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the IDCW naming change as an opportunity to educate clients. Many investors in the IDCW option do not realize they are simply withdrawing their own money. Show them the math: NAV drops by the IDCW amount, so total wealth does not change. For most long-term investors, the growth option is more tax-efficient and better for wealth creation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
