<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor is choosing between the growth option and the IDCW option of the same mutual fund scheme. Which of the following statements is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both options invest in the same portfolio; the only difference is that the IDCW option distributes income periodically which reduces its NAV, while the growth option retains all gains in the NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The growth option invests in growth stocks while the IDCW option invests in dividend-paying stocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The growth option has higher risk than the IDCW option because it does not pay out any income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The IDCW option gives additional returns over and above the growth option because investors receive periodic distributions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Both the growth and IDCW options of a scheme invest in the same underlying portfolio managed by the same fund manager. The only difference is in how returns are treated: the growth option reinvests all gains into the scheme (NAV grows higher), while the IDCW option periodically distributes income to investors (NAV drops by the distribution amount). Total returns before tax are identical.

**The Trap:** Both options invest in the SAME portfolio — not different stocks. The growth option does not have higher risk — the risk profile is identical since the portfolio is the same. IDCW does not give "additional" returns — it simply pays out what would otherwise remain in the NAV. The total pre-tax return is the same.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The growth vs. IDCW option comparison is tested in NISM V-A and V-B. Key exam point: total wealth (NAV + distributions received) is the same for both options before tax. After tax, the growth option is generally more tax-efficient for investors not needing regular income.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Recommend the growth option for wealth creation goals (retirement, children's education) and the IDCW option only when clients genuinely need regular income (retirees). For the IDCW option, consider using Systematic Withdrawal Plan (SWP) from the growth option instead — it is more tax-efficient and gives the investor control over withdrawal amount and timing.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
