<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV Calculations and Fund Valuation_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunrise Mutual Fund operates an equity scheme called Sunrise Growth Fund and a liquid scheme called Sunrise Cash Fund. The following events occur during a particular week:

Monday: Portfolio value of Sunrise Growth Fund is Rs.800 crore with liabilities of Rs.20 crore and 40 crore units outstanding. Mr. Amit Kumar submits a purchase application for the Growth Fund at 2:45 PM with Rs.5 lakh via RTGS (credited same day). Mrs. Rekha Joshi submits a purchase application for the Cash Fund (liquid) at 1:15 PM with Rs.10 lakh via RTGS (credited same day).

Tuesday: The Growth Fund's portfolio rises to Rs.820 crore (same liabilities and units outstanding as Monday for simplicity). Mr. Vikash Patel submits a redemption request for 10,000 units of the Growth Fund at 3:20 PM.

Wednesday: The Growth Fund's portfolio value is Rs.810 crore. Mr. Vikash's redemption is processed using the applicable NAV.

The Growth Fund's closing NAV on Friday of the previous week was Rs.19.40. All days mentioned are business days.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Mr. Vikash Patel submitted his Growth Fund redemption at 3:20 PM on Tuesday. What NAV applies for his redemption?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monday's closing NAV of Rs.19.50 since it was the last confirmed NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The average of Tuesday's and Wednesday's NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Wednesday's closing NAV since the redemption was submitted after the 3 PM cut-off on Tuesday]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tuesday's closing NAV of Rs.20.00 since it was submitted during business hours]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Vikash submitted after 3 PM (the equity redemption cut-off) on Tuesday. Since the application was received after cut-off, the next business day's (Wednesday's) closing NAV applies.
**The Trap:** 'During business hours' is irrelevant -- only the 3 PM cut-off matters. At 3:20 PM, even though the office is open, the cut-off has passed and the NAV shifts to the next business day.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The hard 3 PM cut-off for redemptions is tested frequently. Time stamping proves whether the application was before or after 3 PM.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Had Vikash submitted 35 minutes earlier (at 2:45 PM), he would have gotten Tuesday's NAV. In a falling market, the delay works in his favour (higher NAV on Tuesday). In a rising market, it hurts. The lesson: submit redemptions with time to spare.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>