<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following expenses is NOT included in the Total Expense Ratio (TER) of a mutual fund scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Securities Transaction Tax (STT) on purchases and sales]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investment management and advisory fees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Custodian fees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Audit fees]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** TER includes investment management fees, trustee fees, audit fees, custodian fees, marketing/selling expenses (including brokerage and transaction costs), and other operational expenses. However, Securities Transaction Tax (STT) is a statutory levy on transactions and is not part of TER — it is borne by the scheme separately.

**The Trap:** Investment management fees, custodian fees, and audit fees are all components of TER. Candidates might think STT is part of TER since it affects the scheme, but STT is a government tax, not an operational expense of the scheme. Brokerage is part of TER but STT is not.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The components of TER are tested in NISM V-A. Key TER components to remember: investment management fees, trustee fees, audit fees, custodian fees, marketing/selling expenses including brokerage, and registrar & transfer agent fees. STT and GST on management fees are separate.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients compare fund expenses, ensure they understand that TER captures most operational costs but not all transaction-related taxes. A fund with high portfolio turnover will incur more STT (outside TER), which further reduces returns. Low-turnover funds tend to be more tax-efficient even though this advantage is not visible in TER comparisons.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
