<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_52" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When calculating the distributable surplus for dividend distribution by a mutual fund scheme, ________ from the distributable surplus calculation.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Unrealized appreciation (valuation gains) are excluded]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Unrealized appreciation (valuation gains) are included]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Unrealized appreciation is included only for equity-oriented schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Half of the unrealized appreciation is included]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI regulations, distributable surplus excludes unrealized appreciation (valuation gains). The rule is: "Valuation gains are ignored. But valuation losses need to be adjusted against profits." This means only realized gains (from actual sale of securities) can be distributed as dividends. Unrealized valuation losses, however, must be deducted from the surplus. This asymmetric treatment is a conservative accounting principle that protects investors from receiving dividends funded by paper profits that may never materialize.

**The Trap:** "Included" (Option B) is the most tempting wrong answer since many investors assume all gains contribute to distributable surplus. "Only for equity" (Option C) fabricates a category-based exception that does not exist. "Half included" (Option D) is a made-up compromise. The asymmetry -- gains excluded, losses deducted -- is the critical concept.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This asymmetric treatment (ignore gains, adjust for losses) is a core concept in mutual fund accounting. It reflects prudential norms to prevent distribution of unrealized paper profits.

**Key Takeaway:** Distributable surplus: exclude unrealized gains, but deduct unrealized losses. Only realized profits can be distributed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
