<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the primary purpose of SEBI mandating fair valuation principles for mutual fund schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To ensure that the NAV computed is fair to both existing investors and investors entering or exiting the scheme at that point in time]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To ensure that the AMC earns maximum management fee from the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To ensure that the NAV is always higher than the face value of units]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To ensure that investors never suffer losses in mutual fund investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's fair valuation principles aim to ensure that the NAV reflects the true realizable value of the scheme's securities. This protects all categories of investors — those who are entering (buying units), those who are exiting (redeeming units), and those who continue to hold. If valuations are unfair, one group benefits at the expense of another.

**The Trap:** Fair valuation is not about maximizing AMC fees — it is about investor protection. NAV can fall below face value if investments underperform, so it is not about keeping NAV above face value. Mutual fund investments carry market risk, so losses are possible — valuation norms do not prevent losses.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 10 SEBI fair valuation principles are specifically covered in NISM V-A Chapter 7. The overarching goal is equity among all unitholders. These principles require consistency, transparency, and fairness in valuation methodology.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Fair valuation is the backbone of investor trust in mutual funds. Unlike stocks where the price is set by demand-supply (and can be manipulated), mutual fund NAV is computed based on the actual value of underlying assets. This makes mutual funds a more transparent investment vehicle. Use this as a selling point when introducing clients to mutual funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
