<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, what is the maximum TER permitted for debt-oriented (other than equity-oriented) mutual fund schemes on the first Rs. 500 crore of AUM?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[2.00%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2.25%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[1.50%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2.50%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI's TER slab structure, debt-oriented (or other than equity-oriented) mutual fund schemes can charge a maximum TER of 2.00% on the first Rs. 500 crore of AUM. This is 25 basis points lower than the equity scheme limit of 2.25%.

**The Trap:** 2.25% is the maximum TER for equity-oriented schemes (not debt). 1.50% applies to a higher AUM slab, not the first slab. 2.50% exceeds the regulatory maximum for any scheme type. The 25 bps difference between equity and debt scheme TER limits is a frequently tested distinction.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The TER distinction between equity and debt schemes is critical in NISM V-A. Remember: Equity = 2.25% max on first slab; Debt/Other = 2.00% max on first slab. Both have declining slab rates for higher AUM. Index funds and ETFs have even lower TER limits.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Since debt schemes have lower TER limits, the distributor commission from debt schemes is typically lower than from equity schemes. This is one reason why many distributors focus on equity schemes. However, debt schemes serve an important role in client portfolios for stability and regular income needs. Balance your business between equity and debt recommendations based on client needs, not just commission considerations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
