<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_37" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In the context of mutual fund expense management, what does the term "B30 cities" refer to, and why is it significant for TER?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[B30 refers to cities Beyond the Top 30 cities in India, and AMCs are allowed an additional 30 bps TER for inflows sourced from these cities to incentivize geographical penetration of mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[B30 refers to the Bottom 30 performing mutual fund schemes that are allowed higher TER to cover losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[B30 refers to 30 benchmark indices, and funds tracking these indices get lower TER allowance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[B30 refers to the first 30 business days of a scheme during which higher TER can be charged]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** B30 stands for "Beyond Top 30" cities — these are all cities in India other than the 30 largest cities (T30). SEBI allows AMCs to charge an additional 30 basis points (0.30%) TER for net inflows from B30 cities. This incentivizes AMCs and distributors to expand mutual fund distribution to smaller towns and cities, promoting financial inclusion.

**The Trap:** B30 has nothing to do with bottom-performing schemes, benchmark indices, or business days. It is a geographical classification designed to promote mutual fund penetration in smaller cities where penetration is historically low.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The B30/T30 classification and its TER implications are tested in NISM V-A. The T30 cities include metros like Mumbai, Delhi, Bengaluru, Chennai, etc. Everything else is B30. AMFI publishes the list of T30 cities periodically.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you operate in a B30 city, this is a significant advantage. The additional 30 bps TER means AMCs can afford to pay higher trail commissions for B30 city sourced investments. This creates a business opportunity for distributors in Tier 2, Tier 3, and smaller cities where mutual fund awareness is growing but penetration remains low.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
