<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV Calculations and Fund Valuation_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunrise Mutual Fund operates an equity scheme called Sunrise Growth Fund and a liquid scheme called Sunrise Cash Fund. The following events occur during a particular week:

Monday: Portfolio value of Sunrise Growth Fund is Rs.800 crore with liabilities of Rs.20 crore and 40 crore units outstanding. Mr. Amit Kumar submits a purchase application for the Growth Fund at 2:45 PM with Rs.5 lakh via RTGS (credited same day). Mrs. Rekha Joshi submits a purchase application for the Cash Fund (liquid) at 1:15 PM with Rs.10 lakh via RTGS (credited same day).

Tuesday: The Growth Fund's portfolio rises to Rs.820 crore (same liabilities and units outstanding as Monday for simplicity). Mr. Vikash Patel submits a redemption request for 10,000 units of the Growth Fund at 3:20 PM.

Wednesday: The Growth Fund's portfolio value is Rs.810 crore. Mr. Vikash's redemption is processed using the applicable NAV.

The Growth Fund's closing NAV on Friday of the previous week was Rs.19.40. All days mentioned are business days.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Mrs. Rekha Joshi's liquid fund purchase was submitted at 1:15 PM on Monday with RTGS. What NAV applies?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Monday's closing NAV since RTGS was credited on Monday]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tuesday's closing NAV as the next business day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Thursday's closing NAV of the previous week]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Friday's closing NAV of Rs.19.40 equivalent (the previous day's NAV for liquid fund purchases received before 1:30 PM cutoff)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For liquid fund purchases received before the 1:30 PM cut-off with funds available, the applicable NAV is the closing NAV of the DAY BEFORE receipt. Rekha applied on Monday before 1:30 PM, so the previous business day's (Friday's) closing NAV applies.
**The Trap:** Unlike equity funds where same-day NAV applies for pre-cut-off applications, liquid funds specifically use the PREVIOUS day's NAV. This anti-arbitrage rule prevents investors from investing at a known NAV.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The liquid fund NAV rule is the most counter-intuitive rule in MF operations. Practice multiple scenarios to build clarity.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For corporate treasury clients managing overnight cash, explain that liquid fund purchases get the previous day's NAV. Monday purchases get Friday's NAV -- the weekend doesn't create any free return opportunity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>