<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, when was entry load abolished for mutual fund schemes in India, and what was the rationale?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[August 2009 — to prevent the practice of using investor money to pay distributor commissions upfront, making costs more transparent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[April 2012 — to align Indian mutual fund regulations with international standards]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[January 2013 — to coincide with the launch of direct plans for mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[March 2006 — as part of the first comprehensive mutual fund regulation reform]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI abolished entry load effective August 1, 2009 through a circular. The rationale was that entry load was being used to pay distributor commissions, which meant investors were unknowingly bearing the cost of distribution upfront. By abolishing entry load, SEBI made the cost structure more transparent and shifted distributor compensation to the TER (trail commission model).

**The Trap:** The date is August 2009, not April 2012 (when some other regulatory changes happened) or January 2013 (when direct plans were launched — a related but different initiative). March 2006 is incorrect. The abolition was specifically about entry load, not a comprehensive reform.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The August 2009 entry load abolition is one of the most significant SEBI regulatory actions in mutual fund history, tested in NISM V-A and V-B. It transformed the mutual fund distribution business model from upfront commission to trail commission.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The entry load abolition was a paradigm shift for the distribution industry. It eliminated the incentive for "churning" (advising investors to switch frequently to earn upfront commissions) and promoted long-term relationship-based advisory. Distributors who adapted to the trail commission model built sustainable businesses. Focus on retaining AUM rather than just chasing new sales.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
