<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="NAV TER and Pricing_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following SEBI fair valuation principles states that the valuation should be reflective of the realizable value of the securities?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The principle that valuation shall be based on the current market conditions and shall reflect the fair value of the securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The principle that securities should be valued at historical cost always]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The principle that valuation should maximize the NAV for investor benefit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The principle that valuation should minimize the tax liability of the scheme]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's fair valuation principles require that securities be valued in a manner that reflects their realizable value — the price at which they could be sold in the current market. This ensures that NAV accurately represents the true worth of the scheme's holdings and is fair to both entering and exiting investors.

**The Trap:** Historical cost valuation does not reflect current market conditions and would misrepresent NAV. The goal is not to maximize or minimize NAV, but to arrive at a fair value. Tax minimization is not a valuation objective. The core principle is fairness and accuracy in reflecting realizable values.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI has laid down 10 principles for fair valuation, which guide AMCs in valuing scheme portfolios. These principles ensure consistency, transparency, and fairness in NAV computation. This is specifically tested in NISM V-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Fair valuation protects both existing and new investors. If a security is overvalued, new investors entering at that NAV overpay. If undervalued, exiting investors receive less than fair value. As a distributor, this should give you confidence that the NAV-based pricing system is designed to be equitable for all investors at all times.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
