<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Portfolio Creation for Retirement_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Kavita is 50 years old and plans to retire at 60. She currently earns Rs. 1,50,000 per month and has accumulated Rs. 45 lakh in various retirement-linked investments (EPF: Rs. 20 lakh, PPF: Rs. 10 lakh, NPS: Rs. 15 lakh). Her monthly expenses are Rs. 70,000 (of which Rs. 8,000 is healthcare). She estimates needing Rs. 65,000 per month in today's terms at retirement (reduced due to paid-off home loan). General inflation is 6%, healthcare inflation is 10%, and her pre-retirement portfolio return is 9%. Post-retirement, she expects a 7% nominal return. Her life expectancy is 82 years. Three years ago, she withdrew Rs. 2,00,000 from her EPF for a family emergency. She is considering a step-up SIP strategy for the remaining 10 years and is evaluating whether to invest in an annuity or a systematic withdrawal plan (SWP) at retirement.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> At retirement, Mrs. Kavita will be 60 with a life expectancy of 82 (22 years in retirement). She is evaluating retirement products. Based on the NISM curriculum's criteria for the retirement phase (around retirement age), which combination of evaluation criteria and product recommendations is MOST appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Criteria: Cost, return, and risk tolerance; Products: Continue 100% in equity mutual funds and NPS for maximum growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Criteria: Liquidity for heirs and capital protection; Products: 100% in bank fixed deposits and savings accounts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Criteria: Inflation protection, capital protection, and income generation; Products: A mix of SCSS, PMVVY, balanced/hybrid funds, and a partial annuity for guaranteed income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Criteria: Tax efficiency and high returns; Products: 100% in NPS Tier-I and ELSS funds for tax savings]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For the retirement phase (at or around retirement age), the NISM textbook specifies three key evaluation criteria: inflation protection, capital protection, and income generation. The product mix should balance guaranteed income (SCSS, PMVVY, annuity) with growth to beat inflation (balanced/hybrid funds). 100% equity is too risky, and 100% FDs will not keep pace with inflation over 22 years.

**The Trap:** Option A applies pre-retirement criteria (cost, return, risk) and suggests 100% equity, which is inappropriate at retirement due to sequence-of-returns risk. Option B applies post-retirement (75+) criteria (liquidity for heirs) prematurely and suggests 100% fixed income, which will lose to inflation over 22 years. Option D focuses on tax efficiency (a pre-retirement criterion) and suggests products meant for accumulation, not distribution.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B explicitly categorizes product evaluation criteria into three life stages: pre-retirement (cost, return, risk, tax efficiency), retirement (inflation protection, capital protection, income), and post-retirement 75+ (income, capital protection, liquidity for heirs). This is a high-priority exam topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The bucket strategy works well for clients like Mrs. Kavita: Bucket 1 (1-3 years expenses) in liquid/ultra-short funds for immediate needs; Bucket 2 (4-10 years) in SCSS, PMVVY, and balanced funds for income + moderate growth; Bucket 3 (10+ years) in equity-oriented funds for long-term inflation protection. This balances all three criteria simultaneously.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
