<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Portfolio Creation for Retirement_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the three phases of retirement planning in their proper sequence?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Distribution stage → Accumulation stage → Final retirement stage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pre-retirement stage → Accumulation stage → Final retirement stage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Preparation (accumulation) stage → Pre-retirement/Initial retirement stage → Final retirement stage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Accumulation stage → Distribution stage → Preservation stage]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The textbook identifies three distinct phases: (1) Preparation stage (also called accumulation stage) where wealth is built, (2) Pre-retirement/Initial retirement stage where the transition from working to retired life occurs, and (3) Final retirement stage where the focus shifts to preserving capital and generating income for the remaining years.

**The Trap:** Option A reverses the first two stages. Option B separates pre-retirement from accumulation, but the textbook treats accumulation as the preparation stage. Option D uses terminology (preservation stage) not used in the NISM curriculum for retirement phases, though preservation is an objective within the final retirement stage.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-A introduces the concept of life-stage investing. X-B deepens this with specific retirement phases. Understanding the phase sequence is crucial because asset allocation and product selection change dramatically across phases.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Each phase demands a different investment strategy. Preparation = aggressive growth (equity-heavy). Pre-retirement = gradual de-risking (balanced funds, target-date funds). Final retirement = income and preservation (debt funds, annuities, SCSS). Never apply a one-size-fits-all approach across phases.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
