<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Portfolio Creation for Retirement_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When evaluating retirement products for a client who is 15-20 years away from retirement (pre-retirement phase), which combination of criteria should an investment adviser prioritize?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Income generation, capital protection, and liquidity for heirs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Inflation protection, capital protection, and income generation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Cost efficiency, potential return, risk level, and tax efficiency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteed returns, immediate liquidity, and zero risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For the pre-retirement phase (15-20 years to retirement), the textbook specifies four criteria: cost of the product, potential return, risk, and tax efficiency. Products like EPF, NPS, and PPF are suitable at this stage. The focus is on accumulation and growth, not income generation.

**The Trap:** Option A describes the post-retirement (75+) phase criteria: income generation, capital protection, and liquidity for heirs. Option B describes the retirement phase criteria (around retirement age): inflation protection, capital protection, and income generation. Option D is unrealistic -- no product offers guaranteed returns with zero risk and immediate liquidity.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B explicitly categorizes retirement product evaluation criteria by three life stages: pre-retirement, retirement, and post-retirement. NISM V-A covers product suitability concepts.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Match the product evaluation criteria to the client's life stage. A 40-year-old needs growth and tax efficiency (NPS, equity mutual funds). A 60-year-old needs inflation-protected income (SCSS, PMVVY, annuities). A 75-year-old needs safe income and estate liquidity (FDs, liquid funds, government securities).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
