<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Portfolio Creation for Retirement_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about superannuation benefits is INCORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Superannuation plans must be approved by the Commissioner of Income Tax for tax exemption benefits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Under Section 10(13), superannuation benefits received on death or retirement are exempt from income tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The employer's contribution to a superannuation fund is deductible under Section 80C of the Income Tax Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trustees of a superannuation fund must invest as per Income Tax Rules and deduct TDS where applicable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The employer's contribution to a superannuation fund is deductible under Section 36(iv), NOT Section 80C. Section 80C applies to the EMPLOYEE's contribution to the superannuation fund. This is a critical distinction in the tax treatment of superannuation benefits.

**The Trap:** Candidates often confuse employer and employee tax sections. Section 36(iv) is the employer deduction provision, while Section 80C covers employee contributions. The question tests whether candidates can distinguish between these two provisions, which is a common exam trick.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers basic tax planning concepts. Superannuation tax treatment is also relevant in NISM Series XII (Securities Markets Foundation) and is tested in detail in X-B.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising corporate clients on retirement benefits, always clarify the dual tax advantage: employers claim deduction under Section 36(iv), employees claim under Section 80C, and the corpus is exempt under Section 10(13) on retirement/death. This triple benefit makes superannuation attractive.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
