<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Portfolio Creation for Retirement_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Why is retirement considered unique among all financial goals? Select the MOST comprehensive answer.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because it requires the largest corpus compared to any other goal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because no loans are available for retirement, unlike housing or education]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Because it has the longest accumulation and distribution periods, requires the largest corpus, and cannot be funded through borrowing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because inflation affects retirement expenses more than other financial goals]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The textbook identifies retirement as unique for multiple reasons: it has the longest accumulation period (potentially 30-40 years of working life), the longest distribution period (potentially 20-25 years of retirement), requires the largest corpus of any financial goal, and critically, no loans are available for retirement unlike housing (home loan) or education (education loan). Option C captures all these dimensions.

**The Trap:** Options A and B each state only one of the reasons, making them partially correct but incomplete. Option D, while true that inflation impacts retirement significantly, is not the primary reason retirement is considered unique -- inflation affects all long-term goals.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-A introduces goal-based financial planning. X-B deepens the analysis of why retirement requires special attention. The concept that "you can borrow for a house but not for retirement" is a key differentiator.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients deprioritize retirement for children's education or a house purchase, remind them: banks lend for homes and education, but nobody lends for retirement. Retirement savings should be non-negotiable, even if it means a smaller home or partial education funding.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
