<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Portfolio Creation for Retirement_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor needs Rs. 1.18 crore at retirement (age 60). Instead of a fixed SIP of Rs. 20,217 per month starting at age 35, he opts for a step-up SIP with a 7% annual increase. Which of the following best describes the advantage of the step-up approach?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The step-up SIP generates a higher total corpus than the fixed SIP for the same target amount]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The step-up SIP allows a lower initial monthly investment, making it more affordable in the early earning years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The step-up SIP reduces the total amount invested over the accumulation period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The step-up SIP eliminates the need for inflation adjustment in retirement expense planning]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A step-up SIP allows the investor to start with a lower initial amount (less than Rs. 20,217) and increase it by 7% each year. This aligns with expected salary growth, making the SIP more affordable in the early career years when income is lower. Both fixed and step-up SIPs are designed to reach the same target corpus of Rs. 1.18 crore.

**The Trap:** Option A is wrong because both approaches target the same corpus. Option C is wrong because the total amount invested may actually be similar or slightly different, but that is not the primary advantage. Option D is completely incorrect -- step-up SIP is an accumulation strategy and has nothing to do with inflation adjustment during retirement.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Step-up SIP is a practical concept tested in NISM X-B. NISM V-A (Mutual Fund Distributors) also covers SIP variations including step-up/top-up SIP features offered by mutual funds.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Step-up SIPs are excellent for young professionals whose income grows 7-10% annually. Start with what is comfortable and commit to increasing by a fixed percentage each year. This mirrors the salary hike cycle and builds discipline without initial financial strain.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
