<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under Section 14 of the Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002, a reporting entity that furnishes information to the authorities in good faith is protected from:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only criminal proceedings arising from such disclosure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only civil proceedings arising from such disclosure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both civil and criminal proceedings for furnishing such information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Disciplinary proceedings by the regulator but not court proceedings]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 14 of PMLA provides that no civil or criminal proceedings shall lie against a reporting entity or its officers for furnishing information to authorities in good faith. This "safe harbour" provision is crucial — it encourages reporting entities to file Suspicious Transaction Reports (STRs) without fear of being sued by the client whose transactions are reported.

**The Trap:** The first two options each mention only one type of protection (criminal or civil), but Section 14 explicitly covers BOTH. The fourth option incorrectly limits protection to regulatory disciplinary actions. The key phrase is "no suit, prosecution, or other legal proceeding."

**Cross-Exam Context:** Section 14 protection is the legal backbone that enables the entire STR filing system. Without it, reporting entities would hesitate to report suspicious transactions for fear of client lawsuits. This concept is also relevant in NISM Series III-A for depository participants.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Section 14 PMLA = safe harbour for good faith reporting. Both civil AND criminal immunity. But the protection only applies when information is furnished "in good faith" — malicious or negligent reporting is not protected.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>