<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[The Principal Officer designated by a reporting entity under PMLA is responsible for:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ensuring overall compliance with PMLA across the entire organization]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Acting as a central reference point for facilitating onward reporting of suspicious transactions to FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investigating money laundering offences on behalf of the Enforcement Directorate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Prosecuting persons involved in money laundering in Special Courts]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Principal Officer is an officer at management level designated by the reporting entity for the purpose of Section 12 of PMLA. The Principal Officer acts as a central reference point for facilitating onward reporting of suspicious transactions to FIU-IND. Rule 7 requires the entity to communicate the Principal Officer's details to FIU-IND.

**The Trap:** Option A describes the Designated Director's role (overall compliance). Options C and D describe ED and prosecution functions respectively — these are not the Principal Officer's responsibilities.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM III-A exams, intermediaries are asked about who reports to FIU-IND — the answer is always the Principal Officer. In NISM XXIV, the distinction between Principal Officer and Designated Director is more explicitly tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The Principal Officer must be at "management level" — not a junior employee. This ensures that the person responsible for reporting has sufficient authority and access to information within the organization.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>