<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text>According to Section 12 of PMLA, which of the following is NOT a requirement for every reporting entity?</text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text>Maintain a record of all transactions in a manner to enable reconstruction of individual transactions</text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text>Furnish information relating to transactions to the Director within prescribed time</text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text>Maintain record of documents evidencing identity of its clients and beneficial owners</text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text>Directly investigate and prosecute clients suspected of money laundering</text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text>**The Logic:** Section 12 requires reporting entities to: (a) maintain transaction records enabling reconstruction, (b) furnish information to the Director (FIU-IND), and (c) maintain identity records and business correspondence. Reporting entities are NOT required to investigate or prosecute — that is the role of ED and Special Courts.

**The Trap:** All three legitimate obligations (maintain, furnish, keep identity records) are directly from Section 12(1). The incorrect option (investigate and prosecute) confuses the reporting entity's role with law enforcement. Reporting entities detect and report; they do not investigate or prosecute.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a sample question pattern in the NISM XXIV workbook. In NISM III-A, intermediary obligations under Section 12 are a core topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Section 14 of PMLA provides protection — no civil or criminal proceedings shall lie against a reporting entity, its directors, or employees for furnishing information in good faith. This encourages reporting without fear of litigation from clients.</text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>