<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Primary Markets_59" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[In a book-built IPO where the issuer meets the eligibility criteria regarding net tangible assets and profitability, what is the minimum allocation reserved for retail individual investors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not less than 35 percent of the net offer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not less than 50 percent of the net offer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not less than 25 percent of the net offer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not less than 10 percent of the net offer]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In a book-built offer where the issuer fulfills the eligibility criteria regarding net tangible assets, average operating profit, and net worth, the allocation is: not less than 35 percent to retail individual investors, not less than 15 percent to non-institutional investors, and not more than 50 percent to QIBs (of which 5 percent is reserved for mutual funds).

**The Trap:** The 10 percent figure applies when the issuer does NOT satisfy the profitability criteria. The 50 percent relates to QIB allocation in eligible issuer book-built offers, and for fixed price issues. Students must distinguish between eligible and non-eligible issuer allocation patterns.

**Cross-Exam Context:** IPO allocation norms are heavily tested in NISM XII and NISM XVI (Merchant Banking). The category-wise allocation is a favorite examination topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Retail investors benefit from the mandatory 35 percent reservation. In oversubscribed IPOs, the retail category allotment is done separately, meaning retail subscription levels may differ significantly from institutional categories.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>