<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Processing of Mutual Fund Transactions_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Harish is an active mutual fund investor with folios across multiple schemes of ABC Mutual Fund. On a particular Wednesday (a working day with no holidays that week), the following events occur:

Transaction 1: At 1:30 PM, Harish submits a purchase application for Rs.3,00,000 in ABC Equity Growth Fund with an RTGS payment that is credited to the scheme's account by 2:00 PM. The scheme's current NAV is Rs.125.

Transaction 2: At 3:30 PM (after the 3:00 PM cutoff), he submits another purchase application for Rs.2,00,000 in ABC Liquid Fund through online mode with instant payment.

Transaction 3: On the same day at 2:00 PM, his monthly SIP of Rs.10,000 in ABC Balanced Advantage Fund is auto-triggered by the RTA. The mandate debit is successful.

Transaction 4: He submits a switch request at 2:30 PM to move Rs.1,00,000 from ABC Overnight Fund to ABC Mid Cap Fund.

Transaction 5: His standing STP instruction triggers a transfer of Rs.25,000 from ABC Liquid Fund to ABC Small Cap Fund.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> At which NAV will Transaction 1 (equity fund purchase at 1:30 PM with RTGS credited by 2:00 PM) be processed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Thursday's NAV, since RTGS payments require T+1 settlement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Wednesday's NAV only if the cheque clears the same day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The NAV prevailing at 1:30 PM when the application was submitted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Wednesday's NAV, since both application and funds were received before the 3:00 PM cutoff]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For equity scheme purchases of Rs.2 lakh and above, the cutoff is 3:00 PM. Since Harish submitted his application at 1:30 PM (before cutoff) and the RTGS payment was credited by 2:00 PM (funds realized before cutoff), both conditions for same-day NAV are met. Wednesday's closing NAV of Rs.125 applies.
**The Trap:** RTGS provides real-time settlement, so there's no T+1 delay. The NAV is the day's closing NAV, not the NAV at the time of application — mutual funds compute NAV once at end of day.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A extensively covers NAV cutoff rules; the dual condition of application receipt + funds realization is a critical concept.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** RTGS is ideal for large purchases — same-day fund realization ensures same-day NAV. For amounts above Rs.2 lakh in equity/balanced schemes, ensure both the application and payment reach before 3:00 PM.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
