<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Processing of Mutual Fund Transactions_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Harish is an active mutual fund investor with folios across multiple schemes of ABC Mutual Fund. On a particular Wednesday (a working day with no holidays that week), the following events occur:

Transaction 1: At 1:30 PM, Harish submits a purchase application for Rs.3,00,000 in ABC Equity Growth Fund with an RTGS payment that is credited to the scheme's account by 2:00 PM. The scheme's current NAV is Rs.125.

Transaction 2: At 3:30 PM (after the 3:00 PM cutoff), he submits another purchase application for Rs.2,00,000 in ABC Liquid Fund through online mode with instant payment.

Transaction 3: On the same day at 2:00 PM, his monthly SIP of Rs.10,000 in ABC Balanced Advantage Fund is auto-triggered by the RTA. The mandate debit is successful.

Transaction 4: He submits a switch request at 2:30 PM to move Rs.1,00,000 from ABC Overnight Fund to ABC Mid Cap Fund.

Transaction 5: His standing STP instruction triggers a transfer of Rs.25,000 from ABC Liquid Fund to ABC Small Cap Fund.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> At which NAV will Transaction 2 (liquid fund purchase at 3:30 PM after cutoff) be processed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Thursday's NAV, since the application was submitted after the cutoff time]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Wednesday's NAV, since liquid funds have a different cutoff]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Wednesday's NAV, since payment was made instantly]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Friday's NAV, since liquid fund purchases have a T+2 NAV rule]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For liquid fund purchases, the cutoff time is 1:30 PM (for amounts up to Rs.2 lakh) or 3:00 PM. Since Harish submitted at 3:30 PM — after the cutoff — the application is treated as received on the next business day (Thursday). Thursday's NAV will apply, despite the instant payment.
**The Trap:** Instant payment doesn't override the cutoff time rule. Both conditions (application before cutoff AND funds realization) must be met for same-day NAV. Missing even one condition pushes NAV applicability to the next business day.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A tests cutoff time rules for different scheme categories; liquid funds have stricter cutoffs due to their same-day/next-day redemption feature.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Liquid fund cutoff times are earlier than equity funds for large amounts. If a client needs to park large sums in liquid funds, ensure the application reaches well before the cutoff — even 30 minutes of delay can cost a day's return.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
