<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ankit Sharma is a 28-year-old single software engineer working at an IT company in Bengaluru. His CTC is Rs. 15,00,000 per annum with a monthly take-home pay of Rs. 95,000. His monthly expenses are Rs. 45,000, leaving him with monthly savings of Rs. 50,000. He has no outstanding loans. Ankit has the following financial goals: (1) Build an emergency fund covering 6 months of expenses (immediate priority), (2) Accumulate Rs. 15 lakh for a house down payment in 3 years, (3) Save Rs. 10 lakh for marriage expenses in 5 years, and (4) Build a retirement corpus (he plans to retire at 60, giving him a 32-year horizon). His risk profile has been assessed as Moderately Aggressive. Currently, Ankit has Rs. 2 lakh lying in a savings account as his only investment. His investment adviser is helping him compare various products for each goal.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Ankit's adviser recommends an index fund over an actively managed equity fund for his core long-term equity allocation. Which reasoning BEST supports this recommendation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Index funds guarantee higher returns than active funds over any time period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Index funds are not subject to market risk unlike active equity funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Index funds allow the fund manager to generate alpha by picking the best stocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Index funds replicate the benchmark at a significantly lower cost, and over long periods most active funds struggle to consistently beat the benchmark after fees]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Index funds replicate a benchmark index at a much lower cost (lower expense ratio) compared to actively managed funds. Research consistently shows that over long time periods, the majority of active fund managers fail to beat their benchmark after accounting for higher fees. For a core long-term allocation with a 32-year horizon, the cost savings compound significantly.
**The Trap:** Index funds do NOT guarantee higher returns -- they deliver benchmark returns minus tracking error and costs. They are fully subject to market risk just like active equity funds. Index funds specifically do NOT pick stocks; they replicate the index -- generating alpha is the active manager's job.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A extensively covers active vs passive fund management; NISM Series X-A covers the cost impact of different investment products on long-term returns.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Ankit's 32-year horizon, even a 0.5% annual cost difference between an index fund (0.1-0.2% TER) and an active fund (0.7-1.5% TER) can mean a 15-20% difference in final corpus due to compounding. Use a "core and satellite" approach: index fund as the core, with selective active funds as satellites.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
