<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Padma Krishnamurthy is a 62-year-old retired government servant living in Chennai. She receives a monthly pension of Rs. 40,000. Her retirement corpus is Rs. 50 lakh, accumulated from gratuity, provident fund, and leave encashment. Her monthly expenses are Rs. 55,000, creating a shortfall of Rs. 15,000 per month that must be bridged from her corpus. Padma owns her house outright with no loan outstanding. She has health insurance coverage through the Central Government Health Scheme (CGHS). Her two adult children are well-settled and financially independent. Padma's risk profile has been assessed as Conservative. Her financial goals are: (1) Bridge the monthly income gap of Rs. 15,000 sustainably, (2) Preserve her capital from inflation erosion over a potentially 25-year retirement, and (3) Leave some inheritance for her children. Her investment adviser is evaluating various product options for her Rs. 50 lakh corpus.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Padma wants to allocate a small portion to gold for diversification. Comparing Sovereign Gold Bonds and physical gold, which statement is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Physical gold is better because it can be easily sold at any jeweller with no lock-in period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sovereign Gold Bonds and physical gold have identical tax treatment and costs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Physical gold provides 2.5% annual interest in addition to price appreciation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sovereign Gold Bonds are superior for Padma: no GST on purchase, no storage cost, 2.5% semi-annual interest, no purity concerns, and capital gains are tax-free if redeemed with RBI at maturity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Sovereign Gold Bonds offer multiple advantages over physical gold: no GST on purchase (physical gold attracts 3% GST), no storage or locker costs, no purity concerns, 2.5% per annum interest paid semi-annually (physical gold earns zero income), and capital gains are completely tax-free if held to maturity and redeemed with RBI. The 5-year lock-in (within 8-year maturity) is manageable for Padma's diversification goal.
**The Trap:** Physical gold has significant friction costs -- GST, making charges, storage, purity risk -- and selling at a jeweller involves substantial value loss due to melting charges. The 2.5% interest is unique to SGBs, not physical gold. The two products have very different tax treatments; they are not identical.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers gold ETFs and funds; NISM Series X-A covers gold as an asset class including SGBs.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For conservative retirees like Padma, SGBs serve a dual purpose: gold price-linked diversification PLUS 2.5% semi-annual interest that can supplement income. A Rs. 5 lakh SGB allocation would yield Rs. 12,500 per year (Rs. 6,250 every 6 months) as interest income, contributing to her income needs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
