<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ankit Sharma is a 28-year-old single software engineer working at an IT company in Bengaluru. His CTC is Rs. 15,00,000 per annum with a monthly take-home pay of Rs. 95,000. His monthly expenses are Rs. 45,000, leaving him with monthly savings of Rs. 50,000. He has no outstanding loans. Ankit has the following financial goals: (1) Build an emergency fund covering 6 months of expenses (immediate priority), (2) Accumulate Rs. 15 lakh for a house down payment in 3 years, (3) Save Rs. 10 lakh for marriage expenses in 5 years, and (4) Build a retirement corpus (he plans to retire at 60, giving him a 32-year horizon). His risk profile has been assessed as Moderately Aggressive. Currently, Ankit has Rs. 2 lakh lying in a savings account as his only investment. His investment adviser is helping him compare various products for each goal.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> For Ankit's house down payment goal of Rs. 15 lakh in 3 years, which product comparison is MOST relevant?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS vs NPS: Both offer tax benefits and ELSS has a matching 3-year lock-in]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Short-duration debt fund vs bank FD vs conservative hybrid fund: The 3-year horizon needs capital protection with moderate growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual fund vs PMS: His moderately aggressive profile supports pure equity for 3 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PPF vs Sovereign Gold Bond: Both offer sovereign safety suitable for a critical goal]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A 3-year goal for a non-negotiable expense like a house down payment requires capital protection with moderate growth. Short-duration debt funds, bank FDs, and conservative hybrid funds are the appropriate product set to compare. The goal is too important and the horizon too short for pure equity, which could lose 20-30% in a bad year.
**The Trap:** While ELSS does have a 3-year lock-in that matches the timeline, it invests exclusively in equity with high risk -- unsuitable for a critical goal with a fixed timeline. PMS requires Rs. 50 lakhs minimum and is inappropriate for a Rs. 15 lakh goal. PPF has a 15-year lock-in and SGBs have a 5-year lock-in -- both exceed the 3-year horizon.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers goal-based product selection; NISM Series X-A covers suitability assessment linking time horizon to product choice.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For critical goals within 3-5 years, the golden rule is "protect first, grow second." A conservative hybrid fund (65-75% debt, 25-35% equity) can offer slightly better returns than a pure FD while keeping volatility manageable for a 3-year horizon.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
