<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Padma Krishnamurthy is a 62-year-old retired government servant living in Chennai. She receives a monthly pension of Rs. 40,000. Her retirement corpus is Rs. 50 lakh, accumulated from gratuity, provident fund, and leave encashment. Her monthly expenses are Rs. 55,000, creating a shortfall of Rs. 15,000 per month that must be bridged from her corpus. Padma owns her house outright with no loan outstanding. She has health insurance coverage through the Central Government Health Scheme (CGHS). Her two adult children are well-settled and financially independent. Padma's risk profile has been assessed as Conservative. Her financial goals are: (1) Bridge the monthly income gap of Rs. 15,000 sustainably, (2) Preserve her capital from inflation erosion over a potentially 25-year retirement, and (3) Leave some inheritance for her children. Her investment adviser is evaluating various product options for her Rs. 50 lakh corpus.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> What is the MOST suitable product allocation for Padma's Rs. 50 lakh corpus across her three goals?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50 lakh entirely in SCSS for maximum safety and highest interest income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 30 lakh in SCSS (max limit), Rs. 10 lakh in bank FD ladder and debt MF SWP for income and liquidity, Rs. 5 lakh in conservative hybrid fund for inflation protection, Rs. 5 lakh in Sovereign Gold Bonds for diversification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 25 lakh in equity mutual funds, Rs. 15 lakh in SCSS, Rs. 10 lakh in gold ETF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50 lakh in a single bank FD at the highest available rate for simplicity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The optimal allocation balances Padma's three goals: (1) Income: SCSS (Rs. 30 lakh at max limit) provides the highest safe interest income with quarterly payouts; bank FD ladder and debt MF SWP (Rs. 10 lakh) add liquidity and tax efficiency for income. (2) Inflation protection: Conservative hybrid fund (Rs. 5 lakh) adds modest equity exposure (25-35%) for long-term capital appreciation without excessive risk. (3) Diversification and inheritance: SGBs (Rs. 5 lakh) provide gold-linked returns plus 2.5% interest.
**The Trap:** SCSS has a Rs. 30 lakh maximum limit, so Rs. 50 lakh entirely in SCSS is not possible. Putting 50% (Rs. 25 lakh) in equity is far too aggressive for a conservative retiree who needs predictable income. A single bank FD sacrifices diversification benefits and may offer lower returns than SCSS.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers portfolio construction for retirees; NISM Series V-A covers product suitability across risk profiles.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The "bucket strategy" works well for retirees: Bucket 1 (immediate income, 1-3 years) in SCSS and FDs, Bucket 2 (medium-term, 3-7 years) in debt MFs and conservative hybrid, Bucket 3 (long-term/inheritance) in SGBs and a small equity allocation. This ensures income is never at risk while the long-term buckets beat inflation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
