<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly distinguishes between company deposits and company debentures?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Company deposits are secured while company debentures are unsecured]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both are identically structured with no meaningful difference in security]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Company deposits are unsecured with slightly higher returns, while company debentures are normally secured with slightly lower returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Company debentures are unsecured with higher returns than company deposits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Company deposits are unsecured obligations of the company and offer slightly higher returns to compensate for this additional risk. Company debentures are normally secured against the company's assets, providing a layer of protection to the investor, and consequently offer slightly lower returns than unsecured deposits.
**The Trap:** The first option reverses the security status -- a common error. Candidates may assume "deposits" sound safer (and therefore secured) because the word is associated with bank deposits, which have deposit insurance. But company deposits are fundamentally different from bank deposits.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers debt instruments; NISM Series XII covers debentures and fixed-income securities in capital markets.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always help clients distinguish between bank FDs (insured up to Rs. 5 lakh by DICGC) and company deposits (unsecured, no insurance). Many retail investors chase slightly higher company deposit rates without understanding they are taking unsecured credit risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
