<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ankit Sharma is a 28-year-old single software engineer working at an IT company in Bengaluru. His CTC is Rs. 15,00,000 per annum with a monthly take-home pay of Rs. 95,000. His monthly expenses are Rs. 45,000, leaving him with monthly savings of Rs. 50,000. He has no outstanding loans. Ankit has the following financial goals: (1) Build an emergency fund covering 6 months of expenses (immediate priority), (2) Accumulate Rs. 15 lakh for a house down payment in 3 years, (3) Save Rs. 10 lakh for marriage expenses in 5 years, and (4) Build a retirement corpus (he plans to retire at 60, giving him a 32-year horizon). His risk profile has been assessed as Moderately Aggressive. Currently, Ankit has Rs. 2 lakh lying in a savings account as his only investment. His investment adviser is helping him compare various products for each goal.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Comparing ELSS and NPS for Ankit's tax-saving needs under Section 80C, which analysis is CORRECT given his age and goals?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NPS is better because it offers an additional Rs. 50,000 deduction under Section 80CCD(1B) and guaranteed returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS is inferior because its 3-year lock-in is too short to build meaningful wealth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ELSS offers shorter lock-in (3 years vs till 60) and full equity exposure, but NPS offers additional 80CCD(1B) deduction and forces retirement discipline; both are suitable but serve different purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both are identical in features since they both invest in equity and offer 80C benefits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For a 28-year-old like Ankit, both ELSS and NPS serve different purposes. ELSS has a 3-year lock-in (shortest among 80C instruments), invests exclusively in equity, and offers flexibility after lock-in. NPS is locked till 60 (32 years for Ankit), allows max 75% in equity, but offers an additional Rs. 50,000 deduction under 80CCD(1B) and enforces retirement savings discipline. The 60% tax-free lump sum at retirement makes NPS attractive for the long term.
**The Trap:** NPS does NOT offer guaranteed returns -- it is market-linked. Saying ELSS's 3-year lock-in is "too short" is misleading; shorter lock-in is generally an advantage as it provides flexibility. The two products are not identical since NPS caps equity at 75% and has the mandatory annuity requirement.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers 80C instrument comparison; NISM Series V-A covers ELSS taxation and features.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For young clients like Ankit, recommend BOTH: ELSS for the flexibility to redeploy after 3 years (useful for medium-term goals) and NPS for the extra 80CCD(1B) tax benefit plus forced retirement savings. The Rs. 50,000 additional NPS deduction saves Rs. 15,600 annually for someone in the 30% bracket (plus cess).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
