<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor compares real estate investment with REITs. Which of the following is an advantage of REITs over direct real estate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs offer higher rental yields than direct property ownership]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs have no market risk as they invest in physical properties]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[REITs are listed on exchanges, offer better liquidity, and provide diversification across multiple commercial properties]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[REITs allow the investor to choose which specific properties to invest in]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** REITs are listed on stock exchanges, providing significantly better liquidity than direct real estate which is lumpy and illiquid. REITs also spread investment across multiple commercial properties, reducing concentration risk inherent in owning a single property. They are professionally managed and offer rental income plus potential capital appreciation.
**The Trap:** REITs do have market risk -- their unit prices fluctuate on the exchange based on market sentiment, interest rates, and property valuations. Investors cannot choose specific properties within a REIT; that decision lies with the REIT manager.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers REIT basics; NISM Series X-A covers real estate as an asset class; NISM Series XII covers listed securities.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients wanting real estate exposure without the Rs. 50 lakh to Rs. 1 crore needed for direct commercial property, REITs offer an accessible entry point with professional management and the ability to exit on the exchange -- but remind them that REIT unit prices can be volatile.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
