<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ankit Sharma is a 28-year-old single software engineer working at an IT company in Bengaluru. His CTC is Rs. 15,00,000 per annum with a monthly take-home pay of Rs. 95,000. His monthly expenses are Rs. 45,000, leaving him with monthly savings of Rs. 50,000. He has no outstanding loans. Ankit has the following financial goals: (1) Build an emergency fund covering 6 months of expenses (immediate priority), (2) Accumulate Rs. 15 lakh for a house down payment in 3 years, (3) Save Rs. 10 lakh for marriage expenses in 5 years, and (4) Build a retirement corpus (he plans to retire at 60, giving him a 32-year horizon). His risk profile has been assessed as Moderately Aggressive. Currently, Ankit has Rs. 2 lakh lying in a savings account as his only investment. His investment adviser is helping him compare various products for each goal.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> For Ankit's retirement goal with a 32-year horizon, what is the OPTIMAL product mix?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in PPF for guaranteed, tax-free returns over the long term]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in NPS Tier 1 with maximum equity allocation to leverage the long horizon]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A combination of NPS Tier 1 (for additional tax benefit and retirement discipline), equity mutual funds (for flexibility and full equity exposure), and PPF (for risk-free guaranteed component)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in ELSS since it invests exclusively in equity and offers tax benefits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A 32-year retirement horizon for a moderately aggressive investor calls for a diversified product mix. NPS Tier 1 provides the extra 80CCD(1B) tax deduction and forces retirement discipline. Equity mutual funds offer full equity exposure with flexibility to rebalance and redeem without waiting till 60. PPF adds a risk-free, EEE component that acts as the debt anchor of the retirement portfolio.
**The Trap:** 100% in any single product is sub-optimal. PPF alone would deliver low real returns over 32 years. NPS alone caps equity at 75% and locks 40% into a mandatory annuity. ELSS alone provides no debt diversification and the 3-year lock-in means Ankit would need to constantly reinvest after each lock-in period.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A covers retirement planning product selection; NISM Series V-A tests portfolio construction principles applicable to long-term goals.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For young clients with 30+ year horizons, the ideal split is often: NPS (for tax alpha and forced savings), diversified equity MFs via SIP (for growth and flexibility), and PPF (for the guaranteed debt component). Start equity-heavy (70-80%) and gradually shift to debt as retirement approaches.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
