<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ankit Sharma is a 28-year-old single software engineer working at an IT company in Bengaluru. His CTC is Rs. 15,00,000 per annum with a monthly take-home pay of Rs. 95,000. His monthly expenses are Rs. 45,000, leaving him with monthly savings of Rs. 50,000. He has no outstanding loans. Ankit has the following financial goals: (1) Build an emergency fund covering 6 months of expenses (immediate priority), (2) Accumulate Rs. 15 lakh for a house down payment in 3 years, (3) Save Rs. 10 lakh for marriage expenses in 5 years, and (4) Build a retirement corpus (he plans to retire at 60, giving him a 32-year horizon). His risk profile has been assessed as Moderately Aggressive. Currently, Ankit has Rs. 2 lakh lying in a savings account as his only investment. His investment adviser is helping him compare various products for each goal.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> For Ankit's emergency fund goal of 6 months' expenses (Rs. 2,70,000), which product is MOST suitable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS mutual fund for tax savings along with emergency coverage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Public Provident Fund for guaranteed returns and safety]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A combination of savings account and liquid/ultra-short duration debt fund for instant to next-day liquidity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tax-saving bank fixed deposit for assured returns]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An emergency fund must prioritize liquidity and capital preservation above all else. A combination of savings account (for instant access) and liquid/ultra-short duration fund (for next-day redemption with slightly better returns) is ideal. Ankit already has Rs. 2 lakh in savings, so he only needs to add Rs. 70,000 more to reach his 6-month target of Rs. 2,70,000.
**The Trap:** ELSS has a 3-year lock-in making it completely unsuitable for emergencies. PPF has a 15-year lock-in with partial withdrawal only after 5 years. Tax-saving FDs have a 5-year lock-in. None of these provide the instant liquidity that an emergency fund demands.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers liquid fund features; NISM Series X-A covers emergency fund planning as part of financial planning basics.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always build the emergency fund FIRST before allocating to any other goal. Ankit's existing Rs. 2 lakh in savings account is a good start -- he just needs to top up Rs. 70,000 in a liquid fund. Only after this safety net is in place should he start investing for other goals.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
