<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which statement BEST describes the difference between an ETF and an index fund in the Indian context?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ETFs are purchased from the AMC at end-of-day NAV while index funds are traded on exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Index funds have lower management costs than ETFs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ETFs are traded on exchanges at real-time prices and require a demat account, while index funds are bought from the AMC at end-of-day NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ETFs and index funds are identical products with no meaningful differences]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ETFs trade on stock exchanges at real-time market prices and require a demat account plus brokerage charges. Index funds are purchased directly from the AMC at end-of-day NAV with no need for a demat account. Index funds have marginally higher management costs than ETFs, but ETFs suffer from poor liquidity in India except for the top 2 ETFs by volume.
**The Trap:** The first option reverses the characteristics of ETFs and index funds -- a classic trap for candidates who get confused between the two. Index funds actually have marginally higher (not lower) management costs than ETFs.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A extensively covers ETFs and index funds; NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) covers exchange-traded instruments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In India, poor ETF liquidity means most retail investors are better served by index funds despite the marginally higher cost. An illiquid ETF can trade at a significant premium or discount to NAV, defeating the purpose of low-cost passive investing.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
