<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Padma Krishnamurthy is a 62-year-old retired government servant living in Chennai. She receives a monthly pension of Rs. 40,000. Her retirement corpus is Rs. 50 lakh, accumulated from gratuity, provident fund, and leave encashment. Her monthly expenses are Rs. 55,000, creating a shortfall of Rs. 15,000 per month that must be bridged from her corpus. Padma owns her house outright with no loan outstanding. She has health insurance coverage through the Central Government Health Scheme (CGHS). Her two adult children are well-settled and financially independent. Padma's risk profile has been assessed as Conservative. Her financial goals are: (1) Bridge the monthly income gap of Rs. 15,000 sustainably, (2) Preserve her capital from inflation erosion over a potentially 25-year retirement, and (3) Leave some inheritance for her children. Her investment adviser is evaluating various product options for her Rs. 50 lakh corpus.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Padma's son suggests she invest a significant portion in equity mutual funds for higher returns. Why is this advice INAPPROPRIATE for her monthly income need?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual funds are not available to senior citizens above age 60]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Equity is volatile and unsuitable for generating predictable monthly income; a market downturn could force Padma to sell units at a loss to meet her Rs. 15,000 monthly shortfall, permanently depleting her corpus]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual funds do not allow Systematic Withdrawal Plans for senior citizens]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual funds charge higher exit loads for investors above 60 years of age]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Padma needs Rs. 15,000 every month without fail to meet her living expenses. Equity markets can fall 20-40% in a bear market, and if Padma is forced to redeem equity fund units during a downturn to meet expenses, she sells at depressed prices. This "sequence of returns risk" permanently depletes the corpus because units sold at low NAVs cannot participate in the subsequent recovery. Her conservative risk profile further confirms equity is unsuitable for income generation.
**The Trap:** Equity mutual funds ARE available to senior citizens -- there is no age restriction. SWP is available to all investors regardless of age. Exit loads are standard across all age groups. These are factually incorrect statements designed to trap candidates who may not know the actual rules.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers suitability and risk profiling; NISM Series X-A covers retirement income planning and sequence of returns risk.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The "sequence of returns risk" is the biggest danger for retirees drawing income. Even if equity delivers 12% CAGR over 20 years, a 30% crash in Year 1 combined with forced withdrawals can destroy the portfolio. Keep the income-generating portion in debt; only the surplus (inheritance portion) should have modest equity exposure.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
