<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Product Comparison_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Padma Krishnamurthy is a 62-year-old retired government servant living in Chennai. She receives a monthly pension of Rs. 40,000. Her retirement corpus is Rs. 50 lakh, accumulated from gratuity, provident fund, and leave encashment. Her monthly expenses are Rs. 55,000, creating a shortfall of Rs. 15,000 per month that must be bridged from her corpus. Padma owns her house outright with no loan outstanding. She has health insurance coverage through the Central Government Health Scheme (CGHS). Her two adult children are well-settled and financially independent. Padma's risk profile has been assessed as Conservative. Her financial goals are: (1) Bridge the monthly income gap of Rs. 15,000 sustainably, (2) Preserve her capital from inflation erosion over a potentially 25-year retirement, and (3) Leave some inheritance for her children. Her investment adviser is evaluating various product options for her Rs. 50 lakh corpus.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Comparing the tax efficiency of SCSS interest, bank FD interest, and debt mutual fund SWP for Padma, which statement is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three are taxed identically at Padma's income tax slab rate with no differences]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SCSS and bank FD interest are fully taxable as income from other sources at slab rate; debt MF SWP withdrawals are treated as capital gains where only the gain portion is taxed, making SWP more tax-efficient for the same pre-tax return]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCSS interest is tax-free for senior citizens up to Rs. 50,000 under Section 80TTB, making it completely exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Debt mutual fund gains are always taxed at 20% with indexation regardless of the holding period]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCSS and bank FD interest are fully taxable as income from other sources at the investor's slab rate. In a debt MF SWP, each withdrawal consists of principal return plus capital gain -- only the gain portion is taxable, making the effective tax outgo lower for the same gross payout. Additionally, senior citizens get a Section 80TTB deduction of up to Rs. 50,000 on interest income from deposits (including SCSS), but this is a deduction, not a full exemption -- income above Rs. 50,000 is still taxable.
**The Trap:** Section 80TTB provides a Rs. 50,000 deduction on deposit interest for senior citizens, but it does NOT make SCSS interest "completely exempt." If Padma earns Rs. 2.4 lakh in SCSS interest, only Rs. 50,000 is deductible; the remaining Rs. 1.9 lakh is taxable. The 20% with indexation rule for debt funds was changed by Finance Act 2023, and gains are now taxed at slab rate -- but the SWP structure still offers the advantage of taxing only the gain component of each withdrawal.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A covers mutual fund taxation; NISM Series X-A covers comparative taxation of investment products for different investor categories.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For retirees in lower tax brackets, the 80TTB deduction on SCSS/FD interest may suffice. But for retirees with higher total income (pension + interest), debt MF SWP becomes more tax-efficient because only the small capital gain portion of each withdrawal is taxed. Always compute the total tax impact across all income sources before recommending the product mix.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
