<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Priya is analyzing an upcoming IPO. She notes that the company is issuing new shares to raise capital, while the promoter is simultaneously selling a portion of existing holdings. Which combination correctly describes these two components?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both are fresh issues since shares are being sold to the public for the first time]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The new shares constitute a fresh issue increasing paid-up capital, while the promoter's sale is an Offer for Sale with proceeds going to the promoter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The new shares are an Offer for Sale and the promoter's sale is a fresh issue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both components are classified as Offer for Sale since the public is buying shares]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In an IPO, a fresh issue means the company issues new shares -- this increases paid-up capital and the proceeds go to the company. An Offer for Sale (OFS) means existing shareholders (like promoters) sell their shares -- no new capital is created, and proceeds go to the selling shareholder. Both can occur simultaneously in the same IPO.
**The Trap:** Candidates confuse OFS with fresh issue. The key distinction is: fresh issue = new shares, company gets money; OFS = existing shares change hands, seller gets money.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking) covers IPO structuring in detail; Series II-A tests RTA understanding of issue components.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When reviewing an IPO, always check the split between fresh issue and OFS. A heavy OFS component means the company itself isn't raising much capital -- the promoter is cashing out. This affects your assessment of the company's growth plans.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
