<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sarvottam Fintech Ltd. (SFL), an unlisted fintech company, plans to launch its IPO. The company's financials for the last three years show: net tangible assets of Rs.5 crore, Rs.4.2 crore, and Rs.3.8 crore; average operating profit of Rs.17 crore (positive each year); and net worth of Rs.2 crore each year. The IPO is structured as a book building issue with a price band of Rs.280-Rs.320 per share. The total issue size is 50 lakh shares, comprising 35 lakh fresh issue shares and 15 lakh shares as Offer for Sale by the promoter, Harish Mehta.

The issue receives the following subscription on closing day (T day): QIB category -- 1.5 crore shares bid (against 25 lakh shares reserved); NII category -- 60 lakh shares bid (against 7.5 lakh shares reserved); RII category -- 52.5 lakh shares bid (against 17.5 lakh shares reserved). The cut-off price is determined at Rs.310 per share. Pooja Sharma, a retail investor, applied for 200 shares at cut-off price through ASBA, with funds blocked in her SCSB account. Vikram Desai, the RTA officer, is coordinating the post-issue process.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> What is the oversubscription multiple for the NII (Non-Institutional Investor) category in SFL's IPO?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2 times]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[6 times]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[8 times]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[3 times]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NII bids received = 60 lakh shares. NII reserved = 7.5 lakh shares. Oversubscription = 60 lakh / 7.5 lakh = 8 times. This means for every 8 shares bid, only 1 share can be allotted in the NII category on a proportionate basis.
**The Trap:** Candidates may confuse the NII category numbers with QIB or RII. QIB oversubscription = 1.5 crore / 25 lakh = 6 times. RII oversubscription = 52.5 lakh / 17.5 lakh = 3 times. Each category has a different oversubscription ratio.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A covers allotment mechanics. The RTA prepares the basis of allotment separately for QIB, NII, and RII -- oversubscription directly determines the allotment ratio.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** NII at 8x is the most oversubscribed category here. NIIs (applying > Rs.2 lakh) face the toughest allotment odds. If your client is borderline, applying in the RII category (at 3x) gives better allotment probability -- provided the application is within Rs.2 lakh.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
