<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which statement about Qualified Institutional Placement (QIP) is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[QIP can be done by both listed and unlisted companies to raise funds from qualified institutional buyers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[QIP is a mechanism for listed issuers to raise funds from QIBs on a private placement basis, subject to SEBI ICDR conditions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[QIP requires the company to file a Draft Red Herring Prospectus with SEBI before issuance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[QIP shares have no lock-in period and can be freely traded from the date of allotment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** QIP is exclusively available to listed issuers who want to raise capital from Qualified Institutional Buyers on a private placement basis. It is governed by SEBI ICDR Regulations and has specific eligibility conditions. The Compliance Officer checks eligibility. No DRHP is needed since it is a private placement.
**The Trap:** QIP is NOT available to unlisted companies -- that's a key distinction. Also, while no DRHP is required, there are still compliance conditions. QIP allottees do have certain lock-in/trading restrictions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A covers QIP as a capital-raising method; Series IX covers it from the merchant banker's perspective.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** QIP is a faster route for listed companies to raise institutional capital without the lengthy public offer process. If a listed company you track announces a QIP, understand it signals institutional confidence in the company's prospects.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
