<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly differentiates a fixed price issue from a book building issue in the context of an IPO?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[In fixed price, the price is determined after collecting bids; in book building, the price is set upfront]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In fixed price, demand is known only at the end of the issue period; in book building, demand is visible during the bidding process]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fixed price issues are exclusively for institutional investors, while book building is open to all categories]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no difference -- both terms refer to the same pricing mechanism under SEBI ICDR Regulations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In a fixed price issue, the issuer sets the price upfront, and investors apply at that price -- demand is known only after the issue closes. In book building, a price band is offered, bids are collected, and the final price is discovered after bid closure. Demand is visible during the bidding window as bid quantities are disclosed.
**The Trap:** Reversing the two methods is a common error. Remember: fixed = price fixed, demand unknown until end; book building = price band, demand visible during process.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IX covers pricing mechanisms; Series II-A tests RTA understanding of how demand information flows differently under each method.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Book building provides real-time demand visibility which helps gauge market appetite. If the QIB portion is oversubscribed early, it signals strong institutional interest -- useful information for retail investor clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
