<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In a private placement, Deepak Industries allotted shares on March 15, 2025. Application money was received from all allottees on January 10, 2025. By what date must the allotment have been completed to comply with the Companies Act 2013?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 30 days of receiving application money, i.e., by February 9, 2025]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Within 60 days of receiving application money, i.e., by March 11, 2025]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 90 days of receiving application money, i.e., by April 10, 2025]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 120 days of receiving application money, i.e., by May 10, 2025]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 42 of Companies Act 2013, allotment in a private placement must be completed within 60 days of receiving application money. 60 days from January 10, 2025 = March 11, 2025. Since allotment was done on March 15, 2025, it EXCEEDS the 60-day window by 4 days, meaning the company must refund the application money within 15 days of the 60-day expiry with 12% per annum interest.
**The Trap:** The question asks by what date allotment MUST be completed, not whether the actual allotment was compliant. The correct deadline is March 11, 2025 (60 days from Jan 10). The actual allotment on March 15 violates this deadline -- but the answer to the question is March 11.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 8.1 covers private placement timelines. The 60-day rule and the 12% interest penalty are frequently tested.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If allotment is delayed beyond 60 days, the company faces a costly 12% interest penalty on refunds. As an RTA, flag delays early. For investors, this provision is a protection -- if your money is stuck beyond 60 days, you are entitled to interest.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
