<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Arjun is confused about the difference between a preferential allotment and a private placement. Which explanation is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A preferential allotment is a private placement made by a listed company, with additional conditions such as promoter lock-in of 18 months from trading approval and others locked in for 6 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A private placement is restricted to listed companies, while preferential allotment is for unlisted companies only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both terms are identical and used interchangeably under the Companies Act 2013]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A preferential allotment has no lock-in requirement, while a private placement has a mandatory 3-year lock-in]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Private placement under Section 42 of Companies Act 2013 is the broader concept -- any company (listed or unlisted) can do it with max 50 allottees per FY (excluding QIBs and employees). When a listed company does a private placement, it is specifically called a preferential allotment, and it carries additional conditions: promoter lock-in of 18 months from trading approval and others locked in for 6 months.
**The Trap:** The terms are NOT identical. Preferential allotment is a subset of private placement, specific to listed companies, with stricter conditions. Also, the lock-in periods are specific (18/6 months), not a blanket 3 years.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 8 covers both concepts. The distinction is important for RTAs processing allotment and applying lock-in instructions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a listed company you track does a preferential allotment, note who the allottees are and their lock-in periods. Heavy preferential allotment to promoters may signal consolidation of control; to strategic investors, it may signal confidence.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
