<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Apex Corporation has post-issue paid-up capital of Rs.50 crore. The promoters hold Rs.12 crore worth of shares post-issue. To meet the minimum promoter contribution requirement, how much shortfall exists and what is the maximum any single AIF can contribute?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Shortfall of Rs.2 crore; maximum AIF contribution of Rs.5 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No shortfall; promoters already exceed the 20% requirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Shortfall of Rs.2 crore; maximum AIF contribution of Rs.1 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Shortfall of Rs.3 crore; maximum AIF contribution of Rs.5 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Minimum promoter contribution = 20% of Rs.50 crore = Rs.10 crore. Promoters hold Rs.12 crore, which exceeds the Rs.10 crore requirement. There is NO shortfall. The question about AIF contribution is therefore moot -- no shortfall means no need for shortfall contributors. Each shortfall contributor can contribute maximum 10% of post-issue capital (Rs.5 crore here), but this is irrelevant since there is no shortfall.
**The Trap:** This is a trick question. Candidates may rush to calculate a shortfall without first checking whether one exists. Rs.12 crore is MORE than Rs.10 crore (20% of Rs.50 crore). Always verify the basic condition before jumping to shortfall calculations.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 7 covers promoter contribution and shortfall mechanisms. RTAs must verify these calculations during pre-issue processing.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Promoters holding more than the minimum (24% vs 20% here) is generally a positive signal -- it shows stronger promoter commitment. Track the exact promoter contribution percentage as a quality indicator.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
