<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Dhanvantari Pharma Ltd. (DPL), a listed pharmaceutical company, has 4 crore outstanding equity shares with a face value of Rs.10 each, trading at Rs.250 per share. The company has free reserves of Rs.600 crore and paid-up capital of Rs.40 crore. On February 1, 2026, the Board of Directors approves a buyback of 20 lakh shares at Rs.300 per share through the tender offer method, for a total buyback consideration of Rs.60 crore. The record date is set as March 1, 2026.

Anita Kulkarni, a retail investor, holds 500 shares with a market value of Rs.1.25 lakh on the record date. Suresh Patil holds 1,200 shares with a market value of Rs.3 lakh on the record date. Geeta Nair holds 5,000 shares with a market value of Rs.12.5 lakh on the record date. The total outstanding shares eligible for buyback are 4 crore. Rajesh Kumar, the RTA officer at the company's registrar, is responsible for processing the buyback. The buyback opens on March 10, 2026 and closes on March 24, 2026.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Anita tenders all 500 shares in the buyback. If her entitlement ratio is calculated based on her proportion of total shares and assuming full acceptance in the small shareholder category, by when must DPL make payment to Anita after her shares are accepted?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 10 working days of acceptance of shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Within 5 working days of acceptance of shares]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 15 calendar days of the buyback closing date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 30 days of the Board resolution approving the buyback]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Buy-back) Regulations 2018, payment for accepted shares in a tender offer must be made within 5 working days of acceptance. At Rs.300 per share, if all 500 of Anita's shares are accepted, she receives Rs.1,50,000 within 5 working days. The shares accepted are extinguished (cancelled).
**The Trap:** The timeline is 5 working days from acceptance, not from closing date or Board resolution. Working days exclude weekends and market holidays. Candidates who confuse the payment timeline with other regulatory timelines (like the 60-day private placement allotment window) will err.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 7.7 specifies the 5-working-day payment timeline. RTAs must ensure fund transfer within this window.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The 5-working-day payment guarantee makes tender offers attractive for shareholders. Advise clients to have their demat and bank details updated before tendering -- mismatched details can delay payment. Also, accepted shares are extinguished, reducing the company's outstanding capital.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
