<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Manoj, an RTA officer, discovers that three SCSBs have caused rejection of Retail Individual Investor bids due to technical errors on the SCSBs' end. What action should Manoj take under SEBI's framework?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ignore the rejections as the SCSBs are independent entities and the RTA has no jurisdiction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Invoke SEBI's compensation policy for SCSBs causing RII rejection and ensure affected investors are compensated]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ask the rejected investors to re-apply in the next IPO]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Request the issuer company to increase the issue size to accommodate the rejected bids]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI has a specific compensation policy where SCSBs that cause rejection of RII bids due to their own errors must compensate affected investors. The RTA, being the nodal agency for ASBA complaints, plays a key role in identifying such cases and invoking this policy. This is an investor protection measure.
**The Trap:** The RTA is NOT powerless here. As the nodal agency for ASBA complaints, the RTA has a defined role. Also, asking investors to reapply in the next IPO is not a remedy -- it denies them the specific opportunity they applied for.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 10 establishes the RTA as the nodal agency for ASBA complaints. The compensation policy is a critical operational knowledge area.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Document every SCSB-caused rejection meticulously. The compensation policy requires evidence that the rejection was due to SCSB error, not investor error. Clear documentation by the RTA strengthens the investor's case.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
