<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rajan wants to understand the role of a Self-Certified Syndicate Bank (SCSB) in the ASBA process. Which statement accurately describes the SCSB's function?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The SCSB underwrites the IPO and guarantees allotment to the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The SCSB blocks the application amount in the investor's bank account, uploads bid details, and debits or unblocks funds based on allotment instructions from the RTA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The SCSB directly allots shares to the investor and credits the demat account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The SCSB acts as the lead manager and decides the issue price in book building]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under ASBA (Application Supported by Blocked Amount), the SCSB blocks the application money in the investor's account without withdrawing it. After basis of allotment is finalized, the RTA instructs the controlling branch of the SCSB to either debit the allotment amount or unblock the full amount for non-allottees.
**The Trap:** SCSBs do not underwrite, allot shares, or decide prices. Their role is strictly limited to blocking/unblocking/debiting funds. Share allotment and demat credit are handled by the RTA and depository respectively.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A specifically tests the ASBA mechanism and the RTA's coordination with SCSBs. The RTA is also the nodal agency for ASBA complaints.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Ensure your clients apply through a SEBI-registered SCSB with a designated branch. If the SCSB causes rejection of a retail individual investor's bid due to its own error, SEBI's compensation policy provides relief.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
