<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Dhanvantari Pharma Ltd. (DPL), a listed pharmaceutical company, has 4 crore outstanding equity shares with a face value of Rs.10 each, trading at Rs.250 per share. The company has free reserves of Rs.600 crore and paid-up capital of Rs.40 crore. On February 1, 2026, the Board of Directors approves a buyback of 20 lakh shares at Rs.300 per share through the tender offer method, for a total buyback consideration of Rs.60 crore. The record date is set as March 1, 2026.

Anita Kulkarni, a retail investor, holds 500 shares with a market value of Rs.1.25 lakh on the record date. Suresh Patil holds 1,200 shares with a market value of Rs.3 lakh on the record date. Geeta Nair holds 5,000 shares with a market value of Rs.12.5 lakh on the record date. The total outstanding shares eligible for buyback are 4 crore. Rajesh Kumar, the RTA officer at the company's registrar, is responsible for processing the buyback. The buyback opens on March 10, 2026 and closes on March 24, 2026.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> What is the minimum escrow deposit DPL must make for this Rs.60 crore buyback?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.6 crore (10% of buyback consideration)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs.15 crore (25% of buyback consideration)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.25 crore (25% of first Rs.100 crore)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs.3 crore (5% of buyback consideration)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Escrow deposit: for buyback consideration up to Rs.100 crore, the escrow is 25%. Since DPL's buyback is Rs.60 crore (entirely within the Rs.100 crore first slab), the escrow = 25% of Rs.60 crore = Rs.15 crore. The second slab (10% on amount exceeding Rs.100 crore) does not apply here.
**The Trap:** Rs.25 crore would be 25% of Rs.100 crore, which applies only if the buyback was at least Rs.100 crore. At Rs.60 crore, the entire amount falls within the first slab. Candidates who mechanically apply Rs.25 crore as a flat figure will err.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 7.7 specifies the slab-based escrow calculation. The escrow ensures the company has skin in the game.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The Rs.15 crore escrow (25% of Rs.60 crore) demonstrates the company's commitment to completing the buyback. A company that deposits escrow and then withdraws faces penalties. This escrow is your assurance that the buyback will proceed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
