<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sarvottam Fintech Ltd. (SFL), an unlisted fintech company, plans to launch its IPO. The company's financials for the last three years show: net tangible assets of Rs.5 crore, Rs.4.2 crore, and Rs.3.8 crore; average operating profit of Rs.17 crore (positive each year); and net worth of Rs.2 crore each year. The IPO is structured as a book building issue with a price band of Rs.280-Rs.320 per share. The total issue size is 50 lakh shares, comprising 35 lakh fresh issue shares and 15 lakh shares as Offer for Sale by the promoter, Harish Mehta.

The issue receives the following subscription on closing day (T day): QIB category -- 1.5 crore shares bid (against 25 lakh shares reserved); NII category -- 60 lakh shares bid (against 7.5 lakh shares reserved); RII category -- 52.5 lakh shares bid (against 17.5 lakh shares reserved). The cut-off price is determined at Rs.310 per share. Pooja Sharma, a retail investor, applied for 200 shares at cut-off price through ASBA, with funds blocked in her SCSB account. Vikram Desai, the RTA officer, is coordinating the post-issue process.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> In SFL's IPO, 15 lakh shares are offered through OFS by promoter Harish Mehta. What is the impact on SFL's paid-up capital from this OFS component, and where do the proceeds go?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Paid-up capital increases by the value of 15 lakh shares, and proceeds go to the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Paid-up capital remains unchanged as OFS involves sale of existing shares, and proceeds go to Harish Mehta]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Paid-up capital decreases because the promoter is selling shares back to the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Paid-up capital increases partially, with proceeds split equally between the company and Harish Mehta]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In an Offer for Sale (OFS), existing shares held by the promoter are sold to the public. No new shares are created, so the company's paid-up capital remains unchanged. The proceeds from the sale of 15 lakh shares go entirely to the selling shareholder (Harish Mehta), not to the company. Only the fresh issue of 35 lakh shares increases paid-up capital, with proceeds going to the company.
**The Trap:** Candidates often confuse fresh issue and OFS impacts. Fresh issue = new shares = capital increase = company gets money. OFS = existing shares change hands = no capital change = seller gets money. This is a fundamental distinction.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 7.4 clearly distinguishes fresh issue from OFS. RTAs must track both components separately for allotment and fund flow purposes.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When analyzing IPO proceeds, always separate fresh issue and OFS. If an IPO is predominantly OFS, the company isn't raising much growth capital -- the promoter is monetizing. This significantly changes the investment thesis for your clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
