<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In the context of an IPO, what is the significance of the term 'ineligible issuer' under SEBI ICDR Regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An ineligible issuer is permanently barred from making any public offer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An ineligible issuer must use the book building process, allot at least 75% to QIBs, and refund if the minimum subscription is not met]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An ineligible issuer can only make a private placement and cannot access public markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An ineligible issuer is one that has been delisted and cannot re-list for 10 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An ineligible issuer -- one that does not meet the standard eligibility criteria (net tangible assets, operating profit, net worth thresholds) -- is not permanently barred. Instead, it must follow stricter norms: mandatory book building, at least 75% allotment to QIBs (who are sophisticated investors capable of evaluating risk), and mandatory refund if minimum subscription fails.
**The Trap:** Ineligible does not mean banned. It means additional safeguards are imposed to protect retail investors by ensuring institutional validation. Candidates often assume ineligibility is absolute.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 7.5 covers eligibility and the alternative route for ineligible issuers. Series IX covers this from the merchant banker's structuring perspective.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When you see an IPO where 75% goes to QIBs, check if the issuer is ineligible. If so, the QIB subscription level becomes even more critical as a signal -- strong QIB demand validates the issue despite the issuer not meeting standard criteria.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
