<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A rights issue is offered by a listed company. What is the fundamental purpose of a rights issue from a shareholder's perspective?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To allow the company to raise debt capital from existing shareholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To enable existing shareholders to purchase additional shares proportionately, thereby preventing dilution of their ownership]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To allow only institutional investors to increase their stake in the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To facilitate the exit of promoters from the company]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A rights issue offers existing shareholders the right to buy additional shares in proportion to their current holding. The Companies Act requires that shares be offered to existing shareholders first. This prevents dilution of ownership percentage -- if all shareholders exercise their rights, everyone's proportional stake remains the same.
**The Trap:** Rights issue is equity, not debt. It is offered to ALL existing shareholders proportionately, not just institutions. And it helps shareholders maintain their stake, not exit.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A covers rights issues as a capital category by investor type. NISM Series IX covers the regulatory framework for rights issues under SEBI ICDR.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a company announces a rights issue, clients need to decide quickly. Not exercising rights means dilution. If they cannot invest, they can renounce the rights in favor of another person, converting their rights into value rather than letting them lapse.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
