<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Public Offerings and IPO Processes_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Dhanvantari Pharma Ltd. (DPL), a listed pharmaceutical company, has 4 crore outstanding equity shares with a face value of Rs.10 each, trading at Rs.250 per share. The company has free reserves of Rs.600 crore and paid-up capital of Rs.40 crore. On February 1, 2026, the Board of Directors approves a buyback of 20 lakh shares at Rs.300 per share through the tender offer method, for a total buyback consideration of Rs.60 crore. The record date is set as March 1, 2026.

Anita Kulkarni, a retail investor, holds 500 shares with a market value of Rs.1.25 lakh on the record date. Suresh Patil holds 1,200 shares with a market value of Rs.3 lakh on the record date. Geeta Nair holds 5,000 shares with a market value of Rs.12.5 lakh on the record date. The total outstanding shares eligible for buyback are 4 crore. Rajesh Kumar, the RTA officer at the company's registrar, is responsible for processing the buyback. The buyback opens on March 10, 2026 and closes on March 24, 2026.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Rajesh, the RTA officer, must ensure compliance with the public notice requirement for DPL's buyback. What is the mandated timeline and format for the public notice?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Public notice in 2 newspapers within 5 working days of the Board resolution]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Public notice in 3 newspapers within 2 working days of the Board resolution]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Public notice in 1 national newspaper within 7 calendar days of the Board resolution]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No public notice is required for buybacks below Rs.100 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI (Buy-back) Regulations 2018 mandate a public notice in 3 newspapers within 2 working days of the Board resolution (or special resolution, as applicable). This ensures timely public disclosure of the buyback. The 3-newspaper requirement typically means one English national daily, one Hindi national daily, and one regional language daily where the registered office is located.
**The Trap:** The requirement is 3 newspapers, not 2, and within 2 working days, not 5 or 7. Public notice is mandatory regardless of the buyback size -- there is no exemption for smaller buybacks.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series II-A Chapter 7.7 specifies the public notice requirements. RTAs must ensure compliance with this disclosure obligation.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As an RTA professional, track the 2-working-day deadline for public notice from the date of the Board meeting. Missing this deadline is a regulatory violation. Build an automated alert system that triggers as soon as a Board resolution for buyback is recorded.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
