<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory Requirements for Research Analysts_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Capital Edge Research Pvt Ltd is a newly registered research entity planning to set up operations. The founder, Nikhil Shah, is designing the firm's compliance framework. He needs to address: (1) How to structure analyst compensation without creating IB conflicts. (2) What disclosures to include in every research report. (3) How to handle situations where the firm also provides IB advisory services. (4) What trading restrictions to impose on analysts and their associates. (5) How to maintain a website as per SEBI requirements. The firm plans to cover 50 companies across 5 sectors, employ 8 full-time analysts and 3 part-time analysts, and offer both subscription-based research and fee-based advisory services to accredited investors.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Trading restrictions for all 11 analysts (8 full-time + 3 part-time) include:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only full-time analysts face trading restrictions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both full-time and part-time analysts and their associates cannot trade in recommended securities within 30 days before and 5 days after publication]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Part-time analysts are exempt from all restrictions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trading restrictions apply only to stocks above Rs.500 market price]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 16(2) explicitly covers independent, part-time, and employed RAs AND their associates. The 30/5 day restriction applies to all.
**The Trap:** Part-time status does NOT exempt from trading restrictions. All RAs regardless of employment type face the same restrictions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 14 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a centralized trading monitoring system that covers all analysts and their declared associates. Pre-clearance for all trades is recommended.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>