<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Mehta family runs a large textile business across three generations. They execute a family settlement agreement to divide the business assets among family members. What is the tax implication of a family settlement?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Family settlement is NOT treated as a transfer — no capital gains tax, no gift tax, and no clubbing provisions apply]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains tax applies on the fair market value of assets transferred under the settlement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gift tax applies if any member receives assets exceeding INR 50,000 in value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Clubbing provisions under Sec 64 apply for transfers between family members]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A family settlement is NOT treated as a transfer under tax law. Therefore, no capital gains tax is attracted, no gift tax applies, and clubbing provisions do not kick in. This makes family settlements a powerful tool for dividing business assets tax-efficiently.
**The Trap:** Candidates may apply general transfer tax rules (capital gains, gift tax, clubbing) to family settlements. The specific exemption for family settlements overrides these general provisions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests family business ownership models: Owner-Operator, Partnership, Distributed, Nested, and Public. Family settlement is relevant across all these models.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For family business clients, a well-documented family settlement can save crores in taxes. Ensure the settlement is genuine, covers all members' interests, and is executed with proper legal advice. Courts have consistently upheld bona fide family settlements.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
