<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rajiv takes a life insurance policy of INR 1 crore and specifies it is for the benefit of his wife Nandini under the Married Women's Property Act 1874. If Rajiv faces a business failure and his creditors try to claim the insurance proceeds, what happens?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Creditors can claim the insurance proceeds since Rajiv paid the premiums from his income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Creditors can claim 50% while the remaining 50% goes to Nandini]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The insurance company will decide the distribution between creditors and Nandini]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The insurance proceeds are protected from Rajiv's creditors as it is deemed a trust for Nandini's benefit]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Married Women's Property Act 1874, insurance taken by a husband for the wife's benefit is treated as a deemed trust. This protects the wife's property from the husband's creditors. The Act was specifically designed to protect married women's property rights.
**The Trap:** Candidates may think creditors can claim since Rajiv paid the premiums. But the deemed trust provision creates an impenetrable legal shield — the policy proceeds belong to Nandini, not Rajiv's estate.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B and NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) both test insurance-related provisions. This Act is particularly important for business owners who want to protect family wealth.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The MWP Act is one of the most powerful creditor-protection tools in India. Every married business owner should have at least one insurance policy under MWP Act — it's simple to implement and provides absolute protection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
