<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Gopal writes his will on a plain paper without any stamp duty and does not register it with the sub-registrar. His son later questions the validity of the will. Under Section 18 of the Registration Act, which statement about will registration is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Registration is compulsory for all wills; without it, the will is automatically void]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A will must be written on stamp paper of appropriate value to be valid]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Registration is compulsory and can only be done during the testator's lifetime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Registration is NOT compulsory; a will can be on plain paper without stamp duty and is still valid]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Sec 18 of the Registration Act, registration of a will is NOT compulsory. A will can be written on plain paper with no stamp duty. However, registration provides advantages: it is tamper-proof and ensures safe custody. Registration can be done during lifetime or by the legatee after the testator's death.
**The Trap:** Many candidates believe registration is mandatory. The advantages of registration (tamper-proof, safe custody) are often confused with it being compulsory.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests will formalities extensively. Note the special rule: a non-Hindu bequeathing to charity must deposit the will with the registrar within 6 months AND the testator must survive 12 months after execution.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While registration is optional, always recommend it to clients. An unregistered will on plain paper is legally valid but much easier to challenge in court.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
