<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Lakshmi is 82 years old, completely deaf and partially blind, but has a sound mind. Her family members claim she cannot make a valid will due to her physical disabilities. Under Section 59 of the Indian Succession Act, which statement is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Lakshmi can make a valid will since persons who are deaf, dumb, or blind can make wills if they are of sound mind]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lakshmi cannot make a will because blindness prevents her from reading and understanding the document]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lakshmi can make a will only if she obtains a court order certifying her mental fitness]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lakshmi can make a will only if it is a Privileged Will since she has physical disabilities]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Sec 59, testamentary capacity requires a sound mind and being a major (not a minor). Physical disabilities like being deaf, dumb, or blind do NOT disqualify a person from making a will. Even an insane person can make a will during a lucid interval.
**The Trap:** Many candidates assume physical disabilities affect testamentary capacity. The law is clear — only mental capacity matters, not physical ability. No court order is needed.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests Sec 59 essentials for testamentary capacity. The lucid interval provision for insane persons is also testable.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When elderly clients wish to make a will, focus on documenting their mental soundness. A doctor's certificate of sound mind (though not legally required) can prevent future challenges to the will.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
