<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Harish, a Hindu man, makes a valid will in 2020 and subsequently marries Pooja in 2022. He does not make a new will after his marriage. What happens to his 2020 will under the Indian Succession Act?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The will is automatically revoked because marriage always revokes a prior will]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The will is partially revoked — only the spouse's share is affected]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The will remains valid because under Section 57, marriage does NOT revoke a will for Hindus]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The will is suspended until Harish either confirms or revokes it after marriage]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 57 of the Indian Succession Act, subsequent marriage does NOT revoke a will for Hindus. This is a specific exception. For non-Hindus, subsequent marriage IS one of the 4 modes of revocation. The 4 modes are: (1) later will/codicil, (2) written declaration, (3) burning/tearing/destroying, (4) subsequent marriage (but NOT for Hindus).
**The Trap:** The general rule is that subsequent marriage revokes a will, but Hindu law has a specific exception under Sec 57. Candidates who know the general rule but not the Hindu exception will get this wrong.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests will revocation modes. Also know that a Codicil (Sec 2(b)) is a supplementary document for minor alterations to a will.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always ask Hindu clients whether they've married after making their will. While the will stays valid, it may not reflect their new family situation — updating it is strongly recommended.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
