<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory Requirements for Research Analysts_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera Srinivasan is the compliance officer at Galaxy Research Services, a SEBI-registered research entity. She discovers the following situations during her quarterly review: (1) Analyst Rajan published a Buy report on PharmaTech Ltd and his wife purchased PharmaTech shares 15 days before the report was published. (2) The firm received Rs.50 lakh from InfoSys Corp for investment banking advisory services 6 months ago. Analyst Priya, who covers InfoSys Corp, did not disclose this in her latest research report. (3) Analyst Vikram's compensation for the year was partly determined based on the revenue his research helped generate from brokerage services for specific clients. (4) The research team is located on the same floor as the investment banking team, sharing common meeting rooms and a common server for document storage. (5) Analyst Deepa received a call from the CEO of MicroChip Ltd sharing that the company will announce a major acquisition next week. This information has not been made public.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Deepa receiving UPSI about MicroChip's upcoming acquisition from the CEO requires her to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Immediately publish a Buy report to benefit her clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not use this information, report it to the compliance officer, and the stock should be placed on the restricted list]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Share it only with the firm's top 10 clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Trade in MicroChip shares before telling anyone]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Receiving UPSI triggers immediate compliance obligations: notify compliance, restrict trading in the stock, do not use the information in research until it becomes public.
**The Trap:** Using UPSI for trading or research is illegal. Selective sharing is also prohibited. The only correct action is compliance notification.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 14 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a UPSI log. Every instance of UPSI receipt must be documented with the source, nature, date, and actions taken.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>