<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ramesh nominates his brother Suresh as nominee for his mutual fund holdings worth INR 25 lakh. Ramesh's will, however, bequeaths all mutual fund holdings to his wife Anita. After Ramesh's death, who gets the mutual fund holdings?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suresh, because nomination always overrides a will]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Anita, because a will supersedes nomination in most cases — the nominee holds assets only as a custodian]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both Suresh and Anita share equally as they both have valid claims]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Neither — the assets go to legal heirs determined by succession law, ignoring both will and nomination]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Nomination confers only a custodial right, NOT ownership. The nominee is a caretaker who must hand over the assets to the rightful owner as determined by the will or succession law. A will supersedes nomination in most cases.
**The Trap:** Many candidates believe nomination = ownership. This is the single biggest misconception in estate planning. SEBI has increased max nominees to 10, but this does not change the custodial nature.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund) and X-B both test nomination vs will priority. The exception: under the Insurance Act, nomination for immediate family (spouse, parents, children) creates a beneficial nominee WITH ownership rights.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always tell clients: "Nomination is not inheritance." A nominee is a facilitator for smooth transfer, but the will determines who actually owns the assets. Align nomination and will to avoid family disputes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
