<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory Requirements for Research Analysts_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Capital Edge Research Pvt Ltd is a newly registered research entity planning to set up operations. The founder, Nikhil Shah, is designing the firm's compliance framework. He needs to address: (1) How to structure analyst compensation without creating IB conflicts. (2) What disclosures to include in every research report. (3) How to handle situations where the firm also provides IB advisory services. (4) What trading restrictions to impose on analysts and their associates. (5) How to maintain a website as per SEBI requirements. The firm plans to cover 50 companies across 5 sectors, employ 8 full-time analysts and 3 part-time analysts, and offer both subscription-based research and fee-based advisory services to accredited investors.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Capital Edge's website must contain:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the firm's logo and office address]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Details as specified by SEBI including business activity, disciplinary history, terms of service, and associate details]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a contact form for inquiries]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only links to published research reports]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 19A and other provisions: Website must contain business details, services offered, terms and conditions, disciplinary history, and other SEBI-specified information.
**The Trap:** A minimal website with just a logo or contact form does not comply. SEBI expects comprehensive disclosure.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 14 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The website serves as the public face of regulatory compliance. Ensure it is updated regularly and contains all mandatory disclosures.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>