<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory Requirements for Research Analysts_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Capital Edge Research Pvt Ltd is a newly registered research entity planning to set up operations. The founder, Nikhil Shah, is designing the firm's compliance framework. He needs to address: (1) How to structure analyst compensation without creating IB conflicts. (2) What disclosures to include in every research report. (3) How to handle situations where the firm also provides IB advisory services. (4) What trading restrictions to impose on analysts and their associates. (5) How to maintain a website as per SEBI requirements. The firm plans to cover 50 companies across 5 sectors, employ 8 full-time analysts and 3 part-time analysts, and offer both subscription-based research and fee-based advisory services to accredited investors.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Every research report from Capital Edge must mandatorily disclose:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the analyst's name]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Financial interests, compensation from subject company, IB relationships, ownership of 1%+ securities, and AI tool usage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a generic disclaimer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the stock's PE ratio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 19: Mandatory disclosures include financial interests, compensation received, IB relationships, ownership thresholds, prior officer/director roles, market making, and AI usage.
**The Trap:** Disclosures must be specific and comprehensive, not just generic disclaimers.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 14 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Create a standardized disclosure template that pre-populates with firm-specific data and requires analyst-specific inputs for each report.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>