<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Dinesh, aged 70, gives a Power of Attorney (POA) to his 17-year-old grandson Rohan to manage his bank accounts and investments. Dinesh's family objects, saying a minor cannot be a donee of POA. Which statement is CORRECT regarding this arrangement?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A minor cannot be a donee of POA; the arrangement is invalid and void]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A minor can be a donee only for Special POA, not General POA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A minor can be a donee only if a court-appointed guardian co-signs the POA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Under Sec 184 of the Indian Contract Act, a minor can be appointed as a donee (agent) of a POA]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 184 of the Indian Contract Act, a minor can be appointed as an agent (donee of POA). The principal (donor) is bound by the acts of the minor agent, though the minor agent cannot be held personally liable. There are 3 types of POA: General, Special, and Special for Registration.
**The Trap:** Most candidates assume minors cannot be agents because minors cannot enter into contracts. But Sec 184 specifically allows minors as agents — the principal bears all liability.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests POA provisions. POA is NOT compulsorily registrable unless it creates an interest in immovable property. Revocation is under Sec 201.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While legally valid, appointing a minor as POA donee is practically risky. Advise clients to choose a responsible adult. The POA terminates on death of either party, insolvency of either, or completion of business.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
