<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory Requirements for Research Analysts_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Capital Edge Research Pvt Ltd is a newly registered research entity planning to set up operations. The founder, Nikhil Shah, is designing the firm's compliance framework. He needs to address: (1) How to structure analyst compensation without creating IB conflicts. (2) What disclosures to include in every research report. (3) How to handle situations where the firm also provides IB advisory services. (4) What trading restrictions to impose on analysts and their associates. (5) How to maintain a website as per SEBI requirements. The firm plans to cover 50 companies across 5 sectors, employ 8 full-time analysts and 3 part-time analysts, and offer both subscription-based research and fee-based advisory services to accredited investors.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> For analyst compensation, Nikhil must ensure that:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The compensation committee includes the IB head for better coordination]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Compensation review is by the board/committee WITHOUT representation from IB/MB/brokerage divisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Analyst pay is directly linked to IB revenue they help generate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Compensation is set by the trading desk head]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 17(2-3): Compensation approved by board/committee without IB representation. Must not consider individual contribution to IB business.
**The Trap:** IB representation in compensation decisions creates direct conflict. The reviewing body must be independent of IB.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 14 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Structure compensation around research quality metrics: recommendation accuracy, client feedback, sector expertise, and timeliness of coverage.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>