<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory and Ethical Aspects_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Ashok and Vijay jointly own a commercial property in Pune. The ownership deed states "Joint Tenancy with right of survivorship." Ashok writes in his will that his share of the property should go to his son Nikhil. After Ashok's death, who gets Ashok's share?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nikhil, as per Ashok's valid will]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Vijay, because in Joint Tenancy the right of survivorship applies and the property cannot be bequeathed by will]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nikhil and Vijay share equally as both have legitimate claims]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ashok's legal heirs as per Hindu Succession Act, since will cannot override succession law]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In Joint Tenancy, there is a right of survivorship — when one joint tenant dies, the entire property automatically passes to the surviving tenant(s). The property CANNOT be bequeathed by will. Joint tenants must acquire the property at the same time/transaction.
**The Trap:** Candidates may think a will always governs property distribution. But Joint Tenancy is an exception — the right of survivorship overrides the will. This is different from Tenancy-in-Common where there is NO survivorship and shares pass per will/succession.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-B tests the distinction between Joint Tenancy and Tenancy-in-Common. In Tenancy-in-Common, shares can be unequal and each tenant can bequeath their share.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Many Indian clients hold property jointly without understanding the implications. Clarify whether they want Joint Tenancy (survivorship) or Tenancy-in-Common (transferable shares). The choice has massive estate planning consequences.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
