<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Regulatory Requirements for Research Analysts_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Capital Edge Research Pvt Ltd is a newly registered research entity planning to set up operations. The founder, Nikhil Shah, is designing the firm's compliance framework. He needs to address: (1) How to structure analyst compensation without creating IB conflicts. (2) What disclosures to include in every research report. (3) How to handle situations where the firm also provides IB advisory services. (4) What trading restrictions to impose on analysts and their associates. (5) How to maintain a website as per SEBI requirements. The firm plans to cover 50 companies across 5 sectors, employ 8 full-time analysts and 3 part-time analysts, and offer both subscription-based research and fee-based advisory services to accredited investors.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> If Capital Edge also provides IB advisory, the research team must be:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[On the same team as IB for collaboration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Segregated from IB with information barriers, separate reporting lines, and no IB-directed research activities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only separated by a written policy with no physical separation needed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Free to share all research with IB before publication]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 15, 16(5), 18: Research must be segregated with arms-length relationship, separate from IB. Physical and digital information barriers required.
**The Trap:** Written policy alone is insufficient. Physical separation, access controls, and monitoring are needed.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 14 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For a small firm, this is challenging. Consider outsourcing IB advisory to a separate entity or establishing strict time-based separation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>