<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Ramesh is 55 years old and has been employed with a manufacturing company for 28 years. His current basic salary is Rs. 80,000 per month and dearness allowance (DA) is Rs. 20,000 per month. He is covered under the Payment of Gratuity Act. His EPF balance stands at Rs. 45,00,000 (employee share Rs. 22,00,000, employer share Rs. 23,00,000). He also has an NPS Tier I account with a total corpus of Rs. 32,00,000 (own contributions: Rs. 16,00,000) and a superannuation fund with Rs. 18,00,000. His employer contributes 12% to EPF, 10% of basic+DA to NPS, and Rs. 1,50,000 annually to the superannuation fund. He is considering various pre-retirement withdrawal options and wants to understand his retirement benefits. He has never taken an NPS partial withdrawal before.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Mr. Ramesh's employer contributes 12% of basic+DA to EPF, 10% of basic+DA to NPS, and Rs. 1,50,000 to superannuation annually. What is the total annual employer contribution across these three, and how much is taxable as a perquisite?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total = Rs. 4,14,000; no amount taxable as perquisite since each is within individual limits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total = Rs. 4,14,000; entire amount taxable as perquisite]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Total = Rs. 4,14,000 (EPF Rs. 1,44,000 + NPS Rs. 1,20,000 + Super Rs. 1,50,000); excess of Rs. 4,14,000 over Rs. 7,50,000 = Nil, so no perquisite tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total = Rs. 2,64,000 (EPF Rs. 1,44,000 + NPS Rs. 1,20,000); superannuation is not counted in the aggregate]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Annual employer contributions: EPF = 12% × Rs. 1,00,000 × 12 = Rs. 1,44,000. NPS = 10% × Rs. 1,00,000 × 12 = Rs. 1,20,000. Superannuation = Rs. 1,50,000. Total = Rs. 4,14,000. Since the aggregate (Rs. 4,14,000) is below the Rs. 7,50,000 threshold, no amount is taxable as a perquisite.

**The Trap:** Excluding superannuation from the aggregate calculation is a critical error — all three (EPF, NPS, Superannuation) are aggregated for the Rs. 7.5 lakh threshold test. The option stating the entire amount is taxable confuses the aggregate test (threshold-based) with full taxation. In this case, since the total is below Rs. 7.5 lakh, no perquisite arises.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The aggregate employer contribution threshold is tested in NISM X-B and CA exams. Questions often present scenarios where the total is either just below or just above Rs. 7.5 lakh to test precise calculation ability.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Mr. Ramesh, the employer contributions are well within the Rs. 7.5 lakh limit, so no perquisite issue. However, if his salary increases significantly or employer contributions rise, the aggregate could exceed Rs. 7.5 lakh. Proactively monitor this threshold during salary revision cycles.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
