<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Ramesh is 55 years old and has been employed with a manufacturing company for 28 years. His current basic salary is Rs. 80,000 per month and dearness allowance (DA) is Rs. 20,000 per month. He is covered under the Payment of Gratuity Act. His EPF balance stands at Rs. 45,00,000 (employee share Rs. 22,00,000, employer share Rs. 23,00,000). He also has an NPS Tier I account with a total corpus of Rs. 32,00,000 (own contributions: Rs. 16,00,000) and a superannuation fund with Rs. 18,00,000. His employer contributes 12% to EPF, 10% of basic+DA to NPS, and Rs. 1,50,000 annually to the superannuation fund. He is considering various pre-retirement withdrawal options and wants to understand his retirement benefits. He has never taken an NPS partial withdrawal before.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> At retirement (age 60), Mr. Ramesh plans to commute 1/3 of his superannuation fund and use the balance to buy an annuity. If his superannuation corpus at retirement is Rs. 24,00,000 and he also takes 60% of his NPS corpus (assumed Rs. 40,00,000 at 60) as lump sum, what are the tax implications of each?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Superannuation commutation fully taxable; NPS 60% lump sum fully exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both are fully exempt under EEE provisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Superannuation: 1/3 commutation (Rs. 8,00,000) is exempt from tax; NPS: 60% lump sum (Rs. 24,00,000) is also exempt from tax. However, annuity income from both will be taxable at slab rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Superannuation: 1/3 commutation taxable at 10%; NPS: 60% lump sum exempt but the 40% annuity portion is exempt too]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For superannuation, 1/3 commutation at retirement is exempt from tax. The remaining 2/3 is used to purchase an annuity, and the annuity income received is taxable at slab rates. For NPS, the 60% lump sum withdrawal at normal exit (age 60) is exempt from tax. The 40% used for annuity purchase is not taxed at purchase, but the annuity income is taxable at slab rates. So both lump sum components are tax-free, but ongoing annuity income from both is taxable.

**The Trap:** Assuming annuity income is tax-free is the biggest trap. While the lump sum / commutation portions enjoy tax exemption, annuity income is always taxable as income from other sources. Also, NPS is EE-partly E/partly T (not pure EEE) — the "T" refers to annuity income being taxable. Superannuation commutation at 10% is a fabricated rate.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The tax treatment of retirement corpus withdrawal vs ongoing annuity income is tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and income tax certifications. The distinction between lump sum exemption and annuity taxability is one of the most important retirement tax concepts.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help clients understand that retirement tax planning doesn't end at withdrawal — the annuity income will be a recurring taxable item. Consider the combined annuity income from NPS and superannuation when estimating post-retirement tax liability. Suggest tax-efficient withdrawal strategies that balance lump sum and annuity to optimize the overall tax outcome.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
