<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An employee's EPF account has been inactive (no contributions) for 5 years. Which of the following correctly describes the current status and implications?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The account becomes inoperative after 3 years of inactivity and the balance is forfeited]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The account becomes inactive after 3 years but continues to earn interest until claimed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The account became inactive after 3 years; it becomes inoperative after 7 years and the balance is transferred to the Senior Citizen Welfare Fund, but can be claimed within 25 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The account remains active and continues to earn interest regardless of contribution gaps]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** EPF accounts have a defined lifecycle of inactivity: inactive after 3 years of no contributions, inoperative after 7 years, and then the balance is transferred to the Senior Citizen Welfare Fund. However, the employee retains the right to claim the amount within 25 years of the transfer. The balance is not forfeited permanently.

**The Trap:** "Forfeited" is the key trap word — the balance is never permanently forfeited but transferred to a separate fund. Another trap is assuming interest continues to accrue indefinitely on inactive accounts. The 25-year claim window is an important safeguard often missed by candidates.

**Cross-Exam Context:** EPF dormant account rules are tested in NISM X-B and banking exams dealing with unclaimed amounts. The Senior Citizen Welfare Fund and its claim process are relatively new regulatory additions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients change jobs, always ensure EPF transfer to the new employer's account to prevent inactivity. Use the UAN (Universal Account Number) system for seamless transfers. If a client discovers an old EPF account, initiate the claim immediately — don't wait for the 7-year inoperative threshold.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
