<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which annuity option typically provides the highest monthly payout to the annuitant, and why?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Lifetime annuity without return of purchase price, because the insurer retains the entire corpus upon the annuitant's death]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lifetime annuity with return of purchase price, because the higher corpus generates more income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Joint life annuity, because two lives pooled together create a larger risk pool]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annuity certain for a guaranteed period, because the fixed term allows for higher payouts]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A lifetime annuity without return of purchase price provides the highest payout because the insurer bears no obligation to return the principal upon the annuitant's death. The entire corpus (including the portion that would otherwise be returned) is used to generate the annuity income. This means the insurer can offer a higher periodic payment.

**The Trap:** "With return of purchase price" actually provides the LOWEST annuity because the insurer must reserve capital for returning the principal to nominees. Joint life annuity is lower because payments continue for two lives. The guaranteed period option also reduces payout since the insurer commits to paying for a minimum period regardless of survival.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Annuity type comparisons are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, Series V-A, and insurance certification exams. The inverse relationship between annuity payout and death benefit guarantee is a fundamental concept.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Match annuity type to client needs: clients with dependents may prefer "with return" despite lower payouts. Single clients without heirs benefit most from "without return." Always calculate the break-even period — how long the client must survive for "without return" to be financially superior.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
