<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the NPS Auto Choice Life Cycle Fund LC-75 (High Risk), what is the maximum equity allocation for a subscriber aged 35 or below, and to what level does it reduce at age 55 and above?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[75% equity at age 35 or below, reducing to 15% at age 55 and above]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[75% equity at age 35 or below, reducing to 25% at age 55 and above]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% equity at age 35 or below, reducing to 15% at age 55 and above]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[75% equity at age 40 or below, reducing to 10% at age 55 and above]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The LC-75 High Risk Life Cycle Fund under NPS Auto Choice starts with 75% equity allocation for subscribers aged 35 or below and systematically reduces it to 15% at age 55 and above. This age-based glide path ensures automatic de-risking as the subscriber approaches retirement.

**The Trap:** The 25% at age 55 option is tempting because it seems like a reasonable floor. The LC Aggressive fund (50% equity at ≤45, 35% at 55+) may also cause confusion with LC-75. Remember: LC-75 = 75% start, and the terminal equity is 15%, not 25%.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS lifecycle fund mechanics are tested in NISM Series V-A (MF Distributors) and NISM Series X-A (Investment Adviser Level 1) as well, though with less depth on specific glide path numbers.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always map the client's age to the correct lifecycle fund. A 36-year-old in LC-75 already has equity declining — recommend Active Choice if the client wants to maintain a specific allocation beyond what the glide path allows.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
