<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A PPF account holder has completed the initial 15-year tenure and opts for extension with contributions for a 5-year block. What is the maximum amount she can withdraw during this extension period?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Up to 60% of the balance at the start of the extension period, spread over the 5-year block]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Up to 50% of the balance at the start of the extension period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Up to 100% of the balance since the 15-year lock-in is complete]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No withdrawal is permitted during the extension period with contributions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a PPF account is extended with contributions, the account holder can withdraw up to 60% of the balance standing at the commencement of the extension period. This withdrawal can be spread across the 5-year extension block. If extended without contributions, the entire balance can be withdrawn at any time.

**The Trap:** The 50% rule applies to partial withdrawal during the original 15-year tenure (after completing 5 financial years), not during the extension. The 100% option confuses extension with contributions and extension without contributions — full withdrawal is only allowed in the latter case. The distinction between "with" and "without" contributions is crucial.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PPF extension rules are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and banking exams. The with/without contributions distinction during extension is a nuanced topic that separates prepared candidates from unprepared ones.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients to choose between extension with contributions (60% withdrawal, continued growth) and without contributions (full withdrawal flexibility). Clients needing liquidity should choose "without contributions." Those wanting continued tax-free growth should choose "with contributions" and plan withdrawals strategically.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
