<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Ramesh is 55 years old and has been employed with a manufacturing company for 28 years. His current basic salary is Rs. 80,000 per month and dearness allowance (DA) is Rs. 20,000 per month. He is covered under the Payment of Gratuity Act. His EPF balance stands at Rs. 45,00,000 (employee share Rs. 22,00,000, employer share Rs. 23,00,000). He also has an NPS Tier I account with a total corpus of Rs. 32,00,000 (own contributions: Rs. 16,00,000) and a superannuation fund with Rs. 18,00,000. His employer contributes 12% to EPF, 10% of basic+DA to NPS, and Rs. 1,50,000 annually to the superannuation fund. He is considering various pre-retirement withdrawal options and wants to understand his retirement benefits. He has never taken an NPS partial withdrawal before.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Mr. Ramesh wishes to take a partial withdrawal from his EPF at age 55 for pre-retirement purposes. What is the maximum amount he can withdraw under the pre-retirement partial withdrawal provision?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[90% of the total EPF balance = 90% × Rs. 45,00,000 = Rs. 40,50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[90% of the employee's share = 90% × Rs. 22,00,000 = Rs. 19,80,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[75% of the total EPF balance = 75% × Rs. 45,00,000 = Rs. 33,75,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He cannot take any pre-retirement withdrawal since he has not yet reached the retirement age of 58]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** EPF allows a pre-retirement partial withdrawal of up to 90% of the total EPF balance (both employee and employer shares) when the member reaches age 54. Since Mr. Ramesh is 55, he qualifies. The maximum withdrawal = 90% × Rs. 45,00,000 = Rs. 40,50,000.

**The Trap:** Restricting the calculation to the employee's share only is the key trap — the 90% pre-retirement withdrawal applies to the total balance. The 75% figure relates to post-unemployment withdrawal (75% after 1 month of unemployment). The age restriction option is wrong because the threshold is 54, not 58.

**Cross-Exam Context:** EPF pre-retirement withdrawal rules are tested in NISM X-A and X-B. The age 54 threshold and the 90% limit are specific to this withdrawal type and should not be confused with other partial withdrawal purposes.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Pre-retirement EPF withdrawal at 54+ can be a powerful financial planning tool. However, advise clients to withdraw only what they need — the remaining EPF balance continues to earn interest. Consider the tax implications if the withdrawal pushes the client into a higher tax bracket.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
