<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about PPF accounts held by NRIs is correct as per the latest regulations effective from September 2024?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NRIs cannot open new PPF accounts, and existing NRI PPF accounts will not earn any interest post September 2024 and cannot be extended]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NRIs can continue their existing PPF accounts with full interest and can extend them in 5-year blocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NRIs can open new PPF accounts but cannot extend them beyond the initial 15-year tenure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NRIs must close their PPF accounts immediately upon change in residency status]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NRIs are not eligible to open new PPF accounts. For existing accounts held by NRIs, post September 2024, no interest will be credited and the accounts cannot be extended. The account continues to maturity but without interest accrual.

**The Trap:** Many candidates assume existing NRI PPF accounts continue to earn interest — this was true earlier but changed with the September 2024 regulation. The option about immediate closure is also wrong since PPF premature closure is allowed only for specific reasons (medical emergency, higher education, change in residency), but it is not mandatory.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PPF rules for NRIs are tested across NISM X-A, X-B, and also in NISM Series XIII (Common Derivatives). The residency-based eligibility is a common cross-topic with FEMA regulations.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a client is planning to become an NRI, advise them to maximize PPF contributions before the status change. For existing NRI clients with PPF, recommend exploring premature closure (if eligible) rather than letting money sit without interest.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
