<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In NPS, Asset Class 'A' (Alternative Investments) has specific restrictions. Which of the following correctly describes these restrictions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Maximum allocation of 5%, available only under Active Choice, and only in Tier I accounts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum allocation of 5%, available under both Active and Auto Choice, in both Tier I and Tier II]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum allocation of 10%, available only under Active Choice, in both Tier I and Tier II]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum allocation of 5%, available under both Active and Auto Choice, but only in Tier I accounts]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NPS Asset Class A (Alternative Investments, including REITs, InvITs, and CMBS) has three key restrictions: (1) Maximum 5% allocation cap, (2) Available only under Active Choice (not Auto Choice lifecycle funds), and (3) Available only in Tier I accounts (not Tier II). These restrictions reflect the higher risk and lower liquidity of alternative investments.

**The Trap:** Including Asset Class A in Auto Choice is wrong because lifecycle funds use a pre-set mix of E, C, and G only. Including it in Tier II is wrong because Tier II is designed for more liquid, flexible investments and doesn't include alternatives. The 10% cap is fabricated.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS asset class restrictions are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and Series V-A. The specific limitations on Asset Class A distinguish it from E (max 75%), C (up to 100%), and G (up to 100%).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients wanting alternative investment exposure through NPS, the 5% cap in Tier I Active Choice is quite limiting. Consider suggesting separate REIT/InvIT investments outside NPS for clients wanting higher alternative allocation while using NPS primarily for E, C, G allocation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
