<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Anita is 62 years old and has just retired from a private sector company with a total retirement corpus of Rs. 2,00,00,000 (Rs. 2 crore). She owns a house and has no outstanding loans. Her monthly household expenses are Rs. 80,000. She wants to generate a steady monthly income while preserving her capital for at least 25 years. She is considering multiple distribution options: annuities from an insurance company, SWP from mutual funds, SCSS, POMIS, FD laddering, and possibly a reverse mortgage on her property (valued at Rs. 1.5 crore). She has no other source of income. Her husband (age 65) is also retired. She wants to allocate her Rs. 2 crore optimally across these products.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Mrs. Anita wants to invest the maximum possible in SCSS. Considering her eligibility and the current limits, what is the maximum she can invest, and what is the maturity period including extensions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 15 lakh; maturity 5 years extendable by 3 years once]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 30 lakh; maturity 5 years extendable by 3 years once (total maximum 8 years), with the extension request made within 1 year of maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 30 lakh; maturity 5 years extendable by 5 years once]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 30 lakh; maturity 5 years with no extension facility]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mrs. Anita at age 62 is fully eligible for SCSS (age 60+ requirement met). The maximum investment limit is Rs. 30 lakh. The scheme matures in 5 years and can be extended once for 3 years (total 8 years). The extension must be requested within 1 year of the original maturity date. NRIs and HUFs are not eligible, but she is a resident individual.

**The Trap:** The Rs. 15 lakh was the old SCSS limit — it has been revised to Rs. 30 lakh. The 5-year extension option confuses SCSS with PPF (which extends in 5-year blocks). The "no extension" option is simply incorrect. The 1-year window for requesting extension is a frequently missed detail.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SCSS limits and features are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and banking certification exams. The recent revision from Rs. 15 lakh to Rs. 30 lakh makes this a current affairs topic as well.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Mrs. Anita, SCSS should be a cornerstone of her income strategy — Rs. 30 lakh at current rates generates substantial quarterly interest. The 80C deduction on investment and the predictable income make it ideal for retirees. Remind her to request extension within 1 year of maturity to continue the benefit.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
