<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An NPS subscriber wants to change both her Pension Fund Manager and her asset allocation within the same year. How many times can she make each change in a financial year?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Pension Fund Manager or investment scheme can be changed once per year; asset allocation can be changed up to 4 times per year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both Pension Fund Manager and asset allocation can be changed up to 4 times per year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pension Fund Manager can be changed once per year; asset allocation cannot be changed at all during the year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both Pension Fund Manager and asset allocation can be changed once per year]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NPS allows different frequencies for different types of changes: (1) Change of Pension Fund Manager (PFM) or investment scheme (Active/Auto Choice): once per financial year. (2) Change of asset allocation within the chosen scheme: up to 4 times per financial year. This distinction allows subscribers flexibility in fine-tuning allocation while maintaining stability in fund manager selection.

**The Trap:** Assuming both changes have the same frequency is the common error. The 4-times-per-year limit applies only to allocation changes within a scheme, not to fund manager or scheme changes. This makes intuitive sense — fund manager changes involve actual portfolio transfers, which are more disruptive than mere allocation adjustments.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS operational rules including change frequencies are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and pension fund management modules. The distinction between scheme change and allocation change is frequently confused.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients to make allocation changes at the start of each quarter if needed, and to time fund manager changes carefully. Once the annual PFM change is used, there's no reversal until the next financial year. Research PFM performance trends before recommending a switch.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
