<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An employer contributes Rs. 4,00,000 to EPF, Rs. 2,50,000 to NPS, and Rs. 2,00,000 to a Superannuation fund for an employee in a financial year. What is the tax implication for the employee?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The aggregate employer contribution is Rs. 8,50,000, and the excess of Rs. 1,00,000 over Rs. 7,50,000 is taxable as a perquisite in the employee's hands]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Each contribution is separately exempt under different sections, so no amount is taxable as a perquisite]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the NPS contribution above Rs. 50,000 is taxable as a perquisite]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire Rs. 8,50,000 is exempt since employer contributions are fully deductible]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When the aggregate employer contribution to EPF, NPS, and Superannuation exceeds Rs. 7,50,000 in a financial year, the excess amount is taxable as a perquisite in the employee's hands. Here, Rs. 4,00,000 + Rs. 2,50,000 + Rs. 2,00,000 = Rs. 8,50,000. Excess = Rs. 8,50,000 - Rs. 7,50,000 = Rs. 1,00,000 taxable as perquisite.

**The Trap:** Treating each contribution independently is the biggest trap. Pre-Budget 2020, these were indeed treated separately. The aggregate threshold of Rs. 7.5 lakh was introduced to prevent high-income employees from receiving unlimited tax-free employer contributions across multiple retirement vehicles.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This aggregate threshold is tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and is a favorite in CA/CMA exams. Understanding the interplay between EPF, NPS, and Superannuation employer contributions is critical.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For high-income clients whose employers contribute generously, quantify the perquisite tax impact and consider whether redirecting some employer contribution to salary (and then to other tax-efficient instruments) might be better overall.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
