<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Patel (age 57, retiring in 3 years) wants to take a partial withdrawal from his NPS Tier I account. He joined NPS 12 years ago and has never taken a partial withdrawal before. His own contributions total Rs. 18,00,000. What is the maximum he can withdraw?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 4,50,000 (25% of his own contributions of Rs. 18,00,000)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 4,50,000 (25% of the total corpus including employer contributions and returns)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 18,00,000 (100% of own contributions since he is above 55)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He cannot take a partial withdrawal because he is within 3 years of retirement age]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NPS Tier I allows partial withdrawal of up to 25% of the subscriber's own contributions (not the total corpus including employer contributions and investment returns). With own contributions of Rs. 18,00,000, the maximum partial withdrawal is Rs. 4,50,000. He meets the 3-year membership requirement, and this would be his first withdrawal (maximum 4 allowed before 60).

**The Trap:** Confusing "own contributions" with "total corpus" is the most common error. The 25% is calculated only on what the subscriber has personally contributed, excluding employer contributions and accumulated returns. The option about not being eligible within 3 years of retirement is fabricated — there is no such restriction before 60.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS partial withdrawal limits are tested in NISM X-A and X-B. The distinction between "own contributions" and "total corpus" is a critical exam concept that also appears in mutual fund SIP withdrawal questions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help clients track their own contribution amount separately from total corpus. The NPS statement shows both figures. Plan partial withdrawals strategically — with only 4 allowed before 60 and a 4-year gap between each, timing matters.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
