<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Sharma has an NPS Tier I corpus of Rs. 4.5 lakh and is exiting NPS before the age of 60 due to a career change. What are his options regarding the corpus?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He can withdraw the entire corpus as a lump sum since it is Rs. 5 lakh or below]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He must use at least 80% to purchase an annuity and can withdraw only 20% as lump sum]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He must use at least 40% to purchase an annuity and can withdraw 60% as lump sum]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He cannot exit NPS before 60 unless he has completed at least 10 years of subscription]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For premature exit from NPS (before age 60), the general rule is that at least 80% must be used to purchase an annuity and only 20% can be taken as lump sum. However, if the total corpus is Rs. 5 lakh or below, the subscriber can withdraw the entire amount as a lump sum. Since Mr. Sharma's corpus is Rs. 4.5 lakh (≤Rs. 5 lakh), he qualifies for full withdrawal.

**The Trap:** The 80% annuity rule is the standard premature exit rule and appears correct at first glance. The 40%/60% split applies to normal exit at age 60 (for government employees it's 40% annuity). Candidates must remember the Rs. 5 lakh threshold for premature exit and Rs. 8 lakh threshold for normal exit.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS exit rules are heavily tested in NISM X-A and X-B. The different thresholds (Rs. 5 lakh for premature, Rs. 8 lakh for normal exit, Rs. 8-12 lakh partial annuity) are frequently confused.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For small NPS corpuses, premature exit may actually be beneficial — the client avoids being forced into an annuity with a small amount that would yield negligible monthly income. Guide them to reinvest the lump sum wisely.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
