<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the Unified Pension Scheme (UPS), what is the family payout to the spouse of a deceased subscriber, and what is the minimum guaranteed pension for a subscriber who has completed at least 10 years of service?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Family payout is 60% of the subscriber's pension; minimum guaranteed pension is Rs. 10,000 per month]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Family payout is 50% of the subscriber's pension; minimum guaranteed pension is Rs. 10,000 per month]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Family payout is 60% of the subscriber's pension; minimum guaranteed pension is Rs. 15,000 per month]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Family payout is 75% of the subscriber's pension; minimum guaranteed pension is Rs. 5,000 per month]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under UPS, the family payout to the spouse is 60% of the subscriber's pension amount. The minimum guaranteed pension is Rs. 10,000 per month, applicable for subscribers with at least 10 years of qualifying service. The assured pension is proportionate for 10-25 years of service, and 50% of average basic pay for 25+ years.

**The Trap:** The 50% figure is the subscriber's own pension rate (for 25+ years), not the family payout. Confusing these two percentages (50% for self, 60% of that for spouse) is common. The Rs. 15,000 and Rs. 5,000 minimum pension figures are fabricated distractors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** UPS is a new scheme effective April 2025 and is likely to appear in NISM X-B current affairs sections. Comparison with NPS family pension provisions makes for good cross-topic questions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For government employees choosing between NPS and UPS, the 60% family payout under UPS provides a defined survivor benefit. Under NPS, the family benefit depends on the accumulated corpus and annuity chosen. Risk-averse families may prefer UPS's certainty, but remember the choice is irrevocable.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
