<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Ramesh is 55 years old and has been employed with a manufacturing company for 28 years. His current basic salary is Rs. 80,000 per month and dearness allowance (DA) is Rs. 20,000 per month. He is covered under the Payment of Gratuity Act. His EPF balance stands at Rs. 45,00,000 (employee share Rs. 22,00,000, employer share Rs. 23,00,000). He also has an NPS Tier I account with a total corpus of Rs. 32,00,000 (own contributions: Rs. 16,00,000) and a superannuation fund with Rs. 18,00,000. His employer contributes 12% to EPF, 10% of basic+DA to NPS, and Rs. 1,50,000 annually to the superannuation fund. He is considering various pre-retirement withdrawal options and wants to understand his retirement benefits. He has never taken an NPS partial withdrawal before.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Calculate the gratuity amount payable to Mr. Ramesh under the Payment of Gratuity Act upon retirement after 28 years of service. Also determine the tax-exempt portion.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gratuity = (15 × Rs. 1,00,000 × 28) / 30 = Rs. 14,00,000; fully exempt up to Rs. 20 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Gratuity = (15 × Rs. 1,00,000 × 28) / 26 = Rs. 16,15,385; tax-exempt since it is below Rs. 20 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gratuity = (15 × Rs. 80,000 × 28) / 26 = Rs. 12,92,308; tax-exempt since it is below Rs. 20 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gratuity = (15 × Rs. 1,00,000 × 28) / 26 = Rs. 16,15,385; but only Rs. 10,00,000 is exempt]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Payment of Gratuity Act, the formula is: (15 × last drawn salary × years of service) / 26. Last drawn salary includes basic + DA = Rs. 80,000 + Rs. 20,000 = Rs. 1,00,000. Years = 28 (no rounding needed as it's a complete year). Gratuity = (15 × 1,00,000 × 28) / 26 = Rs. 16,15,385 (approximately). Since this is below the Rs. 20 lakh exemption limit, the entire amount is tax-exempt.

**The Trap:** Using the divisor 30 instead of 26 is the primary trap — 30 applies to non-Act employees. Excluding DA from "last drawn salary" is another error — under the Act, salary includes basic + DA. The Rs. 10 lakh exemption limit is the old limit; it was raised to Rs. 20 lakh.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Gratuity calculation under the Act is one of the most frequently tested numerical problems in NISM X-B. The three components — salary definition, divisor (26 vs 30), and rounding rules — are tested individually and in combination.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The tax exemption on gratuity is the least of: (a) actual gratuity received, (b) Rs. 20 lakh, and (c) the formula amount. For clients covered under the Act, the formula amount is usually the reference point. Government employees get full exemption with no cap.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
