<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A PPF account holder has completed 6 financial years since opening the account. She wants to take a loan against her PPF balance. Is she eligible, and if so, what are the terms?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, she can borrow up to 25% of the balance at the end of the preceding financial year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, she can borrow up to 50% of the balance at the end of the 2nd preceding financial year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, loans against PPF are not permitted after the 6th financial year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, she is not eligible because loans against PPF are available only from the 3rd to the 6th financial year; she has crossed the loan window]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Loans against PPF are available only during a specific window: from the 3rd financial year to the end of the 6th financial year from the date of opening. The maximum loan amount is 25% of the balance at the end of the 2nd preceding financial year. Since she has completed 6 financial years, she has crossed the loan eligibility window. From the 7th year onward, partial withdrawal (up to 50% of balance) becomes available instead.

**The Trap:** Many candidates confuse the loan window (3rd to 6th year) with the partial withdrawal window (after 5th year). After the 6th year, partial withdrawal replaces the loan facility. The option about 50% is the partial withdrawal rule, not the loan rule. This question tests the transition from loan eligibility to withdrawal eligibility.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PPF loan vs withdrawal rules are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and banking certification exams. The temporal boundaries (3rd-6th year for loans, 7th year onward for withdrawal) are frequently tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients in the 3rd-6th year of PPF who need funds, a PPF loan may be better than premature closure. For those beyond the 6th year, partial withdrawal (50% of balance) is the option. Always compare the PPF loan interest rate with the opportunity cost before recommending.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
