<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An employee with basic salary of Rs. 60,000 and DA of Rs. 15,000 has been contributing to EPF for 8 years. She now wishes to take a partial withdrawal for purchasing a house. What is the maximum amount she can withdraw under EPF partial withdrawal rules for house purchase?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[36 months of basic wages and dearness allowance (i.e., 36 × Rs. 75,000 = Rs. 27,00,000) from the employee's share]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[24 months of basic wages and dearness allowance (i.e., 24 × Rs. 75,000 = Rs. 18,00,000) from the employee's share]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% of the employee's share of EPF balance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[90% of the total EPF balance including employer's share]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For house purchase (construction), EPF allows withdrawal of up to 36 months of basic wages and dearness allowance after 5 years of membership. For land purchase alone, the limit is 24 months. Since she is purchasing a house (not just land), 36 months applies. With basic + DA = Rs. 75,000, the maximum is Rs. 27,00,000.

**The Trap:** The 24-month option is the classic trap — it applies to land purchase only, not house construction/purchase. The 50% rule applies to marriage/education withdrawals, and 90% applies to pre-retirement withdrawal at age 54. Candidates must carefully distinguish between land (24 months, 5 years) and house (36 months, 5 years).

**Cross-Exam Context:** EPF partial withdrawal rules are tested in NISM Series X-A and are commonly featured in financial planning certifications. The distinction between land and house purchase limits is a frequently tested nuance.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always ask the client whether they are buying land only or constructing/purchasing a house — the withdrawal limit differs by 12 months of salary. Also verify 5 years of EPF membership before recommending this route.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
