<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Anita is 62 years old and has just retired from a private sector company with a total retirement corpus of Rs. 2,00,00,000 (Rs. 2 crore). She owns a house and has no outstanding loans. Her monthly household expenses are Rs. 80,000. She wants to generate a steady monthly income while preserving her capital for at least 25 years. She is considering multiple distribution options: annuities from an insurance company, SWP from mutual funds, SCSS, POMIS, FD laddering, and possibly a reverse mortgage on her property (valued at Rs. 1.5 crore). She has no other source of income. Her husband (age 65) is also retired. She wants to allocate her Rs. 2 crore optimally across these products.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Mrs. Anita is comparing annuity options for Rs. 50,00,000 of her corpus. She wants to ensure her husband continues to receive income after her death and that the purchase price is returned to their children eventually. Which annuity option best meets her needs, and what is the trade-off?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lifetime annuity without return of purchase price — provides highest income for both lives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Annuity certain for 25 years — guarantees payments for her expected horizon regardless of survival]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Joint life annuity with return of purchase price — covers both lives and returns capital to nominees, but provides the lowest annuity rate among all options]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lifetime annuity with return of purchase price for single life — covers only her life but returns capital]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mrs. Anita has two requirements: (1) income continuation for her husband after her death, and (2) return of purchase price to children. A joint life annuity with return of purchase price meets both needs. However, the trade-off is that this option provides the lowest annuity rate because the insurer bears three risks: paying for two lives sequentially AND returning the principal upon both deaths.

**The Trap:** "Without return of purchase price" provides the highest rate but fails the capital return requirement. The single-life option with return doesn't cover the husband after her death. The annuity certain option provides fixed-term payments but doesn't adapt to actual lifetimes of both spouses. Understanding the inverse relationship between guarantees and payout rates is essential.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Annuity option selection based on client needs is tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and insurance certifications. The ability to match annuity features to specific client requirements is a practical application question.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For couples, joint life annuity is almost always appropriate. The lower annuity rate is the price of survivor protection. Calculate the break-even: at what point does the total received from a joint life option exceed what would have been received from a higher single-life option? This helps clients make informed decisions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
