<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A woman employee joins a company at age 25 and opts for EPF. Under Budget 2018-19 provisions, what is her EPF contribution rate for the first three years, and what is the employer's contribution rate during the same period?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Employee contributes 8% of basic + DA; employer contributes 12% of basic + DA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Employee contributes 8% of basic + DA; employer contributes 8% of basic + DA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Employee contributes 10% of basic + DA; employer contributes 12% of basic + DA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Employee contributes 12% of basic + DA; employer contributes 12% of basic + DA with government paying the difference]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Budget 2018-19 reduced the EPF contribution rate for women employees to 8% (from the standard 12%) for the first three years of employment, to increase take-home pay and encourage female workforce participation. However, the employer's contribution remains unchanged at 12%.

**The Trap:** Assuming the employer's rate also reduces to 8% is the most common mistake. The reduced rate is a benefit exclusively for the employee — the employer continues to contribute at the standard 12%. The 10% rate applies to specific industries (beedi, jute, brick, etc.) and establishments with <20 employees, not to women employees.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Gender-specific EPF provisions are tested in NISM X-B and in labour law sections of company secretary exams. The distinction between employee categories and industry categories for reduced rates is a nuanced topic.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When onboarding women clients, highlight that the 8% rate means higher take-home pay initially but lower retirement corpus growth. Encourage them to voluntarily contribute the remaining 4% to VPF to maintain the same retirement savings trajectory.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
