<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An employee contributes Rs. 3,00,000 per year to EPF (including VPF). From April 2021, what portion of the interest earned is taxable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Interest earned on contributions exceeding Rs. 2,50,000 per year (i.e., interest on Rs. 50,000) is taxable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The entire interest earned on Rs. 3,00,000 is taxable since the contribution exceeds Rs. 2,50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No interest is taxable since EPF enjoys EEE status]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Interest earned on contributions exceeding Rs. 1,50,000 per year is taxable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** From April 2021, interest on EPF contributions (EPF + VPF combined) exceeding Rs. 2,50,000 per year is taxable at the applicable income tax slab rate. The interest on contributions up to Rs. 2,50,000 remains tax-free. So for Rs. 3,00,000 contribution, only the interest earned on the excess Rs. 50,000 is taxable, not the entire interest.

**The Trap:** Thinking that once the threshold is breached, ALL interest becomes taxable is the biggest trap. The taxation applies only to interest on the excess amount. The Rs. 1,50,000 threshold option confuses the 80C deduction limit with the EPF interest taxation threshold. The EEE status is no longer unconditional for high contributors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This 2021 amendment is heavily tested in NISM X-B and income tax certifications. It was introduced to curb the tax benefit for high-income individuals who would contribute large amounts to VPF. The threshold is Rs. 5 lakh if there is no employer contribution.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For high-income clients contributing to VPF above Rs. 2.5 lakh, compare the after-tax return of VPF with other instruments like PPF (which remains fully EEE up to Rs. 1.5 lakh) and debt mutual funds. The VPF advantage diminishes once interest on excess contributions is taxed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
