<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the PMVVY (Pradhan Mantri Vaya Vandana Yojana) is INCORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMVVY is operated by LIC with a 10-year scheme tenure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Loan facility is available after 3 years of holding, up to 75% of purchase price]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[New investments in PMVVY are currently open and available for subscription]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[On premature surrender, 98% of the purchase price is returned]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** PMVVY was closed for new investments after March 2023. While the existing policies continue to operate for their 10-year term, no new subscriptions can be made. All other statements are correct: LIC operates it, tenure is 10 years, loan up to 75% after 3 years, and 98% return on premature surrender.

**The Trap:** Candidates who studied older material may not know about the March 2023 closure. The scheme was very popular and frequently referenced in study materials, making it easy to assume it's still open. This tests current awareness alongside product knowledge.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PMVVY features are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and insurance certification exams. Post-closure, questions may focus on comparing PMVVY with alternative products like SCSS for senior citizens.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For senior citizen clients who missed the PMVVY window, recommend SCSS as the closest alternative for guaranteed income. SCSS offers quarterly interest payments, 80C deduction, and is currently available. Also consider RBI Floating Rate Savings Bonds (2020) as a complement.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
