<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Anita is 62 years old and has just retired from a private sector company with a total retirement corpus of Rs. 2,00,00,000 (Rs. 2 crore). She owns a house and has no outstanding loans. Her monthly household expenses are Rs. 80,000. She wants to generate a steady monthly income while preserving her capital for at least 25 years. She is considering multiple distribution options: annuities from an insurance company, SWP from mutual funds, SCSS, POMIS, FD laddering, and possibly a reverse mortgage on her property (valued at Rs. 1.5 crore). She has no other source of income. Her husband (age 65) is also retired. She wants to allocate her Rs. 2 crore optimally across these products.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Mrs. Anita wants to use FD laddering as part of her income strategy. She plans to invest Rs. 25,00,000 across 5 FDs maturing annually. What is the primary advantage of this laddering approach compared to a single 5-year FD, and what is the tax treatment of FD interest for senior citizens?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Laddering provides higher interest rates than a single FD; FD interest is fully exempt for senior citizens up to Rs. 50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Laddering manages interest rate risk by spreading maturities and provides annual liquidity; FD interest is fully taxable but TDS is deducted only if interest exceeds Rs. 50,000 per year for senior citizens]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Laddering guarantees higher returns through reinvestment at higher rates; FD interest is exempt under Section 80TTB with no TDS]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Laddering eliminates interest rate risk entirely; FD interest for senior citizens is taxed at a flat 10%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** FD laddering spreads maturities across different years, providing two key benefits: (1) Interest rate risk management — as each FD matures, it can be reinvested at prevailing rates, capturing rate increases. (2) Annual liquidity — each maturity provides access to principal without premature withdrawal penalties. FD interest for senior citizens is fully taxable as income, but TDS is deducted only when interest exceeds Rs. 50,000 per year (the higher threshold for seniors vs Rs. 40,000 for others). Section 80TTB provides a deduction of up to Rs. 50,000, but the interest is still part of total income.

**The Trap:** Laddering does NOT guarantee higher returns — it manages risk, not returns. It also doesn't eliminate interest rate risk entirely — it only mitigates it through diversification of maturity dates. FD interest is NOT exempt for seniors — the 80TTB deduction reduces taxable income but doesn't exempt the interest itself. The flat 10% rate is for TDS, not the final tax rate.

**Cross-Exam Context:** FD laddering as a retirement income strategy is tested in NISM X-B and financial planning certifications. The distinction between TDS threshold, 80TTB deduction, and actual tax liability on FD interest is frequently tested.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Mrs. Anita, ladder FDs across 1-5 year terms, reinvesting each maturity at prevailing rates. Combine laddering with SCSS and POMIS for a multi-layered guaranteed income floor. File Form 15H if her total income is below the taxable limit to avoid TDS.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
