<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the Unified Pension Scheme (UPS), what is the assured pension payout for a government employee who has completed 25 years of qualifying service?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[50% of the average basic pay drawn over the last 12 months before retirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% of the last drawn basic pay at the time of retirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[60% of the average basic pay drawn over the last 12 months before retirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% of the average basic pay plus dearness allowance drawn over the last 12 months]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The UPS provides an assured payout of 50% of the average basic pay drawn over the last 12 months before retirement, applicable for employees with 25 or more years of qualifying service. The payout is proportionate for those with 10-25 years.

**The Trap:** "Last drawn basic pay" vs "12-month average basic pay" is the key distinction. UPS specifically uses the 12-month average, not the last drawn. Also, the calculation is on basic pay only, not basic pay + DA, even though DA is part of the contribution base.

**Cross-Exam Context:** UPS is a relatively new scheme (effective April 1, 2025) and may appear in NISM X-B as a current affairs topic. It contrasts with NPS and OPS (Old Pension Scheme), making comparative questions likely.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising government employees choosing between NPS and UPS, emphasize that UPS is irrevocable once opted. The guaranteed 50% payout may appeal to risk-averse clients, but NPS could potentially deliver more for those with a higher risk appetite and longer service horizon.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
