<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the SCSS (Senior Citizens Savings Scheme) eligibility for a person who has taken voluntary retirement at age 56?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not eligible since the minimum age for SCSS is 60 years with no exceptions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Eligible since VRS retirees aged 55 and above can invest, but the account must be opened within one month of receiving retirement benefits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Eligible since VRS retirees aged 50 and above can invest at any time after retirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Eligible but can invest only up to the amount received as retirement benefits, with no maximum cap]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCSS allows early access for individuals aged 55+ who have retired under VRS (Voluntary Retirement Scheme) or superannuation, provided the account is opened within one month of receiving retirement benefits. The standard age is 60+. Defence personnel get an even lower threshold of 50+. The maximum investment limit is Rs. 30 lakh regardless of retirement benefits received.

**The Trap:** The "no exceptions" option ignores the VRS/superannuation/defence provisions. The age 50 option confuses the defence personnel exception with the VRS exception. The "no maximum cap" option ignores the Rs. 30 lakh limit. The one-month deadline for opening the account is a frequently missed detail.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SCSS eligibility conditions are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and in banking certification exams. The one-month window for VRS retirees is a commonly tested time-bound condition.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a client is planning VRS, advise them to have SCSS documentation ready before receiving retirement benefits. The one-month window is strict and missing it means waiting until age 60. Also ensure the investment doesn't exceed Rs. 30 lakh.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
