<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Anita is 62 years old and has just retired from a private sector company with a total retirement corpus of Rs. 2,00,00,000 (Rs. 2 crore). She owns a house and has no outstanding loans. Her monthly household expenses are Rs. 80,000. She wants to generate a steady monthly income while preserving her capital for at least 25 years. She is considering multiple distribution options: annuities from an insurance company, SWP from mutual funds, SCSS, POMIS, FD laddering, and possibly a reverse mortgage on her property (valued at Rs. 1.5 crore). She has no other source of income. Her husband (age 65) is also retired. She wants to allocate her Rs. 2 crore optimally across these products.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Mrs. Anita also wants to invest in POMIS jointly with her husband for guaranteed monthly income. Considering her overall allocation strategy, what is the maximum she can invest in POMIS (joint account), and what are the premature withdrawal penalties if she needs funds before the 5-year maturity?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 9 lakh joint; penalty 2% if withdrawn in first 3 years, 1% between 3-5 years; no withdrawal allowed in first year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 15 lakh joint; penalty 2% deduction from principal if withdrawn between 1-3 years, 1% between 3-5 years; no premature withdrawal in the first year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 15 lakh joint; no premature withdrawal penalty since she is a senior citizen]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximum Rs. 18 lakh joint (Rs. 9 lakh each); penalty 1.5% flat for any premature withdrawal]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** POMIS joint account maximum is Rs. 15 lakh (single account: Rs. 9 lakh). Maturity period is 5 years. Premature withdrawal penalties: 2% deducted from principal if closed between 1-3 years, 1% between 3-5 years. No premature withdrawal is allowed in the first year. There is no senior citizen exemption from these penalties. The minimum investment is Rs. 1,000.

**The Trap:** The Rs. 9 lakh is the single account limit, not joint. Rs. 18 lakh (2 × 9 lakh) seems logical but is incorrect — joint accounts have a separate limit of Rs. 15 lakh. Senior citizens do NOT get penalty exemptions on POMIS premature withdrawal. The 1.5% flat penalty is fabricated. The penalty structure (2% for 1-3 years, 1% for 3-5 years) mirrors SCSS but with different specific percentages.

**Cross-Exam Context:** POMIS limits, penalties, and features are tested in NISM X-A, X-B, and post office scheme certifications. Comparing POMIS penalties with SCSS penalties (1.5% for 1-2 years, 1% for 2-5 years) is a common comparative question.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Mrs. Anita's Rs. 2 crore allocation, POMIS at Rs. 15 lakh provides roughly Rs. 9,000-10,000 per month at current rates. Combined with SCSS (Rs. 30 lakh), FD laddering (Rs. 25 lakh), annuity (Rs. 50 lakh), and SWP (Rs. 60 lakh), she can create a diversified income stream covering her Rs. 80,000 monthly need with buffer for inflation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
