<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Retirement Products - Accumulation and Distribution_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An NPS subscriber aged 60 has a total corpus of Rs. 10,00,000 at the time of normal exit. Which of the following correctly describes the withdrawal rules applicable to this corpus size?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The subscriber can withdraw the entire corpus as a lump sum since it is below Rs. 12 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The subscriber must use at least 40% for annuity and can take 60% as lump sum]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The subscriber can take a maximum lump sum of Rs. 6,00,000 and must use the remaining Rs. 4,00,000 to purchase an annuity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The subscriber must use at least 80% for annuity since the corpus is less than Rs. 12 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** At normal exit (age 60), NPS has three corpus-based rules: (1) If corpus ≤ Rs. 8 lakh: full lump sum withdrawal allowed. (2) If corpus is between Rs. 8-12 lakh: maximum lump sum of Rs. 6 lakh, rest must be used for annuity. (3) If corpus > Rs. 12 lakh: minimum 20% annuity (40% for government), rest as lump sum. Since Rs. 10 lakh falls in the Rs. 8-12 lakh band, maximum lump sum is Rs. 6 lakh, remaining Rs. 4 lakh goes to annuity.

**The Trap:** The Rs. 8-12 lakh band is the most commonly overlooked rule. Many candidates only remember "full withdrawal below Rs. 8 lakh" and "20% annuity above Rs. 12 lakh" and miss this intermediate band. The 80% annuity rule applies to premature exit, not normal exit.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPS exit rules with corpus-based thresholds are a favorite in NISM X-B. The three-tier structure (≤8 lakh, 8-12 lakh, >12 lakh) is unique to normal exit and is distinct from premature exit rules (≤5 lakh for full withdrawal).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients whose NPS corpus is approaching the Rs. 8 lakh threshold, timing the exit carefully matters. A corpus of Rs. 7.9 lakh allows full withdrawal, but Rs. 8.1 lakh triggers the intermediate rule. Consider whether deferral or additional contributions change the outcome favorably.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
