<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A debt fund holds a significant portion of its portfolio in bonds of a single corporate group. During an economic slowdown, the group faces financial stress. Which combination of risks is this fund MOST exposed to?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Currency risk and inflation risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Interest rate risk and political risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk and concentration risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Liquidity risk and re-investment risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The fund faces credit risk because the corporate group is under financial stress and may default on its bond obligations. It also faces concentration risk because a significant portion of the portfolio is allocated to a single group. If the group defaults, the concentrated exposure magnifies the loss impact on the fund's NAV. These two risks compound each other.

**The Trap:** While the fund may also face liquidity risk (stressed bonds are hard to sell), the PRIMARY risks described in the scenario are credit and concentration risk. Currency risk is irrelevant for domestic debt funds. Political risk and inflation risk are macro-level risks, not specific to this scenario.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This scenario mirrors real events like the IL&FS crisis (2018) and DHFL/Reliance Home Finance issues where concentrated debt fund holdings in stressed groups caused significant NAV erosion. SEBI's investment limits (max 10% in single issuer) are designed to prevent extreme concentration risk.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before recommending a debt fund, always check its portfolio for concentration in any single issuer or group. A fund yielding 1-2% more than peers might be achieving this through concentrated positions in lower-rated issuers -- a dangerous combination. Diversified holdings across multiple issuers are essential for managing credit risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
