<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera (age 48) was recently widowed after her husband's sudden demise. She has received an insurance payout of Rs. 1,50,00,000 (Rs. 1.5 crore). She receives a pension of Rs. 35,000 per month from her late husband's employer. Meera has two children — the elder child (age 20) is currently in college, and the younger child (age 16) will need higher education funding in 2 years. Meera owns her house outright with no outstanding loan. Her existing investments include: Rs. 25,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 10,00,000 in fixed deposits, and Rs. 5,00,000 in physical gold. Before her husband's death, the couple had been jointly assessed as having an Aggressive risk profile. Meera's monthly household expenses are Rs. 65,000. She approaches her investment adviser Anand for guidance on managing the insurance corpus and restructuring her portfolio.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> After completing the reassessment, Anand determines that Meera's new risk profile is Conservative-Moderate. Considering her total investible assets (existing investments plus insurance payout of approximately Rs. 1,90,00,000), which allocation approach would BEST suit her revised profile and circumstances?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% equity, 20% sector funds, 10% gold, 10% debt, 10% liquid — following the aggressive model]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in bank fixed deposits for complete safety since she cannot afford any losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A conservative-moderate allocation with a significant portion in income-generating debt instruments (FDs, MIS, debt funds), moderate equity (15-20%) for long-term growth, and adequate liquid reserves]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[35% equity, 10% sector, 15% gold, 30% debt, 10% liquid — following the moderate model for a young married family]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Meera's conservative-moderate profile, combined with her need for regular income (Rs. 30,000/month deficit), near-term education goals, and single pension income, calls for an allocation heavily weighted toward income-generating debt instruments. The model for a couple in their 70s (conservative-moderate) provides a useful reference: 15% equity index, 5% gold, 35% debt hybrid/MIS/SCSS, 30% debt/FD, 15% liquid. While Meera is younger (48), her circumstances (single income, dependents, income gap) warrant a similar conservative-moderate approach with emphasis on income generation.
**The Trap:** Option A applies the old aggressive profile, ignoring the reassessment. Option B is too extreme — 100% FDs would mean lower returns and no growth, which Meera needs for her remaining 12+ years of expenses. Option D applies a model meant for a young dual-income family, which doesn't match Meera's single-income, high-expense reality.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Matching changed life circumstances to revised asset allocation is a core competency tested in NISM Series X-B. The ability to adapt model portfolios to specific client situations goes beyond memorizing fixed percentages.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Meera, consider: Rs. 50-60 lakh in income-generating instruments (SCSS if she qualifies via husband's pension, POMIS, debt funds with SWP) for monthly income; Rs. 20-25 lakh earmarked for children's education in short-term instruments; Rs. 30-35 lakh in conservative hybrid/balanced funds for moderate growth; and Rs. 15-20 lakh in equity index funds for long-term inflation protection. Keep Rs. 10-15 lakh in liquid funds as emergency reserves.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
