<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A client whose primary investment objective is 'regular income' should be advised to invest primarily in:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity shares and real estate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Fixed deposits, debt funds, and rental real estate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cash, bank savings accounts, and ultra-short-term funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold ETFs and sector mutual funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For the regular income objective, suitable instruments include deposits, debt funds, and real estate (for rental income). Equity and gold are primarily growth-oriented. Cash and bank savings provide liquidity, not regular income. The matching is: Growth → equity/real estate/gold; Regular income → deposits/debt/real estate; Liquidity → cash/bank/short-term MF; Capital preservation → cash/bank/ultra-short-term.
**The Trap:** Option A (equity and real estate) serves the growth objective, not income. While real estate can provide rental income, equity shares provide irregular dividends, not dependable regular income. Option C describes the liquidity objective, not income.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Investment objective-to-product matching is a fundamental concept tested in NISM Series X-A, X-B, V-A, and V-B. The ability to match objectives to suitable products is core to the suitability requirement.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For regular income needs, consider a Systematic Withdrawal Plan (SWP) from a debt or hybrid fund. It provides regular monthly/quarterly payouts and is more tax-efficient than interest from FDs for investors in higher tax brackets.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
