<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following factors is most directly within the control of a fund manager in influencing fund performance?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Prevailing market interest rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Government fiscal policy changes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Stock selection and portfolio construction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Global commodity price movements]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Among the given options, stock selection and portfolio construction are directly within the fund manager's control. The fund manager's skill in identifying undervalued stocks, constructing a well-diversified portfolio, and making timely allocation decisions directly impacts fund performance. Market interest rates, government policy, and global commodity prices are external factors beyond the manager's control.

**The Trap:** While external factors like interest rates, fiscal policy, and commodity prices significantly affect fund returns, the question asks about what is within the fund manager's CONTROL. A skilled fund manager can outperform despite adverse external conditions through superior security selection and asset allocation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Fund manager skill is measured through Alpha -- the excess return generated beyond what the benchmark delivers. A positive alpha indicates the fund manager has added value through active management. This distinguishes active fund management from passive (index) investing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When evaluating actively managed funds for clients, look at the fund manager's track record across market cycles. Consistent alpha generation over 5-7 years (not just in bull markets) indicates genuine skill. Also check if the same fund manager is still managing the fund.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
