<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Strategic Asset Allocation is BEST described as an approach that:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Is long-term, goal-aligned, reviewed periodically, and not changed based on short-term market performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Involves making market calls to overweight or underweight asset classes based on market outlook]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Uses pre-defined valuation trigger models to automatically shift between asset classes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is suitable only for seasoned investors with large investible surpluses]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Strategic Asset Allocation is a long-term approach aligned with the client's goals. It is reviewed periodically and rebalanced to the original allocation, but is not changed based on short-term market performance. It provides discipline and consistency.
**The Trap:** Option B describes Tactical Asset Allocation (market calls, overweight/underweight). Option C describes Dynamic Asset Allocation (pre-defined models, valuation triggers). Option D describes a characteristic of Tactical AA, which requires expertise and large surpluses. Students must clearly distinguish between the three types.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The three types of asset allocation — Strategic, Tactical, and Dynamic — are a key topic in both NISM Series X-A and X-B. Series V-A touches on basic asset allocation concepts.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Strategic AA is right for 90% of retail clients in India. Most clients don't have the expertise or temperament for tactical calls. Set the allocation based on goals and risk profile, then rebalance annually — that's the golden rule.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
