<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Prepayment risk in a debt fund arises when:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Borrowers repay their loans earlier than scheduled, forcing reinvestment at potentially lower rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager pays higher expenses than planned]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investors redeem their units before the fund's maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The government prepays its debt obligations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Prepayment risk occurs when borrowers repay their debt obligations (loans, mortgage-backed securities) before the scheduled maturity. This is common when interest rates fall -- borrowers refinance at lower rates. For the fund holding these instruments, the principal is returned early and must be reinvested at the now-lower prevailing rates, reducing the portfolio's yield.

**The Trap:** Prepayment risk is NOT about investors redeeming units from the fund (that is redemption/liquidity risk) or about fund expenses. It is specifically about the underlying borrowers repaying ahead of schedule. It is a form of reinvestment risk triggered by the borrower's action, not the investor's.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Prepayment risk is particularly relevant for funds holding securitized debt (like mortgage-backed securities or loan pass-through certificates). SEBI's regulations on securitized debt instruments in mutual fund portfolios address this risk through diversification and quality requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients investing in funds holding securitized instruments or corporate bonds with call options should understand that in a falling rate environment, these instruments may get prepaid, reducing the fund's yield advantage over government securities.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
