<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Spread risk in debt mutual funds refers to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk of the fund's NAV spreading too widely from day to day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The risk that the yield difference between corporate bonds and government securities may widen]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk of the fund's portfolio being spread across too many securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk of bid-ask spread increasing in equity markets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Spread risk (also called credit spread risk) is the risk that the yield spread between corporate bonds and risk-free government securities may widen. When spreads widen, corporate bond prices fall relative to government bonds. This can happen during economic downturns or credit crises when investors demand higher compensation for holding corporate debt.

**The Trap:** Spread risk has nothing to do with NAV volatility, portfolio diversification, or equity bid-ask spreads. It is specifically about the differential in yields between different credit quality bonds. Even if a bond's credit rating remains unchanged, its price can fall if the market demands a higher spread for that rating category.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Spread risk is distinct from credit risk. Credit risk is about actual default; spread risk is about market perception changing. During the COVID-19 crisis in March 2020, credit spreads widened dramatically even for high-quality issuers, causing NAV declines in debt funds that held corporate bonds.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During periods of market stress, even high-quality corporate bond funds can underperform gilt funds because credit spreads widen. For extremely risk-averse clients seeking debt fund safety, gilt funds carry no credit or spread risk -- only interest rate risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
