<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C2_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera (age 48) was recently widowed after her husband's sudden demise. She has received an insurance payout of Rs. 1,50,00,000 (Rs. 1.5 crore). She receives a pension of Rs. 35,000 per month from her late husband's employer. Meera has two children — the elder child (age 20) is currently in college, and the younger child (age 16) will need higher education funding in 2 years. Meera owns her house outright with no outstanding loan. Her existing investments include: Rs. 25,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 10,00,000 in fixed deposits, and Rs. 5,00,000 in physical gold. Before her husband's death, the couple had been jointly assessed as having an Aggressive risk profile. Meera's monthly household expenses are Rs. 65,000. She approaches her investment adviser Anand for guidance on managing the insurance corpus and restructuring her portfolio.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> For the younger child's higher education goal which is 2 years away, which investment approach for a portion of the insurance corpus would be MOST appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest in small-cap equity funds for maximum growth in 2 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest in a dynamic asset allocation fund to benefit from market valuation triggers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Park in short-term debt funds or fixed deposits to ensure capital preservation for this near-term goal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest in gold ETFs since gold is a safe-haven asset]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The younger child's education funding is needed in just 2 years — this is a near-term, non-negotiable goal. For capital preservation with a short time horizon, the appropriate instruments are short-term debt funds, ultra-short-term funds, or fixed deposits. The investment objective mapping shows: Capital preservation → cash/bank/ultra-short-term. Equity and gold carry too much short-term volatility for a 2-year goal.
**The Trap:** Option A (small-cap equity) is extremely risky for a 2-year horizon — small-caps can lose 40-50% in a bear market. Option B (dynamic AA) still has equity exposure and market timing elements unsuitable for a critical near-term goal. Option D (gold) is volatile in the short term despite being a "safe haven" — gold prices can fluctuate 15-20% in a year.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The principle of matching time horizon to product risk is fundamental across all NISM certifications. Series X-B specifically tests this in the context of goal-based financial planning.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For education goals within 2-3 years, use a combination of bank FDs (for certainty) and short-duration debt funds (for slight return enhancement). Avoid any equity exposure. If the amount needed is Rs. 15-20 lakh for education, you cannot afford even a 10% loss on that corpus.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
