<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI IA Regulations, which of the following events would MOST likely trigger a mandatory review of a client's risk profile?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A 10% rise in the Nifty 50 index over the past quarter]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The RBI changing the repo rate by 25 basis points]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The client's spouse losing their job, reducing the family's income by 40%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A new mutual fund scheme being launched by a leading AMC]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI requires risk profiles to be updated periodically, especially on life events such as family changes, income changes, or asset changes. A spouse losing their job is a major income change that directly impacts risk capacity. Market movements and new product launches do not change a client's risk profile.
**The Trap:** Option A (market rise) might seem relevant because a rising market could increase portfolio value and thus risk capacity. However, market movements are external events — risk profiling focuses on the client's personal circumstances, not market conditions. Similarly, Option B (repo rate change) affects the economy, not the individual's risk profile.
**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI IA Regulation requirements for periodic review and life-event-based reassessment are tested in both X-A and X-B. Understanding the distinction between personal life events and market events is crucial.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Build a "life event alert" system with your clients. Ask them to inform you immediately about: job changes, marriage/divorce, childbirth, retirement, inheritance, major medical events, or significant asset purchases/sales. Each of these may require risk profile reassessment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
