<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Tactical Asset Allocation involves making market calls to overweight or underweight certain asset classes. This approach is most suitable for:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[First-time investors who are new to financial markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative investors who prefer capital preservation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All investors regardless of their experience or surplus]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Seasoned investors with large investible surpluses]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Tactical Asset Allocation involves actively overweighting or underweighting asset classes based on market outlook. This approach is suitable for seasoned investors with large investible surpluses who have the expertise to make market timing calls and the financial cushion to absorb potential losses from incorrect calls.
**The Trap:** Option C ("all investors") is tempting for students who believe active management is universally beneficial. However, tactical calls require market expertise and can result in significant losses if wrong — making it unsuitable for inexperienced or resource-constrained investors.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A and X-B differentiate between Strategic, Tactical, and Dynamic AA. Series V-B (Research Analyst) also covers market-timing aspects relevant to tactical allocation.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a client insists on making tactical calls, ensure they do it with only a small portion (10-20%) of their portfolio. The core allocation should remain strategic. This "core-satellite" approach satisfies the client's desire to be active while protecting the bulk of their wealth.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
