<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_57" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In finance theory, risk is classified into systematic risk (market risk) and unsystematic risk (company-specific risk). ________, and therefore investors are only rewarded for bearing systematic risk.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Systematic risk cannot be reduced through diversification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Systematic risk can be reduced by diversifying across multiple stocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Systematic risk is company-specific and affects only individual securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Systematic risk is completely eliminated by hedging with derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Systematic risk (also called market risk or non-diversifiable risk) affects the entire market -- factors like interest rate changes, inflation, and political events. It CANNOT be eliminated through diversification. Unsystematic risk (company-specific, diversifiable) can be reduced by holding a diversified portfolio. Since investors can easily eliminate unsystematic risk by diversifying, the market does not compensate them for it -- rewards come only for bearing systematic (non-diversifiable) risk.

**The Trap:** Option B directly contradicts the definition -- systematic risk is the one that CANNOT be diversified away. Option C describes unsystematic risk (company-specific). Option D is misleading -- while derivatives can hedge specific market exposures, they cannot completely eliminate all systematic risk, and the statement oversimplifies the concept.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the systematic vs. unsystematic distinction is foundational for CAPM, Beta, and all risk-adjusted performance measures. Beta measures systematic risk; standard deviation measures total risk (both systematic and unsystematic).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Systematic = non-diversifiable = market-wide. Unsystematic = diversifiable = company-specific. Investors are rewarded only for systematic risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
