<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rajendra has Rs. 30,00,000 invested with 60% in equity and 40% in debt. After a strong bull run, his equity portion has grown to Rs. 24,00,000 while debt remains at Rs. 12,00,000. His target allocation is still 60:40. To rebalance, Rajendra should:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell Rs. 6,00,000 of equity and move it to debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sell Rs. 2,40,000 of equity and move it to debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Add Rs. 6,00,000 of fresh investment to debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Do nothing since the portfolio has grown in value]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Total portfolio = Rs. 24,00,000 + Rs. 12,00,000 = Rs. 36,00,000. Target: 60% equity = Rs. 21,60,000; 40% debt = Rs. 14,40,000. Current equity = Rs. 24,00,000. Excess equity = Rs. 24,00,000 - Rs. 21,60,000 = Rs. 2,40,000. Sell Rs. 2,40,000 from equity and move to debt to restore 60:40.
**The Trap:** Rs. 6,00,000 (Option A) is the difference between current equity (Rs. 24,00,000) and original equity (Rs. 18,00,000) — i.e., the gain amount. But rebalancing targets the new total, not the original amount. Option D ignores the need to rebalance entirely.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Rebalancing calculations are commonly tested in NISM Series X-B. The ability to compute target allocations on a changed portfolio value is a practical skill expected of investment advisers.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rebalancing forces you to book profits in the outperforming asset class and invest in the underperforming one. It feels counterintuitive but enforces discipline. Consider tax implications — use systematic transfer plans (STPs) to spread the rebalancing over a few months.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
