<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera (age 48) was recently widowed after her husband's sudden demise. She has received an insurance payout of Rs. 1,50,00,000 (Rs. 1.5 crore). She receives a pension of Rs. 35,000 per month from her late husband's employer. Meera has two children — the elder child (age 20) is currently in college, and the younger child (age 16) will need higher education funding in 2 years. Meera owns her house outright with no outstanding loan. Her existing investments include: Rs. 25,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 10,00,000 in fixed deposits, and Rs. 5,00,000 in physical gold. Before her husband's death, the couple had been jointly assessed as having an Aggressive risk profile. Meera's monthly household expenses are Rs. 65,000. She approaches her investment adviser Anand for guidance on managing the insurance corpus and restructuring her portfolio.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> When reassessing Meera's risk profile, which combination of factors would Anand need to consider MOST carefully?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only her total asset value, since it has increased significantly with the insurance payout]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Her single pension income of Rs. 35,000/month against expenses of Rs. 65,000/month, two dependents needing education funding, and her changed emotional state]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the performance of her existing equity mutual fund portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only her age and the number of years to retirement]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI IA Regulation 16 requires obtaining: age, investment objectives, time frames, income, existing investments, innate ability, and loan details. For Meera, the critical factors are: (1) Income gap — pension Rs. 35,000 vs. expenses Rs. 65,000, creating a monthly deficit of Rs. 30,000; (2) Two dependents needing education funding; (3) Changed emotional/psychological state after bereavement. A holistic assessment covering all these factors is essential.
**The Trap:** Options A, C, and D each focus on only one factor. Risk profiling requires a comprehensive assessment. Option A ignores the income-expense gap — having Rs. 1.5 crore sounds like a lot, but at Rs. 30,000 monthly deficit, she needs Rs. 3,60,000 per year just to cover the gap, plus education costs. Looking at assets alone is dangerously incomplete.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The holistic nature of risk profiling (multiple factors, not just one) is emphasized in both NISM Series X-A and X-B. SEBI's requirement to obtain multiple data points (age, income, objectives, etc.) reinforces this.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Calculate the income gap first: Rs. 65,000 - Rs. 35,000 = Rs. 30,000/month = Rs. 3,60,000/year. This ongoing deficit must be met from investment income. Only after securing this basic need should you plan for education goals and growth.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
