<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[R-squared (R²) of a mutual fund measures:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[How closely the fund's returns track the benchmark returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund's total risk relative to the market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The excess return generated by the fund manager]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund's return per unit of risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** R-squared (R²) measures the percentage of a fund's return movements that can be explained by movements in its benchmark index. It ranges from 0 to 1 (or 0% to 100%). An R² of 0.95 means 95% of the fund's return variability is explained by the benchmark's movements. Index funds typically have R² close to 1, while actively managed funds may have lower R².

**The Trap:** R² does NOT measure total risk (that is standard deviation), excess return (that is alpha), or return per unit of risk (that is Sharpe or Treynor ratio). R² indicates correlation with the benchmark, not performance. A fund can have high R² but still underperform its benchmark.

**Cross-Exam Context:** R² is important for interpreting beta. If R² is low, the beta value is less reliable because the benchmark explains only a small portion of the fund's return variation. The Treynor ratio and beta are most meaningful when R² is high (above 0.70-0.80).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When evaluating an index fund or ETF, R² should be very close to 1. If it is significantly lower, the fund may not be tracking its benchmark well. For actively managed funds, a moderate R² is expected -- a very high R² might indicate the fund is essentially a closet indexer charging active management fees.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
