<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA["Cash drag" in a mutual fund refers to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The delay in processing cash redemption requests]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The negative impact on fund returns due to holding excessive cash in the portfolio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The drag on market performance due to excessive cash inflows]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The cost of converting investments to cash for meeting redemptions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Cash drag refers to the reduction in a fund's overall returns caused by holding a portion of the portfolio in cash or cash equivalents (which earn low returns) rather than being fully invested in the fund's primary asset class. An equity fund holding 10% cash in a bull market will underperform because that cash portion earns minimal returns compared to equities.

**The Trap:** Cash drag is NOT about redemption processing delays or market-wide impacts. It is specifically about the opportunity cost of holding cash within the fund. Fund managers maintain some cash for meeting redemptions, but excessive cash holdings create a performance drag, especially in rising markets.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Cash drag is one reason why index funds may slightly underperform their benchmark index. The index is always 100% invested, but the fund must hold some cash for operational purposes. This contributes to tracking error alongside expense ratio and transaction costs.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When comparing two funds in the same category, check their cash holdings in the portfolio disclosure. A fund consistently holding 8-10% cash will underperform in bull markets. However, some cash can be strategic -- it provides a cushion during market corrections and allows the manager to buy on dips.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
