<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram (age 32) is a software engineer earning Rs. 18,00,000 per annum. His wife Priya (age 30) also works and earns Rs. 8,00,000 per annum. They have one child aged 2 years, who is their only dependent. They own a house valued at Rs. 40,00,000 with an outstanding home loan of Rs. 15,00,000. Their current investments include: Rs. 5,00,000 in bank fixed deposits, Rs. 3,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 2,00,000 in PPF, and an emergency fund of Rs. 1,50,000. Their financial goals are: child's higher education (16 years away), retirement (28 years away), and a car upgrade (2 years away). Vikram completes a risk profiling questionnaire administered by his investment adviser Suresh, and scores 72 out of 100. Suresh must now analyze this profile to make suitable investment recommendations.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> For Vikram's car upgrade goal which is only 2 years away, which category of investment products would be MOST suitable, regardless of his overall aggressive risk profile?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity mutual funds and sector funds, since Vikram has an aggressive profile]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold ETFs, as gold provides inflation protection over any time period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Short-term debt funds, ultra-short-term funds, or fixed deposits, matching the short time horizon]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A mix of equity and debt in the aggressive model portfolio ratio of 70:30]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For a goal only 2 years away, capital preservation and liquidity are priorities regardless of the client's overall risk profile. Short-term debt funds, ultra-short-term funds, or FDs match the investment objective of capital preservation for near-term goals. The investment objective mapping shows: Capital preservation → cash/bank/ultra-short-term; Liquidity → cash/bank/short-term MF.
**The Trap:** Option A is the most dangerous trap — applying the overall aggressive profile to a short-term goal. An aggressive profile guides long-term allocation, but short-term goals must always be conservatively invested. Option D makes the same mistake by applying the model portfolio ratio to a 2-year goal.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Goal-based product selection is a core concept in NISM Series X-B. The principle that time horizon overrides risk profile for product selection is tested across X-A and V-A as well.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never invest money needed within 2-3 years in equity, regardless of the client's risk profile. A 30-40% equity crash just before the goal date could be devastating. For Vikram's car fund, a simple recurring deposit or ultra-short-term fund is the right choice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
