<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Re-investment risk in a debt mutual fund refers to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk that the fund manager may invest in low-rated securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk that the fund may not be able to meet redemption requests]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The risk that coupon payments and maturity proceeds may have to be reinvested at lower interest rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk that the NAV may fall due to market conditions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Re-investment risk arises when cash flows from a debt instrument (coupon payments, principal repayment at maturity) need to be reinvested, but prevailing interest rates have fallen. The investor or fund manager is forced to reinvest at lower rates, reducing overall portfolio returns. This is the opposite side of interest rate risk.

**The Trap:** Re-investment risk is the mirror image of interest rate risk. When rates fall, bond prices rise (good for capital gains) but reinvestment opportunities offer lower yields (bad for income). Many candidates confuse re-investment risk with credit risk (default risk) or liquidity risk (ability to sell).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Re-investment risk is particularly relevant for target maturity funds and FMPs (Fixed Maturity Plans). These hold bonds to maturity, eliminating interest rate risk on the principal, but coupon reinvestment still faces this risk. SEBI norms require disclosure of this risk in scheme documents.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When interest rates are falling, clients in short-duration funds face re-investment risk as maturing papers get replaced with lower-yielding ones. Consider longer-duration funds during rate-cutting cycles to lock in higher yields.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
