<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Credit risk in the context of debt mutual funds refers to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk that interest rates may change unfavorably]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk that inflation may erode returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The risk that the issuer of a debt instrument may default on interest or principal payments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk that the currency value may depreciate]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Credit risk (also called default risk) is the risk that the issuer of a bond or debt instrument may fail to make timely payment of interest or principal. If a company whose bonds are held by a debt fund defaults, the NAV of the fund falls. This risk is higher for bonds with lower credit ratings (AA, A, BBB) compared to AAA-rated or government securities.

**The Trap:** Credit risk is specific to the issuer's ability to pay, not about market-wide interest rate movements (interest rate risk) or purchasing power erosion (inflation risk). A government security has virtually zero credit risk but still carries interest rate risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI introduced the concept of segregated portfolios (side-pocketing) to address credit events. When a bond in a debt fund's portfolio faces a credit event (downgrade to below investment grade or default), the fund can segregate that security into a separate portfolio. This protects existing investors from being forced to sell at distressed prices.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When recommending credit risk funds (which invest in lower-rated papers for higher yields), clearly explain to clients that higher yield comes with higher default risk. Always diversify across multiple debt fund categories rather than concentrating in credit risk funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
