<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram (age 32) is a software engineer earning Rs. 18,00,000 per annum. His wife Priya (age 30) also works and earns Rs. 8,00,000 per annum. They have one child aged 2 years, who is their only dependent. They own a house valued at Rs. 40,00,000 with an outstanding home loan of Rs. 15,00,000. Their current investments include: Rs. 5,00,000 in bank fixed deposits, Rs. 3,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 2,00,000 in PPF, and an emergency fund of Rs. 1,50,000. Their financial goals are: child's higher education (16 years away), retirement (28 years away), and a car upgrade (2 years away). Vikram completes a risk profiling questionnaire administered by his investment adviser Suresh, and scores 72 out of 100. Suresh must now analyze this profile to make suitable investment recommendations.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> During the annual portfolio review, Suresh finds that Vikram's equity investments have grown significantly while debt has underperformed. Vikram asks Suresh to increase equity allocation further since "equity is doing well." What should Suresh advise?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Agree with Vikram and increase equity allocation to 90% since he has an aggressive profile]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Move everything to debt since equity markets are likely to correct after a bull run]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rebalance back to the original strategic allocation, as rebalancing should align to risk/return needs, not short-term market performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Do nothing and let the allocation drift with the market since Vikram is young]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Strategic Asset Allocation should not be changed based on short-term market performance. Rebalancing should align the portfolio to the client's risk and return needs. The correct action is to rebalance back to the original allocation — selling some equity (which has grown disproportionately) and buying debt to restore the target ratio.
**The Trap:** Option A follows the client's recency bias — assuming what has done well recently will continue to do well. This is a behavioral trap, not sound advice. Option B is the opposite extreme (market timing). Option D ignores the discipline of rebalancing. Suresh must educate Vikram on why rebalancing matters rather than simply following client wishes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The principle that rebalancing should not be driven by short-term market movements is explicitly stated in the NISM X-B study material. This also connects to behavioral finance concepts (recency bias, herding) tested in Series X-B Chapter 17.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client says "equity is doing well, put more in equity," that's the signal to rebalance in the OPPOSITE direction. The best advisers are those who can say no to clients at the right time. Use data and goal projections to show why the current allocation is already on track.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
