<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Geeta, aged 35, is a government employee with a steady job, no dependents, well-qualified with an MBA, and has good market knowledge. She describes herself as someone who enjoys taking calculated risks. Based on these factors, what risk profile category would BEST describe her?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative-Moderate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Moderate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Aggressive]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Geeta has multiple factors that increase risk appetite: lower age (35), no dependents, steady job (government), well-qualified (MBA), good market knowledge, and a daring psyche (enjoys calculated risks). All factors point clearly toward an Aggressive risk profile. An aggressive investor is experienced, takes an active approach, and is willing to risk a significant portion of assets.
**The Trap:** Students might select Moderate thinking that "calculated risks" implies moderation. However, the question specifies she "enjoys" taking risks, which indicates psychological willingness (high tolerance). Combined with her strong financial factors (steady job, no dependents), she clearly falls in the Aggressive category.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B tests the ability to identify risk profiles from scenario descriptions. Series X-A covers the theoretical framework. This type of scenario-based profiling is a common exam pattern.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Even for clearly aggressive clients, document the risk profiling process thoroughly. If markets crash and the client complains, your documentation of the risk assessment protects both the client and you. SEBI requires this documentation under IA Regulations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
