<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A fund manager follows a "growth" investment style. In which market condition is this style MOST likely to outperform?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[During bull markets when high-growth companies see rapid earnings expansion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[During deep market corrections when all stocks fall sharply]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[During periods of very high interest rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[During periods of economic recession with falling corporate earnings]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Growth investing focuses on companies with above-average earnings growth potential, often at premium valuations. These stocks tend to outperform during bull markets and economic expansion when investor optimism drives up valuations for high-growth companies. The rapid earnings growth justifies and sustains the premium pricing during bullish conditions.

**The Trap:** During market corrections, recessions, or high-interest rate environments, growth stocks often underperform value stocks. High-growth companies trade at elevated P/E ratios, making them more vulnerable to de-rating when sentiment turns negative or when higher interest rates reduce the present value of future earnings.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investment style (growth vs value) significantly impacts fund performance across market cycles. Growth funds tend to outperform in late-cycle bull markets, while value funds tend to outperform during early recoveries and periods of mean reversion. SEBI does not categorize funds by investment style, but understanding style helps explain performance divergence.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help clients understand that no single investment style works all the time. A client invested solely in growth-style funds will face periods of underperformance. Consider blending growth and value funds, or using a flexi-cap fund where the manager can shift between styles based on market conditions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
