<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the 3-grade risk classification system, a client categorized as 'Moderate' would BEST be described as someone who:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Does not like risk at all and prefers only bank accounts and safe instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is highly experienced and takes an active approach to risk with a significant portion of assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Has some investment experience and is willing to risk a part of their assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invests only in government securities and fixed deposits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the 3-grade classification: Conservative investors don't like risk and prefer bank accounts and safe instruments. Moderate investors have some experience and are willing to risk part of their assets. Aggressive investors are experienced, take an active approach, and risk a significant portion of their assets.
**The Trap:** Option A describes a Conservative investor, while Option B describes an Aggressive investor. Option D is a specific investment pattern of a Conservative investor, not a classification description. Students must match the behavioral description to the correct category.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A uses a similar classification for mutual fund suitability. Series X-A and X-B use the 3-grade system as the basis for asset allocation recommendations.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Most Indian retail investors fall into the Moderate category. They want growth but can't stomach large drawdowns. For these clients, balanced advantage funds and hybrid funds often provide the right mix of participation and protection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
