<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A fund house publishes the following advertisement: "Our Flexi Cap Fund delivered 48% return in the last 8 months! Invest now!" As a SEBI-compliant distributor, you should recognize that this advertisement:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is perfectly compliant as it shows the actual return earned]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Should also show the annualized return of 72% for better comparison]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Must also include benchmark comparison, returns for standard periods, and a past performance disclaimer]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Should convert the 8-month return to CAGR for compliance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** While showing 8-month absolute return (48%) is technically correct for a sub-1-year period, SEBI's advertisement guidelines require additional disclosures: (1) comparison with benchmark returns (using TRI), (2) returns for standard periods (1 year, 3 years, 5 years, since inception), and (3) the mandatory disclaimer that past performance may or may not be sustained and is not a guarantee of future results.

**The Trap:** Annualizing to 72% would be a SEBI violation -- sub-1-year returns must NOT be annualized. Converting to CAGR is also non-compliant for sub-1-year periods. Simply showing the actual return without the required additional disclosures is incomplete and non-compliant. The advertisement cherry-picks a favorable short period without providing context.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's advertising guidelines for mutual funds (under SEBI MF Regulations) are strict about return representation. Performance claims must be accompanied by benchmark comparison, standardized period returns, and disclaimers. AMFI has further guidelines on advertisement content that distributors must follow.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Never use non-compliant advertisements or materials to attract clients. Even if a fund house circulates such materials, as a registered distributor, YOU are also responsible for SEBI compliance. Always verify that performance claims include benchmark comparison, standard period returns, and the past performance disclaimer before sharing with clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
