<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram (age 32) is a software engineer earning Rs. 18,00,000 per annum. His wife Priya (age 30) also works and earns Rs. 8,00,000 per annum. They have one child aged 2 years, who is their only dependent. They own a house valued at Rs. 40,00,000 with an outstanding home loan of Rs. 15,00,000. Their current investments include: Rs. 5,00,000 in bank fixed deposits, Rs. 3,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 2,00,000 in PPF, and an emergency fund of Rs. 1,50,000. Their financial goals are: child's higher education (16 years away), retirement (28 years away), and a car upgrade (2 years away). Vikram completes a risk profiling questionnaire administered by his investment adviser Suresh, and scores 72 out of 100. Suresh must now analyze this profile to make suitable investment recommendations.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> If Priya decides to quit her job to focus on childcare, reducing the family income to Rs. 18,00,000, which aspect of Vikram's risk profile would MOST likely change?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[His risk tolerance would decrease because he would become more fearful]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[His risk capacity would decrease due to the loss of one income source and reduction in family earnings]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[His risk perception would change because market conditions would appear more risky]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No aspect would change since Vikram himself is still earning the same salary]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Priya quitting her job is a major income change — the family income drops from Rs. 26,00,000 to Rs. 18,00,000 (a 31% reduction). This directly impacts risk capacity (financial ability to bear losses) because the family now depends on a single income. The number of earning members decreases (a factor that reduces risk appetite). Risk tolerance (psychological willingness) may not change since that is about Vikram's temperament.
**The Trap:** Option A confuses risk tolerance with risk capacity. Vikram's psychology may not change just because Priya stops working. Option D ignores that family financial circumstances (not just individual income) affect risk capacity. Under SEBI IA Regulations, this is exactly the type of life event (income change) that requires risk profile reassessment.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between what changes risk capacity vs. risk tolerance is a key exam concept in both NISM Series X-A and X-B. SEBI IA Regulation requires reassessment on income changes.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When one spouse stops working, immediately reassess: (1) Can the family still meet EMI obligations? (2) Is the emergency fund sufficient for 6 months on single income? (3) Should the asset allocation shift from aggressive to moderate? Don't wait for a scheduled review — this needs immediate attention.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
