<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram (age 32) is a software engineer earning Rs. 18,00,000 per annum. His wife Priya (age 30) also works and earns Rs. 8,00,000 per annum. They have one child aged 2 years, who is their only dependent. They own a house valued at Rs. 40,00,000 with an outstanding home loan of Rs. 15,00,000. Their current investments include: Rs. 5,00,000 in bank fixed deposits, Rs. 3,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 2,00,000 in PPF, and an emergency fund of Rs. 1,50,000. Their financial goals are: child's higher education (16 years away), retirement (28 years away), and a car upgrade (2 years away). Vikram completes a risk profiling questionnaire administered by his investment adviser Suresh, and scores 72 out of 100. Suresh must now analyze this profile to make suitable investment recommendations.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Based on Vikram's risk questionnaire score of 72/100 and his overall financial profile (dual income, low dependents, young age, long-term goals), which risk profile category would BEST describe him under the 3-grade classification?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative — since he has a home loan liability of Rs. 15,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Moderate — since he has a young child to support]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Aggressive — given his high score, dual income, young age, low dependents, and long time horizons]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Conservative-Moderate — since his emergency fund is only Rs. 1,50,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A score of 72/100 is in the upper range, indicating high willingness to take risk. His financial profile supports high risk capacity: dual income (Rs. 26,00,000 combined), young age (32), only one dependent (child), long time horizons (16 and 28 years), and asset ownership. Under the 3-grade classification (Conservative, Moderate, Aggressive), these factors strongly point to an Aggressive profile.
**The Trap:** Options A and D focus on single negative factors (home loan, low emergency fund) while ignoring the overwhelmingly positive profile. Option B correctly identifies a dependent but one child with dual income is not a significant risk-reducing factor. Students must look at the complete picture, not cherry-pick one factor.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B expects candidates to assess risk profiles holistically using multiple factors. Series X-A teaches the theoretical framework. SEBI IA Regulation 16 requires considering all factors together.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A 72/100 score with strong financial fundamentals is clearly aggressive. However, always validate the score with a conversation — ask Vikram how he felt during the March 2020 crash. Questionnaire scores can be misleading if the client hasn't experienced real market stress.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
