<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI Investment Adviser Regulation 16, which of the following is NOT a mandatory requirement for client risk profiling?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The risk profiling process must be objective]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Questionnaires must be fair, clear, and not misleading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The adviser must use a minimum of 25 questions in the risk profiling questionnaire]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser must obtain details of client's age, investment objectives, income, and existing investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI IA Regulation 16 requires: risk profiling before advice, obtaining age, investment objectives, time frames, income, existing investments, innate ability, and loan details. The process must be objective, tools must be fit for purpose, questionnaires must be fair/clear/not misleading with no leading questions. However, SEBI does not mandate a minimum number of questions.
**The Trap:** Option C sounds regulatory and specific (mentioning "25 questions"), which makes it seem authentic. Students who haven't carefully read the regulation may assume SEBI prescribes a minimum number. SEBI focuses on quality and fairness of questions, not quantity.
**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI IA Regulations are heavily tested in both Series X-A and X-B. Series V-A tests basic suitability requirements. Knowledge of specific regulation numbers (like Regulation 16) is expected in X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SEBI also requires that no free trial of advisory services be provided without completing the risk profile first. Additionally, risk profiles must be updated periodically, especially when life events occur — family changes, income changes, or asset changes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
