<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The expense ratio of a mutual fund:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is charged separately to investors at the time of redemption]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Is deducted from the fund's assets daily, reducing the NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Has no impact on the fund's returns to investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is fixed and cannot vary across different fund categories]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The expense ratio (Total Expense Ratio or TER) is deducted from the fund's assets on a daily accrual basis. This means it is automatically reflected in the NAV. A fund with a 2% expense ratio and a gross return of 12% will deliver approximately 10% net return to investors. The expense ratio includes management fees, administrative costs, distributor commissions, and other operating expenses.

**The Trap:** The expense ratio is NOT charged separately to investors at redemption -- it is already embedded in the NAV. It absolutely impacts returns, as higher expenses directly reduce net returns. SEBI has prescribed maximum TER limits that vary by fund category and AUM slab -- so TER is NOT fixed across categories.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's TER regulations (Regulation 52) specify maximum limits: for equity funds, TER ranges from 2.25% (for first Rs. 500 crore AUM) decreasing to 1.05% (above Rs. 50,000 crore AUM). Direct plans have lower TER than regular plans because they exclude distributor commissions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients compare fund returns, ensure they are looking at returns NET of expenses. The NAV already reflects expense deductions, so published returns are post-expense. However, between regular and direct plans, the TER difference of 0.5-1% annually compounds significantly over long periods.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
