<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Arjun's child's college education is 3 years away, and he currently has 70% of the education corpus in equity mutual funds. As an investment adviser, what rebalancing action would you recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maintain the 70% equity allocation since equity gives the best long-term returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Increase equity to 80% to maximize the corpus before the goal date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Gradually shift from equity to debt to protect the corpus as the goal approaches]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Move everything to liquid funds immediately]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As a goal approaches, the equity allocation should be reduced and shifted to debt/fixed-income instruments. This is because the time available to recover from any market downturn is shrinking. With only 3 years to the goal, a significant equity crash could jeopardize the education corpus. Rebalancing should align to risk/return needs, not to benefit from short-term movements.
**The Trap:** Option A ignores the time horizon risk — 70% equity is too aggressive for a 3-year goal. Option B is reckless. Option D is too extreme — moving everything at once may incur significant exit loads and tax, and liquid funds offer lower returns than short-term debt funds. A gradual shift is the prudent approach.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Goal-based rebalancing as a goal approaches is a key concept in NISM Series X-A and X-B. The principle of reducing risk as time horizon shortens is also tested in Series V-A for mutual fund suitability.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use a glide path approach: at 5 years from a goal, start reducing equity by 10-15% per year. By the time the goal is 1 year away, at least 80-90% should be in debt/liquid instruments. Automate this through Systematic Transfer Plans (STPs) from equity to debt funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
