<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A high portfolio turnover ratio in an equity mutual fund typically results in:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lower risk for investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Higher transaction costs that can reduce net returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Better tax efficiency for the fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Lower expense ratio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** High portfolio turnover means the fund manager is frequently buying and selling securities. Each transaction incurs costs -- brokerage fees, Securities Transaction Tax (STT), stamp duty, and market impact costs. These transaction costs are borne by the fund and reduce the net returns available to investors. Higher turnover does NOT necessarily mean higher returns.

**The Trap:** High turnover does NOT reduce risk -- in fact, it increases costs. It does NOT improve tax efficiency; rather, frequent short-term capital gains may be tax-inefficient. Transaction costs are part of the fund's expenses but are separate from the expense ratio (which covers management fees and operating costs).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Portfolio turnover ratio is calculated as the lower of total purchases or sales divided by average AUM over a period. A turnover ratio of 100% means the entire portfolio was replaced once during the year. Growth/value funds typically have lower turnover than momentum-based strategies.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When comparing similar funds, check the portfolio turnover ratio. A fund with 200% turnover incurs significantly more transaction costs than one with 50% turnover. If both deliver similar gross returns, the lower-turnover fund will likely deliver better net returns to investors.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
