<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a mandatory requirement under SEBI norms for mutual fund performance disclosure?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Comparison with fixed deposit returns of major banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Comparison with benchmark returns using Total Return Index (TRI)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Showing projected future returns for the next 5 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Guaranteeing minimum returns to investors]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates that mutual fund performance must be compared against a benchmark index, and since February 2018, the benchmark must be the Total Return Index (TRI) variant. TRI includes dividend reinvestment in the benchmark calculation, making it a fairer comparison as fund NAVs also reflect dividends received.

**The Trap:** Comparing with bank FD rates is NOT mandatory (though some fund houses do it voluntarily). Projecting future returns is prohibited -- mutual funds cannot promise or project future performance. Guaranteeing minimum returns is illegal for mutual funds in India (except for certain close-ended schemes with specific SEBI approval).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Before the TRI mandate, funds compared against price return indices, which excluded dividends. This made fund outperformance appear larger than it actually was. The shift to TRI benchmarking was a significant investor protection measure, ensuring apples-to-apples comparison.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When presenting fund performance to clients, always show benchmark comparison (TRI). If a fund consistently underperforms its TRI benchmark over 3-5 years, it may not be justifying its expense ratio. This is a strong argument for considering index funds in efficient market segments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
