<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Currency risk is most relevant for which of the following types of mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Liquid funds investing in Indian treasury bills]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gilt funds investing in government securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[International/global funds investing in overseas securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Banking and PSU debt funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Currency risk (also called exchange rate risk) arises when investments are denominated in a foreign currency. International or global funds invest in overseas securities priced in foreign currencies (USD, EUR, etc.). When the foreign currency depreciates against the Indian Rupee, the returns in INR terms are reduced, even if the underlying investment has gained in local currency terms.

**The Trap:** Liquid funds, gilt funds, and banking/PSU debt funds all invest in Indian Rupee-denominated instruments, so they carry no currency risk. Only funds with overseas exposure face this risk. Note that even a domestic fund holding ADRs/GDRs of Indian companies may face some currency risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI allows mutual funds to invest in overseas securities subject to overall industry and individual AMC limits. Fund of Funds investing in international ETFs (like those tracking NASDAQ or S&P 500) carry currency risk as a significant component of overall returns.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When recommending international funds, explain to clients that returns depend on TWO factors: the performance of the underlying foreign securities AND the INR exchange rate. A strong dollar benefits Indian investors in US-focused funds, while a strengthening rupee reduces returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
