<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram (age 32) is a software engineer earning Rs. 18,00,000 per annum. His wife Priya (age 30) also works and earns Rs. 8,00,000 per annum. They have one child aged 2 years, who is their only dependent. They own a house valued at Rs. 40,00,000 with an outstanding home loan of Rs. 15,00,000. Their current investments include: Rs. 5,00,000 in bank fixed deposits, Rs. 3,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 2,00,000 in PPF, and an emergency fund of Rs. 1,50,000. Their financial goals are: child's higher education (16 years away), retirement (28 years away), and a car upgrade (2 years away). Vikram completes a risk profiling questionnaire administered by his investment adviser Suresh, and scores 72 out of 100. Suresh must now analyze this profile to make suitable investment recommendations.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Given Vikram's aggressive risk profile, which asset allocation model from the standard model portfolios would be MOST appropriate for his long-term goals (education and retirement)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[15% equity index, 5% gold, 35% debt hybrid/MIS/SCSS, 30% debt/FD, 15% liquid]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[50% equity, 20% sector, 10% gold ETF, 10% debt, 10% liquid]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[35% equity, 10% sector, 15% gold, 30% debt, 10% liquid]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[35% equity, 15% gold, 10% gilt, 20% debt, 20% liquid]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For Vikram's aggressive profile with long-term goals (16 and 28 years), the high-risk model portfolio is most appropriate: 50% equity, 20% sector, 10% gold ETF, 10% debt, 10% liquid. This gives 70% equity exposure, suitable for his risk appetite and long time horizons.
**The Trap:** Option C (35% equity, 10% sector, 15% gold, 30% debt, 10% liquid) is the moderate-risk model for a young married family — close to Vikram's life stage but not matching his aggressive risk profile. Option D is the conservative model. Option A is for a couple in their 70s. Students must match risk profile to model, not life stage to model.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B tests the ability to match risk profiles to specific model portfolios. Knowing the exact allocations of each model portfolio is essential for the exam.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While the aggressive model portfolio is appropriate for long-term goals, the car upgrade goal (2 years away) requires a separate, conservative allocation. Don't apply a single model across all goals — segment the portfolio by goal and time horizon.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
