<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera (age 48) was recently widowed after her husband's sudden demise. She has received an insurance payout of Rs. 1,50,00,000 (Rs. 1.5 crore). She receives a pension of Rs. 35,000 per month from her late husband's employer. Meera has two children — the elder child (age 20) is currently in college, and the younger child (age 16) will need higher education funding in 2 years. Meera owns her house outright with no outstanding loan. Her existing investments include: Rs. 25,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 10,00,000 in fixed deposits, and Rs. 5,00,000 in physical gold. Before her husband's death, the couple had been jointly assessed as having an Aggressive risk profile. Meera's monthly household expenses are Rs. 65,000. She approaches her investment adviser Anand for guidance on managing the insurance corpus and restructuring her portfolio.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Considering Meera's changed circumstances, what should be the HIGHEST priority goal when restructuring her portfolio?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Generating regular income to bridge the monthly deficit of Rs. 30,000 between her pension and expenses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Maximizing capital growth to build the largest possible corpus for her retirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing the entire insurance payout in equity for long-term wealth creation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Accumulating gold as a hedge against inflation for the next 20 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Meera's pension (Rs. 35,000/month) falls short of her monthly expenses (Rs. 65,000/month) by Rs. 30,000. This creates an immediate, recurring need for regular income. Until this gap is bridged, she will be drawing down her capital, which is unsustainable. Regular income generation must be the highest priority, followed by education funding and then long-term growth.
**The Trap:** Option B (maximizing growth) and Option C (all in equity) ignore the immediate income need. A client who needs Rs. 30,000/month from investments cannot afford to put everything in growth assets that don't generate regular income. Option D focuses on one asset class and ignores the pressing income requirement.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Investment objective matching is tested in NISM Series X-B: Regular income → deposits/debt/real estate. Understanding that immediate needs take priority over long-term goals is a key advisory principle tested across NISM certifications.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For Meera's Rs. 30,000 monthly deficit, a Systematic Withdrawal Plan (SWP) from a debt or conservative hybrid fund is ideal. At approximately 7-8% annual return on Rs. 50,00,000 in debt funds, she can generate Rs. 30,000-35,000 per month while keeping the principal relatively intact.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
