<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Meera (age 48) was recently widowed after her husband's sudden demise. She has received an insurance payout of Rs. 1,50,00,000 (Rs. 1.5 crore). She receives a pension of Rs. 35,000 per month from her late husband's employer. Meera has two children — the elder child (age 20) is currently in college, and the younger child (age 16) will need higher education funding in 2 years. Meera owns her house outright with no outstanding loan. Her existing investments include: Rs. 25,00,000 in equity mutual funds, Rs. 10,00,000 in fixed deposits, and Rs. 5,00,000 in physical gold. Before her husband's death, the couple had been jointly assessed as having an Aggressive risk profile. Meera's monthly household expenses are Rs. 65,000. She approaches her investment adviser Anand for guidance on managing the insurance corpus and restructuring her portfolio.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Given Meera's changed life circumstances, is her previous Aggressive risk profile still valid?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because her total assets (investments plus insurance payout) are now higher than before]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because her risk tolerance as a personality trait does not change due to life events]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because major life events like loss of a spouse and income change require mandatory risk profile reassessment under SEBI IA Regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, but the reassessment can wait until the next scheduled annual review]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations, risk profiles must be updated periodically, especially on life events such as family changes, income changes, or asset changes. Meera has experienced all three: loss of spouse (family change), loss of husband's active income replaced by pension (income change), and receipt of Rs. 1.5 crore insurance payout (asset change). A reassessment is mandatory and immediate.
**The Trap:** Option A focuses only on asset increase, ignoring the fundamental change in income pattern and family structure. Option B is partially correct — risk tolerance as a personality trait may not change, but risk capacity and overall profile certainly do. Option D dangerously delays a critical reassessment. SEBI expects immediate action on major life events, not waiting for annual reviews.
**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI IA Regulation requirements for life-event-based reassessment are tested in both NISM Series X-A and X-B. The specific triggers (family change, income change, asset change) are explicitly mentioned in the study material.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client experiences bereavement, give them time to grieve before making major financial decisions. However, do ensure the insurance payout is parked safely (liquid fund or savings account) immediately. The detailed reassessment can happen after 2-4 weeks, but don't let the money sit idle in a savings account for months.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
