<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Profiling_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Deepak, aged 55, has a single income and grown-up children. He has a conservative risk profile and Rs. 50,00,000 to invest. According to the model portfolio, how much should go into equity mutual funds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 17,50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 7,50,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 25,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10,00,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The model portfolio for a single income person with grown children (conservative) allocates 35% to equity mutual funds. 35% of Rs. 50,00,000 = Rs. 17,50,000. The full allocation is: 35% equity (Rs. 17,50,000), 15% gold (Rs. 7,50,000), 10% gilt (Rs. 5,00,000), 20% debt (Rs. 10,00,000), 20% liquid (Rs. 10,00,000).
**The Trap:** Rs. 7,50,000 (Option B) is the gold allocation (15%). Rs. 25,00,000 (Option C) is 50% — the equity allocation for a high-risk profile. Rs. 10,00,000 (Option D) is either the debt or liquid allocation (20% each). Note that even a "conservative" profile has 35% in equity — reflecting the need for growth even for conservative investors.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B tests whether candidates can correctly identify model portfolios and compute allocations. The fact that even conservative portfolios include equity is a conceptual point tested in X-A as well.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Many conservative Indian investors resist any equity exposure. Explain that at 6-7% inflation, pure fixed-income portfolios lose purchasing power over time. Even a 35% equity allocation in large-cap/index funds can significantly improve long-term real returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
