<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Risk Return and Performance_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Concentration risk in a mutual fund portfolio arises when:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund invests across too many sectors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The fund has a large allocation to a single security, sector, or asset class]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund has too many investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager frequently changes the portfolio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Concentration risk occurs when a portfolio has a disproportionately large exposure to a single security, sector, industry, or asset class. If that concentrated position suffers a decline, the entire portfolio is significantly impacted. Diversification is the primary tool to mitigate concentration risk.

**The Trap:** Investing across too many sectors would actually REDUCE concentration risk through diversification. High portfolio turnover is a separate concern related to transaction costs, not concentration. The number of investors has no bearing on portfolio concentration risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's mutual fund regulations address concentration risk through investment limits -- for example, no more than 10% of NAV in a single issuer's debt instruments (with exceptions for government securities). Sectoral/thematic funds inherently carry higher concentration risk because they focus on a single sector.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Clients who want to invest heavily in a single sectoral fund should be cautioned about concentration risk. Suggest that sectoral/thematic funds should ideally be a satellite allocation (10-15% of portfolio), not the core holding.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
