<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Role of RTAs in Mutual Fund Transactions_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Aditya is a newly certified mutual fund distributor operating from Jamshedpur, a B-30 city. He is reviewing the product offerings of Pinnacle Mutual Fund to advise his clients. The AMC offers the following schemes: (1) Pinnacle Large Cap Fund with AUM of Rs.450 crore, (2) Pinnacle Flexi Cap Fund with AUM of Rs.2,500 crore, (3) Pinnacle ELSS Fund with AUM of Rs.800 crore, and (4) Pinnacle Liquid Fund with AUM of Rs.5,000 crore. Aditya wants to understand the TER structure, NAV reporting, and how his B-30 location affects commissions. His client, Mrs. Deepa Menon, wants to invest Rs.1.5 lakh in the ELSS fund and Rs.3 lakh in the Large Cap fund. Both investments will be through Aditya as the distributor (Regular Plan).

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Mrs. Deepa's Rs.3 lakh investment in the Large Cap fund from the same B-30 city. Does additional TER for B-30 apply?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because any transaction from a B-30 city qualifies regardless of amount]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only on the first Rs.2 lakh of the Rs.3 lakh transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because Large Cap funds are excluded from B-30 incentive provisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because the transaction amount exceeds the Rs.2 lakh retail threshold for B-30 additional TER]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Additional TER for B-30 inflows applies only to retail transactions up to Rs.2 lakh. Mrs. Deepa's Rs.3 lakh transaction exceeds this threshold, so additional B-30 TER does NOT apply to this investment.
**The Trap:** The B-30 benefit does not apply proportionally on the first Rs.2 lakh. The Rs.2 lakh limit is per-transaction, and if the transaction exceeds it, the entire transaction is classified as non-retail for B-30 TER purposes.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The retail vs non-retail distinction for B-30 TER is a nuanced point. RTAs must correctly classify each transaction based on amount.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If Mrs. Deepa is flexible on timing, splitting her Rs.3 lakh into two transactions of Rs.1.5 lakh each (on different days) could qualify both for B-30 additional TER. However, ensure this is genuinely beneficial and not just creating unnecessary paperwork.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>