<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Role of RTAs in Mutual Fund Transactions_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Aditya is a newly certified mutual fund distributor operating from Jamshedpur, a B-30 city. He is reviewing the product offerings of Pinnacle Mutual Fund to advise his clients. The AMC offers the following schemes: (1) Pinnacle Large Cap Fund with AUM of Rs.450 crore, (2) Pinnacle Flexi Cap Fund with AUM of Rs.2,500 crore, (3) Pinnacle ELSS Fund with AUM of Rs.800 crore, and (4) Pinnacle Liquid Fund with AUM of Rs.5,000 crore. Aditya wants to understand the TER structure, NAV reporting, and how his B-30 location affects commissions. His client, Mrs. Deepa Menon, wants to invest Rs.1.5 lakh in the ELSS fund and Rs.3 lakh in the Large Cap fund. Both investments will be through Aditya as the distributor (Regular Plan).

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> If Mrs. Deepa invests in the ELSS fund today, when can she earliest redeem her units?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Immediately, since open-ended ELSS funds allow anytime redemption]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[After exactly 3 years from the date of allotment of units]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[After 1 year from the date of investment with applicable exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[After 5 years from the date of investment as per Section 80C rules]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ELSS has a mandatory lock-in period of 3 years from the date of allotment. No redemption, switch, or transfer is permitted during this period. After 3 years, units can be redeemed freely with no exit load.
**The Trap:** Some confuse ELSS's 3-year lock-in with the 5-year lock-in of tax-saving FDs or NSC. ELSS has the shortest lock-in among all Section 80C instruments.
**Cross-Exam Context:** RTAs must enforce the ELSS lock-in by blocking any redemption request before 3 years from allotment. SIP investments in ELSS have the lock-in applied to each SIP instalment separately.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Explain to Mrs. Deepa that while she cannot redeem ELSS units for 3 years, this discipline often leads to better returns as it prevents panic selling during market corrections. The lock-in works in the investor's favour historically.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>