<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Role of RTAs in Mutual Fund Transactions_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> MegaRTA Services Ltd is a large RTA that currently services 18 AMCs with a total of 2.15 crore investor folios across all AMCs. The company operates 120 Investor Service Centres (ISCs) across India. Recently, the CEO Ms. Kavitha Sharma received a query from SEBI about their QRTA classification status. Meanwhile, the operations team is dealing with NAV computation deadlines for various scheme types including domestic equity schemes, a Fund of Funds scheme investing in overseas ETFs, and an ETCD scheme. The technology team is upgrading the ISC infrastructure to ensure all centres function as effective single-window service points. MegaRTA also recently onboarded a new AMC client — Zenith Mutual Fund — which has both open-ended and closed-ended schemes in its portfolio.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> If MegaRTA's folio count drops to 1.8 crore next financial year, what happens to its QRTA status?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI will conduct a fresh review and may grant an extension of 6 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It retains QRTA status for the next 3 financial years from when it was classified]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It immediately loses QRTA status and reverts to regular RTA classification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It retains QRTA status for 1 financial year only as a transition period]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Once classified as a QRTA, the RTA retains this status for the next 3 financial years even if the folio count drops below 2 crore. This ensures continuity of enhanced oversight and prevents regulatory arbitrage.
**The Trap:** QRTA status doesn't automatically lapse when folios drop. The 3-year retention period is a regulatory safeguard to maintain standards.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Similar retention concepts exist for systemically important entities in banking and insurance. SEBI applies the same principle to prevent frequent status changes.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The 3-year retention means QRTAs cannot reduce their compliance investments even if business shrinks. This protects investors through sustained infrastructure quality.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>