<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Role of RTAs in Mutual Fund Transactions_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Aditya is a newly certified mutual fund distributor operating from Jamshedpur, a B-30 city. He is reviewing the product offerings of Pinnacle Mutual Fund to advise his clients. The AMC offers the following schemes: (1) Pinnacle Large Cap Fund with AUM of Rs.450 crore, (2) Pinnacle Flexi Cap Fund with AUM of Rs.2,500 crore, (3) Pinnacle ELSS Fund with AUM of Rs.800 crore, and (4) Pinnacle Liquid Fund with AUM of Rs.5,000 crore. Aditya wants to understand the TER structure, NAV reporting, and how his B-30 location affects commissions. His client, Mrs. Deepa Menon, wants to invest Rs.1.5 lakh in the ELSS fund and Rs.3 lakh in the Large Cap fund. Both investments will be through Aditya as the distributor (Regular Plan).

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Mrs. Deepa's Rs.1.5 lakh investment in ELSS through Aditya from Jamshedpur (B-30 city). Which statement about additional TER is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Additional TER for B-30 inflows applies since Rs.1.5 lakh is within the Rs.2 lakh retail transaction limit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Additional TER does not apply because ELSS is a tax-saving scheme exempt from B-30 incentives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Additional TER applies only if Mrs. Deepa is a first-time mutual fund investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Additional TER for B-30 applies regardless of transaction size]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** B-30 additional TER applies to retail transactions up to Rs.2 lakh. Mrs. Deepa's Rs.1.5 lakh ELSS investment qualifies as retail (under Rs.2 lakh) and originates from a B-30 city (Jamshedpur), so additional TER applies.
**The Trap:** The B-30 benefit is not restricted to specific scheme types or first-time investors. It applies to any retail transaction from B-30 cities regardless of scheme type.
**Cross-Exam Context:** T-30/B-30 classification and additional TER provisions are covered in NISM Series V-A and II-B. RTAs handle the PIN code-based tagging.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Operating from a B-30 city is actually an advantage for you. The additional TER translates into potentially higher distributor commissions for retail transactions, rewarding you for expanding MF penetration in smaller cities.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>