<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Priya, a first-time investor, approaches her distributor Mr. Verma for advice. She is considering investing in two schemes from the same AMC: (1) "Alpha Growth Fund" — an equity scheme investing in large-cap and mid-cap stocks with a Risk-o-meter showing "High," benchmarked against Nifty 200 TRI, and (2) "Beta Income Fund" — a debt scheme investing in corporate bonds and government securities with a Risk-o-meter showing "Moderate," benchmarked against CRISIL Composite Bond TRI. Mr. Verma needs to guide Priya through the scheme documents and help her understand the key differences. Recently, the AMC has also announced a change in Alpha Growth Fund's investment objective from "long-term capital appreciation through equity" to "aggressive growth through concentrated equity positions."

Question 1: Priya wants to understand the detailed investment strategy and asset allocation pattern of Alpha Growth Fund. Mr. Verma should direct her to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The Scheme Information Document (SID) of Alpha Growth Fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Statement of Additional Information (SAI) of the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Key Information Memorandum (KIM) which has all the detailed information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The monthly Fact Sheet of Alpha Growth Fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The SID is the primary document for scheme-specific information including detailed investment strategy, asset allocation pattern, investment objectives, and risk factors. For understanding HOW the fund will invest, the SID is the definitive source.

**The Trap:** The SAI covers AMC-level information (sponsors, trustees), not scheme strategy. The KIM is a SUMMARY — it does not contain the detailed investment strategy that a first-time investor needs to properly evaluate. Fact Sheets show current portfolio composition but not the forward-looking strategy and allocation rules.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B and XII, directing investors to the correct document is a core competency tested in scenario-based questions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For first-time investors like Priya, start with the KIM for a quick overview, then walk them through the relevant SID sections (Highlights, Investment Objective, Asset Allocation). This staged approach prevents information overload while ensuring they make an informed decision.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
