<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_41" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A corporate treasurer needs to invest Rs 10 crore of company surplus for 45 days until a vendor payment is due. The primary objective is capital preservation with reasonable returns. Which fund type is most suitable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Liquid fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Aggressive hybrid fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Medium duration debt fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dynamic bond fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For a 45-day investment with capital preservation as the primary objective, a liquid fund is the clear choice. Liquid funds invest in debt and money market instruments with maturity up to 91 days, matching the investment horizon. They offer very low volatility (near-zero NAV fluctuation), high liquidity (next-day redemption for amounts up to Rs 50 lakh, T+1 for larger amounts), and returns superior to savings accounts.

**The Trap:** Aggressive hybrid funds (65-80% equity) can lose significant value in 45 days during a market downturn -- entirely unsuitable for a vendor payment commitment. Medium duration and dynamic bond funds have interest rate risk that can cause NAV volatility over short periods. For corporate treasuries, safety of principal is paramount.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For even shorter periods (1-7 days), overnight funds may be more appropriate as they invest only in overnight securities with zero mark-to-market risk. For the 45-day period, liquid funds offer slightly better returns while maintaining adequate safety. The graded exit load for liquid funds (applicable within first 7 days only) would not be an issue for a 45-day investment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For corporate clients, liquid funds are a powerful tool to earn returns on idle cash that would otherwise sit in a current account earning zero interest. Build relationships with CFOs and treasury managers by demonstrating how systematic deployment in liquid funds can add Rs 5-7 lakh annually to a company maintaining Rs 10 crore average cash balance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
