<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the key difference between a Gold ETF and a Gold Fund of Funds (FoF)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold ETFs invest in physical gold while Gold FoFs invest in gold mining company stocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Gold ETFs require a demat account and are traded on exchanges, while Gold FoFs invest in Gold ETFs and can be purchased without a demat account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold FoFs have lower expense ratios than Gold ETFs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gold ETFs offer SIP facility while Gold FoFs do not]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Gold ETFs are exchange-traded funds that hold physical gold and trade on stock exchanges like shares -- they require a demat account and a broker. Gold Fund of Funds (FoF) invest in Gold ETFs as their underlying asset. The FoF route allows investors to access gold without needing a demat account, and they can invest via SIP or lump sum like any regular mutual fund.

**The Trap:** Gold FoFs actually have a HIGHER expense ratio than Gold ETFs because the investor pays two layers of expenses -- the FoF's own expense ratio plus the underlying Gold ETF's expense ratio. Also, both Gold ETFs and Gold FoFs invest in physical gold-backed instruments, NOT in gold mining companies (that would be a gold sector fund).

**Cross-Exam Context:** For scheme selection, the choice between Gold ETF and Gold FoF depends on whether the investor has a demat account, prefers exchange trading vs. mutual fund route, and is sensitive to the additional expense layer. Sovereign Gold Bonds (SGBs) are another alternative offering 2.5% annual interest plus gold price appreciation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For investors without demat accounts or those wanting SIP in gold, Gold FoFs are the most convenient option. For active traders or cost-conscious investors with demat accounts, Gold ETFs offer lower costs. Always discuss gold as a portfolio diversifier (5-10% allocation), not as a primary investment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
