<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor invests Rs 1,50,000 in ELSS under Section 80C. If the investor is in the 30% tax bracket (plus 4% cess), what is the approximate tax saving from this investment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 45,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs 46,800]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 31,200]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 50,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 80C, maximum deduction is Rs 1,50,000 per financial year. Tax saving = Investment amount x Effective tax rate. Effective tax rate = 30% + (4% cess on 30%) = 30% + 1.2% = 31.2%. Tax saving = Rs 1,50,000 x 31.2% = Rs 46,800. This is the direct tax benefit from investing in ELSS.

**The Trap:** Rs 45,000 (30% of 1,50,000) ignores the health and education cess of 4%. The cess is calculated ON the tax amount, not on the income, so 4% of Rs 45,000 = Rs 1,800, making total tax Rs 46,800. Rs 31,200 would be the saving for someone in the 20% bracket (20% + 0.8% cess = 20.8% x 1,50,000 = Rs 31,200).

**Cross-Exam Context:** ELSS offers the dual benefit of tax saving and equity market participation. Compared to other 80C options: PPF (7.1% guaranteed, 15-year lock-in), NSC (7% guaranteed, 5-year lock-in), ELSS (market-linked, 3-year lock-in). ELSS has the shortest lock-in but with market risk. Note: Section 80C is available only under the old tax regime.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When recommending ELSS, calculate the exact tax saving for the client based on their tax bracket. For a 30% bracket investor, the Rs 46,800 tax saving on a Rs 1,50,000 investment represents an immediate 31.2% 'return' through tax benefit alone. This makes ELSS very attractive even before considering investment returns. Always clarify this benefit applies under the old tax regime.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
