<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the key advantage of investing in an international/global fund for an Indian investor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[International funds are exempt from capital gains tax in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[International funds always deliver higher returns than domestic equity funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Geographic diversification reduces country-specific risk and provides exposure to global growth opportunities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[International funds have no currency risk as returns are in Indian rupees]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** International funds provide geographic diversification by investing in companies listed in foreign markets. This reduces the concentration risk of having the entire portfolio in Indian markets. If Indian markets underperform, global exposure can cushion the portfolio. Additionally, investors gain access to global companies and sectors not available in India.

**The Trap:** A major misconception is that international funds eliminate currency risk. In fact, currency risk is a significant factor -- if the Indian rupee appreciates against the foreign currency, returns in rupee terms reduce. Conversely, rupee depreciation can enhance returns. International fund returns are NOT tax-exempt; they are taxable in India based on the fund's equity allocation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** International equity funds with 65% or more in foreign equities do NOT qualify as equity-oriented for tax purposes in India. They are taxed as debt funds (at slab rate for short-term, 12.5% for long-term after 24 months). This tax treatment is an important suitability consideration.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When recommending international funds, explain the dual return component: asset returns plus currency movement. For long-term investors, the historical trend of gradual rupee depreciation against USD has actually added to returns from US-focused funds. Suggest 10-15% of equity allocation in international funds for diversification.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
