<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a potential disadvantage of a mutual fund scheme having a very large AUM (Assets Under Management)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund will have lower expense ratio due to economies of scale]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The fund may face challenges in deploying large amounts in mid and small-cap stocks without impacting prices]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund will have better liquidity management capabilities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager will have more investment options available]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A very large AUM in mid-cap or small-cap funds creates deployment challenges. When a Rs 30,000 crore fund needs to buy a small-cap stock, even a modest allocation (say 2%) means investing Rs 600 crore in a single stock. For small-cap stocks with limited daily trading volumes, this can significantly impact the stock price (impact cost). This may force the fund to invest in larger stocks, diluting its mandate.

**The Trap:** For large-cap funds or debt funds, large AUM is generally beneficial as it reduces expense ratios and improves liquidity management. The deployment challenge is primarily for small and mid-cap strategies. Also, lower expense ratio (option A) is actually a benefit, not a disadvantage.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is why some AMCs restrict fresh inflows into small-cap funds when AUM grows too large. AUM size matters more for concentrated strategies (small-cap, mid-cap, focused) than for diversified large-cap or index strategies. For debt funds, very large AUM can be positive as it enables better pricing in bond markets.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When comparing similar funds, consider AUM as one factor alongside performance and expenses. For small/mid-cap funds, moderate AUM is preferable. For large-cap or index funds, larger AUM often means lower costs. Never recommend a fund solely based on its AUM size.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
