<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_50" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): The Verma Family Financial Plan

Referring to the Verma family scenario described in Question 47:

QUESTION 50: For Mr. Verma (40) and Mrs. Verma's (38) joint retirement goal (approximately 20 years away), what asset allocation and scheme selection would be most suitable, applying the '100 minus age' rule as a starting framework?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in debt funds since retirement money must be protected from any market risk at all times]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in small-cap fund since they have 20 years and should maximize returns aggressively]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% in gold and 50% in real estate funds to protect against inflation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[60% in diversified equity funds (mix of large-cap, flexi-cap, and mid-cap via SIP), 25% in aggressive hybrid fund, 10% in international equity fund, and 5% in gold fund -- with a glide path reducing equity by 5% every 5 years as retirement approaches]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Using '100 minus age' for Mr. Verma (40): Equity = 60%, Debt = 40%. For Mrs. Verma (38): Equity = 62%. Averaging to approximately 60% equity is the starting point. With 20 years to retirement, substantial equity allocation is justified. The recommended portfolio: 60% diversified equity (across large-cap, flexi-cap, mid-cap for adequate diversification) + 25% aggressive hybrid (provides equity with debt cushion, taxed as equity) + 10% international equity (geographic diversification, currency hedge) + 5% gold fund (portfolio diversifier, inflation hedge). The glide path reduces equity by approximately 5% every 5 years: Year 0: 60% equity -> Year 5: 55% -> Year 10: 50% -> Year 15: 45% -> Year 20 (retirement): 40%.

**The Trap:** 100% debt for 20 years will result in a significantly smaller retirement corpus due to inadequate returns against inflation. 100% small-cap is excessively risky even for 20 years -- this is their entire retirement savings, not discretionary money. 50% gold + 50% real estate is poorly diversified across asset classes and misses the wealth-creation power of equity markets.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Monthly SIP allocation for retirement from the Rs 80,000 surplus (after Rs 15,000 for education and Rs 4 lakh emergency fund built up): approximately Rs 50,000-55,000 can go toward retirement. At an assumed blended return of 11-12% over 20 years, this can build a substantial retirement corpus. Annual rebalancing ensures the allocation stays on track with the glide path.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For the Verma family's comprehensive plan: (1) Build emergency fund first (Rs 4 lakh in liquid fund -- 2-3 months to build), (2) Start SIPs simultaneously for education (Rs 15,000) and retirement (Rs 50,000), (3) Grandfather's investment (lump sum bucketed approach), (4) Review the entire plan annually on a fixed date (anniversary or new year). Having all family goals documented in one plan builds deep client relationships and demonstrates the value a distributor adds beyond mere product selling.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
