<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following best describes a sector fund in terms of concentration risk?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It must invest in at least 5 sectors with a minimum 10% allocation to each]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It invests across all sectors but overweights one particular sector]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It invests a minimum of 80% in a single specified sector, carrying high concentration risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It invests equally across all sectors of the economy for maximum diversification]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A sector fund must invest at least 80% of its total assets in equity and equity-related instruments of a particular sector (e.g., banking, pharma, IT). This makes it one of the riskiest equity fund categories because the entire portfolio depends on the fortunes of a single sector. A thematic fund is slightly broader -- investing across a theme that may span multiple sectors.

**The Trap:** The confusion often lies between sector and thematic funds. A banking sector fund invests only in banking stocks. A financial services thematic fund can invest in banks, NBFCs, insurance companies, fintech, and brokerages -- broader than a sector but still concentrated around a theme.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI allows only one scheme per sector/theme per AMC. The high concentration risk of sector funds makes them suitable only for investors who have a strong conviction about a specific sector's prospects and can time entry/exit well.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Sector funds should never be recommended as core portfolio holdings. They work best as tactical, satellite allocations for investors who have sector-specific views. Always warn clients about the cyclical nature of sectors -- today's outperforming sector can be tomorrow's underperformer.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
