<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_48" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): The Verma Family Financial Plan

Referring to the Verma family scenario described in Question 47:

QUESTION 48: For Ananya's higher education goal (Rs 30 lakh in 10 years), which asset allocation strategy and scheme selection would be most appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in small-cap funds for maximum returns, shifting to liquid funds in the 10th year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in conservative hybrid fund throughout the 10-year period for safety]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[60-70% in diversified equity (large-cap or flexi-cap) and 30-40% in aggressive hybrid fund via SIP for the first 7 years, then gradually shift to short-duration debt funds in the last 3 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in gold funds as gold preserves value over long periods]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** With a 10-year horizon and moderate-to-high risk tolerance (Mr. Verma) and moderate risk tolerance (Mrs. Verma), a predominantly equity allocation with a glide path is ideal. For years 1-7: 60-70% in diversified equity provides growth potential, while 30-40% in aggressive hybrid provides equity exposure with a debt cushion. For years 8-10: Systematically shift to short-duration debt funds to protect the accumulated corpus as the goal nears. This ensures growth in early years and preservation closer to the goal.

**The Trap:** 100% small-cap is too aggressive for a non-negotiable goal like child's education -- if markets crash in year 9, there is no recovery time. 100% conservative hybrid (only 10-25% equity) over 10 years will likely underperform inflation-adjusted education costs. 100% gold does not reliably generate the real returns needed to meet education costs that inflate at 8-10% annually.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The estimated SIP needed: assuming 12% CAGR for the equity portion and 8% for the debt portion, blended return of approximately 10.5%. Using SIP calculator: to accumulate Rs 30 lakh in 10 years at 10.5%, approximately Rs 14,500-15,000 monthly SIP is needed. The Verma family can allocate Rs 15,000 from their Rs 80,000 monthly surplus for this goal.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For child education goals, use education inflation (8-10%) not general inflation (5-6%) when calculating the future cost. Create a written plan showing: current cost estimate, inflation-adjusted target, SIP amount needed, fund allocation, and rebalancing milestones. Give the parents a physical copy -- this tangible plan increases follow-through and prevents emotional decisions during market volatility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
