<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a requirement for a credible benchmark used to evaluate mutual fund scheme performance?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The benchmark should be in sync with the investment objective of the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The benchmark should be calculated by an independent agency]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The benchmark must be selected by SEBI for each scheme category]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The benchmark should be published on a regular and timely basis]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A credible benchmark must satisfy three key requirements: (1) it should be in sync with the scheme's investment objective, asset allocation, and investment strategy, (2) it should be calculated by an independent agency, and (3) it should be published on a regular and timely basis. However, SEBI does not select the benchmark -- the AMC decides the benchmark in consultation with the trustees.

**The Trap:** Candidates often assume SEBI mandates specific benchmarks for each scheme. While SEBI provides guidelines and the broad framework for categorization, the actual choice of benchmark is made by the AMC in consultation with trustees and is disclosed in the Scheme Information Document (SID).

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B (MF Foundation), benchmark selection is tested alongside the regulatory role of trustees. In NISM III-C (Investment Adviser), understanding benchmarks is critical for evaluating fund performance for clients.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When reviewing a fund's SID with your client, always check if the benchmark is truly representative of the fund's strategy. A large-cap fund benchmarked against a broad market index may appear to outperform simply because of benchmark mismatch, not genuine alpha generation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
