<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor redeems Rs 5,00,000 from an equity fund after 8 months. The fund charges 1% exit load for redemptions within 1 year. What is the net redemption amount the investor receives (before capital gains tax)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 5,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs 4,95,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 4,90,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 4,99,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The investor redeems within 1 year (8 months), so 1% exit load applies. Exit load amount = Rs 5,00,000 x 1% = Rs 5,000. Net redemption amount = Rs 5,00,000 - Rs 5,000 = Rs 4,95,000. The exit load is deducted from the redemption proceeds at the point of redemption, before any capital gains tax considerations.

**The Trap:** Some candidates might calculate 2% exit load (confusing the percentage) or forget to apply exit load since it is 'only' 8 months. The exit load clearly applies as the redemption is within the 1-year period. Also note that exit load is calculated on the redemption value, not the original investment amount (though in this question they happen to be the same).

**Cross-Exam Context:** The exit load collected goes back into the scheme, benefiting the remaining investors. For calculating capital gains, the exit load reduces the sale consideration. So the taxable gain is calculated on Rs 4,95,000 (not Rs 5,00,000) minus the purchase cost. This reduces the investor's tax liability slightly.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always inform clients about exit load BEFORE they invest, not at the time of redemption. If a client has a potential need for funds within 1 year, consider recommending funds with no exit load (like liquid/overnight funds) for that portion. Document this discussion as part of your suitability assessment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
