<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. Patel invested in a balanced advantage fund. Six months later, the AMC changes the scheme's investment objective from "dynamic equity-debt allocation" to "pure equity growth." What is Mr. Patel's right in this situation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He must receive a written notice and can exit at the prevailing NAV without any exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He has no special rights since the AMC can change investment objectives at any time]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He can demand the AMC buy back his units at the original purchase NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He must wait for the change to be approved by SEBI before he can exit]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A change in investment objective is a change in fundamental attributes. When fundamental attributes change, the AMC must: (1) Send a written notice to all unitholders like Mr. Patel, and (2) Provide an exit option at the prevailing NAV without charging any exit load. This protects investors who invested based on the original scheme character.

**The Trap:** The AMC cannot change fundamental attributes without giving unitholders the exit option — investors DO have special rights. The exit is at prevailing NAV, not purchase NAV. SEBI approval is not required for such changes, but unitholder protection is mandatory.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test fundamental attribute changes through scenario-based questions. The key elements are: written notice + exit at NAV + no exit load.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If any scheme you have recommended undergoes a fundamental attribute change, immediately contact your client. Explain the change and help them evaluate whether the new scheme character aligns with their goals. This is when clients most need your advice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
