<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following debt fund categories is most suitable for an investor with a 1-3 year investment horizon who wants moderate risk?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overnight fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gilt fund with 10-year constant duration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Short duration fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Liquid fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Short duration funds invest in debt instruments with a Macaulay duration of 1 to 3 years. This duration profile matches the investor's 1-3 year horizon, minimizing the risk of loss if the investor holds to the end of the horizon. These funds offer a balance between yield (higher than liquid/ultra-short funds) and risk (lower than medium/long duration funds).

**The Trap:** Overnight and liquid funds are for very short-term parking and would not be optimal for a 1-3 year horizon as they offer lower yields. Gilt funds with 10-year duration have very high interest rate risk and are suitable only for investors betting on declining interest rates or those with a very long horizon.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The hierarchy of debt fund categories by Macaulay duration is: Overnight (1 day) < Liquid (up to 91 days) < Ultra-short (3-6 months) < Low duration (6-12 months) < Money market (up to 1 year) < Short duration (1-3 years) < Medium duration (3-4 years) < Medium to long (4-7 years) < Long duration (7+ years). Matching investment horizon to fund duration is a key principle.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always match the client's investment horizon with the fund's duration profile. This 'duration matching' strategy minimizes interest rate risk. A client with a 2-year goal in a 10-year duration fund faces unnecessary volatility, while a client parking 3-year money in a liquid fund sacrifices returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
