<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A credit risk fund primarily aims to generate higher yields by investing in which type of bonds?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Government securities (G-Secs) with sovereign guarantee]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AAA-rated corporate bonds only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Lower-rated corporate bonds (below highest-rated instruments) to earn credit spread]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Treasury bills issued by the Reserve Bank of India]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A credit risk fund must invest a minimum of 65% of its total assets in corporate bonds rated below the highest quality (i.e., below AA+ rated instruments). By investing in lower-rated bonds, the fund earns a higher yield (credit spread) compared to AAA-rated or government bonds. However, this comes with the risk of rating downgrade or default.

**The Trap:** G-Secs and T-bills carry sovereign guarantee and have virtually zero credit risk -- they are the domain of gilt funds and liquid/money market funds. AAA-rated bonds are the safest corporate debt. Credit risk funds deliberately move down the credit quality ladder for higher returns.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The credit events of 2018-2019 (IL&FS, DHFL defaults) highlighted the risks of credit risk funds. Several funds suffered significant NAV declines due to defaults and downgrades. This underscored that higher yield always comes with commensurately higher risk -- there is no free lunch in investing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Credit risk funds should be recommended only to informed investors who understand default risk. Never position them as 'better FD alternatives' just because they offer higher yields. Always explain that the higher return potential comes with the risk of capital erosion if underlying bonds default.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
