<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the minimum lock-in period for a solution-oriented retirement fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[3 years or till retirement, whichever is earlier]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[5 years or till retirement age, whichever is earlier]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5 years or till the investor attains age 60, whichever is later]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No lock-in period but exit load applies for 5 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Solution-oriented retirement funds have a lock-in period of 5 years or till the retirement age (as specified by the scheme), whichever is earlier. Similarly, children's funds have a lock-in of 5 years or till the child attains the age of majority, whichever is earlier. These lock-ins are designed to ensure the money stays invested for the intended goal.

**The Trap:** The key word is 'whichever is EARLIER' not 'whichever is later.' If an investor is 58 years old and the scheme's retirement age is 60, the lock-in is just 2 years (till retirement at 60), not the full 5 years. Also, do not confuse this with ELSS lock-in of 3 years.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI allows only two solution-oriented scheme types: retirement fund and children's fund. Each AMC can offer only one of each. These funds can have varying equity-debt allocations, so the Risk-o-Meter and investment strategy should still be evaluated for suitability.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Solution-oriented funds are useful for earmarking money for specific goals. The lock-in period acts as behavioral discipline. However, always check the fund's asset allocation and performance against comparable diversified funds -- the 'solution' label does not guarantee suitability just by name.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
