<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Scheduled Offences under PMLA_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following offences under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 is listed as a scheduled offence under Part A of PMLA?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only punishment for terrorist act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only punishment for raising funds for terrorist act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only punishment for holding proceeds of terrorism]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Multiple UAPA offences including punishment for terrorist act, raising funds for terrorism, holding proceeds of terrorism, organizing terrorist camps, and membership of terrorist organizations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Part A, Paragraph 4 of the PMLA Schedule lists numerous UAPA offences including: Section 16 (punishment for terrorist act), Section 17 (raising funds for terrorist act), Section 18/18A/18B (conspiracy, organizing camps, recruiting), Section 21 (holding proceeds of terrorism), Section 38-40 (terrorist organization membership, support, and fundraising).

**The Trap:** Options A, B, and C each mention only one UAPA offence. The Schedule includes a comprehensive list of terrorism-related offences. This breadth reflects the Combating the Financing of Terrorism (CFT) objective of PMLA.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The "CFT" in "AML/CFT" directly connects to UAPA offences in the PMLA Schedule. Understanding this link is important for the NISM XXIV exam title itself — AML and CFT Provisions.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Terrorist financing is distinct from money laundering in that the funds may come from LEGITIMATE sources but are used for terrorist purposes. As an intermediary, watch for any transactions linked to designated entities under UAPA.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>