<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In the context of equity scheme selection, what is the primary distinction between a 'growth style' fund and a 'value style' fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Growth funds invest in large-caps while value funds invest in mid and small-caps]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Growth funds only offer growth option while value funds only offer dividend option]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Growth funds invest in companies with high earnings growth potential while value funds invest in undervalued companies trading below their intrinsic worth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Growth funds have higher expense ratios while value funds have lower expense ratios]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Growth style investing focuses on companies expected to grow earnings at above-average rates, even if current valuations appear expensive. Value style investing seeks companies whose stock prices are below their estimated intrinsic value -- typically identified by low P/E, low P/B ratios, or high dividend yields. These are two distinct investment philosophies that perform differently across market cycles.

**The Trap:** A very common confusion is between the 'growth style' (an investment philosophy) and the 'growth option' (a payout choice where profits are reinvested). These are entirely different concepts. Similarly, value investing is not restricted to any particular market capitalization.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI categorization includes a 'Value Fund/Contra Fund' category. Value and growth styles tend to outperform in different market conditions -- value does well during recoveries while growth outperforms during bull runs. Understanding style helps in building a diversified portfolio.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Explain to clients that growth and value styles go through cycles. Rather than timing these cycles, suggest holding both styles for diversification. A 'blend' approach (mix of growth and value) can reduce portfolio volatility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
