<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[For an index fund, a lower tracking error indicates which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund has generated higher alpha than the benchmark]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund has a higher expense ratio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The fund is more closely and consistently replicating the benchmark index]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager is taking more active bets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For index funds and ETFs, the primary goal is to replicate the benchmark index as closely as possible. A lower tracking error means the difference between the fund's returns and the benchmark's returns is more consistent and smaller, indicating better replication quality. The fund is doing exactly what it is supposed to do -- tracking the index.

**The Trap:** Higher alpha would mean outperforming the benchmark, which is NOT the goal of an index fund. A higher expense ratio would likely increase tracking error, not decrease it. More active bets would increase tracking error, not decrease it. For index funds, lower tracking error = better management.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For actively managed funds, some tracking error is expected and even desired (as the manager deviates from the benchmark to generate alpha). But for index funds, minimizing tracking error is the key performance indicator.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When comparing index funds tracking the same benchmark (e.g., multiple Nifty 50 index funds), tracking error and expense ratio are the two most important differentiators. A Nifty 50 index fund with 0.05% tracking error and 0.10% expense ratio is superior to one with 0.15% tracking error and 0.20% expense ratio.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
