<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_47" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: The Verma Family Financial Plan

The Verma family consists of:
- Mr. Verma (age 40): IT professional earning Rs 20 lakh per annum, moderate-to-high risk tolerance
- Mrs. Verma (age 38): Teacher earning Rs 8 lakh per annum, moderate risk tolerance
- Daughter Ananya (age 8): Currently in Class 3
- Mr. Verma's father (age 65): Retired government employee with a pension of Rs 25,000 per month

Family Financial Goals:
1. Ananya's higher education: Rs 30 lakh needed in approximately 10 years
2. Mr. & Mrs. Verma's retirement: Corpus needed in 20 years
3. Mr. Verma's father: Supplementary monthly income of Rs 15,000 from his savings of Rs 25 lakh
4. Emergency fund: 6 months of family expenses (approximately Rs 4 lakh)

Combined monthly investable surplus: Rs 80,000

---

QUESTION 47: For building the emergency fund of Rs 4 lakh, which scheme type should the Verma family select, and why?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS fund -- it provides tax saving and equity growth for the emergency corpus]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Aggressive hybrid fund -- it provides equity-like returns with some debt cushion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Liquid fund or overnight fund -- the emergency fund requires immediate liquidity, capital preservation, and negligible risk of capital loss]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long duration gilt fund -- government securities ensure safety of the emergency corpus]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An emergency fund has three non-negotiable requirements: (1) Immediate liquidity -- money must be accessible within 24 hours, (2) Capital preservation -- the fund should never lose value when you need it most, (3) Minimal risk -- emergencies often coincide with market stress (job loss during recession, health crisis during pandemic). Liquid funds (maturity up to 91 days) and overnight funds (1-day maturity) meet all three criteria. They offer better returns than savings accounts while maintaining near-instant liquidity.

**The Trap:** ELSS has a 3-year lock-in -- the fund literally CANNOT be accessed during emergencies. Aggressive hybrid funds can lose 20-30% during equity market crashes, which is precisely when job losses (and emergency fund needs) tend to occur. Gilt funds, despite government backing, can lose 5-10% in a rate-hike environment -- not acceptable for emergency money.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Emergency fund sizing: 6 months of expenses for salaried individuals, 12 months for self-employed. The Verma family's Rs 4 lakh emergency fund covers 6 months of non-discretionary expenses. This should be the FIRST investment before any goal-based investing begins. It provides the foundation that prevents premature liquidation of long-term investments.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Build the emergency fund FIRST before starting SIPs for other goals. Many investors skip this step and then break their equity SIPs during emergencies, crystallizing losses. The Rs 4 lakh can be built in 2-3 months by directing the full Rs 80,000 surplus into a liquid fund, then redirecting the monthly surplus to other goals once the emergency fund is established.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
