<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the difference between 'strategic asset allocation' and 'tactical asset allocation'?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Strategic allocation is for short-term goals while tactical allocation is for long-term goals]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Strategic allocation uses only equity while tactical allocation uses only debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Strategic allocation is the long-term target mix based on investor profile, while tactical allocation involves short-term deviations to capitalize on market opportunities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Strategic allocation is done by the fund manager while tactical allocation is done by the distributor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Strategic asset allocation establishes a long-term target mix of asset classes (e.g., 60% equity, 30% debt, 10% gold) based on the investor's risk profile, goals, and time horizon. Tactical asset allocation involves short-term, deliberate deviations from this target to exploit market opportunities (e.g., temporarily increasing equity to 70% when markets are undervalued). The strategic allocation provides the framework, while tactical moves aim to add incremental returns.

**The Trap:** Both strategic and tactical allocation can include any asset class -- neither is restricted to equity or debt alone. Also, both can be implemented at the investor portfolio level (with distributor guidance) or at the fund level (by the fund manager in dynamic asset allocation funds).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Portfolio rebalancing is the process of bringing asset allocation back to the strategic target. If equity markets rally and equity allocation rises from 60% to 70%, rebalancing involves selling equity and buying debt to return to 60:30:10. This enforces the 'buy low, sell high' discipline systematically.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help clients establish a strategic asset allocation first, then review quarterly for rebalancing. Tactical moves should be limited and based on clear market signals, not emotions. Most investor returns are determined by strategic allocation (80-90%), not by tactical timing or individual fund selection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
