<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[For an investor who wants to park surplus funds for a period of up to 91 days with minimal risk, which type of debt fund would be most appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long duration fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Liquid fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dynamic bond fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Liquid funds invest in debt and money market instruments with maturity of up to 91 days. They offer high liquidity, low volatility, and are ideal for short-term parking of surplus funds. They do not have any lock-in period (though exit load may apply for redemption within 7 days on a graded basis). The short maturity profile ensures minimal interest rate risk.

**The Trap:** Credit risk funds invest in lower-rated bonds for higher yield but carry significant credit/default risk -- the opposite of what a conservative short-term investor needs. Long duration funds have high interest rate sensitivity. Dynamic bond funds actively manage duration, which introduces uncertainty.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Within the short-term debt category, the hierarchy by maturity is: Overnight fund (1 day) < Liquid fund (up to 91 days) < Ultra-short duration fund (3-6 months Macaulay duration) < Low duration fund (6-12 months) < Money market fund (up to 1 year). Each step up adds slightly more duration risk.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Liquid funds are the gateway product for new mutual fund investors. Use them to demonstrate how mutual funds work before moving clients to equity. For corporates parking treasury funds, liquid funds offer superior returns to savings accounts with comparable liquidity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
