<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Raj, a 28-year-old software engineer earning Rs 15 lakh per annum, wants to start investing for wealth creation over 15+ years. He has high risk tolerance and no immediate financial liabilities. Which scheme selection would be MOST appropriate as his core holding?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overnight fund for safety of capital]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk fund for higher yields]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Diversified equity fund (flexi-cap or large & mid-cap) via SIP]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gilt fund with 10-year constant duration]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Raj has all the characteristics of an ideal equity investor: young age (28), long time horizon (15+ years), high risk tolerance, stable income, and no liabilities. A diversified equity fund (flexi-cap or large & mid-cap) as a core holding provides broad market exposure with professional management. SIP ensures rupee cost averaging and disciplined investing. Using the '100 minus age' rule, his equity allocation should be about 72%.

**The Trap:** Overnight funds are for parking temporary surplus, not for wealth creation over 15 years -- they barely beat inflation. Credit risk funds are debt instruments, not wealth creators. Gilt funds with 10-year duration are tactical instruments for interest rate bets, not for long-term equity-style wealth creation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For a 15-year horizon, the probability of equity delivering positive real returns (above inflation) is historically very high. Raj can afford to ride out 2-3 market cycles within his timeframe. After establishing the core equity holding, he can add satellite positions in mid-cap, small-cap, or international funds for additional diversification.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For young professionals like Raj, start with one good diversified equity fund via SIP. Keep it simple -- beginners get confused and paralyzed by too many choices. Once the SIP habit is established (6-12 months), gradually add 1-2 complementary funds. The most important thing is to START investing, not to find the 'perfect' fund.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
