<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued): Rajesh, a 40-year-old salaried professional, wants to invest in an equity mutual fund from the SEBI Large Cap category for his daughter's higher education in 10 years. His distributor shortlists three funds and presents the following fact sheet data:

BENCHMARK for all three funds: Nifty 50 TRI
Nifty 50 TRI Returns: 1-year: 14.0%, 3-year CAGR: 13.5%, 5-year CAGR: 12.8%

FUND CRESCENDO:
- 1-year return: 16.2%, 3-year CAGR: 14.8%, 5-year CAGR: 13.5%
- Sharpe Ratio: 1.10, Information Ratio: 0.65, Expense Ratio: 1.80%
- Fund Manager tenure: 7 years, AUM: Rs 18,000 crore

FUND DYNAMO:
- 1-year return: 19.5%, 3-year CAGR: 15.2%, 5-year CAGR: 11.8%
- Sharpe Ratio: 0.95, Information Ratio: 0.40, Expense Ratio: 2.10%
- Fund Manager tenure: 2 years, AUM: Rs 5,500 crore

FUND ELITE:
- 1-year return: 15.0%, 3-year CAGR: 14.2%, 5-year CAGR: 13.8%
- Sharpe Ratio: 1.25, Information Ratio: 0.72, Expense Ratio: 0.85%
- Fund Manager tenure: 5 years, AUM: Rs 25,000 crore

Considering ALL factors -- benchmark outperformance, risk-adjusted ratios, expense ratio, fund manager tenure, and AUM -- which fund is the MOST SUITABLE recommendation for Rajesh's 10-year goal and why?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fund Crescendo, because it has the longest fund manager tenure of 7 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fund Dynamo, because its high recent returns suggest strong momentum going forward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Fund Elite, because it combines the highest Sharpe Ratio (1.25), highest Information Ratio (0.72), lowest expense ratio (0.85%), consistent benchmark outperformance, experienced manager (5 years), and largest AUM (Rs 25,000 crore)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An equal split across all three funds to diversify fund manager risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Evaluating all factors holistically:

Fund Elite wins on most parameters:
- Risk-adjusted returns: Highest Sharpe (1.25) and Information Ratio (0.72)
- Expense Ratio: Lowest at 0.85% -- most cost-efficient for 10-year horizon
- Benchmark outperformance: Consistent across all periods, including BEST 5-year outperformance (+1.0%)
- AUM: Largest at Rs 25,000 crore -- indicates investor confidence and scale efficiency
- Fund Manager: 5-year tenure -- adequately experienced

Fund Crescendo is second-best but loses on expense ratio (1.80%) and risk-adjusted metrics.
Fund Dynamo is weakest: underperformed benchmark on 5-year basis, highest expense ratio (2.10%), lowest ratios, and shortest manager tenure (2 years).

**The Trap:** Fund manager tenure alone (Crescendo's 7 years) does not make a fund the best choice if other metrics are weaker. Past momentum (Dynamo's 19.5% 1-year return) is not a reliable predictor of future performance. Equal split across three funds adds unnecessary exposure to the weakest fund (Dynamo).

**Cross-Exam Context:** This question tests holistic fund evaluation -- integrating quantitative metrics (ratios, returns) with qualitative factors (manager tenure, AUM) and cost considerations (expense ratio). This comprehensive approach is what SEBI expects from distributors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When making recommendations, document your analysis showing ALL factors considered. This protects you and serves the client. Present the comparison table to Rajesh, explain each metric simply, and let the data support your recommendation of Fund Elite. Documented, data-driven recommendations are the hallmark of professional distribution practice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
