<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Scheduled Offences under PMLA_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under Part A of the PMLA Schedule, offences under the SEBI Act, 1992 include:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only failure to register as an intermediary]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only non-compliance with SEBI circulars]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Prohibition of manipulative and deceptive devices, insider trading, and substantial acquisition of securities or control (Section 12A read with Section 24)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All offences under the SEBI Act without any restriction]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Part A, Paragraph 11 of the PMLA Schedule covers SEBI Act offences. Specifically, Section 12A read with Section 24 — which covers the prohibition of manipulative and deceptive devices, insider trading, and substantial acquisition of securities or control. Section 24 provides the penalty for contravention of Section 12A.

**The Trap:** Not all SEBI Act violations are scheduled offences — only those under Section 12A (read with Section 24). Failure to register or non-compliance with circulars are regulatory violations but may not be scheduled offences under PMLA.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For securities market professionals, this is the most directly relevant scheduled offence. In NISM III-A, the focus is on what constitutes market manipulation and insider trading. In NISM XXIV, the focus shifts to how these offences connect to money laundering.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If proceeds from insider trading or market manipulation flow through your intermediary firm, you could be dealing with money laundering proceeds. This is why securities intermediaries have specific AML obligations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>