<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Priya, aged 35, is a first-time investor who wants to save tax under Section 80C but is worried about equity market volatility. She has never invested in mutual funds before. Which scheme type would address both her needs?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Small-cap fund -- it offers the highest growth potential]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gilt fund -- it is safe as it invests in government securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ELSS fund via SIP -- it provides tax saving under 80C and SIP reduces the impact of volatility through rupee cost averaging]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk fund -- it offers higher returns than fixed deposits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Scheme) directly addresses Priya's tax-saving need under Section 80C. While ELSS is equity-oriented and does carry market risk, investing via SIP (Systematic Investment Plan) helps manage volatility through rupee cost averaging -- buying more units when markets are down and fewer when markets are up. The 3-year lock-in also forces discipline and gives adequate time for equity to perform.

**The Trap:** Small-cap funds are extremely volatile and not suitable for a first-time investor worried about volatility. Gilt funds do NOT qualify for 80C deduction. Credit risk funds also do not qualify for 80C and carry default risk. Only ELSS among mutual fund categories qualifies for Section 80C benefits.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For a first-time investor, the SIP route into ELSS serves multiple purposes: tax saving, forced savings discipline (SIP auto-debit), equity market exposure (wealth creation), and the lock-in prevents premature withdrawal from panic. This makes ELSS via SIP one of the best starting points for new investors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For nervous first-time investors like Priya, start with a monthly SIP of a small amount (say Rs 5,000) in a large-cap oriented ELSS fund. Show her after 3-4 months how her SIP has bought units at different prices, demonstrating rupee cost averaging in action. This builds confidence and often leads to increased SIP amounts and additional fund investments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
