<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is NOT a reliable source to track mutual fund scheme performance in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[AMFI website]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mutual fund fact sheets published by AMCs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Social media investment influencer posts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Value Research and Morningstar platforms]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Reliable sources for tracking mutual fund performance include the AMFI website (amfiindia.com), mutual fund fact sheets published by AMCs, independent research platforms like Value Research and Morningstar, and CRISIL fund rankings. Social media posts from investment influencers are NOT reliable sources as they may be biased, unverified, or based on incomplete data.

**The Trap:** While social media may sometimes contain useful opinions, it lacks the regulatory oversight, standardized methodology, and data verification that official sources provide. SEBI has been increasingly concerned about unregistered investment advice on social media platforms.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM III-C (Investment Adviser), the use of verified data sources is emphasized. Registered advisers must rely on credible, verifiable data sources, not social media. In NISM V-A, distributors must guide investors to authentic information sources.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always direct your clients to official sources like AMFI website, fund house websites, and regulated research platforms. Educate them about the risks of following social media tips, which may constitute unregistered investment advice and could be promotional content in disguise.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
