<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI categorization, a multi-cap fund must invest a minimum of what percentage in each of the large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap segments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[20% each in large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[25% each in large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[30% each in large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No mandatory minimum in any segment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandated in September 2020 that multi-cap funds must invest a minimum of 25% each in large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap stocks, totaling at least 75% in equity. This ensures genuine diversification across all market capitalizations. The remaining 25% can be allocated at the fund manager's discretion.

**The Trap:** Before this mandate, multi-cap funds had no minimum allocation requirement for each segment, and many had a large-cap bias. The 'no mandatory minimum' option reflects the old regime. Also, do not confuse multi-cap (25% each) with flexi-cap (no mandated split) or large & mid-cap (35% each in large and mid).

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 25% small-cap mandate created a challenge for large multi-cap funds as deploying significant sums in small-cap stocks without impacting prices is difficult. This is why many AMCs reclassified their multi-cap funds as flexi-cap after the new rules.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Multi-cap funds are ideal for investors who want forced diversification across all market caps. The mandatory 25% small-cap allocation means these funds will have higher volatility than large-cap or large & mid-cap funds. Set appropriate return and risk expectations with clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
