<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI regulations, when two mutual fund schemes of the same AMC are being merged or consolidated, unitholders must be:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Given adequate notice of the merger and provided an option to exit at NAV without exit load before the merger takes effect]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Automatically transferred to the surviving scheme without any notice or exit option]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Required to submit fresh KYC documents and a new application form for the surviving scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Given the option to exit only if SEBI specifically orders it in each individual case]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Scheme merger/consolidation is treated similarly to a change in fundamental attributes. Unitholders must receive adequate notice about the merger and be given an exit option at NAV without exit load before the merger becomes effective. This ensures investors are not trapped in a scheme they did not originally choose.

**The Trap:** Unitholders are NOT automatically transferred without notice — that would violate investor protection norms. Fresh KYC is not required for scheme mergers within the same AMC. The exit option is a standard regulatory requirement, not dependent on case-by-case SEBI orders.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test scheme merger/consolidation as a disclosure and investor protection requirement. The notice + exit option framework mirrors fundamental attribute changes.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** During scheme mergers, help clients understand whether the surviving scheme aligns with their investment goals. If a conservative debt scheme is being merged into an aggressive hybrid scheme, the client may want to use the exit window and reinvest elsewhere.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
