<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When comparing mutual fund scheme performance, why should peer comparison be done only within the same SEBI category?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because SEBI mandates that distributors can only sell funds within one category]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Because schemes in different categories have different risk-return profiles, making cross-category comparison misleading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because expense ratios are identical within a SEBI category]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because all funds within a SEBI category hold exactly the same securities]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Peer comparison should be done within the same SEBI category because schemes in different categories have different investment mandates, risk profiles, and return expectations. Comparing a small-cap fund's return with a liquid fund's return would be meaningless because they operate in entirely different risk-return spectrums. Same-category comparison ensures an apples-to-apples evaluation.

**The Trap:** Expense ratios are NOT identical within a category -- they vary by AMC and fund size. Funds within the same category do NOT hold exactly the same securities; they follow the same broad mandate but stock/bond selection differs. SEBI does not restrict distributors to selling within one category.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's October 2017 categorization circular created 36 scheme categories precisely to enable meaningful peer comparison. Before this, similar-sounding funds could have very different investment strategies, making comparison difficult.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a client compares their large-cap fund's 12% return unfavorably to a friend's small-cap fund's 25% return, explain category differences. Use SEBI categories to show that within large-cap, their fund might be a top performer. Context prevents investors from chasing inappropriate schemes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
