<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is the most critical metric to evaluate when selecting an index fund or ETF?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Alpha generated by the fund manager]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Tracking error]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sharpe ratio]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Portfolio turnover ratio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Tracking error measures how closely the fund replicates the performance of its benchmark index. For passive funds like index funds and ETFs, the primary objective is to mirror the index returns, not beat it. A lower tracking error indicates better replication. Tracking error arises from expense ratio, cash holdings, rebalancing delays, and impact costs.

**The Trap:** Alpha is relevant for actively managed funds where the manager tries to beat the benchmark. For passive funds, generating alpha is NOT the objective -- minimizing tracking error is. Similarly, Sharpe ratio measures risk-adjusted return of the fund, which matters more for active funds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** When comparing two index funds tracking the same index, the one with the lower tracking error and lower expense ratio is generally preferable. ETFs may have lower expense ratios than index funds, but investors must also consider liquidity (bid-ask spread) and the need for a demat account.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For cost-conscious investors, passive funds are excellent core holdings. Compare tracking error across index funds tracking the same benchmark. Also explain that ETFs need a demat account and broker, while index funds can be purchased like regular mutual funds -- this operational difference often determines suitability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
