<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Yield to Maturity (YTM) of a debt fund portfolio indicates which of the following?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The guaranteed return the investor will earn from the fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The estimated annualized return if all bonds in the portfolio are held to maturity, before expenses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The interest rate at which the fund borrows money from banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The coupon rate of the highest-rated bond in the portfolio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Yield to Maturity (YTM) of a debt fund's portfolio represents the estimated annualized return if all the bonds in the portfolio were held until maturity and all coupon payments were reinvested at the same yield. It is a theoretical measure that helps compare the earning potential of different debt funds. The actual return will differ due to changes in interest rates, credit events, and the fund's expense ratio.

**The Trap:** YTM is NOT a guaranteed return. It is a mathematical estimate based on current portfolio composition. Changes in interest rates, bond defaults, early redemptions, and expense deductions will cause actual returns to differ from YTM. Also, YTM is gross of expenses -- after TER deduction, actual returns will be lower.

**Cross-Exam Context:** When comparing two debt funds of similar duration, the one with higher YTM indicates higher potential returns, though it may also indicate higher credit risk (lower-rated bonds offer higher yields). Always evaluate YTM alongside credit quality and duration to get the full picture.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** YTM is a useful tool for setting return expectations with clients investing in debt funds. If a short-duration fund has a YTM of 7.5% and TER of 0.5%, the approximate expected return is around 7%. Never present YTM as guaranteed return. Use phrases like 'the portfolio is currently positioned to earn approximately X% over the next Y years.']]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
