<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investor strongly believes that the Indian banking sector will outperform the broader market over the next 2-3 years. He already has 70% of his portfolio in diversified equity funds. He wants to add a tactical allocation based on his view. Which scheme type is most suitable for this tactical allocation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Banking & PSU debt fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Banking sector equity fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Flexi-cap fund with banking sector overweight]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Overnight fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Since the investor has a specific sector view (banking outperformance) and wants a tactical allocation alongside his existing diversified core, a banking sector equity fund is the most direct way to express this view. The investor already has diversified exposure (70% in diversified equity), so the sector fund serves as a 'satellite' tactical position. He can allocate 10-15% to this sector fund based on conviction.

**The Trap:** Banking & PSU DEBT fund invests in bonds issued by banks and PSUs -- it has NOTHING to do with banking sector equity performance. The name similarity is a deliberate trap. A flexi-cap fund may or may not overweight banking stocks, and the investor cannot control the fund manager's sector allocation. Overnight funds are for liquidity, not for expressing sector views.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The core-satellite approach to portfolio construction uses: Core (60-70%) in diversified equity funds for stable long-term growth, and Satellite (20-30%) in sector/thematic/mid-small cap funds for tactical opportunities. The satellite allocation should be reviewed more frequently (quarterly) than the core (annually).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients express sector views, validate the reasoning before recommending sector funds. Is it based on research or media hype? Set clear entry and exit criteria ('We will review this allocation every 6 months'). Limit sector allocation to 10-15% of the total portfolio. Most importantly, remind them that sector bets can go wrong, so the diversified core is what protects the overall portfolio.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
