<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Using the '100 minus age' rule of thumb, what should be the approximate asset allocation for a 55-year-old investor approaching retirement?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[55% in equity and 45% in debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[45% in equity and 55% in debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[65% in equity and 35% in debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[30% in equity and 70% in debt]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Using the formula: Equity allocation = 100 - Age = 100 - 55 = 45%. Therefore, the allocation would be approximately 45% in equity and 55% in debt/fixed income. As the investor is 55 and approaching retirement, a higher debt allocation provides stability and protects the accumulated corpus from market volatility.

**The Trap:** The common mistake is using age AS the equity percentage (55% equity for a 55-year-old) instead of subtracting age from 100. For a 55-year-old, 55% equity would be too aggressive as retirement is only about 5 years away and recovery time from any equity market crash is limited.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This rule is a starting point. The actual allocation should consider: existing assets (PF, pension, PPF), post-retirement income needs, health expenses, dependent family members, and personal risk tolerance. A 55-year-old with a substantial pension might afford higher equity allocation than one without any pension.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients approaching retirement, implement a 'glide path' strategy -- gradually reducing equity allocation as retirement approaches. Move from 45% equity at age 55 to perhaps 30-35% by age 60. Use systematic transfer plans (STPs) from equity to debt funds to implement this gradual shift without timing risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
