<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund distributor notices that a large-cap fund has changed its benchmark from Nifty 50 TRI to Nifty 100 TRI. The fund's performance relative to the new benchmark appears significantly better. What should the distributor's primary concern be?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund has become an index fund after the benchmark change]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI will automatically penalize the fund for changing benchmarks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Whether the benchmark change was genuinely driven by investment strategy alignment or merely to make performance appear better]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The benchmark change will increase the fund's expense ratio]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When an AMC changes a fund's benchmark, it should be driven by a genuine change in investment strategy or better alignment with the fund's actual investment universe. If the only reason is to make performance look better (by switching to an easier-to-beat benchmark), it is a red flag. The distributor should investigate whether the change is justified and disclosed in the updated SID.

**The Trap:** Changing a benchmark does NOT make a fund an index fund -- it remains actively managed. SEBI does not automatically penalize benchmark changes, but requires proper justification. A benchmark change has no direct connection to expense ratio changes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The AMC must provide justification for benchmark changes, which is disclosed in the SID. Trustees must approve such changes. In NISM V-A, distributors are expected to be vigilant about such changes and inform their clients.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you notice a fund suddenly outperforming after a benchmark change, compare its performance against BOTH the old and new benchmarks. Explain the change to clients transparently. A genuine strategy evolution is fine, but cosmetic benchmark changes should make you cautious about the AMC's transparency.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
