<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When there is a change in the fundamental attributes of a mutual fund scheme, the AMC is required to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Give written notice to unitholders and provide them an exit option at NAV without any exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Obtain prior approval from SEBI before implementing any changes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Automatically convert existing units to the new scheme structure without notice]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Publish a notice only in newspapers and no direct communication to unitholders is needed]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When fundamental attributes of a scheme change (e.g., investment objective, asset allocation pattern, scheme type), the AMC must: (1) Give written notice to each unitholder, and (2) Provide an exit option at prevailing NAV without charging any exit load. This protects investors who may not agree with the changes.

**The Trap:** SEBI approval is not required for changing fundamental attributes — trustee approval suffices. However, unitholder protection through written notice and load-free exit is mandatory. The change cannot be implemented silently.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B and XII, fundamental attribute changes are linked to investor protection regulations. The load-free exit option is a critical investor right.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a scheme's fundamental attributes change, proactively contact your clients and explain the implications. Help them decide whether to stay or exit. This is a trust-building opportunity — clients remember distributors who warn them about changes that matter.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
