<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When evaluating a mutual fund scheme's Total Expense Ratio (TER), which of the following statements is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TER is charged separately to the investor over and above the NAV]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[TER is already deducted from the fund's returns before calculating the NAV, so the NAV is net of expenses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TER is applicable only to equity funds and not to debt funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A higher TER always indicates better fund management quality]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Total Expense Ratio (TER) is deducted from the fund's assets on an ongoing basis and is already reflected in the NAV. When you see a fund's NAV or return, it is net of all expenses. TER covers fund management fees, distributor commissions, custodian fees, registrar fees, audit fees, and other operating costs. SEBI has prescribed maximum TER limits based on AUM slabs.

**The Trap:** Many investors think TER is an additional charge debited from their account -- it is not. It reduces the fund's NAV from what it would have been without expenses. Also, higher TER does NOT indicate better management -- it just means higher costs. Two funds with identical gross returns will have different net returns if their TERs differ.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's TER limits are on a slab basis: for the first Rs 500 crore of AUM, maximum TER is 2.25% for equity and 2% for debt. For direct plans, TER is lower as it excludes distributor commission. The TER differential between direct and regular plans represents the distributor's commission.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While TER is important, it should not be the sole selection criterion. A fund with 1.8% TER delivering 15% returns is better than a fund with 0.5% TER delivering 10% returns. Focus on net-of-expense returns. However, for passive funds tracking the same index, lower TER is almost always preferable as the gross returns should be similar.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
