<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which SEBI regulation specifically requires that the SID must contain a clause stating that SEBI's vetting of the document should NOT be deemed as approval or endorsement of the scheme?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI (Mutual Funds) Regulations, which mandate that all SIDs carry the disclaimer that SEBI vetting does not constitute approval of the scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI (Listing Obligations and Disclosure Requirements) Regulations applicable to listed securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Companies Act provisions related to prospectus requirements for public offerings]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI guidelines on disclosure norms for financial products]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Mutual Funds) Regulations, the SID must carry a specific disclaimer that SEBI's review (vetting) of the document should not be treated as approval, endorsement, or guarantee of the scheme. This is a fundamental regulatory requirement to prevent misrepresentation.

**The Trap:** LODR Regulations apply to listed companies, not mutual fund schemes. The Companies Act governs corporate prospectuses, not mutual fund offer documents. RBI has no direct role in mutual fund document requirements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test regulatory framework knowledge. Understanding which regulation governs mutual fund documentation (SEBI MF Regulations) versus other securities regulations is essential.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This disclaimer is not just a legal formality — it is your defense against client claims that "the government approved this scheme." Always ensure clients understand that SEBI registration and document vetting do NOT equal a guarantee of safety or returns.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
