<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the key difference between a Price Return Index (PRI) and a Total Return Index (TRI)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PRI includes dividends while TRI only tracks price changes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[TRI includes dividends and interest income while PRI only tracks price changes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TRI adjusts for inflation while PRI does not]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PRI is used for equity funds while TRI is used only for debt funds]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Price Return Index (PRI) only captures the capital gains or losses from changes in the prices of the constituent securities. A Total Return Index (TRI) captures both the capital gains/losses AND the dividends or interest income earned from the constituent securities. TRI therefore always shows a higher return than PRI for dividend-paying indices.

**The Trap:** The most common mistake is reversing PRI and TRI definitions. Remember: "Total" Return Index includes the "Total" picture -- both price changes AND income. Also, TRI is not limited to debt funds; it applies to equity indices as well.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B, the TRI mandate is tested as a regulatory development. In NISM III-C (Investment Adviser), understanding TRI vs PRI is essential for making fair performance comparisons for advisory clients.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Since February 1, 2018, SEBI mandated that mutual fund performance must be compared against Total Return Index (TRI) benchmarks. The historical gap between TRI and PRI has been approximately 1.5-2.5% per annum for equity indices. This means pre-2018 performance comparisons using PRI made funds look relatively better.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
