<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund distributor recommends a scheme primarily because it pays the highest commission, rather than considering the investor's needs. This practice violates which fundamental principle?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The principle of portfolio diversification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The principle of rupee cost averaging]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The principle of suitability and fiduciary responsibility toward the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The principle of systematic investment planning]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A mutual fund distributor has a fiduciary-like responsibility to recommend schemes that are suitable for the investor's goals, risk profile, and financial situation. Recommending schemes based on commission rather than investor suitability is a clear violation of this duty. SEBI's conduct regulations for distributors emphasize that the investor's interest must come first.

**The Trap:** While diversification, rupee cost averaging, and SIP are important concepts, the direct violation here is of the suitability principle. Commission-driven selling (mis-selling) puts the distributor's interest above the investor's, which is the most fundamental ethical breach in financial distribution.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI and AMFI have strict regulations against mis-selling. Distributors must complete a suitability assessment before recommending any scheme. AMFI's Code of Conduct requires distributors to act in the investor's best interest. Violations can lead to suspension or cancellation of the ARN (AMFI Registration Number).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Building a practice around suitability, not commissions, creates long-term client relationships and AUM. A client who receives suitable advice stays invested longer, adds more money, and refers others. Commission-chasing leads to client churn and reputational risk. Your commission is a byproduct of good advice, not the primary objective.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
