<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An Aggressive Hybrid Fund must invest within which equity allocation range as per SEBI categorization?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[65% to 80% in equity and equity-related instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[40% to 60% in equity and equity-related instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[75% to 90% in equity and equity-related instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% to 70% in equity and equity-related instruments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An Aggressive Hybrid Fund invests 65% to 80% in equity and equity-related instruments, with 20% to 35% in debt instruments. The minimum 65% equity allocation means these funds qualify for equity taxation (LTCG at 12.5% after 1 year, with Rs 1.25 lakh exemption). This makes them tax-efficient compared to Balanced Hybrid funds.

**The Trap:** The most common confusion is between Aggressive Hybrid (65-80% equity) and Balanced Hybrid (40-60% equity). The tax treatment differs dramatically -- Aggressive Hybrid is taxed as equity while Balanced Hybrid is taxed as debt. Some candidates also confuse this with Conservative Hybrid (10-25% equity).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Before SEBI's recategorization in 2017, many funds called 'Balanced Funds' were actually investing 65-75% in equity. Under the new norms, these were reclassified as Aggressive Hybrid Funds. The old 'Balanced Fund' name caused investor confusion as it implied a 50:50 split.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Aggressive Hybrid funds are ideal for moderate-risk investors wanting equity-like returns with a debt cushion. The 20-35% debt component reduces downside during equity market corrections. Being taxed as equity makes them more tax-efficient than creating a separate equity + debt portfolio for investors in higher tax brackets.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
