<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_43" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mr. and Mrs. Patel have a 5-year-old daughter and want to start accumulating a corpus for her higher education (estimated need in 13 years). They have moderate risk tolerance. Which scheme combination would be most suitable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in liquid funds for safety until the daughter turns 18]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Core allocation in a large-cap or flexi-cap equity fund via SIP, with gradual shift to debt funds as the goal approaches]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in small-cap fund for maximum growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in a credit risk fund for higher returns than FDs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** With a 13-year horizon and moderate risk tolerance, a predominantly equity portfolio is appropriate in the initial years, gradually shifting toward debt as the goal approaches. A large-cap or flexi-cap equity fund provides diversified equity exposure suitable for moderate-risk investors. The SIP approach ensures disciplined investing. As the daughter reaches age 14-15, start shifting from equity to short/medium duration debt funds to protect the accumulated corpus.

**The Trap:** 100% in liquid funds for 13 years would barely beat inflation, resulting in a significantly smaller real corpus. 100% small-cap is too aggressive for moderate risk tolerance and the entire corpus should not ride on one volatile category. Credit risk funds carry default risk and are debt instruments, not suitable for long-term wealth creation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is the 'goal-based investing' approach. Steps: (1) Define the goal and timeline (education, 13 years), (2) Estimate future cost (accounting for education inflation at 8-10%), (3) Determine required SIP amount, (4) Select appropriate schemes, (5) Implement a glide path reducing equity as the goal nears. Solution-oriented children's funds can also be considered.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For child education goals, create a visual plan showing: Year 1-8 (SIP in equity funds), Year 9-11 (STP from equity to balanced/hybrid), Year 12-13 (STP to short duration debt). This phased approach maximizes growth early while protecting the corpus close to the goal. Review annually and adjust for any changes in the education cost estimate or family circumstances.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
