<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the relationship between SID, SAI, and KIM?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SID contains scheme-specific details, SAI contains AMC-level statutory information, and KIM is a summarized version of both]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SAI contains scheme-specific details, SID contains AMC-level statutory information, and KIM replaces both after launch]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KIM is the most detailed document, SID is a summary of KIM, and SAI is optional]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SID and SAI contain identical information in different formats, and KIM is prepared by SEBI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The three mandatory documents have distinct roles: SID covers scheme-specific information (objectives, strategy, risks, fees), SAI covers AMC-level statutory information (sponsors, trustees, custodian, auditors), and KIM provides a summarized version of key information from BOTH documents for quick reference.

**The Trap:** The second option swaps SID and SAI contents — a deliberate trap for candidates who confuse the two. KIM never replaces SID/SAI; it supplements them. KIM is prepared by the AMC, not SEBI.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test this hierarchical relationship repeatedly. The SID-SAI-KIM framework is foundational knowledge for all mutual fund certification exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Think of it as a pyramid: SID (detailed scheme info) + SAI (detailed AMC info) at the base, and KIM (quick summary of both) at the top. For a new investor, start with KIM, then dive into SID/SAI as needed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
