<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which factor should a distributor PRIMARILY consider when selecting a scheme for an investor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund house with the best brand recognition]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The scheme with the highest NAV indicating superior past performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The match between the investor's goals, risk profile, and time horizon with the scheme's characteristics]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The scheme with the lowest NAV as it offers more units per rupee invested]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The most critical factor in scheme selection is suitability -- matching the investor's financial goals, risk tolerance, investment horizon, and liquidity needs with the scheme's investment objective, risk profile, and features. This is the foundation of ethical distribution. A scheme that is excellent for one investor may be entirely wrong for another.

**The Trap:** NAV level is irrelevant for selection. A Rs 500 NAV fund is not 'expensive' and a Rs 10 NAV fund is not 'cheap.' What matters is the percentage return, not the absolute NAV. Similarly, brand recognition alone does not make a fund suitable. The highest NAV does not indicate superior value -- it simply reflects historical growth and initial NAV.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI's suitability requirements mandate that distributors assess: investment objective, risk appetite, investment horizon, income level, existing portfolio, and financial knowledge of the investor. Documentation of this assessment (KYC plus risk profiling) is mandatory before scheme recommendation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Develop a structured process: first assess the investor's profile (goals, risk, horizon), then shortlist suitable categories, then compare specific schemes within those categories on performance, consistency, expense ratio, and fund management quality. Never start with the scheme and work backward to justify it for the client.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
