<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Why is 'exit load' an important consideration in mutual fund scheme selection?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exit load increases the returns for long-term investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exit load is a tax levied by the government on mutual fund redemptions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Exit load reduces the redemption proceeds if units are sold before the specified period, impacting short-term liquidity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exit load is charged only on direct plan investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Exit load is a fee charged by the AMC when an investor redeems units before a specified holding period. For example, a 1% exit load for redemption within 1 year means if you sell Rs 1 lakh worth of units within 1 year, you receive only Rs 99,000. Exit loads discourage early redemption and protect long-term investors from the cost of frequent inflows/outflows. They directly impact the investor's effective return.

**The Trap:** Exit load is NOT a government tax -- it is a fee charged by the fund house. STT (Securities Transaction Tax) and capital gains tax are government levies. Also, exit load applies to both direct and regular plans equally. The exit load collected goes back into the scheme, benefiting remaining investors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Different scheme types have different exit load structures. Liquid funds: graded exit load for first 7 days (0-0.007%). Equity funds: typically 1% for 1 year. ELSS: no exit load (due to 3-year lock-in). Solution-oriented funds: exit load during lock-in period. Exit load details are disclosed in the SID and KIM.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always match the exit load structure with the investor's liquidity needs. If a client might need money within 6 months, recommending a fund with 1% exit load for 1 year is unsuitable. For emergency funds, use liquid or overnight funds with no or minimal exit loads. Document the exit load discussion to demonstrate suitability compliance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
