<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the primary purpose of the Risk-o-Meter displayed on mutual fund scheme documents?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To guarantee a minimum return to the investor based on the risk level]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To indicate the credit rating of the AMC managing the fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To visually depict the level of risk associated with the scheme to help investors assess suitability]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To compare the fund's performance against its benchmark index]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Risk-o-Meter is a visual tool mandated by SEBI that shows the risk level of a mutual fund scheme on a scale of five levels: Low, Moderately Low, Moderate, Moderately High, and High. It helps investors quickly assess whether the scheme's risk level matches their own risk tolerance. AMCs must evaluate and disclose the Risk-o-Meter on a monthly basis.

**The Trap:** The Risk-o-Meter does NOT guarantee returns or indicate AMC creditworthiness. It is a risk communication tool, not a performance metric. Some candidates also mistakenly think the Risk-o-Meter is static -- in reality, it can change monthly based on the actual portfolio composition.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI mandated the enhanced Risk-o-Meter from January 2021, replacing the older color-coded risk classification (Blue-Yellow-Brown). Fund houses must also show the Risk-o-Meter of the benchmark alongside the scheme's Risk-o-Meter. Any change in risk level must be communicated to unitholders.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the Risk-o-Meter as a conversation starter with clients about risk. Match the scheme's risk level to the investor's risk profile. If an investor's risk tolerance is 'Moderate' but they want to invest in a 'Very High' risk scheme, it is your duty to highlight this mismatch and document the discussion.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
