<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which type of debt fund is specifically designed to benefit from rising interest rate scenarios?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gilt fund with 10-year constant duration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long duration fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Credit risk fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Floater fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Floater funds invest a minimum of 65% of total assets in floating rate instruments. These instruments have interest rates that reset periodically (typically linked to a benchmark like MIBOR or T-bill rate). When interest rates rise, the coupon on floating rate instruments increases, directly benefiting investors. This makes floater funds a natural hedge against rising interest rates.

**The Trap:** Gilt funds and long duration funds do the OPPOSITE -- they suffer when interest rates rise because bond prices fall when rates increase (inverse relationship). The longer the duration, the greater the price impact. Credit risk funds are affected by credit events, not primarily by interest rate direction.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding the inverse relationship between bond prices and interest rates is fundamental. Modified duration measures interest rate sensitivity -- a fund with modified duration of 5 years will lose approximately 5% in value for every 1% rise in interest rates. Floater funds have very low modified duration due to the frequent reset mechanism.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When RBI is in a rate-hiking cycle, recommend floater funds for debt allocation. When rates are expected to fall, that is when long duration and gilt funds should be recommended. This tactical view on interest rates can add significant value to client portfolios.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
