<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_32" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued): Priya notices that Alpha Growth Fund has a Risk-o-meter reading of "High" while Beta Income Fund shows "Moderate." She asks Mr. Verma what this means for her investment decision. Mr. Verma should explain that:

Question 2: The difference in Risk-o-meter readings between the two schemes indicates:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Alpha Growth Fund carries significantly higher risk of capital loss or volatility compared to Beta Income Fund, as equity investments in large and mid-cap stocks are inherently more volatile than corporate bonds and government securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Alpha Growth Fund is guaranteed to deliver higher returns than Beta Income Fund because higher risk always means higher returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Beta Income Fund is completely risk-free since its Risk-o-meter shows "Moderate" and not "High" or "Very High"]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The Risk-o-meter readings are only marketing tools and have no regulatory significance in comparing schemes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Risk-o-meter is a SEBI-mandated visual tool that categorizes scheme risk. "High" for the equity scheme reflects the inherent volatility of equity markets, while "Moderate" for the debt scheme reflects lower but still present risks (credit risk, interest rate risk). The difference helps investors like Priya calibrate their risk tolerance.

**The Trap:** Higher risk does NOT guarantee higher returns — it only means higher potential for both gains and losses. "Moderate" risk does NOT mean risk-free; debt funds can still lose value due to credit events or interest rate changes. The Risk-o-meter IS a regulatory tool mandated by SEBI, not just marketing.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test practical interpretation of Risk-o-meter categories and their implications for investor suitability assessment.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the Risk-o-meter comparison as a suitability discussion tool. For Priya as a first-time investor, suggest starting with the "Moderate" risk Beta Income Fund for a portion of her investment, and the "High" risk Alpha Growth Fund only for money she will not need for 5+ years.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
