<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Fund A has a TER of 2.0% and generated a gross return of 14%. Fund B has a TER of 0.5% and generated a gross return of 12%. What are the net returns of Fund A and Fund B respectively?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Fund A: 12.0% and Fund B: 11.5% -- Fund A delivered higher net return despite higher TER]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fund A: 14.0% and Fund B: 12.0% -- TER does not affect investor returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fund A: 12.0% and Fund B: 12.0% -- both deliver same net return]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fund A: 11.5% and Fund B: 12.0% -- Fund B delivered higher net return due to lower TER]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Net return = Gross return - TER. Fund A: 14.0% - 2.0% = 12.0% net return. Fund B: 12.0% - 0.5% = 11.5% net return. Despite Fund A having a TER that is 4 times higher than Fund B, its superior gross return more than compensates for the higher expenses. Fund A delivers 0.5% higher net return to investors.

**The Trap:** Many investors and even distributors focus solely on TER and assume lower-cost funds are always better. This example demonstrates that what matters is the NET return after expenses. A skilled active fund manager justifying higher fees through superior stock selection can deliver better outcomes than a mediocre fund with low fees. However, this logic does NOT apply to passive/index funds tracking the same benchmark.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI has set maximum TER limits on a slab basis. For equity schemes: 2.25% on first Rs 500 crore, reducing to 1.05% for AUM above Rs 50,000 crore. The TER of direct plans is always lower than regular plans (difference equals distributor commission). Comparing direct vs regular plan TER reveals the commission component.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use this calculation with clients who are fixated on TER alone. Show them: 'Yes, Fund A charges more, but after deducting expenses, you keep more money with Fund A.' This evidence-based approach is far more convincing than arguments about brand or past rankings. Always compare net-of-expense returns over meaningful time periods.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
