<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_46" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A salaried employee in the highest tax bracket wants equity market exposure but is very uncomfortable with market volatility. He has a 7-year investment horizon. Which scheme type would best address his need for equity exposure with reduced volatility?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Small-cap fund -- longer horizon justifies the higher risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Dynamic Asset Allocation (Balanced Advantage) Fund -- it manages equity exposure dynamically to reduce volatility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Liquid fund -- it has zero volatility and is safest]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long duration gilt fund -- government bonds are safe investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Dynamic Asset Allocation (Balanced Advantage) Fund is ideal for this investor because: (1) It provides equity market exposure as requested, (2) It dynamically reduces equity when markets are expensive and increases when cheap, reducing volatility, (3) Many BAFs maintain gross equity above 65% for equity taxation (LTCG at 12.5% vs slab rate for debt), which is tax-efficient for the highest bracket, (4) The 7-year horizon is adequate for this fund type.

**The Trap:** Small-cap funds have the HIGHEST volatility among equity categories -- the opposite of what this uncomfortable investor needs, regardless of his time horizon. Liquid funds have zero volatility but provide no equity exposure and returns barely beat inflation. Gilt funds are NOT safe from volatility -- they have high interest rate risk despite being government securities.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For investors who want equity participation but cannot stomach full equity volatility, the product hierarchy from most to least volatile is: Pure equity > Aggressive Hybrid > Dynamic Asset Allocation > Conservative Hybrid > Pure debt. Dynamic Asset Allocation sits in the sweet spot of meaningful equity participation with managed volatility.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Dynamic Asset Allocation funds are powerful for converting debt-only investors into hybrid investors. The pitch is: 'This fund gives you equity returns when markets are favorable but automatically reduces equity when markets are overheated.' For highest tax bracket clients, emphasize the equity taxation benefit -- paying 12.5% LTCG vs 30%+ slab rate on debt fund gains is a significant advantage.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
