<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Where is the benchmark of a mutual fund scheme officially disclosed to investors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only on the AMFI website]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[In the annual report of the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In the Scheme Information Document (SID)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[In the Key Information Memorandum (KIM) only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The benchmark for a mutual fund scheme is officially disclosed in the Scheme Information Document (SID). The SID is the primary disclosure document that contains detailed information about the scheme's investment objective, asset allocation, benchmark, risk factors, and other important details. While the benchmark may also be mentioned in fact sheets and KIM, the SID is the official disclosure document.

**The Trap:** The KIM is an abridged version of the SID and may contain benchmark information, but the SID is the authoritative source. AMFI website publishes NAV and return data but is not the official disclosure document. The AMC annual report covers company-level information, not scheme-specific benchmark disclosure.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-A, understanding the various disclosure documents (SID, SAI, KIM) and their contents is fundamental. In NISM V-B, the regulatory framework for scheme documentation is tested in detail.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always refer to the SID when explaining a scheme to investors. The SID contains the official benchmark, asset allocation strategy, and risk factors. If a client questions why a fund's performance appears different from what was expected, the SID benchmark is the authoritative reference point.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
