<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The risk factors disclosed in the SID include:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both standard risk factors common to all mutual fund schemes and scheme-specific risk factors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only scheme-specific risk factors unique to that particular scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only standard risk factors that apply uniformly to all mutual fund schemes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Risk factors are not disclosed in the SID — they are part of the SAI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The SID must disclose both: (1) Standard risk factors that are common to all mutual fund investments (market risk, liquidity risk, etc.), and (2) Scheme-specific risk factors that are unique to the particular scheme based on its investment strategy, asset class, and structure.

**The Trap:** The SID covers BOTH types of risk factors — not just one. Risk factors are a key component of the SID, not the SAI. Candidates who answer hastily may pick "only scheme-specific" thinking standard risks are too obvious to mention.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM V-B and XII, risk disclosure is a major compliance area. Understanding that both standard and specific risks must be disclosed helps with questions about regulatory requirements and investor protection.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining risks to clients, start with standard risks (market, credit, liquidity) to set the baseline, then layer in scheme-specific risks. A client investing in a credit risk fund needs to understand both general market risk AND the specific concentration risk of lower-rated bonds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
