<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which qualitative indicator, apart from scheme returns, can help evaluate a fund manager's competence over time?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund's NAV on a specific date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The fund manager's track record across multiple schemes and consistent AUM growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The number of NFOs launched by the AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The fund's exit load structure]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A fund manager's track record across multiple schemes they have managed, along with the consistency of AUM growth under their management, serves as qualitative indicators of their competence. A manager who has consistently delivered peer-beating performance across different market cycles and multiple schemes demonstrates skill rather than luck.

**The Trap:** NAV on a specific date is just a snapshot and reveals nothing about management quality. Number of NFOs launched is a marketing metric, not a performance indicator. Exit load is a structural feature of the scheme, unrelated to manager skill.

**Cross-Exam Context:** In NISM III-C (Investment Adviser), evaluating fund managers holistically -- both quantitatively (ratios) and qualitatively (track record, tenure, investment style consistency) -- is essential for making suitable recommendations.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a fund manager changes, it is a significant event for existing investors. Track fund manager tenures from fact sheets and alert clients when their fund's manager changes. A new manager may have a different style, potentially affecting the scheme's risk-return profile.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
