<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which type of benchmark would be most appropriate for a hybrid fund that invests 65% in equity and 35% in debt?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Nifty 50 TRI alone]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[CRISIL Composite Bond Fund Index alone]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A blended benchmark combining an equity index and a debt index in appropriate proportions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Domestic gold price index]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Hybrid funds invest across multiple asset classes, so their benchmark should reflect the same asset allocation. A blended benchmark combines an equity index (like Nifty 50 TRI) and a debt index (like CRISIL Composite Bond Fund Index) in proportions matching the fund's asset allocation. For a 65:35 equity-debt fund, the benchmark might be 65% Nifty 50 TRI + 35% CRISIL Composite Bond Index.

**The Trap:** Using only an equity index would make the hybrid fund look conservative during equity bull runs, while using only a debt index would make it look aggressive. A single-asset benchmark is inappropriate for a multi-asset fund.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Hybrid fund categorization under SEBI includes Aggressive Hybrid (65-80% equity), Balanced Hybrid (40-60% equity), and Conservative Hybrid (10-25% equity). Each sub-category should have appropriately weighted blended benchmarks.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When reviewing hybrid fund performance, ensure the blended benchmark weights match the fund's actual asset allocation, not just its mandate range. If a fund is allowed 65-80% equity but consistently runs at 75% equity, a 65:35 blended benchmark may understate the fund's risk exposure.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
