<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued): Priya asks why the scheme performance in the SID is compared against "Nifty 200 TRI" and "CRISIL Composite Bond TRI" rather than just "Nifty 200" and "CRISIL Composite Bond Index."

Question 3: Mr. Verma should explain that the "TRI" (Total Return Index) is mandated because:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[TRI includes both price appreciation and dividend/interest income reinvested, providing a fairer comparison since mutual funds also reinvest income, whereas a Price Return Index would make fund performance appear artificially better]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TRI adjusts for inflation, giving investors a real return figure that is more meaningful than nominal returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TRI deducts the fund's expense ratio from the benchmark return so that the comparison is on a net-of-fees basis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TRI is simply a newer version of the index with no material difference from the regular index]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates TRI because mutual funds reinvest dividends and interest income they receive from underlying securities. The TRI benchmark also accounts for this reinvestment, creating an apples-to-apples comparison. Using PRI (which ignores dividend income) would make fund outperformance appear larger than it actually is.

**The Trap:** TRI does NOT adjust for inflation — that would be a "real return" calculation. TRI does NOT deduct expense ratios — it is a gross return measure. TRI is fundamentally different from PRI, not just a newer version.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test the TRI vs PRI distinction extensively. The key insight is that TRI prevents AMCs from inflating their apparent alpha by comparing against an incomplete benchmark.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Explain to Priya with a simple example: if a stock index yields 2% in dividends, a fund that merely matches the index would show 2% outperformance against PRI. With TRI, the same fund shows 0% outperformance — the honest picture. This helps clients truly evaluate fund manager skill.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
