<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_37" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A couple, both aged 30, want to build a retirement corpus over 30 years. Using the '100 minus age' rule and considering they will gradually reduce equity, what should be their STARTING equity allocation, and what should it approximately be at age 55?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Start: 30% equity; At 55: 55% equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Start: 70% equity; At 55: 45% equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Start: 50% equity; At 55: 50% equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Start: 100% equity; At 55: 0% equity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** At age 30: Equity allocation = 100 - 30 = 70% equity, 30% debt. At age 55: Equity allocation = 100 - 55 = 45% equity, 55% debt. This illustrates the 'glide path' concept where equity allocation systematically reduces as the investor ages. Over 25 years, equity reduces from 70% to 45%, gradually shifting the portfolio from growth-oriented to stability-oriented.

**The Trap:** Option A reverses the formula (using age as equity percentage instead of 100-age). Option C (50:50 at both ages) ignores the age-based adjustment principle. Option D (100% to 0%) is too extreme -- even retirees benefit from some equity exposure to combat inflation. The glide path should be gradual, not binary.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The glide path concept is used in target-date retirement funds globally. In India, solution-oriented retirement funds may implement a similar approach. The gradual shift can be implemented through: (1) STP from equity to debt funds periodically, (2) adjusting SIP allocations, or (3) periodic rebalancing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Create a visual timeline for the couple showing how their allocation changes over 30 years: Age 30 (70:30) -> Age 40 (60:40) -> Age 50 (50:50) -> Age 55 (45:55) -> Age 60 (40:60). This makes the abstract concept tangible. Set calendar reminders for annual rebalancing reviews. The glide path approach prevents the catastrophic scenario of having 70% equity right when retirement approaches and markets crash.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
