<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which type of equity fund has complete flexibility to invest across large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap stocks without any mandated minimum allocation to any capitalization segment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Multi-cap fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Flexi-cap fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Large & mid-cap fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Focused fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A flexi-cap fund has the flexibility to invest across all market capitalizations without any mandated minimum allocation to large, mid, or small-cap segments. The fund manager can dynamically shift allocations based on market conditions and valuations. The only mandate is minimum 65% in equity.

**The Trap:** The most common confusion is between multi-cap and flexi-cap. A multi-cap fund must invest a minimum of 25% each in large-cap, mid-cap, and small-cap stocks (totaling 75% minimum). Flexi-cap has NO such split mandate -- that is the key difference. Before SEBI introduced the multi-cap mandate in 2020, multi-cap funds operated like today's flexi-cap funds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SEBI introduced the flexi-cap category in November 2020 after mandating 25% minimum allocations for multi-cap funds. Many AMCs converted their existing multi-cap funds to flexi-cap to retain flexibility.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For investors who want the fund manager to have maximum flexibility across market caps, recommend flexi-cap. For those who want guaranteed diversification across all segments, multi-cap ensures minimum 25% in each -- protecting against fund manager bias toward any single segment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
