<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (Continued): Mr. Verma informs Priya about the AMC's announcement that Alpha Growth Fund's investment objective is being changed from "long-term capital appreciation through equity" to "aggressive growth through concentrated equity positions." Priya already holds units in this scheme.

Question 4: Regarding this change in investment objective, which of the following is TRUE?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Priya must receive a written notice about the change and has the right to exit at the prevailing NAV without any exit load if she disagrees with the new objective]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Since Priya has already invested, she is bound by whatever changes the AMC makes to the scheme and cannot exit without paying exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The change requires approval from at least 75% of existing unitholders through a voting process before it can be implemented]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Priya can exit load-free only if she files a formal complaint with SEBI within 15 days of the announcement]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A change in investment objective is a change in fundamental attributes of the scheme. Under SEBI regulations, the AMC MUST: (1) Send written notice to every unitholder including Priya, and (2) Provide Priya the option to exit at the prevailing NAV without any exit load. This protects investors who made their investment decision based on the original objective.

**The Trap:** Investors are NOT bound by fundamental attribute changes — they have explicit exit rights. No unitholder voting is required; it is the trustee's approval plus mandatory exit option that governs. The exit right is automatic upon written notice — no complaint to SEBI is needed.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII heavily test fundamental attribute change scenarios. The three-part framework (written notice + exit at NAV + no exit load) must be memorized as a unit.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In Priya's case, moving from "long-term capital appreciation" to "aggressive concentrated positions" is a significant risk escalation. As her distributor, Mr. Verma should proactively explain that the new objective carries higher concentration risk, help her evaluate if it matches her risk profile, and if not, facilitate her load-free exit and suggest suitable alternatives.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
