<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mrs. Sharma, a 62-year-old retiree, needs regular monthly income from her Rs 50 lakh retirement corpus. She has low risk tolerance and no other source of income. Which scheme type would be MOST suitable for her?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Small-cap equity fund with SWP (Systematic Withdrawal Plan)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sector fund focused on IT sector]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Conservative Hybrid Fund or Short Duration Debt Fund with SWP]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ELSS fund for tax saving benefits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mrs. Sharma needs regular income, has low risk tolerance, and has no other income source -- making capital preservation critical. A Conservative Hybrid Fund (75-90% debt, 10-25% equity) provides stability from debt with a small equity kicker to beat inflation. Alternatively, a Short Duration Debt Fund with SWP provides predictable income with low volatility. The SWP mechanism creates regular cash flows without eroding capital rapidly.

**The Trap:** Small-cap funds have very high volatility -- entirely inappropriate for a retiree dependent on her corpus for income. A sector fund is highly concentrated and risky. ELSS has a 3-year lock-in and is equity-heavy, both unsuitable for her immediate income needs and low risk profile. The question tests suitability assessment, not return maximization.

**Cross-Exam Context:** For regular income needs, the choice between conservative hybrid and debt funds depends on the investor's tax bracket and equity comfort. Conservative hybrid funds offer slight equity exposure for inflation hedging. For extremely risk-averse retirees, a combination of overnight fund (for 3 months' expenses) + short duration fund (for SWP) provides a layered approach.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For retirees, structure the portfolio in 'buckets': Bucket 1 (0-1 year needs) in liquid/ultra-short funds, Bucket 2 (1-5 year needs) in short/medium duration funds with SWP, Bucket 3 (5+ year buffer) in conservative hybrid or balanced advantage funds. This ensures immediate liquidity while maintaining long-term purchasing power.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
