<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_49" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY (continued): The Verma Family Financial Plan

Referring to the Verma family scenario described in Question 47:

QUESTION 49: For Mr. Verma's father (age 65, retired, pension Rs 25,000/month, savings Rs 25 lakh), who needs supplementary monthly income of Rs 15,000, which scheme selection and withdrawal strategy is most appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest the entire Rs 25 lakh in a small-cap fund and set up an SWP of Rs 15,000 per month]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest the entire Rs 25 lakh in an overnight fund to ensure zero risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Split the corpus: Rs 5 lakh in a liquid fund (for 3-6 months of withdrawals), Rs 12 lakh in a short-duration/conservative hybrid fund with SWP of Rs 15,000, and Rs 8 lakh in an aggressive hybrid/dynamic asset allocation fund for growth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Invest the entire Rs 25 lakh in a credit risk fund for maximum yield]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mr. Verma's father needs a sustainable Rs 15,000/month (Rs 1.8 lakh/year) from Rs 25 lakh -- that is a withdrawal rate of 7.2%. A bucketed approach is ideal: Bucket 1 (Rs 5 lakh in liquid fund) provides 3+ months of immediate withdrawals without market risk. Bucket 2 (Rs 12 lakh in short-duration/conservative hybrid) provides the SWP source for regular income with moderate stability. Bucket 3 (Rs 8 lakh in aggressive hybrid/BAF) provides growth to combat inflation and replenishes Bucket 2 periodically. As Bucket 2 depletes, units from Bucket 3 are transferred via STP.

**The Trap:** Full investment in small-cap is extremely inappropriate for a 65-year-old retiree needing income -- a 30% market crash would reduce Rs 25 lakh to Rs 17.5 lakh while he continues withdrawing Rs 15,000/month, creating a devastating sequence-of-returns risk. Full investment in overnight fund means approximately 4-5% returns, which at Rs 1 lakh/year barely covers 55% of the Rs 1.8 lakh annual withdrawal, rapidly depleting capital. Credit risk funds have default risk -- a single default could erode the retirement corpus significantly.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 7.2% withdrawal rate is relatively high. With the pension providing Rs 25,000/month for essential expenses, the supplementary Rs 15,000 is for lifestyle expenses. If markets underperform, this can be temporarily reduced. The growth bucket (Bucket 3) is critical -- without it, the corpus will deplete in approximately 14-15 years even with 6-7% returns on the debt portion.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For retirees, present the bucket strategy visually. Show three jars: 'Immediate' (liquid), 'Income' (debt-oriented with SWP), and 'Growth' (hybrid for inflation protection). Annual review should rebalance by topping up Bucket 1 from Bucket 2, and Bucket 2 from Bucket 3. This gives the retiree peace of mind -- they can see their immediate needs are covered regardless of market conditions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
