<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Performance_37" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[SEBI's October 2021 circular mandated a two-tier benchmark structure for mutual fund schemes. Under this framework, the Tier-1 benchmark is ________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A broad market index reflective of the scheme's category]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A scheme-specific benchmark chosen by the fund manager]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A benchmark selected by the fund manager based on investment style]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A single AMC-wide benchmark applied to all schemes of the fund house]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's two-tier benchmark structure works as follows: Tier-1 is a broad market index that reflects the scheme's category (e.g., Nifty 50 for large-cap equity funds, CRISIL 10 Year Gilt Index for gilt funds). This ensures uniformity and comparability across schemes in the same category. Tier-2 is a bespoke (customized) benchmark that more closely reflects the scheme's specific investment style or strategy, allowing for more nuanced performance evaluation.

**The Trap:** "Scheme-specific" (Option B) and "investment style" (Option C) describe the Tier-2 benchmark, not Tier-1. The Tier-1 benchmark is standardized per category, not customized per scheme. "AMC-wide benchmark" (Option D) is incorrect because benchmarks are category-specific, not AMC-specific -- all large-cap funds across all AMCs would share the same Tier-1 benchmark.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The two-tier system was introduced to improve performance comparability. Tier-1 enables apples-to-apples comparison across AMCs within the same category. Tier-2 enables evaluation of whether the fund manager's specific strategy added value relative to a more tailored benchmark.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Tier-1 = broad category-level index (standardized, for comparability). Tier-2 = bespoke scheme-specific index (customized, for strategy evaluation). Mandated by SEBI Oct 2021 circular.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
