<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="Scheduled Offences under PMLA_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following environmental offences is included as a scheduled offence under Part A of the PMLA Schedule?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minor littering in public places]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Penalty for discharging environmental pollutants under the Environment Protection Act, 1986]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Failure to recycle household waste]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Using single-use plastic bags]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Part A, Paragraph 25 covers offences under the Environment Protection Act, 1986 — specifically Section 15 read with Section 7 (discharging environmental pollutants) and Section 15 read with Section 8 (handling hazardous substances). Paragraph 26 covers Water Pollution Act offences and Paragraph 27 covers Air Pollution Act offences.

**The Trap:** Minor infractions like littering or plastic bag usage are not scheduled offences under PMLA. The Schedule targets serious environmental crimes that may generate significant proceeds — such as illegal dumping of hazardous waste for profit.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The inclusion of environmental offences in the PMLA Schedule reflects the growing recognition that environmental crimes can be highly profitable and involve money laundering. This is consistent with FATF's expanded approach to predicate offences.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Environmental crime syndicates may use the financial system to launder proceeds from illegal waste disposal, illegal mining, or wildlife trafficking. As an intermediary, unusual fund flows from companies in waste management or mining sectors could be red flags.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>