<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[According to the common age-based rule of thumb for asset allocation, what should be the approximate equity allocation for a 35-year-old investor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[35% in equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[65% in equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[100% in equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[50% in equity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The commonly used age-based rule of thumb states: Equity allocation = 100 - Age. For a 35-year-old investor, this gives 100 - 35 = 65% in equity, with the remaining 35% in debt and other asset classes. This rule is based on the principle that younger investors have a longer time horizon to ride out equity volatility, while older investors need more stability.

**The Trap:** The common mistake is to use age as the equity allocation (35% equity for a 35-year-old). The formula is 100 MINUS age, not age itself. Also, this is a starting point rule of thumb, not an absolute mandate. Individual risk tolerance, income stability, financial goals, and existing assets should modify this allocation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Some variations use 110 - age or even 120 - age for more aggressive investors. For a conservative investor, 80 - age might be appropriate. The key principle is that equity allocation should decrease as the investor approaches their goal, not that the formula should be rigidly applied.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use the '100 minus age' rule as a conversation starter, then customize based on the individual's situation. A 35-year-old IT professional with stable income might be comfortable with 75% equity, while a 35-year-old self-employed person with irregular income might need only 50% equity. The rule provides structure, but suitability assessment provides personalization.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
