<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Related Information_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An AMC decides to change the benchmark index of one of its equity schemes from Nifty 50 TRI to Nifty 100 TRI. This change:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[May be considered a change in fundamental attributes, requiring written notice and exit option at NAV without exit load]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Is a routine operational change that requires no communication to unitholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Requires SEBI to personally approve the new benchmark before implementation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Automatically converts the scheme from a large-cap to a multi-cap category]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A change in benchmark index can be considered a change in fundamental attributes because the benchmark is part of the scheme's identity disclosed in the SID. If this constitutes a fundamental attribute change, the AMC must provide written notice to unitholders and offer an exit at NAV without exit load.

**The Trap:** Benchmark changes are NOT routine — they can signal a shift in scheme positioning. SEBI does not personally approve individual benchmark changes. Changing the benchmark does not automatically change the scheme category — those are governed by SEBI categorization norms.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM V-B and XII test whether candidates understand the breadth of what constitutes "fundamental attributes." Benchmark changes, while seemingly technical, can significantly alter how scheme performance is perceived.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a scheme changes its benchmark, investigate why. Sometimes AMCs switch to a broader benchmark to make underperformance less visible. Always evaluate whether the new benchmark is appropriate for the scheme's actual investment universe.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
