<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the equity allocation range for a 'Balanced Hybrid Fund' as per SEBI categorization?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[65% to 80% in equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[40% to 60% in equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[10% to 25% in equity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[25% to 40% in equity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Balanced Hybrid Fund invests 40% to 60% of total assets in equity and 40% to 60% in debt instruments. This creates a roughly equal split between equity and debt. Importantly, no arbitrage is permitted in this category, ensuring genuine balanced exposure.

**The Trap:** The three hybrid categories are often confused: Conservative Hybrid (10-25% equity, 75-90% debt), Balanced Hybrid (40-60% equity, 40-60% debt), and Aggressive Hybrid (65-80% equity, 20-35% debt). Many candidates confuse Aggressive Hybrid with Balanced Hybrid. Note that 'Balanced Advantage Fund' refers to Dynamic Asset Allocation, which is a separate category.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Tax treatment differs significantly among hybrid categories. Aggressive Hybrid funds (65-80% equity) are taxed as equity funds, while Balanced Hybrid and Conservative Hybrid are taxed as debt funds since their equity allocation is below 65%. This tax difference is a critical suitability factor.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask for a 'balanced fund,' clarify which type they need. Many investors actually want Aggressive Hybrid (taxed as equity, higher growth) but use the word 'balanced.' A truly balanced 50:50 allocation (Balanced Hybrid) is taxed as debt, which may not be tax-efficient for long-term investors.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
