<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When assessing the consistency of a mutual fund's performance, what is the most reliable approach?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Looking at only the last 1-year return as it reflects the most current performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Checking if the fund delivered the highest return in any single year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Evaluating the fund's performance across different time periods and market cycles (bull and bear phases)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Selecting the fund with the highest AUM as larger funds always perform better]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Consistency of performance means the fund has delivered competitive returns across different market conditions -- both bull and bear phases. A fund that ranks in the top quartile during bull markets but drops to the bottom quartile during corrections is inconsistent. Evaluating returns across 1-year, 3-year, 5-year, and through complete market cycles gives a more comprehensive picture of the fund manager's skill.

**The Trap:** Looking at only 1-year returns can be misleading -- a fund that took excessive risk might top the charts in one year but crash the next. Similarly, the highest single-year return does not indicate consistency; it might indicate aggressive risk-taking. AUM size has no direct correlation with performance quality.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Quantitative metrics for consistency include: rolling returns (returns over overlapping periods), standard deviation (volatility), Sharpe ratio (risk-adjusted return), and information ratio (consistency of alpha over benchmark). Qualitative factors include fund manager tenure, investment process stability, and AMC pedigree.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When presenting funds to clients, show rolling returns charts rather than point-to-point returns. A fund that consistently delivers 12-15% across most 3-year rolling periods is more reliable than one that swings between -5% and 30%. Consistency builds client confidence and reduces the temptation to switch funds frequently.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
