<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Scheme Selection_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An NRI investor is concerned about the Indian rupee depreciating against the US dollar and wants to hedge this currency risk. The distributor suggests adding international equity funds to the portfolio. Is this suggestion appropriate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because international funds carry additional currency risk that will compound the NRI's existing risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because international funds investing in USD-denominated assets provide a natural hedge -- if the rupee depreciates against USD, the rupee value of these investments increases]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because NRIs are not allowed to invest in international mutual funds in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only if the NRI invests through a Gold ETF instead]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For an NRI earning and spending in USD, investing in Indian mutual funds carries the risk of INR depreciation (when converting back to USD, they get fewer dollars). Adding international funds that invest in USD-denominated assets provides a natural currency hedge. If INR depreciates against USD, the rupee value of the international fund increases, offsetting losses on the NRI's other INR investments. This is a valid diversification and hedging strategy.

**The Trap:** For a RESIDENT Indian investor, international funds ADD currency risk. But for an NRI with USD-denominated liabilities, it is the opposite -- international USD funds REDUCE their effective currency risk. The NRI investing restriction is also incorrect -- NRIs can invest in Indian mutual funds (including fund of funds investing internationally) subject to certain conditions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Currency risk works differently for different investors. A resident Indian investing abroad faces rupee depreciation as a tailwind (returns enhance in INR terms) but appreciation as a headwind. An NRI faces the opposite. Understanding the investor's base currency and liabilities is critical for proper scheme selection.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For NRI clients, always analyze currency exposure holistically. If the NRI earns in USD and plans to retire in India (spending INR), their needs are different from an NRI who will continue living abroad. Tailor the domestic vs international allocation based on where they plan to spend the money eventually.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
