<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI LODR Regulations_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> TrustLink Registrars Ltd. is a SEBI-registered Category I RTA managing 3.2 crore folios across 450 listed companies. The RTA was established in 2010 and employs 800 staff members. Ashok Patel is the Compliance Officer, and Kavita Sharma is the Head of Operations.

During a recent SEBI inspection, the following observations were noted: (a) an investor grievance filed on February 1, 2025 by Deepak Verma remained unresolved as of March 15, 2025; (b) the internal auditor, Mr. Suresh Joshi (a Chartered Accountant with 8 years of experience), has been conducting the annual audit since April 2019; (c) correction of investor details in the database was being done directly by operations staff without company approval; (d) physical share bonus credits for one issuer were processed in demat mode; and (e) the structured digital database for UPSI shared by client companies was being maintained with timestamps but without PAN details of recipients.

TrustLink's Board is reviewing these findings and must take corrective action. Additionally, three issuers have unpaid dividends for investors whose records show no PAN or bank details updates for over 3 years.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Mr. Suresh Joshi has been the internal auditor since April 2019. As of the current inspection, what action must TrustLink take regarding his appointment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suresh can continue for one more year as the maximum term is 7 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Suresh must be replaced after completing his current audit cycle, as he has served for nearly 6 years, exceeding the 5-year maximum term]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suresh's appointment is valid as there is no maximum term limit for internal auditors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suresh must be replaced only if SEBI specifically orders rotation during the inspection]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's strengthening guidelines prescribe a maximum 5-year term for the internal auditor of an RTA, followed by a mandatory 2-year cooling-off period. Suresh Joshi started in April 2019. By 2025, he has served nearly 6 years, which exceeds the 5-year maximum. He should have been rotated out by April 2024. TrustLink must immediately appoint a new auditor.
**The Trap:** There is no 7-year limit or provision for SEBI-ordered rotation only. The 5-year maximum is a firm rule. Note that the auditor must be a CA, CS, CMA, or CISA with at least 3 years of experience -- Suresh meets the qualification (CA with 8 years) but has exceeded the tenure limit.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The internal audit report must be submitted to the issuer within 3 months, and the issuer must provide an action taken report within 1 month thereafter.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a rotation schedule for internal auditors and start the selection process for a replacement at least 6 months before the 5-year term expires. This ensures a smooth transition and uninterrupted audit coverage.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
