<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI LODR Regulations_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Nirmala Sundarajan is the newly appointed Compliance Officer (a qualified Company Secretary) of Pinnacle Industries Ltd., a listed entity with a market capitalization of Rs.8,500 crore and 1.2 lakh shareholders. The company is listed on both NSE and BSE. The current quarter ending is September 30, 2025.

Pinnacle's Board of Directors is scheduled to meet on October 20, 2025, to consider the quarterly financial results and an interim dividend. On October 5, 2025, the promoter group completes a preferential allotment that increases their holding by 2.5%. The company's wholly-owned subsidiary, Pinnacle Solutions Pvt. Ltd. (which contributes 35% of consolidated revenue), is considering selling a manufacturing unit worth Rs.200 crore, representing 25% of its total assets.

Nirmala must ensure all SEBI LODR compliance requirements are met while coordinating with DataServe RTAs, the company's appointed registrar and share transfer agent. DataServe manages 2.8 crore folios across all its clients and has had the same internal auditor for the past 4 years.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> The promoter group's preferential allotment on October 5, 2025 increased shareholding by 2.5%. Under SEBI LODR, what additional filing obligation does this trigger for Nirmala?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No additional filing since the regular quarterly filing will cover this change]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A revised shareholding pattern must be filed within 10 days (by October 15, 2025) due to the >2% capital change]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An immediate filing within 24 hours as a material event disclosure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A special filing within 30 days to SEBI's corporate finance department]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Regulation 31 requires an additional shareholding pattern filing within 10 days when any capital restructuring results in a change of more than 2% in shareholding. Since the 2.5% change exceeds the 2% threshold, Nirmala must file by October 15, 2025 (10 days from October 5).
**The Trap:** Waiting for the regular quarterly filing (due October 21) is not sufficient. The >2% change creates a separate, earlier filing obligation. While 24-hour disclosure applies to material events, the shareholding pattern has its own specific 10-day requirement.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The three triggers for Reg 31 filing are: quarterly (21 days), pre-listing (1 day before), and >2% capital change (10 days). This scenario tests the third trigger.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Preferential allotments frequently exceed the 2% threshold. RTAs should proactively alert the issuer's Compliance Officer about the filing obligation when they process such allotments, rather than waiting to be asked.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
