<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[When a client is subsequently found to be or becomes a Politically Exposed Person (PEP), what approval must the intermediary obtain?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Senior management approval to continue the business relationship]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI's written approval to continue servicing the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FIU-IND's prior permission before any further transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The client's written consent to be classified as PEP]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a client or beneficial owner is subsequently found to be or becomes a PEP, the intermediary must obtain SENIOR MANAGEMENT approval to continue the business relationship. This elevates the decision from routine operations to the highest management level.

**The Trap:** SEBI and FIU-IND do not need to individually approve PEP client relationships. The approval is internal -- senior management of the intermediary. Client consent for PEP classification is irrelevant; PEP status is a factual determination, not a choice.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Senior management approval for PEP relationships is also required for initial onboarding of PEPs. This principle appears in NISM V-A for mutual fund distribution and NISM III-A for securities intermediaries.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Senior management involvement for PEPs is not just a formality. Document the approval with the date, name of the approving officer, and the rationale for continuing the relationship. This becomes vital evidence during compliance inspections.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
