<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI LODR Regulations_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Sanjay Kulkarni, an internal auditor at DataLink RTAs, has been conducting the compulsory annual audit for the past 5 years. Under SEBI's strengthening guidelines for RTAs, what must happen now?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sanjay can continue for another 5 years as the maximum term is 10 years]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sanjay must be replaced as the maximum term is 5 years, followed by a 2-year cooling-off period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sanjay must be replaced as the maximum term is 3 years with no cooling-off period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sanjay's appointment is automatically renewed for another 5 years by SEBI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's strengthening guidelines mandate that the internal auditor of an RTA can serve for a maximum term of 5 years, followed by a mandatory 2-year cooling-off period before reappointment. Since Sanjay has completed 5 years, he must be replaced.
**The Trap:** There is no automatic renewal or 10-year maximum. The 5-year term with 2-year cooling ensures auditor independence and fresh perspectives. The audit must be conducted by a CA, CS, CMA, or CISA with at least 3 years of experience.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The internal audit must cover all RTA operations, with the report submitted to the issuer within 3 months and an action taken report within 1 month thereafter.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** RTAs should plan auditor rotation well in advance of the 5-year deadline. The 2-year cooling period means firms need to maintain relationships with multiple qualified auditors to ensure continuity of audit quality.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
