<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI guidelines, when must intermediaries assess the money laundering and terrorist financing risks associated with new products, business practices, delivery mechanisms, and new technologies?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Before launching the new products or business practices]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within 30 days of launching the new products or business practices]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Within one year of launching the new products, as part of the annual risk assessment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only for products classified as high-risk during the initial product design phase]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI guidelines explicitly require intermediaries to identify and assess ML/TF risks associated with the development of new products, new business practices, new delivery mechanisms, and the use of new or developing technologies - and this assessment must occur prior to the launch. The word "before" is critical and distinguishes this from a post-launch review.

**The Trap:** The 30-day and one-year options sound reasonable as compliance timelines but are incorrect. The requirement is pre-launch, not post-launch. The "only for high-risk products" distractor is also wrong because the assessment applies to all new products regardless of their initial risk classification - the point of the assessment is to determine the risk.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This pre-launch risk assessment requirement aligns with FATF Recommendation 15 on new technologies. It ensures that compliance is built into product design rather than retrofitted after vulnerabilities are exploited.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ML/TF risk assessment for new products, business practices, delivery mechanisms, and technologies must happen before launch - not after. This is a proactive, not reactive, compliance requirement.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
