<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI LODR Regulations_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Nirmala Sundarajan is the newly appointed Compliance Officer (a qualified Company Secretary) of Pinnacle Industries Ltd., a listed entity with a market capitalization of Rs.8,500 crore and 1.2 lakh shareholders. The company is listed on both NSE and BSE. The current quarter ending is September 30, 2025.

Pinnacle's Board of Directors is scheduled to meet on October 20, 2025, to consider the quarterly financial results and an interim dividend. On October 5, 2025, the promoter group completes a preferential allotment that increases their holding by 2.5%. The company's wholly-owned subsidiary, Pinnacle Solutions Pvt. Ltd. (which contributes 35% of consolidated revenue), is considering selling a manufacturing unit worth Rs.200 crore, representing 25% of its total assets.

Nirmala must ensure all SEBI LODR compliance requirements are met while coordinating with DataServe RTAs, the company's appointed registrar and share transfer agent. DataServe manages 2.8 crore folios across all its clients and has had the same internal auditor for the past 4 years.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Given Pinnacle Industries' market capitalization of Rs.8,500 crore, which of the following LODR obligations is specifically triggered by this size?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pinnacle must file financial results within 30 days instead of 45 days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Pinnacle qualifies for the reduced minimum public shareholding of 10% since its post-issue capital is within the Rs.4,000-Rs.1,00,000 crore range]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pinnacle is exempt from quarterly corporate governance reporting]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Pinnacle must appoint two Compliance Officers instead of one]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI LODR, companies with post-issue capital between Rs.4,000 crore and Rs.1,00,000 crore qualify for a reduced minimum public shareholding of 10% instead of the standard 25%. At Rs.8,500 crore, Pinnacle falls within this range.
**The Trap:** The reduced threshold applies to post-issue capital, not market capitalization. However, in this scenario the large market cap is used as an indicator of size. Financial result timelines (45/60 days) and corporate governance reporting requirements do not change based on company size.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Additionally, being among the top 1000 listed entities likely requires Pinnacle to formulate and disclose a Dividend Distribution Policy -- relevant since the Board is considering an interim dividend.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Companies benefiting from the reduced 10% public holding threshold must be monitored carefully. Even small changes in promoter holding can push them below the minimum. RTAs should track promoter shareholding levels as part of their compliance support services.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
