<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Registered intermediaries are required to identify PEPs through which of the following methods?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[All of the above -- seeking information from clients, referring to public information, and accessing commercial electronic PEP databases]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only seeking relevant information from the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only referring to publicly available information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only accessing commercial electronic databases of PEPs]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Intermediaries must proactively put in place risk management systems to identify PEPs through MULTIPLE methods: (1) seeking relevant information from the client, (2) referring to publicly available information, AND (3) accessing commercial electronic databases of PEPs. All three methods should be used together.

**The Trap:** No single method is sufficient on its own. Self-declaration by the client alone is unreliable. Public information alone may be incomplete. Commercial databases alone may not be current. A combination approach is mandatory.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PEP identification is a critical AML requirement across all NISM exams. The multi-method approach ensures comprehensive screening. In practice, most intermediaries use a combination of client disclosure, screening software, and public records.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PEP status can change -- a client may become a PEP after account opening (e.g., gets elected to office). You need ongoing screening, not just initial check. If a client becomes a PEP, obtain senior management approval to continue the relationship.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
