<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI LODR Regulations_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Nirmala Sundarajan is the newly appointed Compliance Officer (a qualified Company Secretary) of Pinnacle Industries Ltd., a listed entity with a market capitalization of Rs.8,500 crore and 1.2 lakh shareholders. The company is listed on both NSE and BSE. The current quarter ending is September 30, 2025.

Pinnacle's Board of Directors is scheduled to meet on October 20, 2025, to consider the quarterly financial results and an interim dividend. On October 5, 2025, the promoter group completes a preferential allotment that increases their holding by 2.5%. The company's wholly-owned subsidiary, Pinnacle Solutions Pvt. Ltd. (which contributes 35% of consolidated revenue), is considering selling a manufacturing unit worth Rs.200 crore, representing 25% of its total assets.

Nirmala must ensure all SEBI LODR compliance requirements are met while coordinating with DataServe RTAs, the company's appointed registrar and share transfer agent. DataServe manages 2.8 crore folios across all its clients and has had the same internal auditor for the past 4 years.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Regarding the proposed sale of 25% of Pinnacle Solutions' assets, what governance requirement applies under SEBI LODR since it is a material subsidiary?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Board approval of Pinnacle Industries is required]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A special resolution of Pinnacle Industries' shareholders is required since disposal exceeds 20% of the material subsidiary's assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI must provide prior written approval for the transaction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The transaction requires approval from the stock exchanges before proceeding]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI LODR corporate governance provisions, disposal of more than 20% of the assets of a material subsidiary requires a special resolution from the shareholders of the listed entity. Since Pinnacle Solutions contributes 35% of consolidated revenue (making it material) and the sale represents 25% of its assets (exceeding the 20% threshold), shareholder approval via special resolution is mandatory.
**The Trap:** Board approval alone is insufficient for asset disposals exceeding 20% of a material subsidiary. SEBI and stock exchange pre-approval is not required -- it is the shareholders who must approve via special resolution.
**Cross-Exam Context:** LODR also requires at least one independent director of the listed entity to be on the material subsidiary's board, providing ongoing governance oversight.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Nirmala must ensure the postal ballot or EGM notice clearly describes the asset sale, its impact on the subsidiary, and the rationale. RTAs will need to process the e-voting or postal ballot for this special resolution.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
