<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What should happen after an STR has been filed on a client's account? Should operations in the account be restricted?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No restrictions should be placed; the intermediary shall continue dealing with the client as normal until told otherwise]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All operations in the account must be immediately frozen]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only debit transactions should be blocked while credit transactions can continue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The account must be closed within 30 days of filing the STR]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Registered intermediaries shall NOT put any restrictions on operations in accounts where an STR has been filed. The intermediary must continue dealing with the client as normal until told otherwise. This is to avoid tipping off the client.

**The Trap:** Filing an STR does NOT automatically mean freezing or restricting the account. Account freezes happen only on specific orders from authorities (like under UAPA Section 51A), not automatically upon STR filing.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is counter-intuitive for many candidates who assume filing an STR should trigger account restrictions. The same principle applies in NISM V-A for mutual fund accounts -- continue processing transactions normally after STR filing.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** After an STR is filed, maintain complete normalcy in account operations. Any unusual restriction would signal to the client that they are under scrutiny. Let the authorities investigate and give specific instructions if action is needed on the account.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
