<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI AML/CFT guidelines, how is a Non-Profit Organisation (NPO) defined?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An entity constituted for religious or charitable purposes under clause 15 of section 2 of the Income-tax Act, 1961, registered as a trust, society, or Section 8 company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any entity registered under the Companies Act, 2013 that operates on a not-for-profit basis, including Section 8 and Section 12 companies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An entity registered under the Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 2010 that receives donations from abroad for charitable purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An entity constituted for religious or charitable purposes and registered only as a public trust or cooperative society]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The SEBI guidelines define an NPO specifically as an entity constituted for religious or charitable purposes referred to in clause 15 of section 2 of the Income-tax Act, 1961. The entity must be registered as a trust, a society, or a company established under Section 8 of the Companies Act. This is a precise, three-part registration definition.

**The Trap:** Candidates may confuse the registration types. The correct answer specifies trust, society, or Section 8 company. Distractors introduce wrong registration categories like Section 12 companies, FCRA-registered entities, or cooperative societies, which are not part of the NPO definition under these guidelines.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NPOs are considered vulnerable to TF abuse due to the volume of funds they handle and their cross-border activities. Understanding the precise definition helps in applying enhanced due diligence requirements appropriately.

**Key Takeaway:** An NPO under SEBI AML/CFT guidelines is specifically defined by reference to the Income-tax Act clause 15 of section 2, and must be registered as a trust, society, or Section 8 company - no other registration forms qualify.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
