<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under SEBI AML/CFT guidelines, how long must records relating to ongoing investigations or suspicious transaction reporting be retained?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Until it is confirmed that the case has been closed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[For a minimum period of 5 years from the date of the suspicious transaction report]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[For a minimum period of 7 years from the date of filing the report with FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[For a minimum period of 10 years from the date of the last transaction in the account]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** While the general record retention period under AML/CFT guidelines is 5 years, there is a critical exception for records relating to ongoing investigations or transactions that have been the subject of a suspicious transaction reporting. In such cases, records must be retained until it is confirmed that the case has been closed. This is an open-ended retention requirement tied to case closure, not a fixed time period.

**The Trap:** Candidates who memorise only the standard 5-year retention rule will select that option. The question specifically asks about records related to ongoing investigations or STR cases, which triggers the exception. The 7-year and 10-year options are fabricated fixed periods designed to tempt candidates who assume a longer fixed period applies.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This exception ensures that evidence and audit trails remain available for the entire duration of enforcement proceedings, which can extend well beyond the standard retention period.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The standard 5-year record retention period does not apply when records relate to ongoing investigations or suspicious transaction reports - such records must be kept until case closure is confirmed, regardless of how long that takes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
