<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A registered intermediary that relies on a third party for CDD must ensure which of the following conditions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The third party must be regulated and supervised, and the intermediary remains ultimately responsible for CDD]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The third party assumes all responsibility for CDD and the intermediary is fully released from obligations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The third party only needs to be a registered company in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No specific conditions apply if the intermediary has a written agreement with the third party]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Rule 9(2) of PML Rules, reliance on third party for CDD requires: (i) immediate access to CDD information, (ii) access to copies of identification data on request, (iii) the third party must be regulated and supervised for CDD compliance, (iv) the third party must NOT be in a high-risk jurisdiction, and (v) the intermediary remains ULTIMATELY RESPONSIBLE for CDD.

**The Trap:** Outsourcing CDD does NOT transfer responsibility. The intermediary is always ultimately responsible, even when using a third party. A written agreement alone is not sufficient without meeting all five conditions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Third-party reliance for CDD is common in mutual fund distribution where distributors rely on KRAs. In NISM V-A, the same principle applies -- the AMC remains responsible even if KYC is done by a distributor.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you use a third-party KYC service, verify that they are regulated, not in a high-risk jurisdiction, and can provide documents on demand. Your intermediary bears the ultimate responsibility -- do not assume the third party has everything covered.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
