<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_21" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What must group-wide AML/CFT programmes for financial groups include as per SEBI guidelines?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Policies for sharing CDD information within the group, provision of customer/account/transaction information from branches and subsidiaries, and adequate safeguards on confidentiality and use of shared information]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only policies for sharing Customer Due Diligence (CDD) information within the group and confidentiality safeguards, but not provision of transaction information from branches]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only provision of customer, account, and transaction information from branches and subsidiaries to the head office, without requiring confidentiality safeguards]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only adequate safeguards on confidentiality and use of information exchanged, without specific requirements for CDD information sharing or branch-level reporting]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI guidelines require financial groups to implement group-wide AML/CFT programmes that include all three components: (1) policies and procedures for sharing CDD information within the group, (2) provision of customer, account, and transaction information from branches and subsidiaries to the group level, and (3) adequate safeguards on the confidentiality and use of information that is exchanged. All three elements are mandatory.

**The Trap:** Each distractor presents only one or two of the three required components, tempting candidates who recall partial information. The exam tests whether you understand the comprehensive nature of the requirement rather than just one element.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Group-wide programmes are critical for financial conglomerates where ML/TF risks can be dispersed across multiple entities. This aligns with FATF Recommendation 18 on internal controls and foreign branches and subsidiaries.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Group-wide AML/CFT programmes must comprehensively cover CDD information sharing, branch/subsidiary reporting of customer and transaction data, and confidentiality safeguards - all three are mandatory, not optional.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
