<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="SEBI Guidelines for AML Standards, CFT and PF with KYC Norms_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Regarding tipping off, which statement is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Intermediaries and their staff are prohibited from disclosing that an STR or related information is being filed or provided to FIU-IND]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The client must be informed before an STR is filed about them]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tipping off is allowed if the client voluntarily asks about their account status]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the Principal Officer is prohibited from tipping off; other staff may disclose]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The prohibition on tipping off applies to registered intermediaries, their directors, officers, and ALL employees (permanent and temporary). It extends not only to the filing of STR but even BEFORE, DURING, and AFTER submission. The client must NOT be told of the report/suspicion at ANY stage.

**The Trap:** The prohibition is absolute -- no exceptions for client inquiries, no limitation to specific staff. Even if a client asks why their account is under review, you cannot disclose the STR filing.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Tipping off is a criminal offense under PMLA. This principle is tested across NISM exams because it is a fundamental AML requirement that every financial professional must internalize.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a client asks about unusual delays or restrictions on their account after an STR has been filed, respond with general operational explanations. Never mention the STR, the investigation, or the suspicion. Train all staff -- including temporary employees -- on this critical obligation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
