<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Secondary Markets_60" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the SEBI-established online platform where investors can lodge complaints against listed companies, intermediaries, and other market participants?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redressal System)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IGMS (Investor Grievance Management System)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI Direct Complaint Portal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSE Investor Service Cell]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redressal System) is the online investor grievance redressal mechanism set up by SEBI to deal with complaints related to all products and entities regulated by it. This includes complaints against companies, mutual funds, portfolio management schemes, brokers, merchant bankers, depositories, depository participants, and other intermediaries. Complaints are acknowledged instantaneously upon submission.

**The Trap:** While stock exchanges have their own Investor Grievance Divisions, SCORES is SEBI's centralized platform for all market-related complaints. Students may confuse exchange-level grievance cells with SEBI's SCORES platform. The ODR portal is for dispute resolution after SCORES escalation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** SCORES is tested in NISM V-A (Mutual Fund), NISM VIII, NISM XII, and NISM XV. Investor grievance mechanisms are a regulatory priority across all exams.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always inform clients about SCORES as their recourse for unresolved complaints. After exhausting the SCORES route, the Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) portal provides mediation and arbitration services for final resolution.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>