<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Secondary Markets_52" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[According to the US SEC, High Frequency Trading (HFT) is characterized by all of the following features EXCEPT __________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Positions are typically held for several weeks to capture medium-term price trends]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Use of extraordinarily fast computer programs for generating, routing, and executing orders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Very short holding periods, often measured in minutes or seconds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[High order-to-trade ratios with many orders cancelled shortly after submission]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** According to the US SEC, HFT is characterized by: (a) use of extraordinarily fast computer programs for generating, routing, and executing orders; (b) very short holding periods often measured in minutes or seconds; (c) high order-to-trade ratios with many orders cancelled; and (d) ending the trading day with positions largely closed (flat). Holding positions for several weeks contradicts the fundamental nature of HFT.

**The Trap:** All three incorrect options are actual HFT features per the US SEC definition. The correct answer (positions held for weeks) directly contradicts the HFT characteristic of very short holding periods and ending the day flat. Students must know all four features to identify the false one.

**Cross-Exam Context:** HFT features are tested in NISM Series XII and VIII (Equity Derivatives). Understanding HFT is important for market microstructure questions.

**Key Takeaway:** HFT = fast programs + short holding periods (minutes/seconds) + high order-to-trade ratios + positions closed by end of day. Any reference to holding for days or weeks rules out HFT.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>