<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Secondary Markets_51" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[In the GIFT City International Financial Services Centre (IFSC), __________ was set up by NSE and __________ was set up by BSE. Since July 2023, SGX Nifty derivatives are traded exclusively on the NSE-promoted exchange.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NSE IX (NSE International Exchange) was set up by NSE; India International Exchange (IndiaINX) was set up by BSE]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IndiaINX was set up by NSE; NSE IX was set up by BSE]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[GIFT Exchange was set up by NSE; BSE International was set up by BSE]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NSE IFSC was set up by NSE; BSE IFSC was set up by BSE]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In GIFT City IFSC, NSE promoted NSE IX (NSE International Exchange) and BSE promoted India International Exchange (IndiaINX). These are the two stock exchanges operating in India's first IFSC. Since July 2023, SGX Nifty derivatives (previously traded on the Singapore Exchange) are traded exclusively on NSE IX through the GIFT City Connect arrangement.

**The Trap:** The most common error is reversing the parent-subsidiary relationship -- thinking IndiaINX belongs to NSE or NSE IX belongs to BSE. The names are somewhat counterintuitive: "India International Exchange" sounds like it could be NSE's, but it is actually BSE's subsidiary.

**Cross-Exam Context:** GIFT City IFSC exchanges are tested in NISM Series XII and are relevant for understanding India's international financial services landscape.

**Key Takeaway:** NSE IX = NSE's IFSC exchange; IndiaINX = BSE's IFSC exchange. SGX Nifty moved exclusively to NSE IX from July 2023.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>