<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[During a period of high inflation, an investor notices that the real value of their fixed deposit returns is being eroded. Which additional asset class should they consider adding to their portfolio to hedge against inflation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Commodities such as gold, as commodity prices tend to rise during inflationary periods]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More bank fixed deposits at the same interest rate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long-duration government bonds with fixed coupons]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Savings bank deposits for better liquidity]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Commodity prices are usually higher during periods of rising inflation. Having exposure to commodities like gold serves as a hedge or protection against inflation. Gold historically maintains purchasing power during inflationary periods, offsetting the erosion of fixed-income returns.

**The Trap:** More FDs at same rate (option B) will face the same erosion. Long-duration bonds (option C) actually lose value when rates rise with inflation. Savings deposits (option D) offer even lower returns than FDs.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. The inflation-hedging role of commodities is tested in NISM XII and relevant to holistic financial planning.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When inflation is high, have a conversation with clients about real returns (nominal return minus inflation). A 7% FD with 6% inflation gives only 1% real return. Adding 10-15% gold allocation can improve real returns because gold typically appreciates during inflation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>