<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Latika invests all her money exclusively in equities. During a market downturn, she finds that the value of her entire portfolio has declined significantly. What investment principle should Latika have followed to reduce this risk?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Diversification across asset classes including debt, gold, and real estate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Investing everything in a single large-cap stock instead]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Timing the market perfectly by selling before every downturn]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Borrowing additional funds to invest more in equities during the downturn]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The risk to Latika comes from concentration of her portfolio in one asset class. When equity markets go down, her entire portfolio goes down. Diversification across asset classes (debt, gold, real estate) would have cushioned the impact because different asset classes do not always move in the same direction.

**The Trap:** Investing in a single stock (option B) increases concentration risk. Perfect market timing (option C) is practically impossible. Leveraging during downturns (option D) amplifies losses.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. This Latika example is directly from the NISM XII workbook illustrating the need for asset allocation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use real-life examples from the textbook to explain diversification. Each case (Jayesh-real estate, Kamal-savings, Latika-equity, Harmeet-gold, Gayatri-FDs) shows a different problem from concentration. A balanced portfolio across these asset classes solves all these problems simultaneously.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>