<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the fundamental difference between equity capital and debt capital raised by a business?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Equity capital is available for the company to use as long as needed; debt capital must be returned after a specified time]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity capital must be returned within 5 years; debt capital is permanent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity capital carries a fixed interest rate; debt capital offers variable dividends]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity capital can only be raised from banks; debt capital can be raised from the public]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Equity capital is available for the company to use as long as it is needed -- there is no maturity date. Debt capital will have to be returned after a specified time. Additionally, equity involves sharing ownership while debt involves a borrowing obligation with fixed interest payments.

**The Trap:** Option B reverses the truth. Option C confuses the characteristics -- it is debt that carries fixed interest, not equity. Option D is wrong because both equity and debt can be raised from the public through securities markets.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. The equity-debt distinction is foundational to NISM V-A (Mutual Fund), VIII (Equity Derivatives), and XII.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is the most basic investment concept clients need to understand. Equity = ownership with unlimited upside but also downside risk. Debt = lending with fixed returns but limited upside. Every portfolio combines these two based on the client's risk tolerance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>