<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Share warrants issued by a company give the holder:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The right but not the obligation to subscribe to equity shares at a predetermined price on or after a predetermined date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The obligation to purchase equity shares at market price on the exercise date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Immediate ownership of equity shares without any additional payment]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The right to receive dividends without owning any equity shares]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Share warrants are options issued by a company giving holders the right (not obligation) to subscribe to equity shares at a predetermined price on or after a predetermined date. Investors pay 25% upfront; if they exercise, they pay the balance and receive shares. If they do not exercise, the upfront amount is forfeited.

**The Trap:** Warrants give rights, not obligations (option B). They do not give immediate ownership (option C) -- shares are allotted only upon exercise. No dividend rights exist without share ownership (option D).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. Warrants are tested in NISM XII and are relevant to understanding equity-linked instruments.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Warrants are similar to stock options but issued by the company with longer life. The 25% upfront payment requirement per SEBI rules ensures investors have skin in the game. If the market price exceeds the warrant price, exercise is profitable; otherwise the investor loses the 25% deposit.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>