<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_62" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[As per SEBI regulations, which of the following best describes the eligibility criteria for stocks to be included in the equity derivatives (futures and options) segment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The stock must meet specific criteria related to market capitalization and trading volume as prescribed by SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any stock listed on a recognized stock exchange is automatically eligible for derivatives trading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only stocks with a market capitalization above Rs. 10,000 crore are eligible]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Nifty 50 constituent stocks are eligible for individual stock derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI has laid down strict eligibility criteria that a stock must satisfy in order to be included in the futures and options segment. These specifications mostly pertain to size (market capitalization) and trading volume so that the derivatives are liquid and can be traded at lower costs. SEBI issues guidelines and circulars specifying these criteria, and exchanges can impose more stringent criteria.

**The Trap:** Not all listed stocks are eligible for derivatives - this is a common misconception. The criteria are not limited to a fixed market cap threshold or index membership, but involve multiple parameters that SEBI periodically revises.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Derivatives eligibility criteria are a key topic in NISM VIII (Equity Derivatives) and NISM XII. Understanding why only select stocks have derivatives is important for market participants.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Stocks in the F&O segment tend to have higher liquidity and institutional interest. When a stock is added to or removed from the derivatives segment, it can impact its trading dynamics in the cash market as well.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>