<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_58" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Zero Coupon Zero Principal (ZCZP) instruments are issued by __________ on the Social Stock Exchange for the purpose of social development. They were added to the definition of securities via a Gazette notification dated July 16, 2022.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Not-for-profit organizations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Government entities and departments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Public Sector Undertakings (PSUs)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Listed for-profit companies]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Zero Coupon Zero Principal (ZCZP) instruments are a unique type of security issued exclusively by not-for-profit organizations (NPOs) registered on the Social Stock Exchange (SSE). As the name suggests, these instruments carry no coupon (interest) and no principal repayment -- essentially functioning as a donation mechanism with transparency and accountability. They were added to the definition of securities under SCRA via Gazette notification dated July 16, 2022.

**The Trap:** Government entities and PSUs issue regular bonds and G-Secs. Listed for-profit companies raise funds through equity and debt on regular stock exchanges. ZCZP instruments are specifically designed for the social sector and are exclusively available through the Social Stock Exchange.

**Cross-Exam Context:** ZCZP instruments and the Social Stock Exchange are recent additions tested in NISM Series XII. This reflects SEBI's initiative to channel capital towards social development.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** ZCZP = No coupon, no principal repayment = essentially a structured donation. Issued only by NPOs on the Social Stock Exchange. Added to SCRA securities definition in July 2022.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>