<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is a key difference between a debenture holder and a preference shareholder?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A debenture holder is a creditor of the company while a preference shareholder is a shareholder of the company]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A preference shareholder receives interest while a debenture holder receives dividends]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A debenture holder has voting rights while a preference shareholder does not]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no practical difference between the two]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A key distinction is that a debenture holder is a creditor of the company (has lent money), while a preference shareholder is a shareholder (part owner). Additionally, debentures are usually secured on company assets while preference shares are not. Debenture interest is a pre-tax expense; preference dividends are paid from post-tax profits.

**The Trap:** Option B reverses the terms -- debenture holders receive interest, preference shareholders receive dividends. Option C is wrong -- neither typically has voting rights in corporate decisions (debenture holders have contractual rights, not voting rights). Option D ignores significant legal and financial differences.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. This distinction is tested in NISM XII and is important for understanding the capital structure of companies.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients ask about the safety of preference shares vs debentures, explain: debenture holders are creditors with security over assets and get paid first; preference shareholders are owners with no security and get paid after creditors. Debentures are generally safer.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>