<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about preference shares is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Preference shareholders receive a pre-defined rate of dividend before equity shareholders, but typically do not have voting rights]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Preference shareholders have voting rights equal to equity shareholders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Preference share dividends are paid before tax, just like interest on debentures]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Preference shares are secured against the assets of the company]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Preference shares pay a pre-defined rate of dividend that is payable after all other payments but before dividend is declared to equity shareholders. Unlike common equity, preference shares do not offer voting rights or a right over the assets of the company.

**The Trap:** Preference shareholders typically do NOT have voting rights (option B is wrong). Dividends on preference shares are paid from residual profits AFTER tax, unlike debenture interest which is a pre-tax expense (option C is wrong). Preference shares are NOT secured since they are not a borrowing (option D is wrong).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. The distinction between preference shares, equity shares, and debentures is tested in NISM XII and V-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Preference shares sit between equity and debt in the risk spectrum. They offer more predictable income than equity but less security than debt. They are useful for investors seeking regular income with moderate risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>