<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A company generates stable and regular profits sufficient to make periodic interest payments. It does not want to dilute its existing promoter ownership. Which form of capital is most suitable for this company?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Debt capital through bond issuance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity capital through a fresh public issue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Preference share capital with voting rights]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Warrant issuance to the general public]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Two key factors are identified: (1) the company has stable profits to pay periodic interest, making debt service feasible, and (2) it does not want to dilute ownership, which equity issuance would do. Debt capital is ideal because it does not confer ownership or voting rights, and the company has stable cash flows to service interest.

**The Trap:** Fresh equity (option B) would dilute promoter ownership. Preference shares with voting rights (option C) is unusual and would still dilute ownership. Warrants (option D) eventually convert to equity, causing dilution.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. The equity vs debt capital decision is tested in NISM XII and IX (Merchant Banking).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understanding why companies choose debt or equity helps you explain corporate actions to clients. When a company issues bonds instead of equity, it signals confidence in stable cash flows and a desire to avoid ownership dilution -- generally a positive sign for existing shareholders.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>