<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_55" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[The Price-to-Book Value (P/BV) ratio is calculated as Market Price per Share divided by Book Value per Share. A P/BV ratio of less than 1 __________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[may indicate that the stock is undervalued relative to its net asset value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[always confirms that the stock is undervalued and should be bought immediately]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[indicates that the stock is overvalued by the market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[means the company is fairly valued at its intrinsic worth]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When the P/BV ratio is less than 1, it means the market is valuing the stock at less than its book value (net assets per share). This may indicate undervaluation -- the market price is below the accounting value of the company's assets minus liabilities. However, it is not a guaranteed signal, as there could be legitimate reasons such as poor earnings prospects or asset quality concerns.

**The Trap:** The word "may" is critical. Option B uses "always confirms" which is too absolute -- a low P/BV could also reflect genuine business problems. Option C (overvalued) is the opposite of what P/BV < 1 suggests. Option D (fairly valued) would imply P/BV close to 1.

**Cross-Exam Context:** P/BV ratio is tested in NISM Series XII, XV (Research Analyst), and V-A (Mutual Fund). It is a fundamental valuation metric alongside P/E ratio.

**Key Takeaway:** P/BV < 1 may indicate undervaluation but is not a definitive signal. Always consider the reason behind the low P/BV before concluding a stock is a bargain.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>