<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Equity capital is also called 'risk capital' because:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Equity investors accept the risk that the business may succeed or fail without expecting a fixed rate of regular return]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity investors receive guaranteed returns regardless of business performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity shares can only be bought during high-risk market conditions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The government guarantees all equity investments against losses]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Equity capital is called risk capital because equity investors are willing to take the risk that the business may succeed or fail, without expecting a fixed rate of regular return. They invest with the view to participate in the success of the business, which would result in higher value of their investment.

**The Trap:** Equity investors do NOT receive guaranteed returns (option B) -- that would be debt. Equity can be bought in any market condition (option C). No government guarantee exists for equity (option D).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. Understanding why equity is risk capital is fundamental to all NISM exams dealing with investments.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When clients question why equity returns are volatile, explain the "risk capital" concept. Equity investors are owners who share in both the upside and downside of business performance. This inherent risk is precisely what generates potentially higher long-term returns compared to fixed-income investments.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>