<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Securities Types Features and Asset Allocation Concepts_43" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An investor has a financial goal that is 15 years away. Based on the risk-return characteristics of equity as an asset class, what is the most appropriate investment strategy?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A higher allocation to equity is suitable because equity tends to deliver better returns over long horizons despite short-term volatility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The investor should avoid equity entirely and invest only in savings bank deposits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The investor should invest exclusively in 91-day Treasury bills and keep rolling them]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The investor should invest entirely in physical gold and hold until the goal date]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Returns from equity investing tend to be much more volatile over the short term but tend to deliver better returns over long investment horizons. A 15-year horizon allows the investor to ride out short-term volatility and benefit from the wealth creation potential of equities. The selection of investment products should be aligned with the investment horizon.

**The Trap:** Savings deposits (option B) will not generate enough returns over 15 years due to inflation erosion. T-bills (option C) are for short-term parking. Physical gold (option D) alone may not generate sufficient long-term returns and involves storage costs.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. Investment horizon alignment is tested in NISM V-A (Mutual Fund) and XII.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For long-term goals like retirement or children's education, equity-heavy portfolios are appropriate. As the goal nears, gradually shift to debt for capital preservation. This "glide path" approach is used in target-date funds and is sound advice for any long-term investor.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>