<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Public Provident Fund (PPF) follows which taxation regime under the old tax system?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[EEE (Exempt-Exempt-Exempt) — contribution is deductible, interest is exempt, and maturity proceeds are exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[EET (Exempt-Exempt-Taxed) — contribution is deductible, interest is exempt, but maturity proceeds are taxed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ETE (Exempt-Taxed-Exempt) — contribution is deductible, interest is taxed annually, and maturity proceeds are exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TEE (Taxed-Exempt-Exempt) — contribution gets no deduction, but interest and maturity are both exempt]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** PPF enjoys EEE status under the old tax regime: (1) Contribution qualifies for deduction under Section 80C (first E — Exempt), (2) Interest earned is not taxable (second E — Exempt), (3) Maturity proceeds are fully exempt (third E — Exempt). This makes PPF one of the most tax-efficient instruments available.
**The Trap:** Option (d) TEE describes what PPF effectively becomes under the new tax regime, where Section 80C deduction is not available — the contribution is made from post-tax income (Taxed), but interest and maturity remain exempt. EET describes ELSS under the old regime (maturity/redemption gains are taxable as capital gains). ETE describes tax-saving FDs under the old regime.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A MFD exam extensively tests EEE/EET classifications to compare mutual funds with other savings instruments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising clients who have chosen the new regime, highlight that PPF loses its first 'E' — making the effective taxation TEE. Clients should reconsider allocation accordingly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
