<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about Gross Total Income (GTI) and Total Income (TI) is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total Income is always greater than or equal to Gross Total Income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Gross Total Income is computed after deductions under Chapter VI-A]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Gross Total Income is the aggregate of income under all five heads after clubbing provisions and set-off of losses, while Total Income is GTI minus deductions under Chapter VI-A]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total Income and Gross Total Income are the same if the assessee claims deductions under Section 80C]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per Section 80B(5), Gross Total Income (GTI) is computed by: (1) computing income under each of the five heads (Salary, House Property, Business/Profession, Capital Gains, Other Sources), (2) applying clubbing provisions, and (3) setting off losses. Total Income = GTI minus deductions under Chapter VI-A (Sections 80C to 80U). Thus, TI ≤ GTI always.
**The Trap:** Option (a) reverses the relationship — TI cannot exceed GTI since deductions reduce income. Option (b) gets the sequence wrong — GTI is computed before Chapter VI-A deductions. Option (d) contradicts itself — if 80C deductions are claimed, TI would be less than GTI, not the same.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This distinction is fundamental and tested across NISM X-A and X-B certification exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always compute GTI first before advising on deductions — some deductions have limits linked to GTI, and certain deductions are not available if GTI is below certain thresholds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
