<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rohit, an investment adviser, has a client Sunita with gross salary of Rs. 9,00,000 and no other income. Under the new regime FY 2025-26, after Rs. 75,000 standard deduction, her total income is Rs. 8,25,000. The marginal relief provision ensures that her tax liability does not exceed the amount by which her income exceeds the rebate threshold of Rs. 12,00,000. What is Sunita's net tax liability?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Nil, as her total income of Rs. 8,25,000 is within the rebate limit under Section 87A]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 21,250 — computed at slab rates without rebate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 41,600 — computed at slab rates plus 4% cess]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 25,000 — computed after partial rebate only]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the new regime for FY 2025-26, the Section 87A rebate is available for individuals whose total income does not exceed Rs. 12,00,000. Sunita's total income of Rs. 8,25,000 is well within this threshold. The rebate effectively reduces her tax liability to Nil. At slab rates, her tax would have been: 4-8L = 4L × 5% = Rs. 20,000; 8-8.25L = 0.25L × 10% = Rs. 2,500. Total = Rs. 22,500. But the full rebate under Section 87A wipes this out.
**The Trap:** Rs. 21,250 is a close but incorrect slab calculation (missing the 10% slab for the 8-8.25L portion). Rs. 41,600 adds cess on a wrong tax amount. Rs. 25,000 implies only a partial rebate — but the rebate covers the full tax amount for income up to Rs. 12L.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-B tests the impact of Section 87A rebate on low-to-middle income earners under the new regime.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For clients with total income up to Rs. 12L under the new regime (FY 2025-26), the effective tax is nil due to Section 87A — a powerful talking point when advising on regime selection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
