<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_19" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Meera invested in ELSS (Equity Linked Savings Scheme) under the old tax regime. Which taxation regime does ELSS follow?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[EEE — contributions are deductible, growth is exempt, and redemption is exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[EET — contributions are deductible under Section 80C, growth is exempt, but redemption gains are taxed as capital gains]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ETE — contributions are deductible, growth is taxed annually, and redemption is exempt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[TET — contributions are not deductible, growth is exempt, and redemption gains are taxed]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** ELSS follows the EET (Exempt-Exempt-Taxed) regime under the old tax system: (1) First E: Contributions qualify for deduction under Section 80C (up to Rs. 1.5 lakh); (2) Second E: The growth/accumulation within the fund is not taxed annually; (3) T: On redemption, gains are taxed — LTCG above Rs. 1.25 lakh is taxed at 12.5% under Section 112A.
**The Trap:** EEE describes PPF where even maturity is exempt — ELSS gains are taxable on redemption. ETE describes tax-saving FDs where interest is taxed annually. TET would apply if there were no Section 80C deduction — this is actually what ELSS becomes under the new regime (where 80C is unavailable).
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A MFD exam extensively tests the EET classification of ELSS versus other tax-saving instruments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When comparing ELSS with PPF for clients on the old regime, highlight that ELSS has a shorter lock-in (3 years vs 15 years) but gains are taxable (EET vs EEE) — the trade-off is liquidity versus tax efficiency.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
