<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The definition of 'Income' under Section 2(24) of the Income Tax Act is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An exhaustive definition covering only salary, house property, and business income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A restrictive definition limited to revenue receipts only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An inclusive definition that covers profits and gains, dividends, capital gains, gifts under Section 56, and perquisites among others]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A definition that excludes capital gains and only covers recurring income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 2(24) uses the word 'includes' making it an inclusive (not exhaustive) definition. It covers a wide range of items such as profits and gains from business/profession, dividends, capital gains, gifts received under Section 56, voluntary contributions to trusts, perquisites, and many more. The use of 'includes' means Parliament can add more items and courts can interpret additional receipts as income.
**The Trap:** Option (a) says 'exhaustive' which contradicts the inclusive nature. Option (b) says 'restrictive' and 'revenue receipts only' — but capital gains (a capital receipt) are explicitly included. Option (d) excludes capital gains, which are specifically listed in Section 2(24).
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series X-A tests this concept when discussing taxability of various investment returns.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The inclusive nature of 'income' means investment advisers must consider all forms of client receipts — even unexpected ones like gifts or awards — when computing tax liability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
