<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about PAN (Permanent Account Number) requirement is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PAN is required only for filing income tax returns and not for any financial transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PAN is issued by SEBI for identification in securities market transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[PAN is required to be quoted in specified financial transactions such as opening bank accounts, buying/selling immovable property, and securities transactions above prescribed limits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PAN is optional for all transactions below Rs. 50,000 and mandatory only for transactions above Rs. 50,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** PAN is a 10-digit alphanumeric identifier issued by the Income Tax Department. It must be quoted in a wide range of prescribed financial transactions including: opening bank accounts, purchase/sale of immovable property exceeding Rs. 10 lakh, securities transactions, motor vehicle purchases, time deposits above Rs. 50,000, and many others as specified under Rule 114B. It serves as a universal identifier for tracking financial transactions and preventing tax evasion.
**The Trap:** Option (a) is too narrow — PAN is required far beyond just tax return filing. Option (b) incorrectly attributes PAN issuance to SEBI — PAN is issued by the Income Tax Department (under CBDT). Option (d) oversimplifies with a single Rs. 50,000 threshold — different transactions have different prescribed limits.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A, VIII, and X-B all reference PAN requirements for KYC compliance in investment transactions.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always ensure clients have a valid PAN before initiating any investment — absence of PAN can trigger higher TDS rates (as per Section 206AA) and delay transaction processing.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
