<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Tax Framework and Key Concepts_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the relationship between 'Previous Year' and 'Assessment Year' under the Income Tax Act?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Previous Year is the year in which tax return is filed; Assessment Year is the year in which income is earned]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both Previous Year and Assessment Year refer to the same financial year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Previous Year is always a calendar year (January to December) while Assessment Year is a financial year (April to March)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Previous Year is the financial year in which income is earned; Assessment Year is the immediately following financial year in which such income is assessed to tax]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the Income Tax Act, the Previous Year (PY) is the financial year (April-March) during which income is earned or received. The Assessment Year (AY) is the financial year immediately following the PY, during which the income of the PY is assessed and the tax return is filed. For example, income earned in FY 2025-26 (PY) is assessed in AY 2026-27.
**The Trap:** Option (a) reverses the definitions. Option (b) ignores that they are always consecutive, never the same. Option (c) incorrectly suggests PY follows a calendar year — both PY and AY follow April-March cycles.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This foundational concept is tested across NISM Series V-A, X-A, and X-B exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When advising clients on tax-saving investments, always clarify the PY deadline (March 31) — investments made after this date fall in the next PY.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
