<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about mutual fund taxation is INCORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Switching between plans (Growth to IDCW) within the same scheme is treated as a transfer and attracts capital gains tax]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A debt mutual fund purchased in May 2024 and held for 30 months qualifies for long-term capital gains treatment at 12.5%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STP (Systematic Transfer Plan) triggers capital gains tax on each transfer as it involves redemption from the source scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IDCW (Income Distribution cum Capital Withdrawal) is taxable in the hands of the investor at slab rate]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Option B is INCORRECT because debt MFs purchased on/after 1 April 2023 have NO long-term capital gains treatment - ALL gains are taxed at the investor's slab rate regardless of holding period. There is no LTCG benefit for post-April 2023 debt fund purchases.

**The Trap:** The question asks for the INCORRECT statement. Option B sounds plausible because 30 months > 24 months (the old holding period for non-equity LTCG), but the new rule eliminates LTCG entirely for post-April 2023 debt fund purchases.

**Cross-Exam Context:** All other statements are correct: switching between plans is a taxable transfer, STP involves redemption (taxable), and IDCW is taxed at slab rate. Understanding what constitutes a "transfer" is important.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Warn clients that switching between plans, STP, and SWP all create taxable events. Many investors assume these are non-taxable internal transfers, leading to unexpected tax bills.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
