<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following mutual fund transactions does NOT trigger a capital gains tax event?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Switching from Growth option to IDCW option within the same scheme]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Redemption of units through a Systematic Withdrawal Plan (SWP)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Transfer of mutual fund units to a spouse under a gift deed (transfer between specified relatives)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Transfer of units from one scheme to another under a Systematic Transfer Plan (STP)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Transfer of MF units as a gift to specified relatives (including spouse) is not regarded as a "transfer" under Section 47 of the Income Tax Act, hence no capital gains tax is triggered at the time of transfer. However, when the recipient eventually sells, the cost of acquisition is the original donor's cost and the holding period includes the donor's holding period.

**The Trap:** All other options are taxable events: switching between options is a redemption + fresh purchase, SWP involves actual unit redemptions, and STP involves transfer (redemption from source scheme). Only gifting to specified relatives gets the exemption.

**Cross-Exam Context:** "Specified relatives" include spouse, siblings, parents, and lineal ascendants/descendants. Gift to non-relatives above Rs. 50,000 is taxable in the recipient's hands.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Gifting MF units to a lower-tax-bracket family member can be a legitimate tax planning strategy, though clubbing provisions under Section 64 may apply for gifts to spouse or minor children.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
