<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following tax changes was introduced by the Union Budget 2024 (effective from 23 July 2024) regarding mutual fund taxation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Introduction of DDT (Dividend Distribution Tax) on mutual fund dividends at 10%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Removal of Section 80C deduction for ELSS investments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[STCG rate on equity MFs increased from 15% to 20% and LTCG rate increased from 10% to 12.5%, with exemption raised to Rs. 1.25 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Restoration of indexation benefit for debt mutual funds purchased after April 2023]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Budget 2024 (effective 23 July 2024) made these key changes: (1) Equity STCG rate increased from 15% to 20% under Section 111A; (2) Equity LTCG rate increased from 10% to 12.5% under Section 112A; (3) LTCG exemption threshold raised from Rs. 1,00,000 to Rs. 1,25,000 per year.

**The Trap:** Option A refers to DDT which was abolished in 2020, not reintroduced. Option B is false - ELSS continues under 80C. Option D is false - indexation was NOT restored for post-April 2023 debt funds.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Budget 2024 changes are highly examinable as they represent the latest amendments. The rates moved in opposite directions from what investors expected - rates increased but exemption also increased slightly.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When discussing Budget 2024 changes with clients, emphasize that despite rate increases, the higher exemption of Rs. 1.25 lakh provides some offset for moderate LTCG amounts. Long-term equity investing remains tax-efficient.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
