<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation of Debt and Equity Products_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Anita Desai, aged 45, is a resident Indian in the 30% tax bracket (old regime). During FY 2025-26, she has the following investment transactions:

1. Equity Mutual Fund A: Purchased 5,000 units at Rs. 120 per unit on 15-Mar-2024. Sold all units at Rs. 155 per unit on 20-Jan-2026. STT paid on sale.
2. Equity Mutual Fund B: Purchased 3,000 units at Rs. 200 per unit on 10-Aug-2025. Sold all units at Rs. 185 per unit on 25-Feb-2026. STT paid on sale.
3. Debt Mutual Fund C (invested 90% in debt securities): Purchased 10,000 units at Rs. 50 per unit on 05-May-2024. Sold all units at Rs. 54 per unit on 15-Nov-2025. This fund was purchased after 1-Apr-2023.
4. Bank Fixed Deposit: Rs. 15,00,000 at 7.5% p.a. for 1 year, matured on 30-Sep-2025. TDS deducted at 10%.
5. Dividend received from Equity MF A during holding period: Rs. 25,000 (TDS of 10% deducted as dividend exceeded Rs. 5,000).
6. Arbitrage Fund D: Purchased 8,000 units at Rs. 15 per unit on 01-Feb-2025. Sold all units at Rs. 16.50 per unit on 10-Mar-2026. STT paid on sale.

Anita's total salary income (after standard deduction) is Rs. 22,00,000. She has no other income or deductions.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> What is the nature of the capital gain on Equity Mutual Fund A and the applicable tax liability on this gain in isolation (before any set-off or aggregation with other 112A gains)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[LTCG of Rs. 1,75,000 taxable under section 112A at 12.5%; tax on this gain alone (after Rs. 1.25 lakh exemption) = Rs. 6,250]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[LTCG of Rs. 1,75,000 taxable under section 112 at 20% with indexation; tax = Rs. 35,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STCG of Rs. 1,75,000 taxable under section 111A at 20%; tax = Rs. 35,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[LTCG of Rs. 1,75,000 taxable at slab rate of 30%; tax = Rs. 52,500]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Equity MF A was purchased on 15-Mar-2024 and sold on 20-Jan-2026, a holding period of approximately 22 months, which exceeds 12 months. For equity-oriented mutual funds (with STT paid), holding period >12 months qualifies as Long-Term Capital Gain (LTCG) under section 112A. Capital gain = (Rs. 155 - Rs. 120) x 5,000 units = Rs. 35 x 5,000 = Rs. 1,75,000. Under section 112A, LTCG up to Rs. 1,25,000 in a financial year is exempt. If considered in isolation, taxable LTCG = Rs. 1,75,000 - Rs. 1,25,000 = Rs. 50,000. Tax = 12.5% x Rs. 50,000 = Rs. 6,250.
**The Trap:** Option B wrongly applies section 112 (with indexation), which applies to non-equity assets, not equity funds with STT. Option C wrongly classifies this as STCG despite 22 months holding. Option D wrongly applies slab rate, which does not apply to equity LTCG with STT paid. Remember: for equity-oriented funds with STT, the threshold is 12 months, and the rate under s.112A is 12.5% (from FY 2024-25 onwards, replacing the earlier 10% rate).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Section 112A is a cornerstone of NISM X-B taxation questions. Key parameters: (1) STT must be paid on sale, (2) holding >12 months, (3) rate is 12.5%, (4) Rs. 1.25 lakh annual exemption on aggregate LTCG under 112A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients to be aware that the Rs. 1.25 lakh exemption applies to the aggregate of all LTCG under section 112A in a financial year — not per fund or per transaction. If a client has multiple equity fund redemptions, the exemption is shared across all of them.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
