<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation of Debt and Equity Products_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about Market Linked Debentures (MLDs) is correct under the current tax regime?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MLDs held for more than 36 months qualify for long-term capital gains at 12.5%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MLDs held for more than 12 months (if listed) qualify for long-term capital gains at 12.5%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains on MLDs are always treated as short-term under Section 50AA and taxed at slab rates, irrespective of holding period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MLDs are taxed as income from other sources and not under the capital gains head]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 50AA specifically covers Market Linked Debentures (MLDs) along with specified mutual funds. Under this section, any gain from transfer of MLDs is deemed short-term capital gain regardless of the actual holding period. The gain is taxed at the investor's applicable income tax slab rate.
**The Trap:** Before Section 50AA was introduced, listed MLDs with >12 months holding qualified for LTCG. Candidates with outdated knowledge may still apply the old rules. Also, some may confuse MLDs with regular listed debentures which do get LTCG treatment after 12 months.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series V-A tests the distinction between MLDs and regular debentures in the context of mutual fund portfolio holdings.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** MLDs lost their tax arbitrage advantage after Section 50AA. Advisers should reassess whether MLDs still make sense for clients compared to direct bond investments or other structures that retain LTCG eligibility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
