<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation_27" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[CASE STUDY: Mr. Sharma, aged 45, is in the 30% income tax bracket. He has the following mutual fund investments during FY 2025-26:

Investment 1: Equity MF - Invested Rs. 5,00,000, held for 15 months, sold at a profit of Rs. 3,00,000.
Investment 2: Debt MF - Purchased in February 2024, invested Rs. 4,00,000, held for 8 months, sold at a profit of Rs. 50,000.
Investment 3: ELSS Fund - Invested Rs. 1,50,000, held for 4 years, sold at a profit of Rs. 80,000.
Investment 4: Received IDCW of Rs. 8,000 from an equity MF scheme during the year.

Question 1: What is the nature of the capital gain on Mr. Sharma's equity MF investment (Investment 1) and the applicable tax rate?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Long-term capital gain taxed at 12.5% under Section 112A (holding period of 15 months exceeds the 12-month threshold for equity MFs)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Short-term capital gain taxed at 20% under Section 111A (15 months is short-term for equity)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long-term capital gain taxed at 10% under Section 112A (old rate applies to pre-July 2024 purchases)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Long-term capital gain taxed at investor's slab rate of 30% (equity MFs taxed at slab rate)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For equity-oriented mutual funds, the holding period threshold for LTCG is 12 months. Mr. Sharma held his equity MF units for 15 months (>12 months), so this qualifies as LTCG. Under Section 112A, equity LTCG is taxed at 12.5% (post-Budget 2024 rate). The first Rs. 1,25,000 of equity LTCG in a financial year is exempt.

**The Trap:** Option B wrongly classifies 15 months as short-term for equity. Option C uses the old 10% rate which was replaced by 12.5% effective July 23, 2024. Option D applies slab rate which is for debt funds, not equity.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 12-month threshold for equity and 12.5% LTCG rate are fundamental to equity MF taxation. Always verify the holding period against the correct threshold for the fund type.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Mr. Sharma benefited from holding beyond 12 months - his 20% STCG rate dropped to 12.5% LTCG rate, plus he gets the Rs. 1.25 lakh exemption. A 3-month difference saved significant tax.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
