<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation of Debt and Equity Products_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under current tax law, which of the following instruments allows the possibility of long-term capital gains treatment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Market Linked Debentures (MLDs) held for more than 12 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Unlisted bonds held for more than 24 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Listed government securities held for more than 12 months]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Specified mutual funds (≥65% debt) purchased after 1st April 2023 and held for more than 24 months]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Listed government securities (G-Secs in bond form) follow the same rules as listed bonds/debentures — they qualify for LTCG after a 12-month holding period, taxed at 12.5% without indexation. The other three options all fall under Section 50AA, which mandates ALWAYS short-term treatment regardless of holding period: MLDs (always STCG), unlisted bonds (always STCG), and specified MFs with ≥65% debt purchased after 1-4-2023 (always STCG).
**The Trap:** G-Secs might seem like they should fall under the same restrictive debt rules, but when issued in bond form and listed, they follow listed bond taxation. Candidates who over-apply Section 50AA to all debt instruments will get this wrong.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series IV (Interest Rate Derivatives) covers G-Sec characteristics; the taxation angle is tested in Series X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Listed G-Sec bonds are among the few remaining debt instruments that offer LTCG at 12.5%. For tax-conscious investors seeking debt exposure, this makes them relatively attractive post the Section 50AA changes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
