<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation of Debt and Equity Products_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Rohit was allotted share warrants of a listed company at Rs.50 per warrant, paying 25% upfront (Rs.12.50 per warrant). He exercised the warrants within 18 months by paying the balance Rs.37.50 per warrant, converting them into equity shares at Rs.50 each. He later sold the shares at Rs.80 per share after 14 months. What is his cost of acquisition per share and the nature of the gain?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cost Rs.37.50; LTCG of Rs.42.50 per share at 12.5%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Cost Rs.50; LTCG of Rs.30 per share at 12.5% under Section 112A]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cost Rs.50; STCG of Rs.30 per share at 20% under Section 111A]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cost Rs.12.50; LTCG of Rs.67.50 per share at 12.5%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When share warrants are exercised, the cost of acquisition of the resulting shares = amount paid for the warrant (Rs.12.50) + exercise price paid (Rs.37.50) = Rs.50 per share. The holding period for the resulting listed equity shares starts from the date of conversion (exercise). Rohit sold after 14 months from exercise, which exceeds 12 months, making it LTCG. With STT paid on a listed equity share, LTCG is taxed at 12.5% under Section 112A (above Rs.1,25,000 exemption). Gain per share = Rs.80 - Rs.50 = Rs.30.
**The Trap:** Option A uses only the exercise price (Rs.37.50) as cost, ignoring the upfront warrant payment. Option D uses only the upfront payment (Rs.12.50) as cost. Both are incorrect — the total cost includes both components. Option C correctly computes Rs.50 cost but misclassifies 14 months as STCG.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Share warrant mechanics and taxation are tested in NISM Series VIII and Series X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For share warrants, always add BOTH the warrant price and the exercise price to arrive at cost of acquisition. The holding period starts from the date of exercise (conversion to shares), not from the date of warrant allotment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
