<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Taxation of Debt and Equity Products_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Deepa, an active trader, incurred a net loss of Rs.3,00,000 from equity futures and options trading during FY 2025-26. Her other income includes salary of Rs.12,00,000 and rental income of Rs.2,40,000. How should this F&O loss be treated for tax purposes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is a speculative business loss and can only be set off against speculative business income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is a capital loss and can be set off against capital gains only]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is a non-speculative business loss and can be set off against salary and rental income in the same year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It is a non-speculative business loss; it cannot be set off against salary income but can be carried forward for 8 assessment years to be set off against business income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 43(5), derivatives (futures and options) trading is specifically excluded from the definition of "speculative transaction." Therefore, F&O losses are classified as non-speculative business losses. Non-speculative business losses can be set off against any income EXCEPT salary income in the current year. However, if not fully set off, they can be carried forward for 8 assessment years and set off only against business income (not any other head).
**The Trap:** Option A is the most common trap — many candidates think derivatives = speculation. The law explicitly excludes exchange-traded derivatives from speculative transactions. Option C is partially right (it IS non-speculative) but wrong on set-off — business losses CANNOT be set off against salary income.
**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) heavily tests the non-speculative classification of F&O under Section 43(5).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise clients that F&O losses, while non-speculative, have limited set-off utility. They cannot offset salary or capital gains, making F&O trading losses potentially "stranded" for salaried individuals without other business income.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
