<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Technical Analysis_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Pooja Malhotra, a technical analyst at Capital First Securities, is analyzing the Nifty 50 index chart. She observes: (1) Nifty has been in a primary uptrend for the past 18 months, moving from 18,000 to 25,500. (2) Currently, Nifty is forming a Head and Shoulders pattern with Left Shoulder at 25,000, Head at 25,500, and Right Shoulder forming near 25,100. The neckline is at 24,200. (3) The 50-day EMA is at 24,800 and the 200-day EMA is at 23,500. Both are still rising. (4) RSI is at 65, down from 78 two weeks ago. (5) MACD fast line has crossed below the slow line. (6) Volume has been declining on recent up-moves and increasing on down-moves. (7) Sensex is also showing a similar pattern, confirming Dow Theory index confirmation principle.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> The Head and Shoulders pattern Pooja has identified suggests:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Continuation of the 18-month uptrend]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A potential bearish reversal of the primary uptrend if the neckline at 24,200 is broken with volume]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Immediate crash to 18,000 levels]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The pattern is meaningless since Nifty is still above 24,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** H&S is a top reversal pattern. The neckline break (24,200) with volume would confirm the reversal. However, until the neckline breaks, the uptrend is intact.
**The Trap:** H&S is confirmed ONLY on neckline break. Premature selling before confirmation wastes potential upside.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 15 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Set a stop-loss slightly above the right shoulder (25,100) for short positions. Target = Head height projected from neckline.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>