<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Technical Analysis_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Pooja Malhotra, a technical analyst at Capital First Securities, is analyzing the Nifty 50 index chart. She observes: (1) Nifty has been in a primary uptrend for the past 18 months, moving from 18,000 to 25,500. (2) Currently, Nifty is forming a Head and Shoulders pattern with Left Shoulder at 25,000, Head at 25,500, and Right Shoulder forming near 25,100. The neckline is at 24,200. (3) The 50-day EMA is at 24,800 and the 200-day EMA is at 23,500. Both are still rising. (4) RSI is at 65, down from 78 two weeks ago. (5) MACD fast line has crossed below the slow line. (6) Volume has been declining on recent up-moves and increasing on down-moves. (7) Sensex is also showing a similar pattern, confirming Dow Theory index confirmation principle.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> The MACD crossover (fast below slow) suggests:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Strong buying momentum building]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Shift in momentum from bullish to bearish, supporting the potential reversal thesis]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A golden cross buy signal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MACD is not relevant for index analysis]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** MACD fast line crossing below slow line is a bearish signal. Combined with the H&S pattern and volume analysis, it supports the reversal thesis.
**The Trap:** MACD cross below = bearish, not bullish. It confirms the weakening momentum shown by other indicators.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Ch 15 NISM XV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Multiple confirming signals (H&S + declining RSI + MACD cross + volume pattern) strengthen the reversal case significantly.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>