<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Terminology in Equity and Debt Markets_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Desai, a fixed income analyst, is evaluating two corporate bonds for inclusion in his portfolio: Bond A — Issued by Infra Corp Ltd: Face Value Rs.1,000, Coupon Rate 9% payable annually, Current Market Price Rs.950, Remaining maturity 5 years. Bond B — Issued by Tech Solutions Ltd: Face Value Rs.1,000, Coupon Rate 7.5% payable annually, Current Market Price Rs.1,050, Remaining maturity 5 years, Callable at Rs.1,020 after 3 years. Both bonds have similar credit ratings (AA+). Vikram needs to analyze these bonds to make his investment recommendation.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Bond B trades at a premium (above face value). This is because:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The bond has higher credit risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The coupon rate of 7.5% is higher than the current market yield for similar bonds, making it more attractive]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The bond will never be repaid]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The issuer is a technology company]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a bond trades above par (premium), it means its coupon rate is higher than the prevailing market yield for similar bonds. Investors pay more because the higher coupon provides better income than new issues.
**The Trap:** Premium does not indicate higher risk. It indicates the coupon is attractive relative to current market rates.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Bond pricing (premium/discount/par) relative to market rates is tested in NISM Series XV and IV.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Even though Bond B pays 7.5% coupon (lower than Bond A's 9%), it trades at a premium, suggesting market rates for AA+ bonds have fallen below 7.5%.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>