<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Understanding Securities Markets and Performance_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A bank issues a Certificate of Deposit (CD) for 1 year at a certain interest rate. An investor purchases the CD but needs money after 6 months. What distinguishes this CD from a regular bank fixed deposit in this situation?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The CD can be transferred to another investor before maturity, while a bank FD cannot be transferred]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The CD pays a higher interest rate than the bank FD]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The CD is guaranteed by the government while the bank FD is not]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The CD cannot be broken before maturity while the bank FD can be broken with a penalty]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A CD is a security and can be transferred to another investor before maturity. The investor who holds the CD on the maturity date submits it to the bank and collects the maturity value. A regular bank FD, on the other hand, is a bilateral contract that is NOT transferable -- the deposit can only be broken, possibly with a penalty.

**The Trap:** Interest rates on CDs may or may not be higher (option B) -- that depends on market conditions. CDs are not government-guaranteed (option C). Actually, bank FDs can typically be broken with penalty, while CDs are transferable instead (option D reverses the distinction).

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. The CD vs FD distinction illustrates the fundamental concept of what makes something a "security" -- transferability.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This is a perfect example to explain to clients why securities markets matter. A CD offers liquidity through transferability; a bank FD offers liquidity through premature withdrawal with penalty. The mechanism is different, but the investor need (accessing money early) is the same.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>