<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Understanding Securities Markets and Performance_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[What is the PRIMARY function of the securities market in the financial system?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To provide a regulated institutional framework for efficient flow of capital from investors to businesses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To provide loans directly to individuals for personal consumption]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To print and distribute currency notes on behalf of the Reserve Bank of India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To collect taxes from corporations and redistribute them to households]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The securities market provides a regulated institutional framework for an efficient flow of capital (equity and debt) from investors to businesses. It channels savings of households, business firms and government to fund capital requirements of enterprises and government.

**The Trap:** Banks provide loans (option B), but the securities market operates differently through standardized, transferable instruments. Currency distribution (option C) is an RBI function. Tax collection (option D) is a government fiscal function, not a market function.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. The capital allocation role of securities markets appears in NISM V-A (Mutual Fund), VIII (Equity Derivatives), and XII.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When explaining securities markets to first-time investors, emphasize that the market is a bridge connecting people with surplus money (savers) to entities needing capital (businesses/government). This regulated bridge is what makes organized investing possible.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>