<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Understanding Securities Markets and Performance_22" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[KYC Registration Agencies (KRAs) provide which key service in the Indian securities market?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A centralized system where KYC information is uploaded by securities market intermediaries, making KYC valid across all SEBI-registered intermediaries]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A platform for trading government securities on behalf of retail investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A system for settling trades between buyers and sellers in the secondary market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A mechanism for credit rating of debt instruments issued by corporates]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** KRAs provide a centralized system where KYC information is uploaded by securities market intermediaries. KYC once completed is valid across all SEBI-registered intermediaries (i.e., across the entire capital market). SEBI has mandated KRAs to share data through inter-operability process (IOP) so retail investors are not inconvenienced.

**The Trap:** Government securities trading (option B) happens through stock exchanges and RBI platforms. Trade settlement (option C) is done by clearing corporations. Credit rating (option D) is done by credit rating agencies.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. KYC and KRA concepts are tested in NISM V-A (Mutual Fund), III-A (Securities Intermediaries), and XII.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The "one KYC, all intermediaries" concept is a huge convenience for clients. Once KYC is done with any SEBI intermediary, the client can transact across mutual funds, brokers, PMS, and other intermediaries without repeating the process.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>