<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Understanding Securities Markets and Performance_29" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's Cybersecurity and Cyber Resilience Framework (CSCRF), five types of entities are classified as Market Infrastructure Institutions (MIIs): Stock Exchanges, Depositories, Clearing Corporations, __________, and __________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[KYC Registration Agencies (KRAs) and Qualified Registrars to an Issue and Share Transfer Agents (QRTAs)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Credit Rating Agencies and Merchant Bankers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Registrars to an Issue (RTAs) and Credit Rating Agencies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Merchant Bankers and Custodians]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI's CSCRF, the five entities classified as Market Infrastructure Institutions (MIIs) are: (1) Stock Exchanges, (2) Depositories, (3) Clearing Corporations, (4) KYC Registration Agencies (KRAs), and (5) Qualified Registrars to an Issue and Share Transfer Agents (QRTAs). These entities form the backbone of market infrastructure and are subject to the highest cybersecurity standards.

**The Trap:** Credit Rating Agencies, Merchant Bankers, and Custodians are important SEBI-registered intermediaries but are not classified as MIIs under CSCRF. The distinction between QRTAs (which are MIIs) and ordinary RTAs (which are not) is a subtle but important test point.

**Cross-Exam Context:** CSCRF is a recent regulatory development tested in NISM Series XII. Understanding the MII classification is essential for cybersecurity compliance questions.

**Key Takeaway:** The five MIIs under CSCRF are Stock Exchanges, Depositories, Clearing Corporations, KRAs, and QRTAs -- remember that KRAs and QRTAs are included alongside the three traditional MIIs.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>