<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Understanding Securities Markets and Performance_25" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An investor purchased 100 shares of XYZ Ltd. at Rs.25 per share. After one year, the share is quoting at Rs.45 per share in the market. If the investor decides to sell all shares, what is the total profit earned, and which market function enables this transaction?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Total profit of Rs.2,000; enabled by the liquidity function of secondary markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total profit of Rs.4,500; enabled by the price discovery function]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total profit of Rs.2,000; enabled by the primary market issuance function]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Total profit of Rs.2,500; enabled by the information signaling function]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Profit = (Selling price - Purchase price) x Number of shares = (Rs.45 - Rs.25) x 100 = Rs.20 x 100 = Rs.2,000. This transaction is possible because secondary markets provide liquidity -- allowing the investor to sell shares and convert to cash. Without liquidity in secondary markets, investors would be locked into their investments.

**The Trap:** Rs.4,500 (option B) is the total sale proceeds, not the profit. Rs.2,500 (option D) is an incorrect calculation. The primary market (option C) is for new issues, not for selling existing holdings.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. This exact example (100 shares at Rs.25, sold at Rs.45) is from the NISM XII workbook illustrating the liquidity function.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When discussing returns with clients, always distinguish between investment amount, sale proceeds, and actual profit. Also remind them about tax implications -- equity gains held over 1 year are taxed differently from short-term gains.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>