<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="Understanding Securities Markets and Performance_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes 'financial disintermediation' in the context of securities markets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Companies raising funds directly from investors through securities instead of borrowing from banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Banks increasing their lending to companies at lower interest rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI removing intermediaries from the securities market]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The government printing more currency to fund infrastructure projects]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Financial disintermediation refers to the process where companies raise funds directly from investors by issuing securities (like commercial paper or bonds) instead of obtaining traditional loans from banks. The expansion of securities markets has contributed to this process, making capital raising more cost-efficient.

**The Trap:** Banks increasing lending (option B) is the opposite -- that is traditional financial intermediation. SEBI removing intermediaries (option C) is not what disintermediation means. Currency printing (option D) is a monetary policy action unrelated to disintermediation.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Foundation topic tested across 22 NISM exams. Disintermediation is a concept relevant to understanding why capital markets exist alongside the banking system.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Disintermediation has been a global trend. When a company issues bonds directly to investors instead of taking a bank loan, both the company (lower cost) and investor (higher return than FD) can benefit. This is the value proposition of debt mutual funds.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>