<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VB Fund Distribution and Channel Management_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under the SEBI (Prohibition of Fraudulent and Unfair Trade Practices) Regulations 2003, mis-selling in mutual funds includes all of the following EXCEPT __________.]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Recommending a scheme after conducting a proper risk assessment and suitability analysis of the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Making false or misleading statements to induce the purchase or sale of mutual fund units]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Concealing or omitting material facts about the scheme from the investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Not taking reasonable care to ensure suitability of the scheme for the investor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Per SEBI PFUTP 2003, mis-selling includes four activities: (1) Making false/misleading statements, (2) Concealing/omitting material facts, (3) Concealing associated risk factors, and (4) Not taking reasonable care to ensure suitability. Recommending a scheme after proper risk assessment and suitability analysis is the correct practice and is NOT mis-selling.

**The Trap:** All three distractors are actual components of the mis-selling definition. The question tests whether you can distinguish proper advisory conduct from the four prohibited mis-selling activities defined by SEBI.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Mis-selling is a critical topic in NISM V-B and V-A. Distributors must understand all four elements to avoid regulatory action.

**Key Takeaway:** Mis-selling = false statements + concealing facts + concealing risks + not ensuring suitability. Proper suitability assessment is the antidote to mis-selling.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>