<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VB Legal Structure of Mutual Funds_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Mrs. Singh, a retired bank manager, is considering investing in a mutual fund. She asks: "If the fund house (AMC) has financial problems, will I lose my investment?" What is the correct answer?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA["Your investments are held separately by the custodian. The AMC's financial problems do not affect your holdings. Another AMC can take over management."]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA["Yes, if the AMC fails, all investor money is lost forever."]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA["The government will reimburse you 100% from the national treasury."]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA["Your money is mixed with the AMC's own funds, so there could be some loss."]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The trust structure of mutual funds ensures that investor assets are separate from the AMC's own assets. The custodian holds the securities on behalf of the trust (investors). If the AMC faces financial difficulties, the trustees (with SEBI's approval) can appoint another AMC to manage the fund, or wind up the scheme and return money to investors.
**The Trap:** Investor money is NEVER mixed with AMC funds — they are legally separate. The government does not directly reimburse investors, but the regulatory structure protects them. Claims that all money is lost are false and fear-mongering.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This is also tested in Series V-A (MF Distributors) under investor protection and trust structure.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This question will come from almost every new investor. Prepare a clear, confident answer about the trust structure, custodian's role, and SEBI oversight. Your knowledge of the legal structure builds trust with clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
