<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VB Legal and Regulatory Environment_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A retired investor visits a bank branch and is told that a particular mutual fund scheme will give "guaranteed 12% returns." What should the investor understand about this claim?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is a genuine offer since banks are trustworthy institutions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The guarantee is backed by SEBI and RBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[This claim violates SEBI regulations as mutual fund returns cannot be guaranteed, and the investor should be cautious]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The bank will compensate if returns are less than 12%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI regulations, no mutual fund scheme can guarantee or promise returns. Mutual funds are market-linked products and returns depend on market performance. Any person or institution claiming guaranteed returns from a mutual fund is violating SEBI's Advertisement Code and the AMFI Code of Conduct. The investor should report such claims to SEBI.
**The Trap:** Even if the claim comes from a bank (which people generally trust), it is still a violation. Banks distribute mutual funds as intermediaries but cannot guarantee returns on behalf of mutual fund schemes. Bank FD guarantees and mutual fund returns are entirely different things.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Application question combining advertising code and investor protection concepts.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a retired investor mentions receiving such guaranteed return claims, educate them that this is a red flag. Legitimate distributors never guarantee mutual fund returns. Suggest they verify with AMFI or SEBI if they encounter such claims, and never invest based on return guarantees.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
