<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VB Legal and Regulatory Environment_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A mutual fund distributor advises a retired investor to invest his entire life savings in a single high-risk equity fund. Is this appropriate as per SEBI and AMFI guidelines?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, if the fund has given good past returns]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, if the investor agrees to it]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, this is unsuitable advice as it does not consider the investor's age, risk tolerance, and need for diversification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, equity funds always give the best returns in the long run]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI and AMFI guidelines, distributors must make suitable recommendations based on the investor's risk profile, age, financial situation, and investment goals. Advising a retired investor to put all savings in a single high-risk fund is clearly unsuitable because: (1) retirees generally need capital protection, (2) putting everything in one fund lacks diversification, (3) high-risk funds may not be appropriate for someone who cannot afford to lose capital.
**The Trap:** Even if the investor agrees, the distributor has a duty to provide suitable advice. Past performance does not justify unsuitable recommendations. The suitability obligation is on the distributor, not the investor.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Application question testing practical understanding of suitability norms.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For retired investors, always recommend a diversified portfolio appropriate for their age and needs. A mix of debt funds (for stability), balanced funds (for moderate growth), and some equity (for inflation protection) is generally more suitable than any single high-risk fund.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
