<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VIII Introduction to Forwards and Futures_95" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A trader notices that near-month Nifty futures (expiring in 10 days) are at 25,050 while the spot Nifty is at 25,030. The fair value for 10 days with r=7% and q=2% is approximately 25,063. What can the trader conclude?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Near-month futures at 25,050 are slightly underpriced relative to fair value of 25,063, but the mispricing of 13 points may not be enough to cover transaction costs for arbitrage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The futures are significantly overpriced and offer a major arbitrage opportunity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The futures are perfectly priced at fair value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The basis of -20 points indicates a strongly bearish market]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Step-by-step analysis:
1. Fair value = 25,063
2. Actual futures = 25,050
3. Underpricing = 25,063 - 25,050 = 13 points
4. Basis = Spot - Futures = 25,030 - 25,050 = -20 (normal contango)
5. While futures are technically underpriced by 13 points, this may not cover transaction costs (brokerage, STT, impact cost)

In practice, arbitrage is only profitable when mispricing exceeds total transaction costs.

**The Trap:** The futures are underpriced (not overpriced). The basis of -20 is normal contango, not bearish signal. "Perfectly priced" is incorrect as there is a 13-point gap.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Practical arbitrage considerations (transaction costs, impact costs) are important Series VIII concepts.

**Key Takeaway:** Theoretical arbitrage may not be practical if mispricing is less than transaction costs (brokerage, taxes, impact cost).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>