<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VIII Accounting and Taxation_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[For income tax purposes, income from exchange-traded derivative transactions is treated as:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Non-speculative business income under 'Profits and Gains from Business or Profession', since the Finance Act 2005 amended Section 43(5) to exclude exchange-traded derivatives from speculative transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Speculative business income, since derivatives are settled otherwise than by actual delivery]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Capital gains income for all categories of taxpayers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tax-free income since STT is already paid on derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Finance Act 2005 amended Section 43(5) of the Income Tax Act to exclude transactions in derivatives carried out on a recognized stock exchange from the definition of speculative transactions. Therefore, F&O income/loss is treated as non-speculative business income under 'Profits and Gains from Business or Profession.' Exception: For FPIs, derivatives gains are taxed as capital gains.

**The Trap:** Before 2005, derivatives WERE speculative. The amendment changed this. The old classification (speculative) is a common exam distractor. Also, STT payment does not make the income tax-free — it only qualifies for deduction under the IT Act.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a critical distinction tested in Series VIII, I, and XIII. The carry-forward period for such losses is 8 assessment years.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Exchange-traded F&O = non-speculative business income (since 2005). Losses can be set off against any non-speculative business income (not salary). Must file ITR on time to carry forward.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
