<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VIII Sales Practices and Investor Protection Services_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the maximum time limit prescribed by SEBI for completion of arbitration proceedings at stock exchanges?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[4 months from the date of appointment of arbitrator(s)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[6 months from the date of filing the arbitration complaint]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[12 months from the date the dispute originally arose]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[30 days from the date of the first arbitration hearing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI has prescribed that arbitration proceedings at stock exchanges must be completed within 4 months from the date of appointment of the arbitrator(s). This time-bound requirement ensures that investor disputes with trading members are resolved expeditiously, making exchange arbitration a faster alternative to regular court proceedings.

**The Trap:** The 4-month clock starts from the date of appointment of arbitrator(s) — not from the date of filing the complaint, the date the dispute arose, or the first hearing. The starting point of the time limit is a frequently tested detail. Also, 6 months and 12 months are plausible-sounding but incorrect timeframes.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This time limit is part of SEBI's broader investor protection framework tested in NISM Series VIII. The arbitration mechanism, along with the Investor Grievance Redressal mechanism and SCORES platform, forms the three-tier dispute resolution system available to investors.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Key arbitration facts: 4-month completion timeline from arbitrator appointment, the award is binding (appealable to appellate arbitration panel within 1 month), and no minimum dispute value is required. Advisors should inform clients about this mechanism as it is faster and cheaper than civil courts.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
