<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="VIII Introduction to Forwards and Futures_102" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund manager holds a diversified equity portfolio worth Rs. 100 crore with beta 1.1. Due to an upcoming budget announcement, she expects short-term volatility. She wants to temporarily reduce the portfolio beta to 0.3. Nifty futures are at 25,000 (lot size 65). How should she proceed?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Sell approximately 492 Nifty futures contracts to reduce beta from 1.1 to 0.3, using the formula: Contracts = Portfolio Value x (Current Beta - Target Beta) / Futures Value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell all equity holdings and move to cash, then rebuy after the budget]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Sell approximately 677 contracts to bring beta to zero]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buy 492 put options instead, as futures create unlimited downside risk]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Step-by-step calculation:
1. Beta reduction = 1.1 - 0.3 = 0.8
2. Contracts = (100,00,00,000 x 0.8) / (25,000 x 65) = 80,00,00,000 / 16,25,000 = 492.3
3. Sell 492 contracts

This temporarily reduces market exposure without selling the portfolio (avoiding transaction costs, capital gains tax, and the risk of not being able to buy back at same prices).

**The Trap:** Selling all holdings is impractical and costly. 677 contracts brings beta to zero (full hedge). The question asks for beta 0.3, not zero. Put options are a valid alternative but the question asks about futures strategy.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Tactical beta adjustment is an advanced portfolio management topic in Series VIII.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Contracts to sell = PV x (Current Beta - Target Beta) / Contract Value. Tactical, not permanent.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>