<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ms. Ananya Kapoor, a SEBI Registered Investment Adviser, is evaluating two mid-cap stocks for her client Mr. Deepak Joshi. Stock A (Technovate Ltd) is in the IT services sector and Stock B (BankFirst Ltd) is in the banking sector. The following data is available:

Stock A — Technovate Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 800, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 32, Book Value per share Rs. 200, Dividend per share Rs. 8, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 20% p.a., Last year's dividend Rs. 7.50 (D0), Expected growth in dividends 15% p.a. indefinitely, Industry average P/E 28x.

Stock B — BankFirst Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 450, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 30, Book Value per share Rs. 500, Dividend per share Rs. 15, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 12% p.a., Net Interest Margin 3.2%, Industry average P/B 1.8x.

The risk-free rate is 7% and Deepak's required rate of return on equity is 18%. The IT sector P/E average is 28x and Banking sector P/B average is 1.8x.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> What is the P/E ratio of Technovate Ltd and is it undervalued or overvalued relative to the IT sector average?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[P/E = 25x, undervalued relative to industry average of 28x]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[P/E = 28x, fairly valued relative to industry average]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[P/E = 32x, overvalued relative to industry average of 28x]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[P/E = 20x, significantly undervalued]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** P/E = Market Price / EPS = Rs. 800 / Rs. 32 = 25x. Since the industry average P/E is 28x and Technovate's P/E is 25x, the stock appears undervalued relative to its sector peers.
**The Trap:** 32x might be guessed by confusing EPS with something else, or 20x by using growth rate instead of EPS.
**Cross-Exam Context:** P/E ratio comparison with industry benchmarks is a core valuation concept in X-A and V-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A P/E below industry average doesn't automatically mean 'buy' — investigate whether lower P/E reflects genuine undervaluation or deteriorating fundamentals.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>