<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C3_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Padmini Iyer, aged 62, has recently retired with a corpus of Rs. 1.2 crore. She needs a monthly income of Rs. 60,000 to meet her living expenses. She has no pension and her only other income is rental income of Rs. 15,000 per month. She wants to invest in safe instruments with government backing or high credit quality. Her investment adviser suggests the following allocation:

1. Senior Citizens' Saving Scheme (SCSS): Rs. 30 lakh at 8.2% p.a. (quarterly interest payout)
2. Post Office Monthly Income Scheme (POMIS): Rs. 9 lakh (joint account with spouse) at 7.4% p.a. (monthly payout)
3. Public Provident Fund (PPF): Rs. 1.5 lakh annual contribution (she already has a PPF account with Rs. 8 lakh balance, 4 years remaining)
4. Bank Fixed Deposits: Rs. 40 lakh across 4 banks at 7.0% p.a. (quarterly interest)
5. RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond: Rs. 15 lakh at current rate of 8.05% p.a. (semi-annual interest)
6. National Savings Certificate (NSC): Rs. 10 lakh at 7.7% p.a. (interest compounded, paid at maturity in 5 years)
7. Remaining in savings bank account for liquidity

Total invested: Rs. 30 + 9 + 1.5 + 40 + 15 + 10 = Rs. 105.5 lakh. Remaining: Rs. 14.5 lakh in savings bank.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Including rental income, approximately what percentage of Mrs. Iyer's monthly expense need of Rs. 60,000 is covered by her total regular income from all income-generating investments and rental?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[About 85%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[About 100% — her income approximately meets her expenses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[About 124% — her income exceeds her expenses comfortably]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[About 65% — there is a significant shortfall]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Monthly income: SCSS Rs. 20,500 + POMIS Rs. 5,550 + Bank FDs (Rs. 40L × 7% / 12) Rs. 23,333 + RBI Bond (Rs. 15L × 8.05% / 12) Rs. 10,063 + Rental Rs. 15,000 = Rs. 74,446. NSC and PPF do not provide regular income. Coverage = Rs. 74,446 / Rs. 60,000 = 124%. Her income exceeds needs by Rs. 14,446/month.
**The Trap:** Candidates might include NSC interest as monthly income, but NSC compounds to maturity and provides no interim payouts.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Income sufficiency analysis is a core financial planning skill tested in X-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The surplus of Rs. 14,446/month can be reinvested through SIPs for inflation protection — this growing corpus will help when real expenses rise over time.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>