<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C3_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Padmini Iyer, aged 62, has recently retired with a corpus of Rs. 1.2 crore. She needs a monthly income of Rs. 60,000 to meet her living expenses. She has no pension and her only other income is rental income of Rs. 15,000 per month. She wants to invest in safe instruments with government backing or high credit quality. Her investment adviser suggests the following allocation:

1. Senior Citizens' Saving Scheme (SCSS): Rs. 30 lakh at 8.2% p.a. (quarterly interest payout)
2. Post Office Monthly Income Scheme (POMIS): Rs. 9 lakh (joint account with spouse) at 7.4% p.a. (monthly payout)
3. Public Provident Fund (PPF): Rs. 1.5 lakh annual contribution (she already has a PPF account with Rs. 8 lakh balance, 4 years remaining)
4. Bank Fixed Deposits: Rs. 40 lakh across 4 banks at 7.0% p.a. (quarterly interest)
5. RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond: Rs. 15 lakh at current rate of 8.05% p.a. (semi-annual interest)
6. National Savings Certificate (NSC): Rs. 10 lakh at 7.7% p.a. (interest compounded, paid at maturity in 5 years)
7. Remaining in savings bank account for liquidity

Total invested: Rs. 30 + 9 + 1.5 + 40 + 15 + 10 = Rs. 105.5 lakh. Remaining: Rs. 14.5 lakh in savings bank.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Mrs. Iyer's bank FDs are spread across 4 banks at Rs. 10 lakh each. What is the total DICGC insurance coverage she receives?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 5 lakh total across all banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10 lakh (Rs. 5 lakh per bank, but only 2 banks covered)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 20 lakh (Rs. 5 lakh per bank across all 4 banks)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 40 lakh (full coverage of all deposits)]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** DICGC insures Rs. 5 lakh per depositor per bank. Since Mrs. Iyer has deposits across 4 different banks, she gets Rs. 5 lakh × 4 = Rs. 20 lakh coverage. The remaining Rs. 20 lakh (Rs. 5 lakh per bank above Rs. 5 lakh limit) is uninsured.
**The Trap:** Rs. 40 lakh full coverage is incorrect — DICGC limit is Rs. 5 lakh per bank, not per deposit.
**Cross-Exam Context:** DICGC coverage and its implications for deposit planning are tested in X-A and XII.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Spreading across banks is smart, but even smarter is keeping each bank's exposure at or below Rs. 5 lakh for full insurance — Mrs. Iyer's Rs. 10 lakh per bank leaves Rs. 5 lakh per bank uninsured.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>