<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ms. Ananya Kapoor, a SEBI Registered Investment Adviser, is evaluating two mid-cap stocks for her client Mr. Deepak Joshi. Stock A (Technovate Ltd) is in the IT services sector and Stock B (BankFirst Ltd) is in the banking sector. The following data is available:

Stock A — Technovate Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 800, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 32, Book Value per share Rs. 200, Dividend per share Rs. 8, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 20% p.a., Last year's dividend Rs. 7.50 (D0), Expected growth in dividends 15% p.a. indefinitely, Industry average P/E 28x.

Stock B — BankFirst Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 450, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 30, Book Value per share Rs. 500, Dividend per share Rs. 15, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 12% p.a., Net Interest Margin 3.2%, Industry average P/B 1.8x.

The risk-free rate is 7% and Deepak's required rate of return on equity is 18%. The IT sector P/E average is 28x and Banking sector P/B average is 1.8x.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Based on the valuation analysis, which of the following recommendations would be most appropriate for Ms. Kapoor to make to her client?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buy only Technovate Ltd as its P/E is below industry average]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buy only BankFirst Ltd as it is trading below book value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Technovate appears overvalued by DDM despite low P/E; BankFirst warrants further investigation into asset quality before recommending]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Buy both stocks equally as both show signs of undervaluation]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Technovate has a low P/E (25x vs 28x industry) but DDM values it at only Rs. 287.50 vs market price of Rs. 800 — conflicting signals suggest the high growth rate may not sustain. BankFirst at P/B 0.9x is below book value, which could be a value trap or genuine opportunity — asset quality investigation is needed.
**The Trap:** Relying on a single valuation metric leads to incomplete conclusions — a prudent adviser combines multiple approaches.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Multi-metric valuation judgment is an advanced X-A concept also relevant to X-B.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** As an RIA, never recommend based on a single ratio. Use P/E, PEG, DDM, and P/B together — when metrics conflict, dig deeper into fundamentals before making a recommendation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>