<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C3_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Padmini Iyer, aged 62, has recently retired with a corpus of Rs. 1.2 crore. She needs a monthly income of Rs. 60,000 to meet her living expenses. She has no pension and her only other income is rental income of Rs. 15,000 per month. She wants to invest in safe instruments with government backing or high credit quality. Her investment adviser suggests the following allocation:

1. Senior Citizens' Saving Scheme (SCSS): Rs. 30 lakh at 8.2% p.a. (quarterly interest payout)
2. Post Office Monthly Income Scheme (POMIS): Rs. 9 lakh (joint account with spouse) at 7.4% p.a. (monthly payout)
3. Public Provident Fund (PPF): Rs. 1.5 lakh annual contribution (she already has a PPF account with Rs. 8 lakh balance, 4 years remaining)
4. Bank Fixed Deposits: Rs. 40 lakh across 4 banks at 7.0% p.a. (quarterly interest)
5. RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond: Rs. 15 lakh at current rate of 8.05% p.a. (semi-annual interest)
6. National Savings Certificate (NSC): Rs. 10 lakh at 7.7% p.a. (interest compounded, paid at maturity in 5 years)
7. Remaining in savings bank account for liquidity

Total invested: Rs. 30 + 9 + 1.5 + 40 + 15 + 10 = Rs. 105.5 lakh. Remaining: Rs. 14.5 lakh in savings bank.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> What is the key risk of the RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond for Mrs. Iyer compared to fixed-rate instruments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Default risk since it is not backed by the government]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Interest rate will reset lower if NSC rates decline, reducing her income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The bond cannot be held to maturity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no tax benefit on the interest earned]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The RBI floating rate bond resets its interest rate every 6 months linked to NSC rate + 35 bps. If NSC rates decline (during a rate-cutting cycle), Mrs. Iyer's interest income will reduce, creating income uncertainty. Fixed-rate instruments like SCSS and FDs lock in the rate.
**The Trap:** The bond IS government-backed, so there's no default risk. The risk is purely income variability due to rate resets.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Floating vs fixed rate risk is tested in X-A and IV (Interest Rate Derivatives).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** In a falling rate environment, fixed-rate instruments are better for income certainty. The RBI floating bond suits investors who expect rates to rise — for a retiree, income stability usually takes priority over rate speculation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>