<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ms. Ananya Kapoor, a SEBI Registered Investment Adviser, is evaluating two mid-cap stocks for her client Mr. Deepak Joshi. Stock A (Technovate Ltd) is in the IT services sector and Stock B (BankFirst Ltd) is in the banking sector. The following data is available:

Stock A — Technovate Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 800, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 32, Book Value per share Rs. 200, Dividend per share Rs. 8, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 20% p.a., Last year's dividend Rs. 7.50 (D0), Expected growth in dividends 15% p.a. indefinitely, Industry average P/E 28x.

Stock B — BankFirst Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 450, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 30, Book Value per share Rs. 500, Dividend per share Rs. 15, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 12% p.a., Net Interest Margin 3.2%, Industry average P/B 1.8x.

The risk-free rate is 7% and Deepak's required rate of return on equity is 18%. The IT sector P/E average is 28x and Banking sector P/B average is 1.8x.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Using the Gordon Growth Model (DDM), what is the intrinsic value of Technovate Ltd if D0 = Rs. 7.50, growth rate = 15%, and required return = 18%?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 250.00]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 287.50]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 375.00]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 150.00]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Gordon Growth Model: P = D1 / (r - g) where D1 = D0 × (1+g) = Rs. 7.50 × 1.15 = Rs. 8.625. P = 8.625 / (0.18 - 0.15) = 8.625 / 0.03 = Rs. 287.50. Since market price (Rs. 800) far exceeds intrinsic value (Rs. 287.50), the stock appears overvalued by DDM.
**The Trap:** Rs. 250 would result from using D0 (7.50) instead of D1 (8.625) — always use next year's expected dividend in the formula.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Gordon Growth Model is tested in X-A and is a fundamental equity valuation tool also appearing in V-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** DDM is sensitive to the (r-g) denominator — a small change in growth or required return dramatically changes the value. When r-g is small (0.03), even minor input changes cause large valuation swings.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>