<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C3_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Padmini Iyer, aged 62, has recently retired with a corpus of Rs. 1.2 crore. She needs a monthly income of Rs. 60,000 to meet her living expenses. She has no pension and her only other income is rental income of Rs. 15,000 per month. She wants to invest in safe instruments with government backing or high credit quality. Her investment adviser suggests the following allocation:

1. Senior Citizens' Saving Scheme (SCSS): Rs. 30 lakh at 8.2% p.a. (quarterly interest payout)
2. Post Office Monthly Income Scheme (POMIS): Rs. 9 lakh (joint account with spouse) at 7.4% p.a. (monthly payout)
3. Public Provident Fund (PPF): Rs. 1.5 lakh annual contribution (she already has a PPF account with Rs. 8 lakh balance, 4 years remaining)
4. Bank Fixed Deposits: Rs. 40 lakh across 4 banks at 7.0% p.a. (quarterly interest)
5. RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond: Rs. 15 lakh at current rate of 8.05% p.a. (semi-annual interest)
6. National Savings Certificate (NSC): Rs. 10 lakh at 7.7% p.a. (interest compounded, paid at maturity in 5 years)
7. Remaining in savings bank account for liquidity

Total invested: Rs. 30 + 9 + 1.5 + 40 + 15 + 10 = Rs. 105.5 lakh. Remaining: Rs. 14.5 lakh in savings bank.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> What is the approximate total monthly income Mrs. Iyer will receive from SCSS and POMIS combined (before tax)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 26,050]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 30,150]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 21,500]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 35,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCSS: Rs. 30 lakh × 8.2% = Rs. 2,46,000 p.a. = Rs. 20,500/month (paid quarterly as Rs. 61,500 per quarter). POMIS: Rs. 9 lakh × 7.4% = Rs. 66,600 p.a. = Rs. 5,550/month. Combined monthly equivalent = Rs. 20,500 + Rs. 5,550 = Rs. 26,050.
**The Trap:** Rs. 30,150 might result from incorrectly using a higher SCSS rate or adding PPF income which is not available as regular payout.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Income planning from small savings is core to X-A retirement advisory.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SCSS pays quarterly, not monthly — ensure Mrs. Iyer budgets for this. POMIS provides true monthly income, making it ideal as the monthly cash flow anchor.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>