<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C3_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Padmini Iyer, aged 62, has recently retired with a corpus of Rs. 1.2 crore. She needs a monthly income of Rs. 60,000 to meet her living expenses. She has no pension and her only other income is rental income of Rs. 15,000 per month. She wants to invest in safe instruments with government backing or high credit quality. Her investment adviser suggests the following allocation:

1. Senior Citizens' Saving Scheme (SCSS): Rs. 30 lakh at 8.2% p.a. (quarterly interest payout)
2. Post Office Monthly Income Scheme (POMIS): Rs. 9 lakh (joint account with spouse) at 7.4% p.a. (monthly payout)
3. Public Provident Fund (PPF): Rs. 1.5 lakh annual contribution (she already has a PPF account with Rs. 8 lakh balance, 4 years remaining)
4. Bank Fixed Deposits: Rs. 40 lakh across 4 banks at 7.0% p.a. (quarterly interest)
5. RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond: Rs. 15 lakh at current rate of 8.05% p.a. (semi-annual interest)
6. National Savings Certificate (NSC): Rs. 10 lakh at 7.7% p.a. (interest compounded, paid at maturity in 5 years)
7. Remaining in savings bank account for liquidity

Total invested: Rs. 30 + 9 + 1.5 + 40 + 15 + 10 = Rs. 105.5 lakh. Remaining: Rs. 14.5 lakh in savings bank.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Which of Mrs. Iyer's investments provides the EEE (Exempt-Exempt-Exempt) tax benefit?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Senior Citizens' Saving Scheme (SCSS)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Public Provident Fund (PPF)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[National Savings Certificate (NSC)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI Floating Rate Savings Bond]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** PPF enjoys EEE tax benefit — contributions qualify for Section 80C deduction (Exempt), annual interest is tax-free (Exempt), and maturity proceeds are tax-free (Exempt). SCSS interest is taxable, NSC accrued interest is taxable (though deemed reinvested for 80C), and RBI bond interest is fully taxable.
**The Trap:** SCSS provides Section 80C deduction on investment but interest is fully taxable — it's EET, not EEE.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Tax treatment of small savings is tested in X-A and V-A for tax planning advisory.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PPF is one of only a few instruments offering complete EEE benefit — maximize the Rs. 1.5 lakh annual contribution for highest tax efficiency, especially for clients in the highest tax bracket.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>