<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Investment Products_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ms. Ananya Kapoor, a SEBI Registered Investment Adviser, is evaluating two mid-cap stocks for her client Mr. Deepak Joshi. Stock A (Technovate Ltd) is in the IT services sector and Stock B (BankFirst Ltd) is in the banking sector. The following data is available:

Stock A — Technovate Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 800, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 32, Book Value per share Rs. 200, Dividend per share Rs. 8, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 20% p.a., Last year's dividend Rs. 7.50 (D0), Expected growth in dividends 15% p.a. indefinitely, Industry average P/E 28x.

Stock B — BankFirst Ltd: Current Market Price Rs. 450, EPS (trailing 12 months) Rs. 30, Book Value per share Rs. 500, Dividend per share Rs. 15, Expected 5-year EPS growth rate 12% p.a., Net Interest Margin 3.2%, Industry average P/B 1.8x.

The risk-free rate is 7% and Deepak's required rate of return on equity is 18%. The IT sector P/E average is 28x and Banking sector P/B average is 1.8x.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> What is the P/B ratio of BankFirst Ltd, and is it undervalued or overvalued compared to the banking sector average P/B of 1.8x?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[P/B = 0.9x, undervalued — stock is trading below book value]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[P/B = 1.5x, undervalued relative to sector]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[P/B = 1.8x, fairly valued relative to sector]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[P/B = 2.0x, overvalued relative to sector]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** P/B = Market Price / Book Value per share = Rs. 450 / Rs. 500 = 0.9x. BankFirst is trading below its book value (P/B < 1) and significantly below the sector average of 1.8x, suggesting potential undervaluation or the market perceiving some hidden risks.
**The Trap:** A P/B below 1 could mean undervaluation OR hidden asset quality problems — it's not automatically a buy signal.
**Cross-Exam Context:** P/B ratio is the preferred valuation metric for banks, tested in X-A and important for bank stock selection.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For banking stocks, always check NPA levels and provisioning when P/B is below 1 — the market may be pricing in unrecognized bad loans that would erode actual book value.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>