<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Managed Portfolios_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Harish Gupta, aged 50, is a business owner with a net worth of Rs. 8 crore. He has Rs. 1 crore available for equity investment and is evaluating two options:

Option A — Equity Mutual Fund (Direct Plan, Growth): Large & Mid-Cap Fund with expense ratio 0.75%, SEBI-mandated diversification (minimum 35% large-cap, 35% mid-cap), no minimum investment, exit load 1% if redeemed within 1 year, daily NAV disclosure, SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations apply.

Option B — Discretionary Equity PMS: Minimum investment Rs. 50 lakh, fixed management fee 1.5% p.a., performance fee 20% of profits above 10% hurdle rate (no catch-up, high watermark applies), portfolio of 15-25 stocks customized to Harish's risk profile, Rs. 5 crore net worth of PMS provider, quarterly portfolio disclosure.

Additional information: Harish is in the 30% income tax bracket. He expects a 5-year investment horizon. He wants concentrated, high-conviction stock picking rather than broad diversification. He has a separate emergency fund and does not need liquidity from this investment.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> In the PMS, Harish's securities will be held in a separate demat account in his name. How does this differ from mutual fund holdings?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In MFs, securities are held in a pooled account in the name of the scheme, and the investor holds units; in PMS, securities are directly in the investor's demat account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Both PMS and MF securities are held identically in the investor's demat]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[MF securities are held by the stock exchange, not by the fund]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMS securities are held by SEBI directly]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In PMS, each client's securities are held in separate demat accounts (segregated). In mutual funds, all securities are pooled in the scheme's demat account, and investors hold units representing their proportional share. This segregation gives PMS investors direct ownership of specific securities.
**The Trap:** MF investors don't directly own the securities — they own units of the scheme. PMS investors own the actual stocks in their name.
**Cross-Exam Context:** PMS vs MF holding structure is tested in X-A and VI (Depository Operations).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Direct ownership in PMS means the client can see exactly which stocks they own and can transfer them out (exit the PMS and keep stocks). In MFs, exit means converting to cash.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>