<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Managed Portfolios_C3_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Vikram Choudhary, aged 45, is an ultra-HNI with a total investment portfolio of Rs. 25 crore. His current allocation is: Equity Mutual Funds Rs. 8 crore, Fixed Deposits Rs. 5 crore, Direct Equity Rs. 5 crore, Real Estate Rs. 4 crore, Gold Rs. 1.5 crore, and Cash Rs. 1.5 crore. His annual income is Rs. 3 crore. His investment adviser, Ms. Neha Sharma, suggests allocating Rs. 3 crore (12% of portfolio) to Alternative Investment Funds for diversification. She proposes:

Option 1 — Category I AIF (Venture Capital Fund): Invests in early-stage tech startups. Minimum Rs. 1 crore. Close-ended with 7-year lock-in. Target return 20-25% IRR. Manager continuing interest 2.5% of corpus. Fund corpus Rs. 200 crore with maximum 250 investors.

Option 2 — Category II AIF (Private Equity Fund): Invests in mid-market growth companies. Minimum Rs. 1 crore. Close-ended with 5-year lock-in plus 2-year extension option. Target return 15-18% IRR. No leverage permitted except for day-to-day operations. Management fee 2% + carried interest 20% above 8% hurdle.

Option 3 — Category III AIF (Long-Short Equity Hedge Fund): Employs long-short equity strategies using derivatives. Minimum Rs. 1 crore. Open-ended with 1-year lock-in. Target return 12-15% with low correlation to equity markets. Manager continuing interest 5% of corpus. Can employ leverage through derivatives.

Vikram qualifies as an accredited investor (annual income ≥ Rs. 2 crore).

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Which AIF category can use leverage (borrowing through derivatives) as part of its investment strategy?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Category I AIF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Category II AIF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Only Category III AIF]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three categories equally]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Category III AIFs (like hedge funds) can employ leverage including through investment in listed or unlisted derivatives. Category I and II AIFs cannot undertake leverage or borrowing other than to meet day-to-day operational requirements. This distinction reflects the different risk profiles.
**The Trap:** Cat II 'does not undertake leverage except for day-to-day operations' — this exception is for operational needs, not investment strategy.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Leverage permissions by AIF category is a frequently tested concept in X-A and III-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Leverage amplifies both gains and losses — Cat III AIFs using leverage can have significantly higher volatility than Cat I/II. Ensure Vikram understands that the 12-15% target return comes with proportionally higher risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>