<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Managed Portfolios_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Harish Gupta, aged 50, is a business owner with a net worth of Rs. 8 crore. He has Rs. 1 crore available for equity investment and is evaluating two options:

Option A — Equity Mutual Fund (Direct Plan, Growth): Large & Mid-Cap Fund with expense ratio 0.75%, SEBI-mandated diversification (minimum 35% large-cap, 35% mid-cap), no minimum investment, exit load 1% if redeemed within 1 year, daily NAV disclosure, SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations apply.

Option B — Discretionary Equity PMS: Minimum investment Rs. 50 lakh, fixed management fee 1.5% p.a., performance fee 20% of profits above 10% hurdle rate (no catch-up, high watermark applies), portfolio of 15-25 stocks customized to Harish's risk profile, Rs. 5 crore net worth of PMS provider, quarterly portfolio disclosure.

Additional information: Harish is in the 30% income tax bracket. He expects a 5-year investment horizon. He wants concentrated, high-conviction stock picking rather than broad diversification. He has a separate emergency fund and does not need liquidity from this investment.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Given Harish's profile (Rs. 1 crore, 5-year horizon, wants concentrated stock picking, has emergency fund separately), which option would an investment adviser most appropriately recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Mutual Fund — PMS is too expensive for any investor]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only PMS — all HNIs should use PMS instead of mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[PMS is more suitable given his preference for concentration and customization, ability to bear higher fees, and HNI status — but the higher cost must be justified by demonstrably better after-fee performance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Neither — he should invest directly in stocks without intermediary]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Harish meets PMS minimum (Rs. 50L), prefers concentrated high-conviction stock picking (MF can't deliver this due to diversification mandates), has a 5-year horizon, and doesn't need liquidity. PMS suits his needs better. However, the adviser must ensure the PMS can deliver alpha after its higher fees (3%+ vs 0.75%).
**The Trap:** PMS isn't automatically better for all HNIs — the recommendation depends on the client's specific needs. An HNI wanting broad diversification may be better served by mutual funds.
**Cross-Exam Context:** MF vs PMS suitability analysis is a key advisory skill tested in X-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The acid test for PMS recommendation: can the PMS generate at least 2-3% excess return over comparable MFs to justify its higher fees? If not, the mutual fund is the better choice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>