<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Managed Portfolios_C1_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Ms. Prerna Desai, aged 28, is a software engineer earning Rs. 15 lakh per annum. She has the following financial goals:
1. Emergency fund: 6 months' expenses (monthly expenses Rs. 40,000) — needed immediately
2. Down payment for a house: Rs. 15 lakh in 3 years
3. Child's education fund: Rs. 50 lakh in 20 years
4. Retirement corpus: Rs. 5 crore in 32 years (retire at 60)

She can save Rs. 50,000 per month. She is filing under the old tax regime and has not utilized her Section 80C limit. Her investment adviser, Mr. Kartik, suggests the following allocation:
- Emergency fund: Rs. 2.4 lakh lump sum in a Liquid Fund (current yield ~6.5% p.a.)
- House down payment: Rs. 30,000/month SIP in a Short Duration Debt Fund (expected return 7.5% p.a.)
- Education fund: Rs. 10,000/month SIP in a Flexi-Cap Equity Fund (expected return 12% p.a., expense ratio 0.8% Direct Plan)
- Retirement: Rs. 10,000/month SIP split between ELSS Fund (Rs. 5,000 for Section 80C) and Nifty 50 Index Fund (Rs. 5,000, expense ratio 0.15%)

Total monthly SIP: Rs. 50,000. Prerna opts for Direct Plans and Growth option for all equity funds.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Why has Mr. Kartik recommended a Short Duration Debt Fund (Macaulay duration 1-3 years) for the house down payment goal rather than an equity fund?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because debt funds always give higher returns than equity funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Because the 3-year horizon is too short for equity exposure; a short duration debt fund matches the goal horizon and minimizes interest rate risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because debt funds have zero risk of any kind]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Because SEBI mandates debt funds for goals under 5 years]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** For a 3-year goal, equity exposure carries significant risk of capital loss due to market volatility. A Short Duration Debt Fund (Macaulay duration 1-3 years) matches the investment horizon, minimizes interest rate risk, and provides relatively stable returns with lower volatility than equity.
**The Trap:** Debt funds are not risk-free — they carry credit risk and interest rate risk. But for a 3-year horizon, they're more appropriate than equity.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Goal-based fund selection based on time horizon is a core advisory skill tested in X-A and V-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The golden rule: match fund duration to goal duration. Short goals = debt funds. Long goals = equity funds. This simple principle protects clients from inappropriate asset allocation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>