<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Managed Portfolios_C3_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Vikram Choudhary, aged 45, is an ultra-HNI with a total investment portfolio of Rs. 25 crore. His current allocation is: Equity Mutual Funds Rs. 8 crore, Fixed Deposits Rs. 5 crore, Direct Equity Rs. 5 crore, Real Estate Rs. 4 crore, Gold Rs. 1.5 crore, and Cash Rs. 1.5 crore. His annual income is Rs. 3 crore. His investment adviser, Ms. Neha Sharma, suggests allocating Rs. 3 crore (12% of portfolio) to Alternative Investment Funds for diversification. She proposes:

Option 1 — Category I AIF (Venture Capital Fund): Invests in early-stage tech startups. Minimum Rs. 1 crore. Close-ended with 7-year lock-in. Target return 20-25% IRR. Manager continuing interest 2.5% of corpus. Fund corpus Rs. 200 crore with maximum 250 investors.

Option 2 — Category II AIF (Private Equity Fund): Invests in mid-market growth companies. Minimum Rs. 1 crore. Close-ended with 5-year lock-in plus 2-year extension option. Target return 15-18% IRR. No leverage permitted except for day-to-day operations. Management fee 2% + carried interest 20% above 8% hurdle.

Option 3 — Category III AIF (Long-Short Equity Hedge Fund): Employs long-short equity strategies using derivatives. Minimum Rs. 1 crore. Open-ended with 1-year lock-in. Target return 12-15% with low correlation to equity markets. Manager continuing interest 5% of corpus. Can employ leverage through derivatives.

Vikram qualifies as an accredited investor (annual income ≥ Rs. 2 crore).

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> As an accredited investor, Vikram can potentially invest in some AIFs with a reduced minimum ticket size of Rs. 25 lakh instead of Rs. 1 crore. Which statement about this facility is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All AIFs must offer reduced minimums to accredited investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Accredited investor facility is optional — not all AIFs adopt it, and reduced ticket size does not reduce investment risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Accredited investors get guaranteed returns from AIFs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI mandates all AIFs to accept accredited investors at Rs. 25 lakh minimum]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The accredited investor concept is optional — it is not compulsory for AIFs to adopt it. Only a few AIFs have chosen to offer reduced minimums of Rs. 25 lakh to accredited investors. The reduced ticket size does NOT reduce the inherent investment risk of the AIF strategy.
**The Trap:** Reduced minimum doesn't mean reduced risk — an investor putting Rs. 25 lakh in a hedge fund faces the same strategy risk as one putting Rs. 1 crore.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Accredited investor provisions are tested in X-A for understanding AIF access frameworks.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Even at Rs. 25 lakh, AIF investments remain high-risk — the accredited investor framework is about demonstrating financial sophistication, not about making AIFs safer. Only use this for clients who truly understand and can absorb AIF-level risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>