<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Managed Portfolios_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Harish Gupta, aged 50, is a business owner with a net worth of Rs. 8 crore. He has Rs. 1 crore available for equity investment and is evaluating two options:

Option A — Equity Mutual Fund (Direct Plan, Growth): Large & Mid-Cap Fund with expense ratio 0.75%, SEBI-mandated diversification (minimum 35% large-cap, 35% mid-cap), no minimum investment, exit load 1% if redeemed within 1 year, daily NAV disclosure, SEBI Mutual Fund Regulations apply.

Option B — Discretionary Equity PMS: Minimum investment Rs. 50 lakh, fixed management fee 1.5% p.a., performance fee 20% of profits above 10% hurdle rate (no catch-up, high watermark applies), portfolio of 15-25 stocks customized to Harish's risk profile, Rs. 5 crore net worth of PMS provider, quarterly portfolio disclosure.

Additional information: Harish is in the 30% income tax bracket. He expects a 5-year investment horizon. He wants concentrated, high-conviction stock picking rather than broad diversification. He has a separate emergency fund and does not need liquidity from this investment.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> What is a key structural advantage of PMS over a mutual fund for Harish's stated preference of concentrated, high-conviction stock picking?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMS offers tax-free returns unlike mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[PMS can hold a concentrated portfolio of 15-25 stocks customized to client's risk profile without SEBI's mutual fund diversification mandates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMS guarantees higher returns than mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[PMS has no regulatory oversight while MFs are regulated]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** PMS can customize the portfolio to Harish's specific risk profile with concentrated stock selection (15-25 stocks), unlike mutual funds that must follow SEBI categorization rules (e.g., 35% large-cap, 35% mid-cap for a Large & Mid-Cap fund). PMS is individually managed, not pooled.
**The Trap:** PMS is regulated by SEBI (Portfolio Managers Regulations 2020) — it's not unregulated, just lighter-touch than MFs.
**Cross-Exam Context:** PMS vs MF structural differences are tested in X-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** PMS customization is its biggest selling point — it can build a portfolio aligned with a specific client's tax situation, existing holdings, and investment philosophy. MFs are one-size-fits-all.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>