<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about NRI bank accounts is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NRE accounts hold rupee-denominated deposits from Indian income sources and are non-repatriable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[FCNR accounts hold rupee-denominated deposits and are repatriable up to USD 1 million per year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NRE accounts hold funds from foreign currency sources (fully repatriable), while NRO accounts hold funds from rupee/Indian income sources (repatriable up to USD 1 million per year)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NRO accounts are fully repatriable as they hold foreign currency-denominated deposits]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** NRE (Non-Resident External) accounts hold funds sourced from foreign currency earnings and are fully repatriable — both principal and interest can be freely remitted abroad. NRO (Non-Resident Ordinary) accounts hold funds from Indian/rupee income sources (like rent, dividends, pension) and are non-repatriable, except that up to USD 1 million per financial year can be repatriated after taxes. FCNR (Foreign Currency Non-Resident) accounts hold foreign currency-denominated fixed deposits (not rupee-denominated).

**The Trap:** NRE accounts are for foreign currency sources, not Indian income. FCNR accounts are foreign currency denominated, not rupee denominated. NRO accounts have limited repatriability (USD 1 million/year), not full repatriability.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NRI banking account types and their repatriation characteristics are tested in NISM Series X-A and V-A. This is one of the most frequently confused topics.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Use a simple mental model: NRE = money coming IN to India from abroad (fully repatriable). NRO = money earned IN India by an NRI (limited repatriability). FCNR = foreign currency deposits (fully repatriable, no currency risk).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
