<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_30" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the Power of Attorney in the context of Indian securities market operations is INCORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The grantor retains the right to operate the account even after granting a PoA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A PoA can be validly granted by a minor through their natural guardian for investment purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A PoA executed within India must be on non-judicial stamp paper and signed on all pages]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The PoA holder cannot open or close a bank account or demat account on behalf of the grantor]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A Power of Attorney CANNOT be granted by or for a minor. Minors lack the legal capacity to execute a PoA. Their investments are managed through the guardian relationship (natural guardian or court-appointed guardian), not through a PoA mechanism. This is the INCORRECT statement, making it the correct answer.

**The Trap:** The other three statements are all correct: (1) the grantor retains the right to operate the account even after giving PoA, (2) domestic PoA must be on non-judicial stamp paper and signed on all pages, and (3) the PoA holder cannot open/close bank or demat accounts. Many candidates incorrectly assume that a guardian can grant a PoA on a minor's behalf.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PoA restrictions, especially regarding minors, are tested in NISM Series X-A and V-A. The distinction between guardian authority and PoA authority is a nuanced but important concept.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When dealing with minor accounts, always work through the guardian framework — never accept a PoA claimed to be on behalf of a minor. The guardian's authority comes from the Guardians and Wards Act, not from a PoA.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
