<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_26" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A 15-year-old minor wishes to invest in a mutual fund scheme. Which of the following statements about the investment process is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A minor can independently open a mutual fund folio and invest without any guardian involvement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A minor's investment must be routed through a Power of Attorney holder since minors cannot have guardians for financial purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A minor can invest in mutual funds only through a guardian, and the folio must be in the name of the minor with the guardian signing on behalf]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minors are not permitted to invest in mutual funds under any circumstances until they turn 18]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Minors are eligible to invest in Indian mutual funds, but only through a guardian. The folio is opened in the minor's name, with the guardian (natural guardian or court-appointed guardian) signing all documents and managing the investment on the minor's behalf. Upon attaining majority, the minor must submit a status change request.

**The Trap:** Minors CAN invest in mutual funds — they are not prohibited. However, they cannot invest independently; a guardian is mandatory. A PoA is not the correct mechanism for minors — it is a guardian relationship. Also, no PoA can be granted by or for a minor.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Minor investment rules are tested in NISM Series V-A and X-A. The transition from minor to major status and its operational implications are important concepts.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When onboarding a minor's investment, ensure the guardian's KYC is complete along with the minor's birth certificate. Set a reminder for the minor's 18th birthday — the folio status must be changed, and the now-adult investor must complete their own KYC.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
