<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C1_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Mehta, a CFA charterholder with 7 years of experience in wealth management at a private bank, wants to set up his own investment advisory firm. He plans to register as an individual Investment Adviser with SEBI under the SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013. He has a net worth of Rs. 8 lakh. His wife Neha is an AMFI-registered mutual fund distributor who currently serves 50 clients. Vikram expects to start with 100 clients, charging an annual fee of Rs. 25,000 per client. One of his prospective clients, Mr. Rao, has assets worth Rs. 2 crore and wants both advisory and distribution services from the same family. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an individual Investment Adviser must have a minimum net worth of Rs. 5 lakh, can serve a maximum of 300 clients, and must convert to a non-individual IA if clients exceed 300 or advisory fees exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year. A part-time Investment Adviser is limited to 75 clients. Accepted qualifications include CFA Charter, post-graduate diploma in finance, or a professional qualification such as CA/CS/CWA with relevant experience. The IA must hold a valid NISM Investment Adviser certification. Records of investment advice, rationale, and client interactions must be maintained for a minimum of 5 years. An annual compliance audit by a CA is mandatory. Importantly, a family member of an individual IA cannot provide distribution services to the same client to whom the IA provides advisory services, ensuring segregation of advisory and distribution activities.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Under what circumstances would Vikram be required to convert his individual IA registration to a non-individual IA registration?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[When his clients exceed 150 or his annual fees exceed Rs. 1 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[When his clients exceed 500 or his annual fees exceed Rs. 5 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[When his clients exceed 300 or his advisory fees exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[When his clients exceed 300 and his advisory fees simultaneously exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, an individual IA must convert to a non-individual IA registration when either of two triggers is met: (i) the number of clients exceeds 300, OR (ii) advisory fees exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year. Currently, Vikram has 100 clients at Rs. 25,000 each, generating Rs. 25 lakh annually — well within both limits. However, as his practice grows, he must monitor both thresholds.

**The Trap:** Option D uses "and" instead of "or," implying both conditions must be met simultaneously. This is incorrect — either condition alone triggers the conversion requirement. Options A and B use incorrect numerical thresholds. The distinction between "or" and "and" is a classic exam trap.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The conversion triggers are critical because a non-individual IA has a significantly higher net worth requirement of Rs. 50 lakh (compared to Rs. 5 lakh for individual IAs), requiring substantial capital planning. The IA must also then comply with additional corporate governance requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Track your client count and fee revenue quarterly. When approaching either threshold (e.g., 250 clients or Rs. 2.5 crore in fees), begin planning for the non-individual IA conversion — including arranging the higher net worth and necessary organizational structure.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
