<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_41" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A fund manager of a SEBI-registered Alternative Investment Fund (AIF) provides investment advice to the fund's investors as part of portfolio management. Under SEBI IA Regulations, does the fund manager need separate SEBI IA registration?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, investment advice to any investor requires separate IA registration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only if the AIF manages more than Rs. 500 crore in assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, but only if the fund manager holds NISM Series X-A certification]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, fund managers of Mutual Funds and AIFs are exempt from separate IA registration]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations 2013, fund managers of Mutual Funds and AIFs are explicitly exempt from the requirement of separate SEBI IA registration. Their advisory function is integral to their role as fund managers and is already regulated under their respective SEBI regulations.

**The Trap:** Candidates may not recall the full list of exemptions. The exemption is categorical — it applies to all MF and AIF fund managers regardless of AUM size or certification status.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This exemption is important for NISM Series X-A and also relevant for Series XIX-A (AIF) and Series V-A (MF) candidates who may want to understand the regulatory boundaries.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The exemption covers advice given in the capacity of fund manager. If the same person provides independent advisory services outside the fund management role, a separate IA registration would be required.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
