<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_53" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Suresh is a SEBI-registered individual investment adviser. His wife, Meena, is an AMFI-registered mutual fund distributor. Under SEBI IA Regulations on client segregation, which of the following is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no restriction — Suresh can advise and Meena can distribute to the same client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Meena cannot distribute mutual fund products to the same clients whom Suresh advises]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Meena can distribute to Suresh's clients as long as she discloses the relationship]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The restriction applies only if they share the same office premises]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations, an individual IA cannot engage in distribution. Furthermore, family members of the individual IA cannot distribute products to the same clients whom the IA advises. This ensures complete separation of advisory and distribution functions, preventing conflicts of interest where advisory recommendations could be influenced by distribution commissions.

**The Trap:** Disclosure of the relationship is NOT sufficient to cure the conflict. The regulation mandates actual client-level segregation, not mere disclosure. The restriction applies regardless of office arrangements.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Client segregation between advisory and distribution is a hallmark of SEBI IA Regulations and is heavily tested in Series X-A. The mutual fund distribution model (Series V-A) operates on commission — the IA model is fee-only.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If your spouse or family member is a distributor, maintain completely separate client lists. No overlap is permitted. Consider having a written family arrangement documenting client segregation for audit purposes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
