<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An NRI based in the USA wishes to trade in the Indian equity market. Which of the following statements about the PINS (Portfolio Investment NRI Scheme) account is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[An NRI can maintain multiple PINS accounts with different brokers simultaneously]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A PINS account can be linked to either an NRE or NRO account as per the NRI's preference]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[An NRI can maintain only one PINS account at a time, and it must be linked to an NRE account]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A PINS account is optional for NRIs who only wish to invest in mutual funds and not in direct equities]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the PINS scheme, an NRI can hold only ONE PINS account at any given time. This account must be linked to an NRE (Non-Resident External) account. The single-account restriction ensures proper monitoring of NRI investment limits.

**The Trap:** The PINS account is specifically linked to the NRE account (not NRO), as it deals with repatriable portfolio investments. While an NRI can have both NRE and NRO accounts, PINS is linked only to NRE. Multiple PINS accounts are not permitted.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NRI investment framework including PINS account requirements is tested in NISM Series X-A and Series VIII (Equity Derivatives).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before an NRI client starts equity trading, ensure they have the PINS account set up and linked to their NRE account. If they are moving from one broker to another, the old PINS account must be closed before opening a new one.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
