<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_54" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under SEBI IA Regulations, when an investment adviser implements investment recommendations on behalf of a client, through which route must the implementation be done?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Through regular plans of mutual funds to earn trail commission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Only through direct schemes/plans, with no implementation fees or embedded commissions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Through either direct or regular plans, at the client's discretion]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Through a third-party distributor selected by the IA]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations 2013, implementation of investment advice must be done only through direct schemes/plans. The IA cannot charge any implementation fees and cannot receive embedded commissions. This ensures the IA's income comes solely from the advisory fee, eliminating the conflict of interest inherent in commission-based distribution.

**The Trap:** "Client's discretion" sounds reasonable but is incorrect — the regulation mandates direct schemes only. Similarly, using a regular plan to earn trail commission directly contradicts the fee-only model.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The direct-vs-regular plan distinction is central to both NISM Series X-A (IA) and Series V-A (MF Distributors). Distributors use regular plans (commission model); IAs must use direct plans (fee-only model).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The fee-only model is non-negotiable. If you're tempted to earn commissions through regular plans, remember: one complaint to SEBI and you risk losing your IA registration entirely.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
