<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_42" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Amit is a US-based financial adviser who exclusively advises clients residing in the United States on Indian securities. Separately, he also advises some NRI clients residing in the US on Indian mutual fund investments. Under SEBI IA Regulations, which statement is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He is fully exempt from SEBI IA registration for all his clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He is exempt for advising clients exclusively outside India, but NRI/PIO advisory requires SEBI IA registration]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He needs SEBI IA registration for all clients since the advice relates to Indian securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He is exempt only if his total NRI clients are fewer than 75]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations, persons advising clients exclusively outside India are exempt from SEBI IA registration. However, this exemption specifically carves out NRI/PIO clients — advice to NRIs/PIOs on Indian securities IS covered under the regulations and requires SEBI registration, regardless of where the NRI physically resides.

**The Trap:** The instinct is to treat all overseas clients the same. But SEBI distinguishes between foreign nationals (exempt) and NRIs/PIOs (not exempt). The NRI carve-out is a critical distinction.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The NRI/PIO coverage under IA regulations connects to FEMA provisions tested in NISM Series X-A and investment limits tested in Series V-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you have even one NRI/PIO client to whom you provide investment advice on Indian securities, the "exclusively outside India" exemption breaks down. Register with SEBI or stop advising NRI/PIO clients.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
