<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C1_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Mehta, a CFA charterholder with 7 years of experience in wealth management at a private bank, wants to set up his own investment advisory firm. He plans to register as an individual Investment Adviser with SEBI under the SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013. He has a net worth of Rs. 8 lakh. His wife Neha is an AMFI-registered mutual fund distributor who currently serves 50 clients. Vikram expects to start with 100 clients, charging an annual fee of Rs. 25,000 per client. One of his prospective clients, Mr. Rao, has assets worth Rs. 2 crore and wants both advisory and distribution services from the same family. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an individual Investment Adviser must have a minimum net worth of Rs. 5 lakh, can serve a maximum of 300 clients, and must convert to a non-individual IA if clients exceed 300 or advisory fees exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year. A part-time Investment Adviser is limited to 75 clients. Accepted qualifications include CFA Charter, post-graduate diploma in finance, or a professional qualification such as CA/CS/CWA with relevant experience. The IA must hold a valid NISM Investment Adviser certification. Records of investment advice, rationale, and client interactions must be maintained for a minimum of 5 years. An annual compliance audit by a CA is mandatory. Importantly, a family member of an individual IA cannot provide distribution services to the same client to whom the IA provides advisory services, ensuring segregation of advisory and distribution activities.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> For how long must Vikram maintain records of the investment advice provided to his clients, including the rationale for such advice?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 3 years from the date of advice]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 7 years from the date of advice]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 10 years from the date of advice]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 5 years from the date of advice]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, an Investment Adviser must maintain records of investment advice, the rationale behind such advice, and all client interactions for a minimum period of 5 years. This includes risk profiling documents, suitability assessments, client agreements, fee receipts, and all written and electronic communications with clients.

**The Trap:** Option A (3 years) is the general limitation period under many Indian statutes, which candidates may confuse with the IA record-keeping requirement. Option B (7 years) is the record-keeping period under some tax and banking regulations, creating a plausible distractor. Option C (10 years) is an exaggeration.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 5-year record-keeping requirement aligns with the need for regulatory audit trails. SEBI can inspect these records during routine inspections or in response to client complaints. The annual compliance audit by a Chartered Accountant also relies on the availability of these records.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Implement a robust digital record management system from day one. Store all client communications (emails, messages, call recordings where permitted), risk profiling documents, investment rationale notes, and portfolio review reports systematically. Cloud-based solutions with automated backup ensure compliance even if physical records are damaged.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
