<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C1_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Mehta, a CFA charterholder with 7 years of experience in wealth management at a private bank, wants to set up his own investment advisory firm. He plans to register as an individual Investment Adviser with SEBI under the SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013. He has a net worth of Rs. 8 lakh. His wife Neha is an AMFI-registered mutual fund distributor who currently serves 50 clients. Vikram expects to start with 100 clients, charging an annual fee of Rs. 25,000 per client. One of his prospective clients, Mr. Rao, has assets worth Rs. 2 crore and wants both advisory and distribution services from the same family. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an individual Investment Adviser must have a minimum net worth of Rs. 5 lakh, can serve a maximum of 300 clients, and must convert to a non-individual IA if clients exceed 300 or advisory fees exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year. A part-time Investment Adviser is limited to 75 clients. Accepted qualifications include CFA Charter, post-graduate diploma in finance, or a professional qualification such as CA/CS/CWA with relevant experience. The IA must hold a valid NISM Investment Adviser certification. Records of investment advice, rationale, and client interactions must be maintained for a minimum of 5 years. An annual compliance audit by a CA is mandatory. Importantly, a family member of an individual IA cannot provide distribution services to the same client to whom the IA provides advisory services, ensuring segregation of advisory and distribution activities.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Does Vikram meet the qualification requirement to register as an individual Investment Adviser under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because a CFA Charter is an accepted qualification under SEBI IA Regulations 2013]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because only CA, CS, or CWA holders can register as Investment Advisers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because he needs a minimum of 10 years of experience in wealth management]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only if he additionally passes the AMFI registration exam]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, the qualification requirements for an individual IA include professional qualifications such as CFA Charter, post-graduate diploma in finance, or CA/CS/CWA with relevant experience. Vikram's CFA Charter with 7 years of wealth management experience satisfies this requirement. He will additionally need to hold a valid NISM Investment Adviser (Series X-A) certification.

**The Trap:** Option B tries to restrict the qualification to only CA/CS/CWA, ignoring the CFA Charter which is equally accepted. Option C inflates the experience requirement. Option D confuses AMFI registration (for distributors) with IA qualification.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NISM X-A candidates must understand that the qualification framework is broad and includes globally recognized certifications like CFA. The NISM certification itself is a separate requirement on top of the educational qualification.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Professionals transitioning from banking/wealth management should verify which of their existing qualifications are accepted under SEBI IA Regulations before applying. CFA, CFP, and post-graduate finance qualifications all meet the eligibility criteria.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
