<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_74" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A "pure ethical dilemma" in the context of investment advisory is best described as a situation where:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser must choose between a profitable and an unprofitable course of action]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both available alternatives violate some ethical principle, making neither choice clearly acceptable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser faces a choice between following SEBI regulations and following AMFI guidelines]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser must decide whether to disclose confidential client information to tax authorities]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A pure ethical dilemma is a situation requiring a choice between two alternatives where neither is clearly superior because both options violate some ethical principle. It is not simply a difficult decision — it is one where every available option involves an ethical compromise. Resolution requires deeper analysis, considering the highest good for all, the approach causing least damage, or reconsidering the problem from a different perspective.
**The Trap:** A choice between profitable and unprofitable actions is a business decision, not an ethical dilemma. The option about SEBI vs. AMFI describes a regulatory conflict, not an ethical dilemma in its pure form.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Understanding ethical dilemmas is tested in NISM Series X-A and X-B exams, and is also relevant for Series V-A.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When facing an ethical dilemma, document your reasoning process. Consider what causes the least harm, serves the greatest number of stakeholders, and is consistent with your fiduciary duty.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
