<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_56" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A SEBI-registered investment adviser commits a regulatory violation. Under Section 15EB of the SEBI Act, what is the penalty structure applicable?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum Rs. 50,000, up to Rs. 50,000 per day, maximum Rs. 50 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum Rs. 5 lakh, up to Rs. 5 lakh per day, maximum Rs. 5 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Minimum Rs. 1 lakh, up to Rs. 1 lakh per day, maximum Rs. 1 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum Rs. 10 lakh, up to Rs. 10 lakh per day, maximum Rs. 10 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under Section 15EB of the SEBI Act, the penalty for investment adviser violations has a three-tier structure: minimum penalty of Rs. 1 lakh, up to Rs. 1 lakh per day of continuing violation, with a maximum cap of Rs. 1 crore. This calculation structure is: Rs. 1 lakh (minimum) + Rs. 1 lakh/day (continuing penalty) capped at Rs. 1 crore (maximum).

**The Trap:** The symmetry of the numbers (1 lakh / 1 lakh per day / 1 crore) makes this easier to remember, but candidates often confuse it with penalty structures for other SEBI violations which may have different amounts. The 1-1-1 pattern (lakh-lakh/day-crore) is distinctive to Section 15EB.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Penalty provisions are tested in NISM Series X-A and have practical implications for compliance. Compare with penalties under PFUTP or Insider Trading regulations which have different penalty structures.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A continuing violation can accumulate quickly — Rs. 1 lakh per day means a 30-day unresolved violation could result in a Rs. 30 lakh penalty. Fix compliance issues immediately upon detection.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
