<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A Power of Attorney (PoA) is executed by an Indian investor residing in London, UK. Which of the following requirements must be satisfied for the PoA to be valid?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It must be executed on non-judicial stamp paper of the country where the grantor resides]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It must be notarized by a local notary in the UK and apostilled under the Hague Convention]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It can be executed on plain paper but must be attested by the Indian embassy or consulate in the UK]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It must be executed on Indian non-judicial stamp paper, which must be procured from India before execution]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** When a PoA is executed abroad, it can be done on plain paper (since Indian stamp paper is not available overseas), but it MUST be attested by the Indian embassy or consulate in the country where it is executed. This attestation serves as authentication of the document.

**The Trap:** When executed within India, a PoA must be on non-judicial stamp paper. But when executed abroad, the stamp paper requirement is relaxed, and plain paper with Indian embassy attestation is acceptable. Apostille under the Hague Convention is not the specified requirement — Indian embassy attestation is the standard.

**Cross-Exam Context:** PoA execution requirements, especially the distinction between domestic and overseas execution, are tested in NISM Series X-A and V-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For NRI clients executing PoA from abroad, guide them to the nearest Indian embassy or consulate. Ensure the PoA is signed on all pages by the grantor before attestation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
