<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about the Basic Savings Bank Deposit Account (BSBDA) is CORRECT in the context of KYC and PAN requirements?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[BSBDA does not require PAN for opening, as it is designed for financial inclusion of underserved populations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[BSBDA requires PAN but exempts the account holder from the full KYC process]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[BSBDA requires both PAN and full KYC but allows a 6-month grace period for document submission]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[BSBDA is exempt from both PAN and KYC requirements since it is regulated by RBI and not SEBI]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Basic Savings Bank Deposit Accounts (BSBDAs) are designed for financial inclusion and do not require PAN for opening. These accounts have simplified KYC norms (small accounts under RBI guidelines) to ensure that basic banking services are accessible to all sections of society, including those without formal documentation.

**The Trap:** While PAN is not required, BSBDA is NOT entirely exempt from KYC — simplified/reduced KYC (such as a self-attested photograph and address declaration) is still required. The account has operational limits on balance and transactions. It is not about being regulated by RBI vs. SEBI — PAN exemption for BSBDA is specifically designed for financial inclusion.

**Cross-Exam Context:** BSBDA and its PAN/KYC relaxations are tested in NISM Series X-A and are referenced in RBI's financial inclusion guidelines. Understanding this exception helps differentiate it from capital market PAN requirements.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** BSBDA is a useful entry point for clients who are new to the formal financial system. Once they are comfortable, guide them to obtain PAN and complete full KYC for accessing a wider range of investment products.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
