<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_18" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following investor categories is eligible to invest in Indian mutual fund schemes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only resident individuals and NRIs; companies and trusts are not permitted]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only entities with a minimum net worth of Rs. 10 crore, as per SEBI's Accredited Investor norms]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A wide range including resident individuals, HUFs, minors through guardians, NRIs, PIOs, FPIs, companies, trusts, partnership firms, insurance companies, pension funds, and other mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only resident individuals and domestic institutional investors; foreign entities like FPIs are restricted to direct equity investments]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Indian mutual fund schemes are open to a wide variety of investor categories including resident individuals, HUFs, minors (through guardians), NRIs, PIOs, FPIs (Foreign Portfolio Investors), companies, trusts, partnership firms, insurance companies, pension funds, and even other mutual funds. This broad eligibility makes mutual funds one of the most accessible investment vehicles.

**The Trap:** There is no minimum net worth requirement for general mutual fund investment — Accredited Investor status is a separate concept with specific criteria. FPIs are NOT restricted to direct equities; they can invest in mutual funds too. Companies and trusts are eligible investors.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Investor eligibility categories are tested in NISM Series V-A and X-A. Understanding the breadth of eligible investors helps distributors identify potential clients.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Each investor category may have specific documentation requirements and regulatory restrictions. Always check the scheme's offer document for any category-specific restrictions before accepting an application.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
