<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C2_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunita Iyer is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser based in Mumbai with 200 clients. She has been advising her client Mr. Patel, a 58-year-old conservative investor with a documented low-risk profile, for the past 3 years. Recently, Sunita recommended that Mr. Patel invest Rs. 20 lakh in a mid-cap equity fund managed by Zenith AMC, citing potential high returns of 18-20% over 2 years. However, she did not disclose that her brother-in-law, Mr. Ashok Iyer, is a director of Zenith AMC. Mr. Patel invested the full Rs. 20 lakh based on Sunita's recommendation. Within 6 months, the fund lost 25% in value, reducing his investment to Rs. 15 lakh. Mr. Patel subsequently discovered through a newspaper article that Sunita's brother-in-law is a director at Zenith AMC and that she had not disclosed this conflict of interest. Additionally, Sunita has been using an AI-based algorithmic tool to generate investment recommendations for some of her clients, including Mr. Patel, without disclosing the use of such automated tools in her advisory process. Under SEBI IA Regulations, advisers must disclose the extent of use of AI or algorithmic tools to clients. Furthermore, Sunita traded in the same Zenith mid-cap fund on her personal demat account just 5 days after recommending it to Mr. Patel, purchasing units at a lower NAV. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an Investment Adviser is prohibited from trading on their own account in securities contrary to or ahead of advice given to clients for a period of 15 days. Mr. Patel now wants to file a formal complaint against Sunita. SEBI provides the SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redress System) portal for investors to lodge complaints against registered intermediaries.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Which ethical obligation did Sunita primarily violate by not disclosing her brother-in-law's association with Zenith AMC to Mr. Patel?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Fiduciary duty of full disclosure — she was obligated to disclose all conflicts of interest, including her brother-in-law's directorship at Zenith AMC]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Duty of confidentiality — she should have kept her family relationships confidential from clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Duty of best execution — she failed to execute the trade at the best available price for Mr. Patel]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No violation occurred, as the brother-in-law relationship is too distant to constitute a conflict of interest]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, an Investment Adviser owes a fiduciary duty to clients, which includes the obligation to disclose all material conflicts of interest. Sunita's brother-in-law being a director at Zenith AMC — the very fund house whose product she recommended — is a direct conflict of interest. She was obligated to disclose this relationship to Mr. Patel before making the recommendation, allowing him to make an informed decision.

**The Trap:** Option B reverses the obligation — confidentiality applies to client information, not to the adviser's conflicts. Option C refers to best execution, which relates to trade execution quality, not disclosure of relationships. Option D tries to minimize the brother-in-law relationship, but under SEBI regulations, the definition of "related party" and "associate" broadly covers such relationships.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The fiduciary duty concept is central to the IA regulatory framework. It encompasses duties of loyalty, care, full disclosure, and acting in the client's best interest. Conflict of interest disclosure is non-negotiable regardless of whether the conflict actually influenced the recommendation.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain an updated register of all relationships with AMCs, brokers, and other market participants. Disclose any relationship proactively in the client agreement and before each recommendation that involves an entity with which you have a connection. Document the disclosure with client acknowledgment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
