<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An NRI individual holds 4.8% of the paid-up equity capital of a listed Indian company. The aggregate NRI holding in this company is at 9.5%, and the company's general body has NOT passed any resolution to increase the NRI ceiling. Which of the following actions can this NRI legally take?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Purchase additional shares up to 0.5% of paid-up capital to reach the 5.3% individual limit]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Purchase additional shares up to 0.2% of paid-up capital, as the individual limit is 5% and overall limit is 10%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Purchase additional shares without restriction since the aggregate ceiling of 24% has not been breached]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Cannot purchase any further shares since the aggregate holding of 9.5% exceeds the 5% overall ceiling]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the default NRI investment framework, individual NRI purchase is limited to 5% of the paid-up capital, and the overall NRI ceiling is 10%. Since the NRI already holds 4.8%, they can buy up to 0.2% more (to reach 5%). The aggregate would then be 9.7%, still within the 10% default ceiling.

**The Trap:** The 24% figure is the enhanced ceiling that requires a special resolution by the company's general body — it is NOT the default limit. The default aggregate limit is 10%, not 24%. Also, 5% is the individual NRI limit, not 5.3%.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NRI investment limits are tested across NISM Series V-A (Mutual Fund Distributors), NISM Series X-A, and NISM Series VIII (Equity Derivatives).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always verify two ceilings before advising an NRI client — the individual 5% cap AND the aggregate 10% (or 24% if enhanced by resolution). Both must be satisfied simultaneously.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
