<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_64" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Money laundering under PMLA 2002 is defined as the process of disguising the proceeds of crime as legitimate income. Which of the following is NOT an element of the offense of money laundering under the Act?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Directly or indirectly attempting to indulge in concealment of proceeds of crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Possession or acquisition of proceeds of crime]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Failing to file income tax returns on proceeds of crime within the due date]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Projecting or claiming proceeds of crime as untainted property]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under PMLA 2002, the offense of money laundering includes directly or indirectly attempting to indulge in, or knowingly assisting in, the concealment, possession, acquisition, use, or projecting as untainted property any proceeds of crime. Failure to file income tax returns is a separate offense under the Income Tax Act, not an element of money laundering under PMLA.
**The Trap:** Since money laundering involves illegal proceeds and taxation, candidates may assume non-filing of tax returns on such proceeds is also covered under PMLA. However, PMLA specifically addresses concealment, possession, acquisition, use, and projection of crime proceeds as legitimate.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The definition of money laundering is a frequently tested concept across NISM Series V-A, X-A, and X-B exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Understand the four pillars of money laundering offense — concealment, possession/acquisition, use, and projection as untainted. This helps identify suspicious activities in practice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
