<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_73" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The "Client First" principle in investment advisory ethics emphasizes that:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser should prioritize the interests of the AMC whose products generate the highest revenue]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser should first ensure regulatory compliance and then consider client interests]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The adviser should recommend the most popular products in the market to minimize risk to the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The interest of the client should be placed above everything else, as trust is central to the advisory relationship]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The "Client First" principle mandates that the interest of the client must be placed above everything else — above the adviser's own interest, the interest of the employer, or any product manufacturer. Trust is central to this relationship, and as the principle states, it takes years to build trust but only moments to lose it.
**The Trap:** Regulatory compliance is important but does not take precedence over client interests — they should be aligned. Recommending popular products ignores the client's unique needs and risk profile, which violates the suitability principle.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The Client First principle is a cornerstone concept tested in NISM Series X-A, X-B, and Series V-A exams.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before making any recommendation, ask yourself: "Am I recommending this because it is best for my client, or because it is best for me?" If the answer is the latter, reconsider your recommendation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
