<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[In the rematerialisation process, when an investor converts dematerialised securities back to physical form, which of the following statements is CORRECT?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The original certificate numbers from the time of dematerialisation are restored on the new physical certificates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[New certificate numbers are assigned by the R&T agent, as the original certificates were mutilated during dematerialisation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The depository directly issues the physical certificates without involving the R&T agent]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rematerialisation is no longer permitted after physical transfer of securities was discontinued from April 2019]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** During rematerialisation, the investor submits a Remat Request Form (RRF) to the DP, who validates it and forwards it to the depository. The depository then forwards the request to the R&T agent, who issues NEW physical certificates with NEW certificate numbers. The original certificates were mutilated during dematerialisation and cannot be reused.

**The Trap:** The discontinuation of physical transfer from April 2019 means securities cannot be transferred in physical form — but rematerialisation itself (converting demat to physical) is still permitted. Also, original certificate numbers cannot be restored since dematerialised securities are fungible.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The rematerialisation process and its distinction from physical transfer is tested in NISM Series VI and X-A.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While rematerialisation is technically possible, strongly advise clients against it. Physical certificates carry risks of loss, theft, and forgery. Moreover, physical transfer has been discontinued since April 2019, making physical holding impractical.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
