<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An investment adviser recommends a particular stock to a client on Monday. The IA personally holds shares of the same stock and wants to sell them. Under SEBI IA Regulations, what is the restriction on the IA's personal trading?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The IA can trade freely after a 7-day cooling-off period]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The IA can sell immediately if the sale is disclosed to the client within 48 hours]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The IA cannot trade on own account contrary to the advice given for 15 days, unless a revised assessment is communicated to the client 24 hours in advance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The IA can sell only through a different broker to maintain confidentiality]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations, an investment adviser cannot trade on their own account contrary to the advice given to clients for a period of 15 days. The only exception is if the IA communicates a revised assessment to the client at least 24 hours in advance of making the contrary trade.

**The Trap:** The 15-day restriction is specific — not 7 days or 30 days. Also, the exception requires 24-hour advance notice of a revised assessment, not just post-trade disclosure. Using a different broker is irrelevant.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Personal trading restrictions for IAs are tested in Series X-A. Compare with the personal trading restrictions for Research Analysts under SEBI RA Regulations (Series X-B).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a trading log and match it against your advisory records. If you need to exit a position after recommending it, send the revised assessment email first and wait 24 hours. Document everything.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
