<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunita Iyer is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser based in Mumbai with 200 clients. She has been advising her client Mr. Patel, a 58-year-old conservative investor with a documented low-risk profile, for the past 3 years. Recently, Sunita recommended that Mr. Patel invest Rs. 20 lakh in a mid-cap equity fund managed by Zenith AMC, citing potential high returns of 18-20% over 2 years. However, she did not disclose that her brother-in-law, Mr. Ashok Iyer, is a director of Zenith AMC. Mr. Patel invested the full Rs. 20 lakh based on Sunita's recommendation. Within 6 months, the fund lost 25% in value, reducing his investment to Rs. 15 lakh. Mr. Patel subsequently discovered through a newspaper article that Sunita's brother-in-law is a director at Zenith AMC and that she had not disclosed this conflict of interest. Additionally, Sunita has been using an AI-based algorithmic tool to generate investment recommendations for some of her clients, including Mr. Patel, without disclosing the use of such automated tools in her advisory process. Under SEBI IA Regulations, advisers must disclose the extent of use of AI or algorithmic tools to clients. Furthermore, Sunita traded in the same Zenith mid-cap fund on her personal demat account just 5 days after recommending it to Mr. Patel, purchasing units at a lower NAV. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an Investment Adviser is prohibited from trading on their own account in securities contrary to or ahead of advice given to clients for a period of 15 days. Mr. Patel now wants to file a formal complaint against Sunita. SEBI provides the SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redress System) portal for investors to lodge complaints against registered intermediaries.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Did Sunita violate any SEBI regulation by purchasing units of the same Zenith mid-cap fund in her personal demat account 5 days after recommending it to Mr. Patel?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because she bought the fund at a lower NAV, which shows she was not front-running the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because Investment Advisers are free to invest in any securities for their personal accounts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because SEBI IA Regulations prohibit an IA from trading on their own account in the same security for 15 days after giving advice, and she traded within 5 days]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, but only because the fund subsequently lost value; if it had gained value, the trade would be permissible]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, an Investment Adviser is prohibited from trading on their own account in securities that are contrary to or in the same direction as the advice given to clients for a period of 15 days from the date of such advice. Sunita recommended the Zenith mid-cap fund to Mr. Patel and then bought the same fund for her personal account just 5 days later — well within the 15-day prohibition window. This is a clear violation regardless of the price at which she bought or the subsequent performance.

**The Trap:** Option A incorrectly suggests that buying at a lower NAV means no front-running. The regulation does not depend on the price — it imposes a blanket 15-day cooling-off period. Option B ignores the personal trading restrictions entirely. Option D again introduces the outcome fallacy — the violation is in the act of trading within the prohibited period, not in the result.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The 15-day personal trading restriction is designed to prevent conflicts between the IA's personal financial interests and client interests. This applies to both buying and selling. The IA must maintain a record of all personal trades and make it available for audit.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Maintain a personal trading log and cross-reference it with client advice records. Set up calendar reminders for the 15-day cooling-off period after every recommendation. Compliance software can automate this check to prevent inadvertent violations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
