<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_59" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under SEBI IA Regulations, which of the following disclosures must an investment adviser make to clients?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the IA's educational qualifications and years of experience]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only conflicts of interest related to the recommended products]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the IA's business information and fee structure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Business information, disciplinary history, holdings in recommended products, conflicts of interest, AI tool usage, and products outside SEBI purview]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations 2013, the disclosure requirements are comprehensive and include: business information, disciplinary history, holdings in recommended products, all conflicts of interest, usage of AI tools in generating advice, and information about products that fall outside SEBI's regulatory purview. The AI tool usage disclosure is a particularly modern requirement reflecting the growing use of robo-advisory and AI-driven tools.

**The Trap:** Each of the first three options contains a subset of the required disclosures but is incomplete. The regulation mandates a holistic disclosure framework — not just one or two categories.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Disclosure requirements are heavily tested in NISM Series X-A and have parallels in Series X-B (Research Analyst disclosures) and Series XII (PMS disclosures).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Create a standard disclosure document that covers all mandatory items and provide it during client onboarding. Update it whenever there are material changes. AI tool disclosure is increasingly important — if you use any AI/algorithm for generating recommendations, disclose it upfront.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
