<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_38" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Priya is a SEBI-registered individual investment adviser. She currently has 280 clients and earned Rs. 2.8 crore in advisory fees last financial year. Her client base is growing rapidly. At what threshold must she mandatorily convert to a non-individual investment adviser?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than 200 clients OR more than Rs. 2 crore in fees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than 500 clients OR more than Rs. 5 crore in fees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[More than 300 clients OR more than Rs. 3 crore in fees]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[More than 150 clients OR more than Rs. 1.5 crore in fees]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations 2013, an individual investment adviser who exceeds 300 clients OR Rs. 3 crore in advisory fees must mandatorily convert to a non-individual IA entity (body corporate, LLP, or partnership firm). A 3-month transition period is provided for this conversion. Priya has not yet breached either threshold (280 clients, Rs. 2.8 crore fees), but she must monitor closely.

**The Trap:** The thresholds are 300 clients and Rs. 3 crore — not round numbers like 200/500. Also note the OR condition: breaching either one (not both) triggers the conversion requirement.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Individual IA thresholds and the conversion requirement are frequently tested in NISM Series X-A. The 3-month transition window is an important operational detail.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Track both metrics — client count and fee income — quarterly. Breaching either threshold without converting exposes you to regulatory action. Plan your entity structure well before approaching the limits.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
