<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Rajiv is an IRDAI-registered insurance agent. He also wants to advise clients on equity mutual funds and direct equity. Under SEBI IA Regulations, which statement is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He is fully exempt from SEBI IA registration since he is IRDAI-registered]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He needs SEBI IA registration only if he advises on direct equity, not mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[His exemption is limited to insurance products only; he needs SEBI IA registration to advise on equity and mutual funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He cannot hold both IRDAI and SEBI registrations simultaneously]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** IRDAI-registered insurance agents are exempt from SEBI IA registration ONLY for advising on insurance products. The moment they advise on securities like equity mutual funds or direct equity, they fall within SEBI's purview and must obtain SEBI IA registration.

**The Trap:** The blanket assumption that IRDAI registration exempts from all SEBI requirements is incorrect. The exemption is product-specific, not entity-specific. Similarly, there is no prohibition on holding dual registrations.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Registration exemptions under IA Regulations are a high-frequency topic in NISM Series X-A. Similar product-specific exemptions apply to PFRDA pension advisors (pension products only) and MF distributors (incidental advice only).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before advising on any product, verify which regulator governs it. Your registration exemption is only as broad as the product category it covers.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
