<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Vikram Mehta, a CFA charterholder with 7 years of experience in wealth management at a private bank, wants to set up his own investment advisory firm. He plans to register as an individual Investment Adviser with SEBI under the SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013. He has a net worth of Rs. 8 lakh. His wife Neha is an AMFI-registered mutual fund distributor who currently serves 50 clients. Vikram expects to start with 100 clients, charging an annual fee of Rs. 25,000 per client. One of his prospective clients, Mr. Rao, has assets worth Rs. 2 crore and wants both advisory and distribution services from the same family. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an individual Investment Adviser must have a minimum net worth of Rs. 5 lakh, can serve a maximum of 300 clients, and must convert to a non-individual IA if clients exceed 300 or advisory fees exceed Rs. 3 crore in a financial year. A part-time Investment Adviser is limited to 75 clients. Accepted qualifications include CFA Charter, post-graduate diploma in finance, or a professional qualification such as CA/CS/CWA with relevant experience. The IA must hold a valid NISM Investment Adviser certification. Records of investment advice, rationale, and client interactions must be maintained for a minimum of 5 years. An annual compliance audit by a CA is mandatory. Importantly, a family member of an individual IA cannot provide distribution services to the same client to whom the IA provides advisory services, ensuring segregation of advisory and distribution activities.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> Mr. Rao wants to receive investment advisory services from Vikram and mutual fund distribution services from Vikram's wife Neha. Is this arrangement permissible under SEBI IA Regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because Neha is independently registered with AMFI and operates as a separate entity]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, provided Vikram discloses the family relationship to Mr. Rao in writing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because advisory and distribution are two different activities regulated by different bodies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because a family member of an individual IA cannot provide distribution services to the same client to whom the IA provides advisory services]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, there is a strict segregation requirement between advisory and distribution activities. A family member of an individual Investment Adviser is prohibited from providing distribution services to the same client who receives advisory services from the IA. Since Neha is Vikram's wife (and therefore a family member), she cannot distribute mutual fund products to Mr. Rao if Vikram is advising him.

**The Trap:** Options A, B, and C all try to create exceptions to this rule — through separate registration, written disclosure, or regulatory jurisdiction arguments. None of these override the explicit prohibition. The regulation is designed to prevent conflicts of interest where an IA might recommend products that benefit the family member's distribution commissions.

**Cross-Exam Context:** This segregation principle is fundamental to the SEBI IA framework. It extends to the concept that an IA cannot simultaneously act as a distributor for the same client. The definition of "family" under the regulations typically includes spouse, parents, siblings, and children.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If a spouse is an existing distributor, the IA must ensure that their client bases do not overlap. Maintain separate client lists and have a documented process to verify no client receives both advisory and distribution services from the family unit.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
