<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_20" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An investor who is a first-time mutual fund buyer completes the KYC process. Which of the following verification steps is MANDATORY for this investor?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Verification by a Chartered Accountant certifying the investor's net worth]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Video-based identification through a SEBI-registered intermediary only during business hours]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[In-Person Verification (IPV), which can also be conducted through Video IPV (VIPV) via an app]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Physical visit to the AMC's registered office for biometric verification]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** In-Person Verification (IPV) is mandatory for first-time investors in the securities market. IPV can be conducted in person or through Video IPV (VIPV) via an app, providing a convenient digital alternative. The purpose is to verify that the person completing KYC is the same person whose documents are being submitted.

**The Trap:** Net worth certification is not part of standard KYC for retail investors. VIPV is not restricted to business hours — it can be done through the app at the investor's convenience. Physical visit to AMC office is not required; IPV can be done by distributors, AMC staff, or through VIPV.

**Cross-Exam Context:** IPV requirements and the VIPV alternative are tested in NISM Series V-A and X-A. The evolution from physical-only IPV to digital VIPV is an important regulatory development.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** VIPV through an app has made the first-time investor onboarding process much smoother. Guide clients through the VIPV process on their smartphone — it takes just a few minutes and eliminates the need for a physical meeting.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
