<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_49" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[A SEBI-registered investment adviser recommends a complex structured product to a retired school teacher with a conservative risk profile and no prior experience with derivatives. Under SEBI IA Regulations on suitability, this recommendation is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Acceptable if the expected return exceeds the risk-free rate by at least 3%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Acceptable if the IA obtains a signed disclaimer from the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Acceptable if the IA discloses the product risks in writing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A violation of suitability requirements as the product is inappropriate for the client's risk profile and experience level]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations, suitability assessment requires that the recommended product must be appropriate to the client's risk profile. Additionally, the IA must ensure the client has the necessary experience and knowledge to understand the product risks. A complex structured product is unsuitable for a conservative retiree with no derivatives experience — regardless of disclaimers, disclosures, or return expectations.

**The Trap:** Disclaimers and disclosures do NOT cure suitability violations. An IA cannot shift responsibility to the client by obtaining a signed waiver. The fiduciary duty to ensure suitability is non-delegable.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Suitability is tested across NISM Series X-A, Series XII (PMS), and Series V-A (MF). The principle that disclosure cannot replace suitability is a universal regulatory concept.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before recommending any product, ask yourself: "Would a reasonable adviser recommend this to someone with this specific client's profile?" If the answer is no, don't make the recommendation — no disclaimer can protect you.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
