<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C2_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunita Iyer is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser based in Mumbai with 200 clients. She has been advising her client Mr. Patel, a 58-year-old conservative investor with a documented low-risk profile, for the past 3 years. Recently, Sunita recommended that Mr. Patel invest Rs. 20 lakh in a mid-cap equity fund managed by Zenith AMC, citing potential high returns of 18-20% over 2 years. However, she did not disclose that her brother-in-law, Mr. Ashok Iyer, is a director of Zenith AMC. Mr. Patel invested the full Rs. 20 lakh based on Sunita's recommendation. Within 6 months, the fund lost 25% in value, reducing his investment to Rs. 15 lakh. Mr. Patel subsequently discovered through a newspaper article that Sunita's brother-in-law is a director at Zenith AMC and that she had not disclosed this conflict of interest. Additionally, Sunita has been using an AI-based algorithmic tool to generate investment recommendations for some of her clients, including Mr. Patel, without disclosing the use of such automated tools in her advisory process. Under SEBI IA Regulations, advisers must disclose the extent of use of AI or algorithmic tools to clients. Furthermore, Sunita traded in the same Zenith mid-cap fund on her personal demat account just 5 days after recommending it to Mr. Patel, purchasing units at a lower NAV. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an Investment Adviser is prohibited from trading on their own account in securities contrary to or ahead of advice given to clients for a period of 15 days. Mr. Patel now wants to file a formal complaint against Sunita. SEBI provides the SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redress System) portal for investors to lodge complaints against registered intermediaries.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Did Sunita violate any SEBI regulation by using an AI-based algorithmic tool to generate investment recommendations without informing her clients?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because AI tools improve the quality of recommendations and benefit clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, because SEBI regulations do not address the use of technology tools by Investment Advisers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because Investment Advisers are completely prohibited from using AI or algorithmic tools under SEBI regulations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because SEBI IA Regulations require Investment Advisers to disclose the extent of use of AI or algorithmic tools to their clients]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, Investment Advisers are required to disclose the extent of use of AI or algorithmic tools in their advisory process to clients. Sunita used an AI-based tool to generate recommendations for clients including Mr. Patel but did not disclose this usage. The violation is not in using the tool itself — IAs are permitted to use technology — but in failing to disclose its use. Clients have a right to know whether their advice is human-generated, AI-assisted, or fully automated.

**The Trap:** Option A correctly notes that AI can improve quality but uses that as justification to skip disclosure — benefit does not negate the disclosure obligation. Option B incorrectly claims SEBI does not address AI tools. Option C goes to the opposite extreme, claiming AI tools are completely banned — they are permitted but must be disclosed.

**Cross-Exam Context:** As technology evolves in financial services, SEBI has progressively introduced guidelines on the use of automated advisory tools and algorithm-based recommendations. The key principle is transparency: clients must understand the methodology behind the advice they receive, including the role of human judgment versus automated analysis.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** If you use AI tools, robo-advisory algorithms, or any automated screening/recommendation systems, include a clear disclosure in your client agreement and advisory reports. Specify whether the AI provides initial screening, full recommendations, or portfolio rebalancing signals. This transparency builds trust and ensures regulatory compliance.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
