<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_13" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following statements about ASBA (Application Supported by Blocked Amount) for IPO applications is CORRECT as per current SEBI regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ASBA is optional for retail investors who prefer to pay upfront through demand drafts]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[ASBA was made mandatory for institutional investors in 2016, but remains optional for retail investors]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Under ASBA, the full application amount is debited from the investor's bank account at the time of application]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[ASBA has been mandatory for all IPO applications since January 2016, and the amount is only blocked (not debited) until allotment]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI made ASBA mandatory for all IPO applications from January 2016. Under ASBA, the application money is blocked in the investor's bank account but NOT debited. The amount is debited only to the extent of allotment, and the remaining blocked amount is automatically released. Additionally, UPI with ASBA facility is available for retail investors.

**The Trap:** ASBA is mandatory (not optional) for all categories of investors since January 2016. The key feature of ASBA is that money is blocked, not debited — the investor continues to earn interest on the blocked amount until allotment.

**Cross-Exam Context:** ASBA mechanism and its mandatory status are tested in NISM Series X-A and NISM Series IX (Merchant Banking). Understanding the blocking vs. debiting distinction is crucial.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Remind clients that with ASBA, their money stays in their bank account earning interest until allotment. For retail investors, UPI-based ASBA through apps makes the process even more convenient.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
