<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_23" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the difference between a General Power of Attorney and a Specific/Limited Power of Attorney?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A General PoA allows the holder to appoint nominees, while a Specific PoA does not]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A General PoA can only be granted by individuals, while a Specific PoA can be granted by both individuals and companies]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A General PoA must be attested by the Indian embassy when executed abroad, but a Specific PoA does not require attestation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[A General PoA authorises the holder to act on behalf of the grantor across a wide range of matters, while a Specific/Limited PoA restricts the holder's authority to particular transactions or actions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** A General PoA grants broad authority to the holder to act on behalf of the grantor across many matters. A Specific or Limited PoA restricts the holder's authority to particular, defined transactions or actions. The fundamental difference is the SCOPE of authority granted — broad vs. narrow.

**The Trap:** Neither type of PoA allows the holder to appoint nominees — that prohibition applies universally. Both types require Indian embassy attestation when executed abroad. Both can be granted by individuals (companies use board resolutions). The core distinction is scope, not who can grant or what formalities apply.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between General and Specific PoA is tested in NISM Series X-A. Understanding this helps advisers recommend the appropriate type based on client needs.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For most investment-related purposes, recommend a Specific/Limited PoA to clients. It provides adequate authority for defined transactions while limiting the risk of misuse. Always ensure the PoA clearly specifies the permitted actions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
