<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Under SEBI IA Regulations, an investment adviser must maintain a deposit with a scheduled bank. Which of the following correctly describes the purpose and usage of this deposit?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It serves as capital adequacy for the IA's business operations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It can be used by the IA for working capital needs with prior SEBI approval]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It is maintained with a lien in favor of the recognized body and is available for dues arising from arbitration or ODR]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It is refundable to the IA upon completion of 5 years of continuous registration]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The deposit required under SEBI IA Regulations must be maintained with a scheduled bank, with a lien in favor of the recognized body (such as BSE Administration & Supervision Ltd). The deposit is specifically available for settling dues arising from arbitration or Online Dispute Resolution (ODR) proceedings against the IA.

**The Trap:** The deposit is NOT capital adequacy (which is a banking concept) nor working capital. It is a client-protection mechanism. It cannot be withdrawn for business use — it is encumbered by the lien.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Deposit requirements and their purposes are tested in NISM Series X-A. Compare with net worth requirements for other SEBI intermediaries like portfolio managers (Series XII).

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Think of the deposit as your clients' safety net. If a dispute goes to arbitration and you lose, the deposit ensures the client can recover their dues without chasing you.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
