<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An Indian citizen who has been residing in Dubai for the past 3 years wishes to invest in Indian securities. His father was born in pre-partition Lahore (undivided India). What is the correct classification of this individual?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[He is an NRI (Non-Resident Indian) because he is an Indian citizen residing outside India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He is a PIO (Person of Indian Origin) because his father was born in undivided India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He is both an NRI and PIO simultaneously, and can choose either status for investment purposes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[He is a resident Indian since Indian citizens are always treated as residents for securities market purposes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** An NRI is defined as a citizen of India who is not a resident of India (i.e., has stayed outside India for more than 182 days in the preceding financial year, or has not satisfied the 60+365 days combined rule). Since this person is an Indian citizen living abroad for 3 years, he qualifies as an NRI. The PIO classification applies to foreign nationals (not Indian citizens) whose parents or grandparents were born in undivided India.

**The Trap:** PIO status is for foreign passport holders of Indian origin — NOT for Indian citizens. Since this individual holds Indian citizenship, the PIO classification does not apply to him, regardless of his father's birthplace. One cannot be both NRI and PIO simultaneously.

**Cross-Exam Context:** The distinction between NRI and PIO is fundamental and tested in NISM Series X-A. The 182-day residency rule is also relevant for tax purposes under the Income Tax Act.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always verify the client's citizenship first. If they hold an Indian passport, they are either resident or NRI. PIO status is only relevant for foreign passport holders with Indian ancestry.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
