<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_12" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[An NRI has earnings from rental income on a property in India credited to his NRO account. He wishes to repatriate funds from this account. What is the maximum amount he can repatriate per financial year from the NRO account?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[USD 500,000 per financial year after applicable taxes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There is no limit on repatriation from NRO account as it is freely repatriable]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[USD 1 million per financial year, subject to applicable taxes]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Funds in an NRO account are completely non-repatriable under any circumstances]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The NRO account is primarily non-repatriable, but repatriation is permitted up to USD 1 million per financial year, subject to applicable taxes. This facility allows NRIs to repatriate income earned in India (such as rent, dividends, pension) after deduction of taxes.

**The Trap:** While the NRO account is classified as "non-repatriable," it does allow limited repatriation up to USD 1 million. It is NOT completely non-repatriable (unlike what many candidates assume), nor is it freely repatriable like the NRE account. The limit is USD 1 million, not USD 500,000.

**Cross-Exam Context:** NRE vs. NRO repatriation rules are tested in NISM Series X-A and are also relevant in NISM Series V-A for understanding NRI mutual fund investment flows.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Advise NRI clients that for amounts exceeding USD 1 million per year, they should plan their investments through the NRE account or FCNR account, which are fully repatriable without any ceiling.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
