<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_C2_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Sunita Iyer is a SEBI-registered Investment Adviser based in Mumbai with 200 clients. She has been advising her client Mr. Patel, a 58-year-old conservative investor with a documented low-risk profile, for the past 3 years. Recently, Sunita recommended that Mr. Patel invest Rs. 20 lakh in a mid-cap equity fund managed by Zenith AMC, citing potential high returns of 18-20% over 2 years. However, she did not disclose that her brother-in-law, Mr. Ashok Iyer, is a director of Zenith AMC. Mr. Patel invested the full Rs. 20 lakh based on Sunita's recommendation. Within 6 months, the fund lost 25% in value, reducing his investment to Rs. 15 lakh. Mr. Patel subsequently discovered through a newspaper article that Sunita's brother-in-law is a director at Zenith AMC and that she had not disclosed this conflict of interest. Additionally, Sunita has been using an AI-based algorithmic tool to generate investment recommendations for some of her clients, including Mr. Patel, without disclosing the use of such automated tools in her advisory process. Under SEBI IA Regulations, advisers must disclose the extent of use of AI or algorithmic tools to clients. Furthermore, Sunita traded in the same Zenith mid-cap fund on her personal demat account just 5 days after recommending it to Mr. Patel, purchasing units at a lower NAV. Under SEBI IA Regulations, an Investment Adviser is prohibited from trading on their own account in securities contrary to or ahead of advice given to clients for a period of 15 days. Mr. Patel now wants to file a formal complaint against Sunita. SEBI provides the SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redress System) portal for investors to lodge complaints against registered intermediaries.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> Was Sunita's recommendation of a mid-cap equity fund suitable for Mr. Patel given his investor profile?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because mid-cap funds can deliver high returns which benefit all investors regardless of risk profile]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Yes, because Mr. Patel has Rs. 20 lakh available to invest, indicating he can absorb potential losses]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[No, because a mid-cap equity fund is unsuitable for a 58-year-old conservative investor with a documented low-risk profile, violating the suitability obligation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No, but only because the fund lost 25% in value; the recommendation would have been suitable if the fund had performed well]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI (Investment Advisers) Regulations, 2013, an IA must ensure that investment advice is suitable for the client based on their documented risk profile, financial situation, investment objectives, and time horizon. Mr. Patel is 58 years old, has a conservative outlook, and a documented low-risk profile. A mid-cap equity fund — which carries significant volatility and market risk — is fundamentally unsuitable for such an investor. The suitability violation occurred at the point of recommendation, not because of the subsequent loss.

**The Trap:** Option A ignores risk profiling entirely. Option B incorrectly equates available capital with risk capacity — having money to invest does not mean the investor should take high risks. Option D is a critical trap: it suggests suitability depends on outcome. Suitability is assessed at the time of recommendation based on the client's profile, not on hindsight performance.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Suitability is a process-based obligation, not an outcome-based one. Even if the mid-cap fund had gained 50%, the recommendation would still be unsuitable because it did not match Mr. Patel's risk profile. The risk profiling and suitability assessment documentation is key evidence in any dispute.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always document the suitability rationale for every recommendation. For conservative investors nearing retirement, focus on debt funds, balanced advantage funds with equity capping, or capital protection-oriented products. If a client insists on equity exposure against their risk profile, obtain written acknowledgment of the mismatch.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
