<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<QF id="XA Operations Regulation and Ethics_43" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question><text><![CDATA[Which of the following qualifications is accepted for the principal officer/proprietor of an individual investment adviser under SEBI IA Regulations?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Any undergraduate degree from a recognized university]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a Master's degree in Finance or Economics]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Professional/graduate/PG degree in finance, commerce, economics, or related fields, OR CFA Charter, OR NISM PG Program (minimum 1 year)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only CFA or CFP certification is accepted; academic degrees are not sufficient]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under SEBI IA Regulations 2013, the qualification requirement for investment advisers includes a professional, graduate, or post-graduate degree in finance, commerce, economics, banking, capital markets, insurance, actuarial science, business management, or related fields. Alternatively, a CFA Charter or completion of the NISM Post Graduate Program (minimum 1 year) is also accepted.

**The Trap:** A general undergraduate degree (e.g., BA in History) would not suffice — the degree must be in a finance-related field. Similarly, CFA/CFP is accepted but is not the only pathway — academic qualifications also work.

**Cross-Exam Context:** Qualification requirements are specific to NISM Series X-A. Note that persons "associated with advice" (not the principal) have a lower threshold — minimum graduate degree.

**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Ensure both you and your associated persons maintain valid NISM certifications at all times. The qualification is a one-time requirement; NISM certification is an ongoing obligation.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>
