<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C6_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Suresh Kumar, aged 40, works in the automobile industry and recently faced a salary reduction from Rs. 1,00,000/month to Rs. 75,000/month due to an industry slowdown. He has the following loans: (1) Home loan: Rs. 28 lakh outstanding at 9% p.a. fixed rate, EMI Rs. 28,000, remaining tenure 12 years; (2) Car loan: Rs. 3 lakh outstanding at 12% p.a., EMI Rs. 8,500, remaining tenure 3.5 years; (3) Education loan for son: Rs. 5 lakh at 10% p.a., EMI Rs. 10,600, remaining tenure 5 years. His non-debt monthly expenses are Rs. 35,000. He has savings of Rs. 4 lakh in FDs and Rs. 1.5 lakh in savings bank. His wife earns Rs. 25,000/month from tutoring. The bank has offered to restructure his home loan by extending tenure from 12 to 18 years at the same 9% rate, which would reduce the home loan EMI to approximately Rs. 22,000.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> Before the salary cut, what was Suresh's debt-to-income ratio? And what is it after the cut?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Before: 37.7%, After: 47.1%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Before: 47.1%, After: 62.8%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Before: 37.7%, After: 62.8%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Before: 47.1%, After: 47.1%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Total debt servicing = 28,000 + 8,500 + 10,600 = Rs. 47,100. Before: Total income = 1,00,000 + 25,000 = Rs. 1,25,000. DTI = 47,100/1,25,000 = 37.7%. After: Total income = 75,000 + 25,000 = Rs. 1,00,000. DTI = 47,100/1,00,000 = 47.1%.
**The Trap:** Using only Suresh's income (without wife's) gives higher DTI. Family income should be used. Also, the salary cut pushes DTI from moderate (37.7%) to dangerous (47.1%).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Impact of income changes on DTI is a practical X-A scenario.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** 47.1% DTI is unsustainable — more than 47% of family income going to debt servicing leaves too little for expenses and savings.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>