<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C1_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Arvind Sharma, aged 42, is a senior manager at an IT company earning Rs. 18 lakh per annum (gross). His wife Mrs. Priya works part-time earning Rs. 6 lakh per annum. Their combined monthly expenses are Rs. 1,20,000. They have two children aged 14 and 10. Arvind's current investments include: Equity Mutual Funds Rs. 35 lakh, PPF Rs. 12 lakh (current balance), Bank Fixed Deposits Rs. 8 lakh, Employee PF balance Rs. 18 lakh, and a savings bank balance of Rs. 3 lakh. He has an outstanding home loan of Rs. 22 lakh with EMI of Rs. 25,000/month (included in expenses above) and no other loans. His employer contributes Rs. 1,800/month to PF and he contributes the same. He wants to retire at age 58 and needs a retirement corpus of Rs. 3 crore. He also needs Rs. 30 lakh for his elder child's education in 4 years and Rs. 25 lakh for the younger child in 8 years. Assume equity returns at 12% CAGR and debt returns at 7% CAGR. Inflation is 6% p.a.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> The monthly savings ratio of the Sharma family (considering gross salary, PF contributions, and expenses of Rs. 1,20,000) is closest to:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[20.0%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[40.0%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[33.3%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[25.0%]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Monthly income = (18,00,000 + 6,00,000)/12 = Rs. 2,00,000. Monthly expenses = Rs. 1,20,000 (includes EMI). Monthly savings = 2,00,000 - 1,20,000 = Rs. 80,000 (which includes PF of Rs. 3,600). Savings ratio = 80,000/2,00,000 = 40%.
**The Trap:** Using only Arvind's salary (Rs. 1,50,000/month) gives a different ratio. Use total family income for family savings ratio.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Savings ratio calculation is tested in X-A (Ch 3).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A 40% savings ratio is excellent — the Sharmas are in a strong position to meet their goals if savings are properly allocated.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>