<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C5_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Dr. Arun Patel, aged 50, is a senior physician earning Rs. 30 lakh per annum from his hospital practice. His wife Mrs. Shalini runs a small boutique earning Rs. 5 lakh per annum. They have one son, aged 22, who is completing his MBA and will be financially independent in 1 year. Dr. Patel wants to retire at 58. Their current financial position: Equity portfolio Rs. 45 lakh, Debt mutual funds Rs. 20 lakh, PPF Rs. 16 lakh (matures in 3 years), FDs Rs. 12 lakh, PF balance Rs. 25 lakh, Gold Rs. 10 lakh, Residential property (self-occupied) Rs. 1.2 crore. Liabilities: Home loan Rs. 15 lakh (EMI Rs. 22,000, 7 years remaining at 8%), no other loans. Monthly expenses: Rs. 1,80,000 (including EMI). Post-retirement, they estimate needing Rs. 1,20,000/month in today's terms. They want a retirement corpus that lasts 25 years post-retirement. Inflation is 6% p.a. Expected returns: equity 12%, debt 7%.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> Which step of the six-step financial planning process is Dr. Patel's adviser currently performing by gathering all this financial data?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Step 1: Establishing the client-planner relationship]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Step 2: Gathering client data including goals]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Step 3: Analysing and evaluating financial status]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Step 4: Developing financial planning recommendations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Gathering all financial data — income, expenses, assets, liabilities, goals — is Step 2 of the six-step process. Step 1 (defining the relationship) would already be complete. Step 3 (analysis) and Step 4 (recommendations) come after data gathering.
**The Trap:** The analysis hasn't started yet — we're still collecting data. Analysis would involve computing ratios, gap analysis, etc.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The six-step financial planning process is a fundamental X-A concept (Ch 1).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Thorough data gathering is the foundation of good advice — rush this step and the entire plan will be flawed.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>