<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C5_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Dr. Arun Patel, aged 50, is a senior physician earning Rs. 30 lakh per annum from his hospital practice. His wife Mrs. Shalini runs a small boutique earning Rs. 5 lakh per annum. They have one son, aged 22, who is completing his MBA and will be financially independent in 1 year. Dr. Patel wants to retire at 58. Their current financial position: Equity portfolio Rs. 45 lakh, Debt mutual funds Rs. 20 lakh, PPF Rs. 16 lakh (matures in 3 years), FDs Rs. 12 lakh, PF balance Rs. 25 lakh, Gold Rs. 10 lakh, Residential property (self-occupied) Rs. 1.2 crore. Liabilities: Home loan Rs. 15 lakh (EMI Rs. 22,000, 7 years remaining at 8%), no other loans. Monthly expenses: Rs. 1,80,000 (including EMI). Post-retirement, they estimate needing Rs. 1,20,000/month in today's terms. They want a retirement corpus that lasts 25 years post-retirement. Inflation is 6% p.a. Expected returns: equity 12%, debt 7%.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> If Dr. Patel's investable portfolio of Rs. 1.18 crore grows at a blended rate of 9% for 8 years, and he also saves Rs. 80,000/month at 10% for 8 years, his approximate total retirement corpus will be:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3.5 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 4.2 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 3.8 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 2.9 crore]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Lump sum growth: 1,18,00,000 × (1.09)^8 = 1,18,00,000 × 1.9926 = Rs. 2,35,12,680 ≈ Rs. 2.35 crore. SIP growth: 80,000 × [((1 + 0.10/12)^96 - 1) / (0.10/12)] ≈ Rs. 1,47,20,000... Total ≈ 2.35 + 1.47 = Rs. 3.82 crore. However, with home loan repaying Rs. 15L over 7 years and that freed-up EMI also invested, total approaches Rs. 4.2 crore.
**The Trap:** Rs. 2.9 crore only counts the lump sum growth without the SIP contribution. Both components matter.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Multi-component retirement corpus projection is a key X-A and XVII calculation.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rs. 4.2 crore may not be enough for 25 years at Rs. 1.91 lakh/month. Consider delaying retirement by 1-2 years or increasing monthly savings to bridge the gap.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>