<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C4_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> The Kapoor family consists of Mr. Rajiv (45, software engineer, gross salary Rs. 15 lakh p.a.) and Mrs. Neha (42, freelance designer, annual income Rs. 6 lakh). Their monthly breakdown is: Gross salary (Rajiv) Rs. 1,25,000, Freelance income (Neha) Rs. 50,000, Employer PF contribution Rs. 1,800, Employee PF contribution Rs. 1,800. Mandatory expenses: Tax deductions Rs. 12,000, Loan EMIs Rs. 35,000. Essential expenses: Groceries Rs. 15,000, Children's education Rs. 20,000, Rent Rs. 25,000, Utilities Rs. 8,000, Transportation Rs. 10,000. Discretionary expenses: Entertainment Rs. 8,000, Lifestyle Rs. 12,000, Annual holiday fund Rs. 5,000. Their assets include: Equity MFs Rs. 22 lakh, FDs Rs. 10 lakh, PPF Rs. 8 lakh, PF balance Rs. 14 lakh, Savings bank Rs. 2 lakh, Gold jewellery Rs. 6 lakh, Car (3 years old) Rs. 5 lakh. Liabilities: Home loan Rs. 18 lakh, Car loan Rs. 2,50,000.

<b>Question 4 of 5:</b> The Kapoor family's liquidity ratio (using savings bank and FDs maturing within 6 months as liquid assets) assuming Rs. 4 lakh of FDs are short-term, is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[2.67]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[4.00]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[5.33]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[8.00]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Liquid assets = Savings bank Rs. 2 lakh + Short-term FDs Rs. 4 lakh = Rs. 6 lakh. Monthly expenses (total) = Rs. 1,50,000. Liquidity ratio = 6,00,000 / 1,50,000 = 4.00. This means the family can cover 4 months of expenses from liquid assets.
**The Trap:** Including all FDs (Rs. 10 lakh) as liquid would give 12/1.5 = 8.0, which overstates liquidity. Only short-term FDs count.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Liquidity ratio interpretation is tested in X-A (Ch 3). 4-6 months is considered comfortable.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A ratio of 4.0 is at the lower end of comfortable. The Kapoors should build their emergency fund to at least 6 months (Rs. 9 lakh in liquid assets).]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>