<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C5_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Dr. Arun Patel, aged 50, is a senior physician earning Rs. 30 lakh per annum from his hospital practice. His wife Mrs. Shalini runs a small boutique earning Rs. 5 lakh per annum. They have one son, aged 22, who is completing his MBA and will be financially independent in 1 year. Dr. Patel wants to retire at 58. Their current financial position: Equity portfolio Rs. 45 lakh, Debt mutual funds Rs. 20 lakh, PPF Rs. 16 lakh (matures in 3 years), FDs Rs. 12 lakh, PF balance Rs. 25 lakh, Gold Rs. 10 lakh, Residential property (self-occupied) Rs. 1.2 crore. Liabilities: Home loan Rs. 15 lakh (EMI Rs. 22,000, 7 years remaining at 8%), no other loans. Monthly expenses: Rs. 1,80,000 (including EMI). Post-retirement, they estimate needing Rs. 1,20,000/month in today's terms. They want a retirement corpus that lasts 25 years post-retirement. Inflation is 6% p.a. Expected returns: equity 12%, debt 7%.

<b>Question 1 of 5:</b> What is Dr. Patel's total investable portfolio (excluding self-occupied property and gold)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1,18,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1,28,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1,03,00,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 1,38,00,000]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Investable portfolio = Equity (45L) + Debt MFs (20L) + PPF (16L) + FDs (12L) + PF (25L) = Rs. 1,18,00,000. Self-occupied property and gold are excluded as they're not readily available for retirement funding.
**The Trap:** Rs. 1,28,00,000 includes gold (which is a physical asset not easily liquidated for retirement). Rs. 1,38,00,000 includes both gold and property.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Conservative asset estimation excludes self-occupied home as taught in X-A (Ch 3).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Dr. Patel has a solid Rs. 1.18 crore investable base at age 50 — with 8 years to retirement, proper asset allocation can help achieve retirement goals.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>