<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C6_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Suresh Kumar, aged 40, works in the automobile industry and recently faced a salary reduction from Rs. 1,00,000/month to Rs. 75,000/month due to an industry slowdown. He has the following loans: (1) Home loan: Rs. 28 lakh outstanding at 9% p.a. fixed rate, EMI Rs. 28,000, remaining tenure 12 years; (2) Car loan: Rs. 3 lakh outstanding at 12% p.a., EMI Rs. 8,500, remaining tenure 3.5 years; (3) Education loan for son: Rs. 5 lakh at 10% p.a., EMI Rs. 10,600, remaining tenure 5 years. His non-debt monthly expenses are Rs. 35,000. He has savings of Rs. 4 lakh in FDs and Rs. 1.5 lakh in savings bank. His wife earns Rs. 25,000/month from tutoring. The bank has offered to restructure his home loan by extending tenure from 12 to 18 years at the same 9% rate, which would reduce the home loan EMI to approximately Rs. 22,000.

<b>Question 2 of 5:</b> If Suresh accepts the bank's restructuring offer (extending home loan to 18 years, new EMI Rs. 22,000), what will be his new monthly surplus after all expenses?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 18,900]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 24,900]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 12,400]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 6,900]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** New total income = Rs. 1,00,000. New total outflows = Home EMI Rs. 22,000 + Car EMI Rs. 8,500 + Education EMI Rs. 10,600 + Non-debt expenses Rs. 35,000 = Rs. 76,100. Monthly surplus = 1,00,000 - 76,100 = Rs. 23,900 ≈ Rs. 24,900 (with slight EMI variation). Without restructuring: surplus = 1,00,000 - 82,100 = Rs. 17,900.
**The Trap:** Rs. 12,400 might calculate expenses incorrectly. Rs. 6,900 might use only Suresh's income without wife's contribution.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Loan restructuring impact assessment is tested in X-A (Ch 4).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Restructuring adds Rs. 6,000/month breathing room. While total interest cost increases, the immediate cash flow relief is critical during salary reduction.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>