<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C2_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mrs. Lakshmi Iyer, aged 38, is a school teacher earning Rs. 8 lakh per annum. Her husband Mr. Venkat earns Rs. 14 lakh per annum as a bank officer. They have a daughter Ananya, aged 12, who they plan to send abroad for undergraduate studies at age 18. The estimated cost of the 4-year programme is Rs. 60 lakh at today's prices, with education inflation at 8% p.a. Their current education fund has Rs. 15 lakh in a recurring deposit earning 6.5% p.a. and Rs. 5 lakh in a balanced mutual fund earning 11% p.a. They can additionally save Rs. 25,000 per month specifically for this goal. They are in the 20% tax bracket. The household has monthly expenses of Rs. 85,000 and a car loan EMI of Rs. 12,000 with 2 years remaining.

<b>Question 3 of 5:</b> The shortfall between the target education corpus and the existing fund's projected value is approximately:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 54 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 64 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 48 lakh]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 72 lakh]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Target = Rs. 95,23,270 (from Q1). Projected existing fund = Rs. 31,24,580 (from Q2). Shortfall = 95,23,270 - 31,24,580 = Rs. 63,98,690 ≈ Rs. 64 lakh.
**The Trap:** Using today's education cost (Rs. 60 lakh) instead of the inflation-adjusted future cost significantly underestimates the shortfall.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Gap analysis between goals and resources is a key X-A planning exercise.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Always work with inflation-adjusted future values when assessing goal shortfalls — today's cost is irrelevant for a future expense.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>