<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C3_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Rahul Mehta, aged 35, earns Rs. 1,20,000 per month (net take-home). He has the following outstanding debts: (1) Home loan: Rs. 35 lakh outstanding at 8.5% p.a., EMI Rs. 32,000, remaining tenure 15 years; (2) Car loan: Rs. 4,50,000 outstanding at 11% p.a., EMI Rs. 10,000, remaining tenure 5 years; (3) Personal loan: Rs. 2,00,000 outstanding at 16% p.a., EMI Rs. 6,500, remaining tenure 3 years; (4) Credit card outstanding: Rs. 80,000 at 42% p.a. (revolving credit), minimum payment Rs. 4,000/month. His total monthly expenses (excluding debt servicing) are Rs. 45,000. He has recently received an annual bonus of Rs. 3,00,000 and wants advice on how to deploy it. His savings bank balance is Rs. 1,50,000 and he has Rs. 2,00,000 in a liquid mutual fund.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> What is the approximate annual interest saving from clearing the credit card (Rs. 80,000 at 42% p.a.) and personal loan (Rs. 2,00,000 at 16% p.a.)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 33,600]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 65,600]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 48,000]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 55,200]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Credit card interest saved = 80,000 × 42% = Rs. 33,600 per year. Personal loan interest saved ≈ 2,00,000 × 16% = Rs. 32,000 per year (approximate, as EMI would have gradually reduced principal). Total ≈ Rs. 65,600 per year.
**The Trap:** Rs. 33,600 only counts the credit card savings. Both debts must be considered.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Interest cost comparison is a practical X-A calculation demonstrating the impact of debt elimination.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rs. 65,600 annual interest saving from a Rs. 2.8 lakh deployment is equivalent to a 23.4% guaranteed return — no investment can match this risk-free.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>