<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XA Personal Financial Planning_C6_5" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[<b>Scenario:</b> Mr. Suresh Kumar, aged 40, works in the automobile industry and recently faced a salary reduction from Rs. 1,00,000/month to Rs. 75,000/month due to an industry slowdown. He has the following loans: (1) Home loan: Rs. 28 lakh outstanding at 9% p.a. fixed rate, EMI Rs. 28,000, remaining tenure 12 years; (2) Car loan: Rs. 3 lakh outstanding at 12% p.a., EMI Rs. 8,500, remaining tenure 3.5 years; (3) Education loan for son: Rs. 5 lakh at 10% p.a., EMI Rs. 10,600, remaining tenure 5 years. His non-debt monthly expenses are Rs. 35,000. He has savings of Rs. 4 lakh in FDs and Rs. 1.5 lakh in savings bank. His wife earns Rs. 25,000/month from tutoring. The bank has offered to restructure his home loan by extending tenure from 12 to 18 years at the same 9% rate, which would reduce the home loan EMI to approximately Rs. 22,000.

<b>Question 5 of 5:</b> Given that Suresh's salary may recover in 2-3 years, which combination of actions would a prudent Investment Adviser recommend?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Accept restructuring now and never revert to higher EMI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Accept restructuring for immediate relief, plan to increase EMI back to original level when salary recovers, and avoid any new debt]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Refuse restructuring and liquidate all FDs to prepay the home loan]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Take a personal loan to supplement the reduced income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The prudent approach is: (1) Accept restructuring for immediate cash flow relief, (2) Plan to revert to original or higher EMI when salary recovers to minimize total interest cost, (3) Avoid new debt during the recovery period, (4) Maintain the emergency fund intact.
**The Trap:** Liquidating FDs removes the safety net during an income downturn — extremely risky. Taking a personal loan at 16%+ to service a 9% home loan makes no mathematical sense.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Comprehensive debt counselling advice combining multiple concepts from X-A (Ch 4).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Restructuring is a temporary solution, not a permanent one. Set a calendar reminder to review EMIs annually and increase them as income grows — the goal is to return to the original payoff schedule or better.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>