<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XC Case Studies and Practical Application_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[An investment adviser recommends a balanced advantage fund to a conservative client. Three months later, the fund takes a significant equity position during a market rally, and the NAV drops 8% in a subsequent correction. The client complains. The adviser's best defence is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Blaming the fund manager for poor market timing]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Demonstrating that the fund was suitable based on the client's documented risk profile, that balanced advantage funds are designed to dynamically shift allocations, and that short-term fluctuations are expected]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Offering to compensate the client for the loss from personal funds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Promising that the fund will recover and the client will earn guaranteed returns going forward]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** If the recommendation was based on proper risk profiling, suitability assessment, and documented analysis (including explanation of how BAFs work), the adviser has fulfilled their obligation. Short-term NAV movements in a suitable product don't constitute advisory failure.
**The Trap:** Blaming fund managers deflects responsibility. Personal compensation sets a dangerous precedent. Guaranteeing future returns violates regulations.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series X-A covers suitability documentation as defence against complaints. Series V-A covers BAF characteristics.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** At the time of recommendation, always explain how BAFs work (dynamic equity-debt shifting) and that temporary drawdowns are part of the fund's design — pre-emptive education prevents complaints.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>