<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XC Case Studies and Practical Application_4" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Mohan invested Rs.10 lakh in a mutual fund SIP of Rs.25,000 per month for 3 years. The fund's value is now Rs.11.5 lakh. His annualized return (XIRR) is approximately 9.2%. Mohan is unhappy because his friend earned 15% in direct equity. As his adviser, what is the most appropriate response?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Agree that mutual funds underperformed and switch Mohan to direct equity trading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Explain that comparison with direct equity is inappropriate due to different risk profiles, and evaluate Mohan's fund performance against its benchmark and category peers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Suggest Mohan invest in the same stocks his friend bought]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Recommend Mohan file a complaint against the fund house for underperformance]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Performance comparison must be like-for-like. Mohan's MF should be evaluated against its benchmark and category peers, not against an individual's cherry-picked equity returns. Different risk profiles merit different return expectations.
**The Trap:** Switching to direct equity based on someone else's performance is not suitable advisory — it ignores Mohan's own risk profile, investment horizon, and capability.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series X-A covers performance evaluation and benchmarking. Series V-A covers fund comparison and suitability assessment.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Help clients understand survivorship bias — they hear about friends' winning trades but not their losing ones. A systematic MF approach often outperforms over full market cycles when adjusted for risk.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>