<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is Ind AS 109 and how is it relevant to derivative transactions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Ind AS 109 (Financial Instruments) is the Indian accounting standard for recognizing, measuring, and reporting financial instruments including derivatives — it requires fair value measurement and provides hedge accounting rules]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ind AS 109 is a tax regulation that determines the tax rate for derivative income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ind AS 109 only applies to banks and financial institutions, not to regular derivative traders]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Ind AS 109 was replaced by the ICAI 2021 Guidance Note and is no longer applicable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Ind AS 109 is the comprehensive standard for financial instruments under Indian GAAP (converged with IFRS 9). It covers: classification and measurement (amortized cost, FVOCI, FVTPL), impairment, and hedge accounting. Derivatives are always measured at fair value through P&L unless designated in a qualifying hedging relationship.
**The Trap:** Ind AS 109 is an accounting standard, not a tax regulation. It applies to ALL entities using Ind AS (not just banks). The ICAI guidance is supplementary to Ind AS 109, not a replacement.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series I Ch9 and IV Ch9 reference Ind AS 109 for derivative accounting. The standard applies uniformly across currency, interest rate, and equity derivatives.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Hedge accounting under Ind AS 109 allows entities to match the timing of derivative gains/losses with the underlying hedged item, reducing P&L volatility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>