<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Sales Practices, Code of Conduct and Investor Protection_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What prohibitions does SEBI impose on market intermediaries regarding derivative trading practices?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Prohibited practices include: front-running, churning (excessive trading for commissions), insider trading, market manipulation, and misuse of client funds/securities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI only prohibits insider trading — other practices are allowed if disclosed to the client]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[These prohibitions apply only to equity markets, not to derivative segments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI prohibitions are guidelines only and carry no legal penalties]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI prohibits multiple unfair practices: (1) Front-running — trading ahead of client orders, (2) Churning — excessive trading to generate commissions, (3) Insider trading — using non-public material information, (4) Market manipulation — creating artificial price movements, (5) Misuse — mixing client funds with proprietary funds. Violations attract severe penalties.
**The Trap:** ALL these practices are prohibited, not just insider trading. They apply to ALL market segments including derivatives. They carry actual legal penalties including fines and imprisonment.
**Cross-Exam Context:** These prohibitions are covered in all three series (I, IV, VIII Ch10) and are universal across derivative and cash market segments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SEBI's FUTP (Fraudulent and Unfair Trade Practices) regulations and Insider Trading regulations have been strengthened with higher penalties — up to Rs. 25 crore or 3x profit, and potential imprisonment.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>