<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[When is a tax audit mandatory for a derivative trader under Section 44AB?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[When business turnover exceeds Rs. 1 crore (Rs. 10 crore if 95% digital) OR when the trader has opted for presumptive taxation under Section 44AD and declares income below the presumptive rate]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tax audit is always mandatory for derivative traders regardless of turnover]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only when losses exceed Rs. 50 lakh in a financial year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Tax audit applies only to equity derivatives, not to currency or interest rate derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Tax audit under Section 44AB is required when: (1) business turnover exceeds Rs. 1 crore (or Rs. 10 crore if 95% transactions are digital), OR (2) the trader opted for presumptive taxation but actual income is below the prescribed rate (6%/8%), OR (3) the trader has profits but opted out of presumptive scheme with turnover below the threshold.
**The Trap:** Tax audit applies to ALL derivative trading businesses that meet the threshold — not limited to any specific derivative type. It's not always mandatory — small traders below the threshold with adequate profits don't need it.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Tax audit requirements are covered in Series I Ch9 and VIII Ch9. They apply uniformly across all derivative segments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For derivative traders, the enhanced Rs. 10 crore limit (digital transactions) is particularly relevant since all exchange-traded derivatives are electronic — this significantly raises the audit threshold.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>