<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Basics of Derivatives_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What was the role of the J.R. Varma Committee (1998) in Indian derivative market development?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It recommended risk containment measures including margining methodology, initial margin calculations, membership criteria, net worth requirements, and real-time position monitoring]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It recommended the introduction of derivatives and declaring them as securities under SCRA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It recommended the establishment of SEBI as the regulator of derivative markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It recommended allowing foreign investors to participate in Indian derivative markets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The J.R. Varma Committee (June 1998) focused on risk management: SPAN-like margining, initial margin methodology, membership net worth criteria, deposit requirements, and real-time monitoring. It complemented the L.C. Gupta Committee which provided the regulatory framework.
**The Trap:** Declaring derivatives as securities was L.C. Gupta Committee's recommendation. SEBI was established in 1988/1992, before derivatives were introduced. FPI access came later through separate regulations.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series VIII Ch1 and Ch8 cover both committees. L.C. Gupta = regulatory framework, J.R. Varma = risk management. Both are foundational for all Indian derivative markets.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** J.R. Varma's risk management framework is still the basis of Indian derivative market risk management — SPAN margining, position limits, and real-time monitoring all trace back to these recommendations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>