<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_85" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the regulatory oversight structure for different derivative segments in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI regulates all exchange-traded derivatives, while RBI has additional oversight over currency and interest rate derivatives given the underlying assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI regulates only equity derivatives; RBI regulates currency derivatives; and the Ministry of Finance regulates commodity derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Each exchange self-regulates its own derivative products without SEBI involvement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI has sole authority over all derivative products traded on Indian exchanges]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI is the primary regulator for all exchange-traded derivatives in India under the SCRA. However, currency derivatives involve forex (RBI's domain) and interest rate derivatives involve government securities (also RBI's domain), so RBI has concurrent regulatory authority over these segments. SEBI and RBI coordinate through joint guidelines for currency and interest rate derivatives.
**The Trap:** SEBI's jurisdiction covers ALL exchange-traded derivatives, not just equity. Exchanges are regulated by SEBI — they do not self-regulate independently. RBI does not have sole authority — it shares regulatory space with SEBI for currency and IR derivatives.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series I (Currency) discusses SEBI-RBI joint regulation, Series IV (Interest Rate) also covers this dual regulatory framework, and Series VIII (Equity) focuses on SEBI's sole jurisdiction. Series XIII requires understanding the complete regulatory architecture across all segments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The dual regulatory framework for currency and interest rate derivatives means compliance requirements can be more complex. Trading members operating across all segments must satisfy both SEBI and RBI requirements, which can differ in areas like position limits and participant eligibility.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>