<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_74" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Regarding client fund segregation by trading members, which statement is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trading members must keep client funds in a separate bank account and cannot use one client's funds for another client's obligations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Client funds can be pooled with the trading member's proprietary funds if disclosed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Segregation is required only for institutional clients, not retail clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Client funds need to be segregated only at the end of each quarter for reporting purposes]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates strict segregation of client funds from the trading member's own funds. Client funds must be held in designated client bank accounts and cannot be co-mingled with proprietary funds or used for other clients' margin obligations. This protects client assets in case of the TM's default.
**The Trap:** Pooling with proprietary funds is explicitly prohibited regardless of disclosure. Segregation applies to ALL clients — retail and institutional equally. Segregation is continuous, not quarterly — it must be maintained at all times.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Client fund segregation is a universal regulatory requirement across all derivative segments (Series I, IV, VIII, XVI). Series XII (Securities Foundation) and Series XIII cover this as a core investor protection measure.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The 2020-era broker defaults highlighted the importance of client fund segregation. Distributors should verify that their broker maintains proper segregation — a key indicator of the broker's operational integrity.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>