<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_36" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Why is mandatory NISM certification required for dealers and Authorized Persons (APs) handling derivative transactions?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To ensure minimum competency standards, as derivatives involve complex instruments with leverage and significant risk; certified personnel can better advise clients and manage risks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NISM certification is optional and only provides a competitive advantage; it is not a regulatory requirement]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NISM certification is required only for equity derivative dealers, not for currency or interest rate derivative dealers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NISM certification is a one-time qualification with no renewal requirement and covers all financial products]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates NISM certification for all persons dealing in derivatives — dealers, APs, and sales personnel. The rationale is investor protection: derivatives are leveraged, complex instruments, and persons advising or executing trades must demonstrate minimum knowledge of products, regulations, and risk management.
**The Trap:** NISM certification is mandatory, not optional. It applies across derivative segments (not just equity). It requires periodic renewal — it's not a one-time lifetime qualification.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Different NISM series cover different segments: Series VIII for equity derivatives, Series I for currency derivatives, Series IV for interest rate derivatives. Series XIII covers common regulatory aspects.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Ensure all client-facing staff complete the relevant NISM certification before they begin derivative transactions. Non-compliance can lead to SEBI enforcement action against the broker.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>