<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_7" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[How does the tax treatment of currency derivative gains differ from equity derivative gains for a resident individual?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Both are treated as non-speculative business income. However, equity derivatives attract STT while currency derivatives do not — the income classification and tax treatment are otherwise identical]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Currency derivative gains are taxed as capital gains while equity derivatives are taxed as business income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Currency derivatives are taxed at a flat 20% rate while equity derivatives are taxed at slab rates]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Currency derivative gains are tax-free up to Rs. 1 lakh while equity derivative gains are fully taxable]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Both currency and equity exchange-traded derivative gains are classified as non-speculative business income (post Finance Act 2005). Tax rates depend on the individual's slab. The key difference is STT: equity F&O attracts STT, currency F&O does not. Both allow 8-year loss carry forward.
**The Trap:** Neither is taxed as capital gains (that applies to stocks/MFs). There's no flat 20% rate or Rs. 1 lakh exemption for derivative income. The tax treatment is fundamentally the same — the difference is in transaction costs (STT).
**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a XIII-unique cross-asset comparison question combining knowledge from Series I Ch9 (currency tax) and VIII Ch9 (equity tax).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The absence of STT on currency derivatives makes them more cost-efficient for frequent traders, especially when trading with small profit margins.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>