<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_35" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[In which of the following scenarios does RBI have a regulatory role?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Setting bank eligibility criteria for currency derivative TMs, prescribing position limits for banks in interest rate futures, and approving product specifications for exchange-traded currency derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Setting margin requirements for equity index futures, approving equity derivative product specifications, and regulating equity derivative clearing corporations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Granting recognition to derivative exchanges under SCRA, conducting inspections of stock brokers, and registering clearing members for all segments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Mandating NISM certification for derivative dealers, setting net worth norms for equity CMs, and operating the Trade Guarantee Fund]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** RBI's role is limited to currency and interest rate segments: bank TM eligibility (Rs 500 Cr net worth, CRAR, NPA), position limits for banks in IRF (INR 50 billion), and joint approval of currency derivative product specs with SEBI. RBI has NO role in equity derivatives.
**The Trap:** Exchange recognition (SCRA Section 4), broker inspection, clearing member registration, NISM certification, and TGF are all SEBI's domain. RBI does not control any of these.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a comprehensive cross-asset comparison testing the boundary between SEBI's and RBI's jurisdictions. The exam frequently tests whether students can correctly attribute regulatory functions to the right regulator.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Rule of thumb: if it's about the exchange, intermediaries, or market infrastructure — it's SEBI. If it's about the underlying currency/interest rate market or bank participation — it's RBI.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>