<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Sales Practices, Code of Conduct and Investor Protection_8" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What are the obligations of a trading member regarding segregation of client funds and securities?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trading members must maintain separate bank accounts for client funds and proprietary funds, and must not use client funds for proprietary trading or any other purpose]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Client and proprietary funds can be commingled as long as the total balance covers all obligations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Segregation is required only for institutional clients, not for retail clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Fund segregation is optional for derivative segments since all settlements are through the clearing corporation]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI mandates strict segregation: separate bank accounts for client funds, separate demat accounts for client securities, and prohibition on using client funds for proprietary trading. Trading members must maintain proper records and reconcile client accounts regularly. Running account settlements must be done every 30 days (or 90 days if the client opts).
**The Trap:** Commingling is strictly prohibited — not even temporarily. Segregation applies to ALL clients (retail and institutional) and ALL segments (cash and derivatives).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Client fund segregation is a universal requirement covered in all three series (I, IV, VIII Ch10). It's a cornerstone of investor protection.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Running account statements must be sent to clients at least quarterly. Clients can also demand immediate settlement of their running account at any time.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>