<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_44" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What are the consequences for a trading member who violates position limits in derivative trading?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The exchange/CC monitors position limits and imposes penalties for violations — the member may be required to reduce positions within prescribed time; persistent violations can lead to suspension of trading rights]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[There are no penalties for position limit violations as they are only advisory limits]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The member is permanently banned from trading on all exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a warning letter is issued with no financial penalty]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Position limit monitoring is done by exchanges and clearing corporations. Violations trigger: (1) immediate alerts and warnings, (2) financial penalties proportional to the violation, (3) mandatory reduction of positions within prescribed time, (4) escalating actions for repeated violations including suspension. The member must ensure compliance at all times.
**The Trap:** Position limits are mandatory, not advisory. Penalties ARE financial and can escalate. Permanent banning is extreme — the system uses graduated penalties.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Position limit enforcement applies across all derivative segments. The monitoring mechanism is similar across currency (I), interest rate (IV), and equity (VIII) derivatives.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Position limits are monitored at multiple levels — client, TM, CM, and market-wide. Proactive monitoring and automated alerts help prevent inadvertent violations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>