<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Introduction to the Underlying Markets_75" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the significance of the 'repo rate' set by RBI, and how does it connect all three underlying markets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The repo rate is the rate at which RBI lends to banks — it influences short-term money market rates, bond yields (through the yield curve), equity valuations (through discount rates), and currency rates (through interest rate differentials)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The repo rate only affects the banking sector and has no impact on equity or currency markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The repo rate determines the exact price of all government bonds]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The repo rate is set by SEBI and applies only to derivative margin calculations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The repo rate is the central policy rate: (1) It anchors short-term money market rates, (2) It influences the yield curve and bond prices, (3) It affects equity valuations through the discount rate (higher repo = higher discount = lower equity values), (4) It impacts currency markets through interest rate differentials and IRP.
**The Trap:** The repo rate affects ALL financial markets, not just banking. It doesn't directly set bond prices but influences them through market expectations. It's set by RBI, not SEBI.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series IV covers repo rate's impact on bond markets. Series VIII covers its impact on equity derivative pricing. Series I covers interest rate differentials for currency pricing.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** RBI policy decisions are among the most impactful events for derivative markets — all three markets (bonds, equities, currencies) react simultaneously to repo rate changes.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>