<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_16" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What stamp duty applies to derivative transactions in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Stamp duty is levied under the Indian Stamp Act as amended — rates vary by state and instrument type, with derivative transactions typically charged at lower rates than delivery-based equity transactions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No stamp duty applies to any derivative transaction in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[A uniform 0.5% stamp duty applies to all derivative transactions across all states]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Stamp duty is only applicable to physically settled derivative contracts, not cash-settled ones]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The Indian Stamp Act (as amended by Finance Act 2019) imposes stamp duty on securities transactions including derivatives. The rates for derivatives (futures and options) are typically lower than for delivery-based cash market transactions. Stamp duty is collected by the exchange and remitted to the respective state government.
**The Trap:** Stamp duty DOES apply to derivatives. It's not uniform across all transactions — derivative rates are lower than cash market rates. It applies to both cash and physically settled contracts.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Stamp duty applies across all derivative segments — equity, currency, interest rate, and commodity. Series I, IV, and VIII all mention stamp duty in their trading/tax chapters.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Stamp duty, though small, adds to trading costs. High-frequency traders should factor it into their cost-per-trade calculation alongside brokerage, STT/CTT, and exchange charges.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>