<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_1" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which two regulators jointly oversee exchange-traded currency and interest rate derivatives in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI and RBI — SEBI regulates the exchanges and intermediaries while RBI regulates the underlying currency and interest rate markets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI and IRDAI — SEBI regulates derivatives while IRDAI regulates the interest rate component]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[RBI and Ministry of Finance — as currency and interest rate are both monetary policy instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI alone regulates all exchange-traded derivatives without involvement of any other regulator]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Exchange-traded currency and interest rate derivatives are under dual regulation. RBI's role covers the underlying markets (forex under FEMA, G-Secs) and is primary and fundamental. SEBI's role is limited to regulating the exchange-traded contracts, exchanges, clearing corporations, and intermediaries.
**The Trap:** SEBI alone regulates equity derivatives. But for currency and interest rate derivatives, RBI has primary jurisdiction over the underlying instruments, making it dual regulation.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series I Ch8 and IV Ch8 both discuss SEBI-RBI dual regulation. Series VIII Ch8 covers SEBI's sole jurisdiction over equity derivatives. Series XIII compares these regulatory frameworks.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The RBI-SEBI Standing Technical Committee coordinates between the two regulators on matters of product design, eligibility, and position limits for currency and IR derivatives.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>