<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_6" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under the presumptive taxation scheme (Section 44AD), what is the turnover limit for derivative traders?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 2 crore (Rs. 3 crore if 95% of receipts are through digital/banking channels) — traders below this limit can declare 6% (digital) or 8% (cash) of turnover as income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 50 lakh — applicable only to professionals under Section 44ADA]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs. 10 crore — the enhanced limit applies to all businesses including derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No presumptive taxation is available for derivative traders]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Section 44AD allows presumptive taxation for businesses with turnover up to Rs. 2 crore (Rs. 3 crore if 95% receipts are digital). For F&O trading, turnover is calculated as absolute sum of settlement profits/losses. If turnover is below the limit, traders can declare 6% (digital) or 8% (cash) of turnover as presumptive income.
**The Trap:** Rs. 50 lakh is for professionals (Section 44ADA). The Rs. 3 crore limit applies only when 95% of transactions are through banking channels. For derivative turnover calculation, BOTH profits and losses are summed as absolute values.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series I Ch9 and VIII Ch9 cover presumptive taxation for derivative traders. This applies across all exchange-traded derivative segments.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** For derivative traders, 'turnover' = absolute profit + absolute loss + premium received + premium paid. This special calculation often pushes traders above the Rs. 2/3 crore threshold.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>