<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_83" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under SEBI's penalty framework for margin short-collection, if a trading member's shortfall in client margin collection exceeds Rs 10 lakh, the penalty rate is:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[1% of the shortfall amount per day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[0.5% of the shortfall amount per day]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Rs 5,000 flat penalty per instance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[0.1% of the total margin required per day]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's penalty framework is graduated based on the shortfall amount: shortfalls up to Rs 1 lakh attract 0.5% per day, and shortfalls exceeding Rs 1 lakh attract 1% per day. This graduated structure incentivizes trading members to ensure full margin collection from clients, with higher penalties for larger shortfalls.
**The Trap:** 0.5% per day applies only to smaller shortfalls (up to Rs 1 lakh), not to shortfalls above Rs 10 lakh. The penalty is not a flat amount — it is proportional to the shortfall. It is calculated on the shortfall amount, not on the total required margin.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The penalty framework is uniform across all derivative segments — equity (Series VIII), currency (Series I), commodity (Series XVI), and interest rate (Series IV). Series XIII tests the consolidated understanding of the margin penalty regime.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The graduated penalty structure means larger shortfalls attract proportionally higher penalties. Trading members should build a buffer above the minimum margin requirement to account for intraday fluctuations that could create temporary shortfalls during random snapshot monitoring.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>