<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Strategies Using Futures_80" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is a limitation common to hedging with exchange-traded derivatives across ALL asset classes (currency, interest rate, and equity)?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Standardized contract specifications (lot size, expiry dates, contract months) may not perfectly match the hedger's exposure, creating residual risk]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exchange-traded derivatives are only available for the top 10 most traded assets]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Hedging with exchange-traded derivatives always results in a loss for the hedger]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Exchange-traded derivatives cannot be used by corporate entities, only by individual traders]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Exchange-traded derivatives have standardized specifications — fixed lot sizes, predetermined expiry dates, and limited contract months. A hedger whose exposure doesn't match these specifications (e.g., odd lot size, exposure date between expiry dates) will have an imperfect hedge with residual risk.
**The Trap:** ETDs are available for many assets, not just top 10. Hedging can result in either gain or loss (it locks in a rate). Both corporates and individuals can use ETDs.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This limitation is discussed across all three series (I, IV, VIII). It's universal to exchange-traded derivatives regardless of asset class.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** OTC derivatives can provide exact customization (size, expiry, terms), but at the cost of counterparty risk. ETDs trade standardized but have exchange guarantee — choose based on your priority.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>