<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Sales Practices, Code of Conduct and Investor Protection_2" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the KYC (Know Your Client) obligation for derivative trading members?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Trading members must complete KYC for all clients before allowing them to trade — this includes identity verification, address proof, financial details, and risk profiling through KRA (KYC Registration Agency)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC is optional for derivative trading — only cash market transactions require it]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC only requires identity verification — no financial or risk profiling is needed]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC is done by the exchange, not by the trading member]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** As per SEBI KYC regulations and L.C. Gupta Committee recommendations, trading members must: (1) verify client identity through valid documents, (2) obtain address proof, (3) assess financial background, (4) conduct risk profiling, and (5) register with KRA for centralized KYC. Clients must also sign a Risk Disclosure Document before trading derivatives.
**The Trap:** KYC is MANDATORY for all derivative trading, not optional. It includes financial details and risk profiling beyond just identity. The TM is responsible, not the exchange.
**Cross-Exam Context:** KYC requirements are identical across all derivative segments (I, IV, VIII Ch10). Series XIII tests this as a universal investor protection measure.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** KYC data must be uploaded to the KRA within 10 days of account opening. Incomplete or outdated KYC can result in account restrictions and penalties for the trading member.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>