<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Introduction to Forwards and Futures_46" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is 'price discovery' in futures markets and how does it benefit the underlying spot market?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Futures prices aggregate information about future supply, demand, and expectations from a wide range of participants, providing forward-looking price signals that help spot market participants make better economic decisions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Futures markets set mandatory prices that spot markets must follow]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Price discovery only works in commodity markets where supply is seasonal]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Futures prices are always more accurate than spot prices]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Futures markets enable efficient price discovery because: (1) Low transaction costs attract diverse participants, (2) Leverage allows expressing views with less capital, (3) Standardization provides a common reference, (4) Transparent order book. The futures price often leads the spot price as informed traders act on futures first.
**The Trap:** Futures markets don't mandate spot prices — they inform them. Price discovery works across all asset classes. Futures can be wrong (they're expectations, not guarantees).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Price discovery is a universal function covered in Series VIII, I, IV, and XVI. It's particularly important in commodity markets where physical supply information flows into futures.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Watch futures price movements to anticipate spot moves — in India, NIFTY futures (especially SGX Nifty during off-hours) and USDINR futures provide early signals for equity and forex traders.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>