<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_14" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A trader incurred a loss of Rs. 5 lakh on equity F&O trading and has non-speculative business income of Rs. 8 lakh from a proprietorship. Can the loss be set off?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Yes — the Rs. 5 lakh F&O loss (non-speculative business loss) can be fully set off against the Rs. 8 lakh business income in the same year]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No — F&O loss is speculative and can only be set off against speculative income]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only Rs. 2 lakh can be set off in the current year with the balance carried forward]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[F&O losses can only be set off against F&O gains, not other business income]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Since F&O trading is classified as non-speculative business under Section 43(5) (post 2005 amendment), the Rs. 5 lakh loss can be set off against ANY non-speculative business income in the same year. The proprietorship income of Rs. 8 lakh qualifies, so the full Rs. 5 lakh is set off, leaving taxable income of Rs. 3 lakh.
**The Trap:** F&O losses are NOT speculative. They CAN be set off against any non-speculative business income, not just other F&O income. The full amount is eligible for set-off.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This set-off applies to losses from ALL exchange-traded derivatives — equity, currency, and interest rate. Series XIII tests unified understanding.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** To claim set-off, ensure the F&O trading loss is properly reported as non-speculative business loss in your tax return. Incorrect classification (as speculative) would limit set-off options.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>