<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_24" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[A mutual fund wants to hedge its government bond portfolio using interest rate futures. Which regulatory approvals or permissions does it need?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI's permission under its mutual fund regulations/guidelines for participating in exchange-traded interest rate derivatives, and trading through a SEBI-registered broker on a recognized exchange]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only RBI approval since interest rate derivatives are solely under RBI's jurisdiction]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Approval from both SEBI and the Ministry of Finance, since government bonds are sovereign instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No regulatory approval is needed — any registered mutual fund can freely trade any derivative]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Mutual funds participate in ETIRDs per SEBI guidelines (not RBI). They must comply with SEBI mutual fund regulations regarding derivative usage (hedging vs speculation limits, disclosure, etc.) and trade through registered brokers on recognized exchanges.
**The Trap:** While RBI regulates banks/PDs in ETIRD, mutual funds fall under SEBI's regulatory ambit. RBI approval is not needed for mutual funds. Ministry of Finance has no direct role here.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This illustrates how different participant types fall under different regulators even in the same product segment. Banks need RBI approval; mutual funds need SEBI approval.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Mutual fund participation in IRF is typically limited to hedging purposes. SEBI guidelines may restrict speculative positions, making the regulatory framework more nuanced than just 'permission to trade'.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>