<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_45" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Members registered with SEBI for which segment can also trade in interest rate derivatives without additional registration?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Members registered for trading in Currency or Equity Derivative segments can also trade in Interest Rate Derivatives, subject to meeting balance sheet net worth requirements specified by SEBI/exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only dedicated IR derivative members can trade in that segment — no cross-segment eligibility]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only equity segment members can trade in IR derivatives; currency segment members cannot]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All members automatically get access to all derivative segments without any additional requirements]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI allows cross-segment eligibility: members registered for Currency or Equity Derivative segments can also trade in IR Derivatives without separate SEBI registration. However, they must meet the balance sheet net worth and deposit requirements for the IR segment as specified by SEBI/exchanges.
**The Trap:** While no separate SEBI registration is needed, additional net worth/deposit requirements must be met. Access is not fully automatic — there are financial conditions.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series IV Ch8 specifically covers this eligibility provision. It facilitates broader participation in IR derivatives by leveraging existing memberships.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** This cross-segment eligibility reduces barriers to entry for existing members, promoting liquidity in the IR derivatives segment which historically has had lower participation than equity or currency derivatives.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>