<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What was the role of the L.C. Gupta Committee in the development of derivatives trading in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[It was set up by SEBI to develop the regulatory framework for derivatives trading — it recommended eligibility criteria for exchanges, clearing corporations, and members]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It was set up by RBI to design currency derivative products for Indian exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It was a joint SEBI-RBI committee that designed the SPAN margining system]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[It was established by the Ministry of Finance to determine tax treatment of derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI constituted the L.C. Gupta Committee in 1998 to recommend the regulatory framework for derivatives trading. Key recommendations: separate governing council with max 40% trading member representation, minimum 50 exchange members, clearing through SEBI-approved CC, Rs. 3 crore minimum net worth for CMs, mandatory NISM certification, and strict KYC enforcement.
**The Trap:** The L.C. Gupta Committee was a SEBI committee, not RBI. The J.R. Verma Committee (separate) worked on risk management and margining — they are often confused.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series VIII Ch8 covers L.C. Gupta Committee in detail. Series IV Ch8 mentions the RBI-SEBI Standing Technical Committee (different from L.C. Gupta). Series XIII tests understanding of different committees.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** L.C. Gupta = regulatory framework. J.R. Verma = risk management/margining. RBI-SEBI STC = currency and IR derivatives coordination. Know which committee did what.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>