<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_33" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[SEBI has issued a Standard Operating Procedure (SOP) for exchanges regarding which operational scenario?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Exchange outages or technical disruptions — prescribing steps for trading halt, communication, order management, and resumption of operations]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[IPO allotment disputes — prescribing how exchanges should resolve over-subscription of derivative product launches]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Broker insolvency — prescribing how exchanges should distribute a failed broker's assets to clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Dividend adjustment — prescribing exact formulas for adjusting derivative contracts on ex-dividend dates]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI's SOP for exchange outages addresses technical disruptions that can affect trading. It prescribes how the exchange should halt trading, communicate with members and the public, manage pending orders, handle open positions, and resume operations — ensuring orderly market function during and after disruptions.
**The Trap:** The SOP is specifically about operational/technology disruptions, not about IPO allotment, broker insolvency, or corporate action adjustments (which are covered under separate regulations).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Exchange operational resilience is a cross-cutting topic. The SOP applies to all segments — equity, currency, and IR derivatives — wherever exchange outages can impact trading.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The SOP includes provisions for shifting trading to alternate platforms/exchanges during extended outages — ensuring business continuity for the market.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>