<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_11" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the primary role of the RBI-SEBI Standing Technical Committee in the context of exchange-traded currency and interest rate derivatives?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To coordinate regulatory policies between RBI and SEBI on product design, participant eligibility, risk management, and position limits for currency and IR derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To replace both RBI and SEBI as the sole regulatory authority for all exchange-traded derivatives in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To regulate only OTC derivatives transactions between banks and their corporate clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To act as an appellate body where brokers can challenge SEBI enforcement actions related to currency derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The RBI-SEBI Standing Technical Committee was established to coordinate between the two regulators on matters where their jurisdictions overlap — specifically exchange-traded currency derivatives and interest rate derivatives. It addresses product specifications, eligibility norms, risk management, and position limits.
**The Trap:** The committee does not replace either regulator. It is a coordination mechanism, not an appellate or independent regulatory body.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series I (Currency) and IV (Interest Rate) both reference this committee. It does not apply to equity derivatives (Series VIII) where SEBI is the sole regulator.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When a new currency or IR derivative product is proposed for exchange trading, both RBI and SEBI must agree through this committee before it can be launched.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>