<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Introduction to the Underlying Markets_31" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Comparing the three derivative underlying markets, which statement about market regulation in India is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Equity derivatives are regulated solely by SEBI, currency derivatives are jointly regulated by SEBI and RBI, and interest rate derivatives on exchanges are regulated by SEBI with RBI oversight]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three derivative markets are regulated solely by SEBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Equity and currency derivatives are regulated by SEBI while interest rate derivatives are regulated solely by RBI]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Currency derivatives are regulated by RBI, equity derivatives by SEBI, and interest rate derivatives by the Finance Ministry]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Equity derivatives fall under SEBI jurisdiction. Currency derivatives have dual regulation — SEBI regulates exchange trading while RBI regulates the underlying forex market and OTC products. IR derivatives on exchanges are under SEBI but RBI retains oversight since the underlying (G-Secs, interest rates) falls under RBI's domain.
**The Trap:** It's tempting to think SEBI regulates all exchange-traded derivatives alone, but RBI has specific jurisdiction over currency and interest rate markets that creates a dual regulatory structure.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series VIII Ch8, Series I Ch8, and Series IV Ch8 each cover the regulatory framework for their respective derivative types. This comparison is unique to Series XIII.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The dual regulation of currency derivatives means product approvals require both SEBI and RBI sign-off — this has historically slowed new product introductions in currency markets.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>