<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Accounting and Taxation_17" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Under hedge accounting, what documentation is required at the inception of a hedging relationship?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Formal designation including: identification of hedged item and hedging instrument, nature of risk being hedged, how effectiveness will be assessed, and the entity's risk management objective and strategy]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No documentation is required — hedge accounting is automatic for all derivative positions]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only a declaration to the exchange that the position is for hedging, not speculation]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Documentation is only required at the end of the financial year during tax filing]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Ind AS 109 / ICAI guidance requires comprehensive upfront documentation: (1) the hedged item and hedging instrument, (2) the specific risk being hedged, (3) how hedge effectiveness will be assessed prospectively, (4) the risk management objective and strategy. Without this documentation, hedge accounting cannot be applied.
**The Trap:** Hedge accounting is NOT automatic — it requires formal designation and documentation. Exchange declarations don't qualify. The documentation must be at inception, not year-end.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This applies to all derivative types used for hedging — currency (I), interest rate (IV), and equity (VIII). It's a universal accounting requirement.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Hedge accounting is optional — entities can choose to measure all derivatives at fair value through P&L without hedge accounting. But hedge accounting reduces P&L volatility for genuine hedges.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>