<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Sales Practices, Code of Conduct and Investor Protection_3" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the SCORES portal and how does it assist derivative investors?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SCORES (SEBI Complaints Redress System) is SEBI's online platform where investors can lodge complaints against listed companies and SEBI-registered intermediaries — complaints are tracked with a 21-day resolution target]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCORES is a credit scoring system used by exchanges to rate the financial health of trading members]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCORES is a trading platform operated by SEBI for direct investor participation in derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCORES is an educational portal by SEBI that provides derivative trading training]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCORES 2.0 (launched April 2024) allows investors to file grievances against intermediaries (brokers, exchanges, clearing corporations). The complaint is routed to the concerned entity with a 21-day Action Taken Report (ATR) deadline. It tracks complaint status online with auto-escalation for delayed responses.
**The Trap:** SCORES is for complaints/grievances, not for credit scoring, trading, or education. It targets intermediaries and listed companies, not individual traders.
**Cross-Exam Context:** SCORES is referenced in all three derivative series (I Ch10, IV Ch10, VIII Ch10) as the primary investor grievance platform. Series XIII tests unified understanding.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Before approaching SEBI through SCORES, investors should first exhaust the complaint mechanism at the trading member and exchange level — there's a defined escalation path.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>