<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_39" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the applicability of SCRA across different derivative segments?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SCRA applies to all exchange-traded derivatives — equity, currency, and interest rate — providing the legal framework for exchange recognition (Section 4) and derivative contract validity (Section 18A)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCRA applies only to equity derivatives; currency derivatives are governed exclusively by FEMA and interest rate derivatives by the RBI Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCRA applies only to cash market securities and was never extended to cover derivative instruments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SCRA was repealed in 2002 and replaced by the SEBI Act for governing all derivative markets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SCRA is the common legal foundation for ALL exchange-traded segments. Section 4 (exchange recognition) applies to all derivative exchanges. Section 18A (legal validity) covers all exchange-traded derivatives. FEMA and RBI Act supplement SCRA for currency and IR segments but do not replace it.
**The Trap:** SCRA has NOT been repealed. It coexists with FEMA and the RBI Act. For currency derivatives, SCRA covers the exchange-traded aspect while FEMA covers the underlying forex. They complement each other.
**Cross-Exam Context:** SCRA is tested across Series I, IV, VIII, and XIII. It is the single most important statute for exchange-traded derivatives — applicable universally regardless of the underlying asset.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Think of SCRA as the 'exchange umbrella' — any contract traded on a recognized exchange falls under SCRA. The underlying asset's regulator (SEBI for equity, RBI for forex/bonds) provides additional regulatory layers.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>