<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_52" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the regulatory status of Securities Transaction Tax (STT) across different derivative segments in India?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[STT is levied only on equity derivatives (futures and options); currency derivatives and interest rate derivatives are exempt from STT]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STT applies uniformly across all exchange-traded derivatives including equity, currency, and interest rate segments]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[STT applies to equity and currency derivatives but not to interest rate derivatives due to their government security linkage]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[No derivative transactions attract STT — it applies only to cash market equity transactions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** STT is levied only on equity derivative transactions. Currency futures/options and interest rate futures/options are fully exempt from STT. For equity: futures attract 0.02% (sell side), options attract 0.0625% (sell side on premium) or 0.10% (on exercise).
**The Trap:** STT is NOT universal across all derivatives — it applies ONLY to equity. This exemption makes currency and interest rate derivatives relatively more cost-effective. Derivatives ARE subject to STT (option D is wrong).
**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a quintessential Series XIII cross-segment question. The STT differential across segments affects total trading costs and can influence the choice of hedging instrument. Add stamp duty (all segments) and GST to get the full cost picture.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The STT exemption for currency and IR derivatives was designed to boost liquidity in these segments. For corporate treasuries comparing hedging costs, the absence of STT on currency derivatives can be a meaningful cost saving.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>