<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_48" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the regulatory framework for brokerage charges in the equity derivatives segment?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI has prescribed maximum brokerage limits — for derivatives, brokerage cannot exceed 2.5% of the contract value, and members must disclose all charges upfront to clients]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Brokerage in derivatives is completely deregulated — brokers can charge any amount as determined by market competition]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI fixes a uniform brokerage rate of 0.05% for all derivative transactions across all brokers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Brokerage is capped at 1% of premium for options and 0.5% of contract value for futures]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI prescribes maximum brokerage limits for derivative transactions. The maximum permissible brokerage is 2.5% of the contract value. In practice, competitive pressures mean actual brokerage rates are far lower (often 0.01-0.05% or flat per-order fees). Brokers must transparently disclose all charges.
**The Trap:** Brokerage is NOT completely deregulated — there is a SEBI-prescribed ceiling. Nor is there a uniform fixed rate — brokers can charge any rate up to the maximum. The 2.5% is a maximum, not the actual rate charged.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Brokerage limits apply across equity, currency, and interest rate derivative segments. The total cost of trading includes brokerage + STT (equity only) + exchange charges + stamp duty + GST + SEBI turnover fees.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The actual brokerage landscape has shifted dramatically — many discount brokers charge flat Rs 20 per order or zero for certain segments. The regulatory maximum of 2.5% exists as consumer protection but is rarely approached in practice.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>