<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Sales Practices, Code of Conduct and Investor Protection_10" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the SMART ODR (Online Dispute Resolution) mechanism for resolving investor disputes?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SMART ODR is a SEBI-mandated online platform for resolving investor disputes through conciliation (21 days) and arbitration (30 days) — making the process faster, paperless, and accessible from anywhere]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SMART ODR is a physical arbitration center at the exchange premises]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SMART ODR is a voluntary mediation service that has no binding authority]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SMART ODR only handles disputes above Rs. 1 crore — smaller disputes go to consumer courts]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SMART ODR (launched by SEBI) enables online resolution of investor disputes. Process: (1) Conciliation attempt within 21 days — a neutral conciliator tries to help parties reach agreement, (2) If conciliation fails, arbitration within 30 days — an arbitrator makes a binding award. For claims above Rs. 30 lakh, a panel of 3 arbitrators is constituted.
**The Trap:** SMART ODR is online (not physical), has binding authority (arbitration awards are enforceable), and handles disputes of all sizes (no minimum threshold).
**Cross-Exam Context:** SMART ODR applies across all exchange-traded segments including derivatives. Series I, IV, and VIII Ch10 all reference the dispute resolution mechanism.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** SMART ODR significantly reduces resolution time and cost compared to traditional courts. Investors should use this mechanism before escalating to SEBI or SAT.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>