<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Sales Practices, Code of Conduct and Investor Protection_9" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What NISM certification is mandatory for persons dealing in exchange-traded derivatives?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[NISM certification specific to the derivative segment is mandatory for all dealers and users entering orders in the trading system — without it, they cannot trade on behalf of clients or the member firm]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NISM certification is optional and only enhances career prospects]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Only the compliance officer needs NISM certification, not individual dealers]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[NISM certification is required only for equity derivatives, not for currency or interest rate derivatives]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** All persons who enter orders in the trading system (dealers) on behalf of a trading member must pass the relevant NISM certification exam. For currency derivatives, it's the NISM Series I exam. For equity derivatives, it's NISM Series VIII. For interest rate derivatives, it's NISM Series IV. The certification is MANDATORY, not optional.
**The Trap:** Every dealer needs certification, not just the compliance officer. The requirement applies to ALL derivative segments, not just equity.
**Cross-Exam Context:** The NISM certification requirement is mentioned in all three series as a mandatory prerequisite. Series XIII is itself a combined certification covering all three areas.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** NISM certifications have a validity period (typically 3-5 years) and must be renewed through continuing education or re-examination. Trading without valid certification can result in penalties.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>