<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Introduction to the Underlying Markets_80" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Comparing the three derivative underlying markets, which market is most directly influenced by the actions of a FOREIGN central bank?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[The currency market — because exchange rates directly reflect the monetary policy differential between domestic and foreign central banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The equity market — because foreign central bank actions determine stock prices in India]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[The bond market — because Indian bond yields are entirely set by foreign central banks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[All three markets are equally and directly influenced by foreign central bank actions]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Currency exchange rates are directly determined by relative monetary policies. If the US Fed raises rates while RBI holds, the USDINR rate moves directly. Bond markets are influenced (through FPI flows and global rates) but domestic factors dominate. Equity markets are affected indirectly through capital flows and risk appetite.
**The Trap:** While all markets are interconnected globally, the DIRECT impact of a foreign central bank is strongest on currency markets. Indian bond yields are primarily determined by domestic factors (RBI, fiscal deficit, SLR).
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series I covers how RBI and Fed policies affect currency markets. Series IV covers domestic bond market dynamics. Series VIII covers equity market drivers. This is a Series XIII synthesis question.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Currency derivative traders must monitor multiple central banks simultaneously (RBI, Fed, ECB, BOJ) — this makes currency the most globally interconnected derivative market.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>