<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_28" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Why was Section 18A inserted into the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act specifically for derivative contracts?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[To provide legal validity to derivative contracts traded on recognized exchanges, preventing them from being treated as wagering agreements void under the Indian Contract Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To impose a special tax on derivative transactions conducted on recognized exchanges]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To mandate that all derivative contracts must be physically settled through delivery of the underlying asset]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[To prohibit foreign investors from participating in Indian derivative markets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Before Section 18A, derivative contracts (which involve future settlement and can result in only differential payments) could be challenged as wagering agreements under Section 30 of the Indian Contract Act, making them void and unenforceable. Section 18A specifically provides legal protection to exchange-traded derivatives.
**The Trap:** Section 18A is about legal validity, not taxation, settlement mode, or participant restrictions. It solves the fundamental legal problem of derivatives being classified as gambling.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This legal protection applies across equity, currency, and IR derivatives. It is the common legal foundation for all exchange-traded derivatives in India.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** OTC derivatives not traded on exchanges don't get Section 18A protection. They rely on the RBI's master directions and ISDA-style documentation for legal enforceability.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>