<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_64" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[For a stock to be eligible for derivatives trading on Indian exchanges, which of the following criteria must be met?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Median Quarter Sigma Order Size (MQSOS) of at least Rs 25 lakh and Market Wide Position Limit (MWPL) of at least Rs 500 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Market capitalization of at least Rs 10,000 crore and daily turnover of Rs 500 crore]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Listing on at least two stock exchanges and minimum free-float of 50%]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Minimum 5 years of listing history and no corporate governance violations]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** SEBI specifies quantitative eligibility criteria for stock derivatives including MQSOS (measuring liquidity depth), MWPL (measuring overall market capacity), minimum number of active trading members, and average daily turnover thresholds. These ensure the underlying stock has sufficient liquidity to support a derivatives market.
**The Trap:** Market capitalization alone is not a criterion — a large-cap stock with poor liquidity may still be ineligible. Dual listing is not required. Listing history of 5 years is not a specific criterion.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series VIII (Equity Derivatives) covers these eligibility criteria in detail. Currency derivatives (Series I) have different underlying eligibility — based on RBI-permitted currency pairs. Interest rate derivatives (Series IV) are based on government securities.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Stocks can be removed from the derivatives-eligible list if they fail to meet the continued eligibility criteria — advisors should monitor quarterly reviews to alert clients holding long-dated positions.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>