<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_79" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Regarding Know Your Client (KYC) obligations for trading members in derivatives, which statement is correct?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[KYC must be completed before the client places the first trade, and the TM must verify the client's identity, address, and financial details]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC can be completed within 30 days after the client starts trading]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC is required only for clients trading above Rs 10 lakh per month]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC for derivatives is less stringent than for equity cash markets]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** KYC is a mandatory pre-condition for trading — no client can place a single trade without completed KYC. The TM must verify identity (PAN, Aadhaar), address, financial information (income, net worth), and trading experience. The KYC process is now centralized through KRA (KYC Registration Agencies).
**The Trap:** KYC cannot be deferred — it must be done before the first trade. There is no threshold below which KYC is waived. KYC requirements for derivatives are at least as stringent as for cash markets, often requiring additional declarations about derivatives trading experience and risk appetite.
**Cross-Exam Context:** KYC requirements are universal across all derivative segments and are covered in Series I, IV, VIII, XII, and XVI. Series XIII tests the consolidated KYC framework applicable to multi-segment trading.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** The shift to digital KYC (eKYC, Video KYC) has made the process faster, but the regulatory requirements remain unchanged. Ensure clients provide accurate financial information — this affects the suitability assessment for derivatives trading.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>