<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_40" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following is TRUE about SEBI's role in regulating Trading Members (TMs) of equity derivative exchanges?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[SEBI has not prescribed a specific net worth requirement for TMs in equity derivatives; net worth requirements are specified only for Clearing Members (Rs 3 Cr) and Self-Clearing Members (Rs 1 Cr)]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI requires a minimum net worth of Rs 500 Cr for all TMs in equity derivatives, similar to RBI's requirement for currency TMs]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI requires a minimum net worth of Rs 3 Cr for TMs, the same as for Clearing Members]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[SEBI requires a minimum net worth of Rs 10 Cr for TMs in equity derivatives to ensure financial stability]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Under the L.C. Gupta Committee framework adopted by SEBI, net worth requirements were specified for CMs (Rs 3 Cr) and SCMs (Rs 1 Cr), but NOT for TMs in equity derivatives. TMs route their clearing through CMs and don't directly face settlement risk, so the net worth requirement was not specified at the TM level.
**The Trap:** Rs 500 Cr is RBI's norm for bank TMs in currency derivatives, NOT SEBI's norm for equity TMs. Don't confuse cross-segment requirements. SEBI's silence on TM net worth is itself a testable fact.
**Cross-Exam Context:** This is a frequent exam trap: confusing CM net worth with TM net worth, or confusing equity segment norms with currency segment norms.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** While SEBI hasn't specified TM net worth, exchanges may set their own minimum requirements as part of membership criteria. Check the specific exchange's rules.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>