<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Legal and Regulatory Environment_34" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[What is the significance of KYC (Know Your Customer) norms as recommended by the L.C. Gupta Committee for derivative markets?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[KYC ensures proper identification and suitability assessment of derivative market participants, preventing money laundering and protecting uninformed investors from inappropriate risk exposure]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC is only a formality required for record-keeping and has no practical regulatory significance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC norms apply only to institutional investors and are waived for retail participants in derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[KYC in derivatives is conducted by SEBI directly rather than by the broker or exchange]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** The L.C. Gupta Committee emphasized strict KYC as essential for derivative markets due to the inherent leverage and risk. KYC serves dual purposes: (1) anti-money laundering compliance by verifying identity and source of funds, and (2) suitability assessment ensuring the participant understands derivative risks.
**The Trap:** KYC is not a mere formality — it has substantive regulatory significance. It applies to ALL participants (retail and institutional). It is conducted by the broker/intermediary, not by SEBI directly.
**Cross-Exam Context:** KYC requirements apply uniformly across equity, currency, and IR derivatives. Enhanced KYC may apply for certain categories (NRIs in currency, FPIs in equity).
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** A robust KYC process protects the broker too — in case of client default, proper KYC documentation strengthens the broker's legal position for recovery.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>