<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XIII Trading, Clearing, Settlement and Risk Management_47" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[Which of the following correctly describes the stamp duty applicability on derivative contracts?]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Stamp duty is levied on derivative transactions and the rates are specified under the Indian Stamp Act as amended, applicable to both futures and options trades]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Derivative contracts are exempt from stamp duty as they are not considered instruments of transfer under the Indian Stamp Act]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Stamp duty applies only to physically settled derivatives, not to cash-settled derivatives]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[Stamp duty on derivatives is levied only at the state level and varies by state where the exchange is located]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** Following the amendment to the Indian Stamp Act (effective July 2020), stamp duty is levied on derivative transactions at specified rates. It is collected by the stock exchange/clearing corporation on behalf of the state government and applies to all derivative trades regardless of settlement mode.
**The Trap:** Derivatives are NOT exempt from stamp duty — this changed with the 2020 amendment. The duty applies to both cash-settled and physically settled derivatives. Rates are uniform (centralized collection), not varying by state of exchange location.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Stamp duty applies across all derivative segments — equity, currency, and interest rate. Combined with STT (equity only), brokerage, exchange charges, and GST, it forms the total transaction cost picture tested in Series XIII.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** Stamp duty rates for derivatives are much lower than for delivery-based equity trades. For futures and options, the rates are in the range of 0.002% to 0.003%. Still, for high-frequency traders, cumulative stamp duty can be material.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>