<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<QF id="XXVA Regulatory Compliance for Non-Core Research Personnel_15" sectionNumber="" articleNumber="0" articleName="">
    <question>
        <text><![CDATA[The Exchange surveillance mechanisms GSM (Graded Surveillance Measure) and ASM (Additional Surveillance Measure) are relevant for research services because:]]></text>
        <answers>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They provide guaranteed buy signals for stocks under surveillance]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="yes"><text><![CDATA[Stocks under GSM/ASM face additional trading restrictions and margin requirements, which may affect the implementability and risk profile of research recommendations on these stocks]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They are only relevant for stock exchanges and have no impact on research activities]]></text></answer>
            <answer correct="no"><text><![CDATA[They automatically disqualify stocks from being covered in research reports]]></text></answer>
        </answers>
        <explanation><text><![CDATA[**The Logic:** GSM and ASM impose additional trading restrictions (margin requirements, circuit limits, trading frequency limits) on stocks identified for enhanced surveillance. Research recommendations on these stocks must account for the additional risk and trading constraints.
**The Trap:** GSM/ASM don't provide buy signals or disqualify research coverage — but they significantly affect implementability of recommendations. Sales personnel must inform clients about these constraints.
**Cross-Exam Context:** Series XV Chapter 14 covers GSM/ASM. Series VII and VIII cover exchange surveillance mechanisms.
**Distributor's Pro-Tip:** When distributing research on GSM/ASM stocks, proactively inform clients about the additional surveillance measures — failure to disclose trading restrictions could lead to client complaints when they face unexpected margin calls or trading limitations.]]></text></explanation>
    </question>
</QF>